<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06001131">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, May 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lambert, Gustaf E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06001131</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-05-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Graham, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Gillan, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Lottie</name>
<name type="person">Ryan, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Sheppard, Morris</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-05-00">May 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06001131</idno>
<title>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, May 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lambert describes buildings at Columbia Barracks, and recollects about the people involved and their roles in the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-05-00">
<head>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Philip Showalter Hench, May 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06001131"/>
<opener>
Mrs Reed's scrapbook photo<lb/>
of Y F <unclear>hospital</unclear><lb/>
Date?<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-05-00">May or June 1954</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I give you my version of the photograph. First the cottages in Mrs. Reed's<lb/>
picture could have been the original big buildings, if so, they have been re-<lb/>
modeled. We had no windows on the north side, no entry way, and steps. North<lb/>
end of building was on the ground back end eight or ten inches off the ground,<lb/>
if you were down there while visiting Cuba you no doubt recollect that the<lb/>
land sloped down towards the river. These houses are standing on level ground<lb/>
and raised about 18 inches. Inside of building it would have been impossible<lb/>
to put two beds end to end (not wide enough) so if door had been in center,<lb/>
bed when placed against west wall would have extended more then half way in<lb/>
front of door. I kept tub for ice inside door right hand side going in. Could<lb/>
it be possible buildings have been turned around north end to the west. The<lb/>
ground then would look as level as shown on picture. Whoever fixed up picture<lb/>
No. 1 was a master at distortion, <hi>death house had</hi> one window north, one south,<lb/>
door to east, and seventy five feet south east, he have it placed longside of<lb/>
road. Disinfection plant should be placed 50 feet to the east and 30 feet south<lb/>
<hi>we had 4 tents pitched</hi> between plant and road for men who broke quarantine and<lb/>
a tank 4 1/2 or 5 feet high east of tents full of disinfectant where men had to dip<lb/>
in before undressing. My quarters have one window on each side west, north and<lb/>
south<unclear>,</unclear> door on east leading out on platform between my quarters and plant<unclear>,</unclear> door on<lb/>
west end of plant was single, on east end double, the two windows on west end of<lb/>
plant is correct, because plenty of air was needed when opening chamber even<lb/>
after drawing vacuum there was a strong smell of formaldehyde. There were no<lb/>
windows on east end of building, no door on north side, if there had been, one<lb/>
would have run against disinfection chamber. Picture shows walk from east of<lb/>
building 105 (Gen. Truby Book). There were no walks, but a path starting west<lb/>
of my quarters due south to each of 114<unclear>,</unclear> Y. F. Hospt. building is too far apart,<lb/>
if timber (bridge) had been placed where showing in picture a pile of rocks 4-5<lb/>
feet high would have to be climbed over in order to get to the grounds. There<lb/>
are seven distinct buildings or huts on right side shown in picture 4 on left,<lb/>
but no trees are visible, two big ones, one only about 15 feet from building 105<lb/>
the other about 50 or 60 further east, <hi>south</hi> of road. Even the trees one on each<lb/>
side of railroad cut ought to show if it was a camera picture taken in 1900.<lb/>
Tree on north side was very small but big enough to show. Picture is cleverly<lb/>
made, <hi>but its made</hi>; no camera took the original. <hi>Where the remark (Dr. Ames'<lb/>
quarters) came from I don't know</hi>. <hi>Dr. Ames never stayed but one whole night<lb/>
which was the first night Grayham was with us</hi>. That night Dr. Ames and I carried<lb/>
two bedsteads from 115 which had been used by Cuban itch cases to 116, 115 being<lb/>
littered with paper and rags also had a strong smell of iodine. The Doctors<lb/>
brought down some blankets, that was the only time Dr. Ames stayed the whole<lb/>
night, but he came down sometimes several times during the night. After moving<lb/>
<hi>his quarters to Camp Lazear</hi> he came in every night between land 3 a.m. And as<lb/>
for Ames office there was a field table and a chair there but if Dr. Ames kept<lb/>
any books or papers it was not in 114 or any other building. We had in 114 be-<lb/>
side<del><unclear>s</unclear></del> table and chair a jar of epsom salt and a pocket case with two scalpels<lb/>
and a pair of scissors a telephone was at one time hung in. If Dr. Ames did<lb/>
any writing he must have done it in his room later at <hi>Camp Lazear after he moved<lb/>
there</hi>. I am not certain of exact date but I entered Y. F. Hospt. about 12 days<lb/>
before Major Kean, I say 12 days <hi>Graham was</hi> a very sick man &ldquo;he was the one who<lb/>
had 92 or 94 percent of albumin in his urine&rdquo; and it must havd been at least 12<lb/>
before he got away. So from about <hi>June 10, 1900 to March 2, 1901</hi>, I lived down<lb/>
there it was my home. I have never laid claim to being smart or bright, but I<lb/>
refuse to be considered ignorant, only an ignorant person could have lived down<lb/>
there over eight months without seeing or noticing if there were 4 or 8 buildings.<lb/>
There were four while I was there; what was contemplated or intended, of course,<lb/>
I don't know. We had only one death down there a man from one of the batteries.<lb/>
I can't remember his name. I can take my dying oath that neither Lazear or<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06001132"/>
2<lb/>
Carthwright died down there. The same statement goes for my saying that Dr. Ames'<lb/>
sent me up to help with Carroll at the time he &ldquo;went over the hump&rdquo;. I thought<lb/>
at first he was in his own quarters but but must have been in &ldquo;officers ward&rdquo; if<lb/>
that was the place were Ames was later quartered (place is marked with small<lb/>
inkspot on gable of building 93 in Gen. Truby Book). I am glad I did not take<lb/>
care of Lazear or Carthwright as they both died<unclear>.</unclear> <hi>Where they and Dean were at, I<lb/>
don't know, I've never made a guess</hi>. I've been foolish enough<del>g</del> to think that if<lb/>
Carroll had been allowed to get out of bed and walk around he might have brought<lb/>
on black vomit and gone the way Lazear did. <hi>Without disrespect for Dr. Pinto<lb/>
I must say that he has been talking through his hat</hi>. How did he know what building<lb/>
any of the patients occupied. <hi>He was never across the railroad cut</hi>. Ames was the<lb/>
Doctor and did not need any help as <hi>there never were more than three patients at<lb/>
one time</hi> except when Ames himself was sick and then only for two days<unclear>,</unclear> Pinto was not<lb/>
there then. And it is certain that Dr. Ames would not have allowed any non-immune<lb/>
to come in there if he knew he had a positive case of yellow fever and to be frank<lb/>
I don't think Dr. Pinto would have cared to go in there, not at that time. After<lb/>
three or four had been through the soiled clothing test without getting sick, I<lb/>
think some men would have dared to come in, but not at the time Dr. Pinto claimed<lb/>
he had knowledge of the place. I was in there a non-immune but I know Dr. Ames<lb/>
would not have allowed me to go out of there. He would not even allow me to step<lb/>
out of the ambulance <hi>when he took me out and showed me Camp Lazear where that was<lb/>
built.</hi> Andrus was no sicker than the rest when he came in. His sickness was<lb/>
brought on by not being watched, unlimited water was given and no urine passed, then<lb/>
later when carbuncle developed that gave Andrus another bad spell, why he was not<lb/>
put in with Folk and Forbes I don't know except it was the Doctor's first patient<lb/>
and exclusive one but why he did not put him in 114 and leave the woman where they<lb/>
were I don't know. He was the boss for the time being and did as it pleased him.<lb/>
<hi>I told Gen. Truby in one of my letters that it was Pinto who took Dr. Ames' place<lb/>
that was wrong, but Andrus suggested that name</hi>. If you will take the copies of<lb/>
Andrus' letters that is still in your possession look in lower corner left side<lb/>
third or fourth line from bottom, from word Doctor there is a line drawn with pencil<lb/>
to clean part of paper and the name Pinto is written there is where I got the name<lb/>
Pinto from. Later I received from Hanbury the group picture (Gen. Truby's book<lb/>
page 155). I saw then the mistake Dr. Pinto was a well built heavy set man. Dr. Ames<lb/>
substitute was anemic looking, wearing black full beard. Patients in Y.F. Hospt. did<lb/>
not need any toilet, they were cleaned and when admitted from there on nothing but<lb/>
ice and water two days after fever went down or when temperature had been normal two<lb/>
days they were started on two ounces of milk. They generally left a day or two after<lb/>
getting up<unclear>.</unclear> Your paper Mention<add>s</add> Moran in 115 and Folk in 115, there were 4 patients<lb/>
between Moran and Folks all in 115. I don't know if I heard Dr. Ames say it or if<lb/>
I have dreamed it: &ldquo;Ice and water for a week or ten days and live, or beef <unclear>steak</unclear> and<lb/>
french fry today and die tomorrow.&rdquo; I wish I had kep a day book and marked down<lb/>
names and dates. Things I've actually been doing and things I have seen I remember<lb/>
but what I've heard and read I admit some have slipped my mind. Pictures 2,3,4,<lb/>
are like 1 not photographs. They show walks all over where there wasn't any but<lb/>
the only real layed out walk in the hospital the camera missed, the crushed stone<lb/>
walk between the officers quarters and the wards (See Gen. Truby's book page 76).<lb/>
Five and six are right except for Y.F. Hospt. 8 buildings where it should be 4. I'VE<lb/>
told what I saw and what I did. I have not added or withheld anything. It would-<lb/>
n't do me any good to tell a falsehood because I expect no favor or consideration<lb/>
for work I did, at least not for work between June and December. But after the<lb/>
guinea pigs started to come in that's another thing, I know that Major Reed could<lb/>
have reported success in the work with one less to take soiled clothing test but<lb/>
had to be some one to care for the ones that took sick. I also know that Major Reed<lb/>
would have figured the same way if he had been alive. In Gen. Truby's book page 81<lb/>
it says Lambert was a non-immune and he and other non-immune attendants -- if there<lb/>
were other non-immune attendants why wasn't their names mentioned? The fact is<lb/>
that both <hi>Mrs. Gillen and Lottie Cook were</hi> immunes, that's why they had been hired.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06001133"/>
3<lb/>
They had one patient (Andrus), How they cared for him the letter copies you now<lb/>
have explains better than I can tell. I have tried in Congress for recognition<lb/>
in 1940 both Committees of the House, also the Senate recognized the Justice of<lb/>
my claim but pressure was brought to bear on my Congressman and he let bill lay<lb/>
and die<del>t</del> in Committee. I might try again. Its a shame to have wasted so much<lb/>
paper in saying so little but I have done the best I know.</p>
<p>see<lb/>
<unclear>6/21/46</unclear><lb/>
p 7 &amp; 24</p>
<p><unclear>See</unclear><lb/>
interview
6/21/46<lb/>
<unclear>p 7 &amp; 24</unclear></p>
<p>See<lb/>
<unclear>interview</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>of 6/21/46</unclear><lb/>
p 20</p>
<p>?</p>
<p>Kean<lb/>
<unclear>got back<lb/>
about<lb/>
June 20</unclear></p>
<p>Lazear died<lb/>
<unclear>Sept 25?</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Lambert wasnt available</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>&amp; to Truby</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>But Lambert didn't nurse Lazear Miss Leur's<lb/>
helped nurse him &amp; she says he did die in the<lb/>
Y F huts</unclear></p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Gust E. Lambert</signed>
<seg>
PS: Please return the two thin paper copies of letters, Andrus sent Senators'<lb/>
Lewis and Connelly or Shepperd. Both maps are good, Morgue should be a little<lb/>
further from the road then disinfection plant<unclear>.</unclear> Y.F. Hospt. had at one time been<lb/>
fenced in. 12 or 15 feet from S.E. corner of Building 116 was an 8 foot post<lb/>
with several strands of barb wire. The longest one laying toward La Playa. I<lb/>
suppose Cubans had stolen the rest. I think you, Dr. Hench, I think you will give<lb/>
Ames credit for his excellent work. I think you will mention that he had yellow<lb/>
fever himself (something that has never been shown in print). I liked Dr. Ames,<lb/>
I have been an employee for over 60 years. He was my best boss. I know Ames<lb/>
liked me as a Man. He was a Mason and recommended me as a member of the fraternity!<lb/>
Sergeant Ryan, patient<unclear></unclear> in 115, was a member of committee investigating my fitness<lb/>
for membership and the one why string was used to keep me awake. This information<lb/>
is not for your book. for whom <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
Respt. Lambert<lb/>
Later:<lb/>
Please disregard all mention of Andrus copies when puting letter back in same<lb/>
envelop in which it came I found your personal letter also copies I received<lb/>
from Andrus. I hadn't seen them or noticed when they came I am sorry Doctor<lb/>
that I can't convince you about the number of buildings we had at the Y. F. Hospt.<lb/>
It resolves itself into two things, either I was at that time so stupid and<lb/>
dullwitted that I couldn't tell the difference between four and eight or I would<lb/>
be lying now. To the first I answer, I refuse to be considered to ever having<lb/>
been in that condition, to the second I answer So help me God I am telling the<lb/>
truth, no good could come to me by telling a falsehood or harm to any one else.<lb/>
I am telling just what I saw while living down there between middle of June and<lb/>
March 2nd card 5 is a surveyors map and correct, card 6 is a draftsmans copy,<lb/>
cards 1,2,3,4, <unclear>O</unclear> marked the backs, pardon) is made <unclear><del>u</del>up</unclear> and frauds of camera<lb/>
pictures only, what was there would have showed<unclear>.</unclear> Take hut 113 for example, if<lb/>
entrance had faced toward the Gen. Hospt. it had a toilet either in front or along-<lb/>
side the entrance. There was no toilet, huts 113 and 114 faced away from and build<lb/>
ings 115 and 116 faced toward the Gen. Hospt. All my meals carried down from Miss<lb/>
Lottie and Mrs. Gillen got theirs from their mess. The little diet patients<lb/>
received came from diet kitchen hospt. boys could <unclear>leave</unclear> as soon as dressed<unclear>.</unclear> When any-<lb/>
one was transferred while I was in the service the order was made in triplicate,<lb/>
one kept in place from where he was sent one copy was sent to Washington Adj. Gen.<lb/>
Office which was the permanent record and one copy sent to place where going,<lb/>
Officers I suppose brought their copy with them, men had theirs sent after.<lb/>
Mrs. Ames had the copy given Ames but it was no good except it could be duplicated<lb/>
or verified by one from the Adj. Gen. Office<unclear>.</unclear> You must believe me Doctor when I tell<lb/>
you that attempts have been made since 1929 to get a copy of Gen. order 83 from<lb/>
Washington but without success. Senator <unclear>Shepperd</unclear>, the Congressman before Tho<del>r</del>mason<lb/>
Tho<del>r</del>mason, later Brunby all got the same answers-no such order. I have Ames'<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06001134"/>
(4<lb/>
service record. Its not mentioned. If I stated that Ames was a major in the<lb/>
regular army I made an unforgiveable mistake because Ames could. never have been<lb/>
a regular Army officer. It was not in him. All contract doctors entered the<lb/>
service as A.A.S.V. and attained higher rank by professional ability but the<lb/>
difference between U.S. Officers and U.S.A.V. was as night and day. The feeling<lb/>
of regular army officers toward Vol. officers was nicely expressed in a letter<lb/>
to you &ldquo;copy of which Mrs. Ames showed me&rdquo; Vol. was neither flesh, fish, or salt<lb/>
herring. Gen. Truby a <unclear><del></del></unclear> <add><unclear>sends</unclear></add> to it on page 67 in the case of Gen. Wood it was not<lb/>
age. It was the Vol. and his quick advancement. Maj. Kean was only a Capt. of<lb/>
the regular army at that time he held the rank of Maj. Vol. for reason of better<lb/>
pay or prestige, but he had the rank of regular U.S.A. Capt. for a backing.<lb/>
Dear Dr. Hench:<lb/>
I know you are after the true record. I have given you what I know after living<lb/>
at Quemadas for 15 months, over eight months of the time below railroad out. I<lb/>
don't think I could dictate to a stenographer. If you have occasion to write<lb/>
again please tell girl to use good carbon paper, if original letter, blacker<lb/>
ribbon. Even with two reading glasses one in front of the other I had to guess<lb/>
part of your letter.<lb/>
Very respt. yours.<lb/>
Gust. E. Lambert<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
