<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06001172">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Gustaf E. Lambert] to [Albert E. Truby?], [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lambert, Gustaf E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06001172</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena A.</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Patterson, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Ludlow, William</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Colby, Newell R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Graham, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Gillan, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Lottie</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Winifred</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Reilly [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital No. 1 (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06001172</idno>
<title>Letter from [Gustaf E. Lambert] to [Albert E. Truby?], [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Lambert] answers twenty-one questions dealing with the yellow fever experiments at Camp Lazear. He describes how he assisted with the care of the patients, the work of female nurses, his involvement with the sanitary work, and an incident in which he broke quarantine to get Ames' help with his patient, Andrus.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Letter from [Gustaf E. Lambert] to [Albert E. Truby?], [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06001172"/>
<p>Date of letter <unclear>1__?</unclear></p>
<p>FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1) From what Dr Ames told me<lb/>
yellow fever Hosp. in 1899 was about<lb/>
1/2 mile closer La Playa I came to<lb/>
Quemados in May 1900 and never<lb/>
saw the <unclear>first hosp.</unclear> I was told that<lb/>
the four buildings we used had at one<lb/>
time <unclear>been</unclear> a smalpox <unclear>Hosp'l</unclear>they were</item>
<item>2) old. The two small <unclear>onse</unclear> were 7 by 9<lb/>
the big <unclear>ones</unclear> 10-16</item>
<item>3) Tar Paper</item>
<item>4) The small buildings had no windows,<lb/>
the two bigest, one each; no screen<lb/>
for doors or windows</item>
<item>5) no Sir I have often wished I have<lb/>
had one</item>
<item>6) About 12 feet- About 25 feet from the<lb/>
small to the big one and About 60 feet<lb/>
between the two big <unclear>onse</unclear></item>
<item>7 I would say 200 from the hosp. to<lb/>
the road and 200 from the road to the<lb/>
officers quarters</item>
<item>8) I don't know I was not on his<lb/>
case <hi>Mrs. Warner and the other two</hi><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06001173"/>
2<lb/>
<hi><unclear>immune</unclear> nurses took care of<lb/>
Maj's Carthwright Patterson Edmunds<lb/>
and Dr's Carroll and Lezear</hi> I worked<lb/>
as orderly <unclear>on</unclear> the case of Maj. Edmunds<lb/>
in his home in Quemados</item>
<item>9) I don't know, I think it was<lb/>
the forth night of Dr. Carrols sicknes that<lb/>
Dr Ames came to my room in the<lb/>
disinfection plant and told me to go<lb/>
and <hi>help with Dr Carrol he is bad<lb/>
tonight</hi> it was late because I had<lb/>
taken off my clothes so I dressed and<lb/>
went down to building 3 just as I<lb/>
got inside the door I heard the nurse<lb/>
(not Lena Warner) say, now Dr, you<lb/>
shouldn't do that, you know you<lb/>
should not try to get up, Dr Carrol<lb/>
had his left foot on the floor and the<lb/>
right one half way down and holding<lb/>
himself up on his left arm. I stepped<lb/>
up to the bed took both of his leggs<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06001174"/>
3<lb/>
and put them back in bed then<lb/>
took hold under his arm and laid<lb/>
him back in <unclear>bedd</unclear>he was not<lb/>
unconscious but irrational and in<lb/>
great pain, he tried several times<lb/>
during the night to get up and got<lb/>
angry when restrained Dr Ames<lb/>
did not tell me to go back the<lb/>
next night. I was disinfecting some<lb/>
houses in quemados with a <unclear>port-<lb/>
able</unclear> machine at that time so went<lb/>
back to my work</item>
<item>10) Not at the hospital but he did an<lb/>
autopsy on the only one who died while<lb/>
I was working down there a Sergeant<lb/>
from the battery</item>
<item>11) I don't know</item>
<item>12) " " "</item>
<item>13) yes Sir About Sept 15 Dr Ames<lb/>
came to me and asked me if I would<lb/>
go down and take care of a patient<lb/>
that was coming in I reminded Dr<lb/>
Ames<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06001175"/>
4<lb/>
about having been in quarantine<lb/>
7 1/2 month at N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi>1 during which time<lb/>
I lived in the office building of the<lb/>
yellow fever section. I might just as<lb/>
well tell now how it happened that<lb/>
I landed in that bad place. One morning<lb/>
at roll call Maj. Carter came out and<lb/>
asked if there were any one who<lb/>
would <del><unclear>voloter</unclear></del> volunter to go out<lb/>
on sanitary work, I folishly wispered<lb/>
to the man on my left, I wouldn't be<lb/>

afraid to go if I were detailed, and<lb/>
without a seconds hesitation he stepped<lb/>
forward held up his hand and said,<lb/>
Maj. here is a guy who wants to go<lb/>
Maj. Carter asked me if I were afraid<lb/>
of yellow fever I said no (but I am<lb/>
afraid I did not tell the truth) I was<lb/>
then told to report to Dr Ames. I did<lb/>
so and was taken down to the palace<lb/>
where I looked after the cleaning gang,<lb/>
scraping all walls and ceilings then<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06001176"/>
5<lb/>
spraying, floors were washed with<lb/>
a 50-50 <unclear>muriatic</unclear> acid and water.<lb/>
In late fall when yellow fever brook<lb/>
out at headquarters Dr Ames said<lb/>
now I'll see if you are afraid of<lb/>
yellow fever, he gave me a list of<lb/>
things needed and told me to go<lb/>
back to the hosp present the list to<lb/>
Maj. Carter for approval and then go<lb/>
to ware house and bring the things<lb/>
over to the yellow fever section I<lb/>
was hardly ready before ambulance<lb/>
drove in with Gen. Brooks Secretary<lb/>
Dr Ames got a civilian from<lb/>
New Orleans to come in with<lb/>
us, we had 6 or 7 cases, later I was<lb/>
sent over to Pyrotecnia to take care<lb/>
of an officer I am not certain but<lb/>
it seems to me the name was<lb/>
Ludlow. Later I was sent to the same<lb/>
place to care for Col. O'Reilly who<lb/>
later became Surg General but he<lb/>
he did not have yellow fever only suspect<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06001177"/>
6<lb/>
sick only 3 or 4 day's after x-mass<lb/>
I got typhoid fever when recovered<lb/>
April 1900<lb/>
I was given 30 day's furlough and<lb/>
when I got back was sent out to<lb/>
Quemados, day after reporting was<lb/>
sent downtown to learn disinfecting<lb/>
first on the <unclear>wharf</unclear> later on the big<lb/>
barge that is how I louded in the<lb/>
disinfection plant in Quemados</item>
<item>14) Four day's after Commissary<lb/>
Sergeant Reilly came in they<lb/>
brought in Colby <unclear>H.C.</unclear> man then<lb/>
I asked Dr Ames if he couldn't<lb/>
get some ne to help next day<lb/>
the Doctor came down with a<lb/>
<unclear>man</unclear> I never saw before the Doctor<lb/>
also brought a bottle of champagne<lb/>
for Reilly <unclear>when</unclear>Dr Ames left<lb/>
he told me to come outside as<lb/>
there was something he wanted<lb/>
to tell me when I got inside<lb/>
the new man had put the screw top<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06001178"/>
7<lb/>
in the bottle and drawn<lb/>
nearly a half glass of wine and<lb/>
was sampling it I tore the glass<lb/>
out off his hand and threw wine<lb/>
on the floor Reilly didn't say a<lb/>
word but Colby and the new man<lb/>
got in an argument so Colby got<lb/>
out of <unclear>bedd</unclear>and knocked him<lb/>
down after I got Colby to <unclear>bedd</unclear>I<lb/>
threw out my <del>my</del> assistant and<lb/>
told him to stay out When Dr Ames<lb/>
came down again I told what has<lb/>
happened and that I would manage<lb/>
alone, I thought Dr Ames would<lb/>
keep Colby after he got well but he<lb/>
drank and Dr Ames wouldn't have<lb/>
anyone around that used liqueur</item><lb/>
<item>15) The first patient down there was<lb/>
Packmaster <unclear>Grayham</unclear>, the same night<lb/>
his wife came in, a day or two<lb/>
after they left. Maj. Kean came in, the<lb/>
day after Capt Hepburn came<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06001179"/>
8<lb/>
the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> patient was Mrs Blont or<lb/>
Blunt wife of a Capt in 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <del><unclear>Col</unclear></del> <unclear>Cav.</unclear><lb/>
she was in only two day's a suspect,<lb/>
but her husband complained because<lb/>
there was a man taking care of his<lb/>
wife, his kick must have carried weight<lb/>
because Maj. Stark or some one sent <unclear>to</unclear><lb/>
new Orleans after two immune<lb/>
women who would care for lady patients<lb/>
if we had any more, we never had,<lb/>
so Dr Ames never put Mrs Gillen or<lb/>
<unclear>Lattie.</unclear> to work Mrs Gillen had been<lb/>
a cook and Lattie an office worker<lb/>
When Dr Ames took sick Dr Pinto took his<lb/>
place, two day's later Andrus came in<lb/>
and Dr Pinto made the women move in<lb/>
to building 1, they used to have 3, but<lb/>
Andrus was put in 3, I had Folks and<lb/>
Forbes in 4 and Dr Ames in 2 so I<lb/>
was glad that Dr Pinto put <unclear>them</unclear> to work,<lb/>
I can't remember if it was the same<lb/>
day, or the day after Dr Ames was<lb/>
moved up to the Hosp. and given a<lb/>
room and Miss <unclear>Vinifred</unclear> Lewis took<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06001180"/>
9<lb/>
care off him, the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> day Andrus<lb/>
were sick Mrs Gillen came over<lb/>
and asked me to come over and<lb/>
help her tie Andrus to the bed<lb/>
because he acted horribly I went<lb/>
with her and Andrus was laying<lb/>
across the bed naked feet on one<lb/>
side and arms on the other I put<lb/>
him back in <unclear>bedd</unclear>and covered him<lb/>
up I asked what the trouble was but<lb/>
he couldn't answer only cried and<lb/>
<unclear>groned</unclear> as if in pain I asked Mrs<lb/>
Gillen if the Dr had seen him but<lb/>
the Dr had not been in that day it was<lb/>
2. P. M. I knew he had not been to see<lb/>
my patients Andrus had been drinking<lb/>
plenty of water Mrs Gillen said but<lb/>
when I looked on the notes he had<lb/>
not passed any urine for over eight<lb/>
hours I asked Mrs Gillen if she had<lb/>
tried to catherize him she said &ldquo;oh<lb/>
I couldn't do that&rdquo; so I went over after<lb/>
what I needed and drew 710. c. c. from<lb/>
him, I went back at 7. P. M. and helped<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06001181"/>
10<lb/>
him, went back again at 12 M. N.<lb/>
but he was asleep and did not wake<lb/>
him, at 3 A. M. or there about he urinated<lb/>
without help. The <unclear>fift</unclear> day I was again<lb/>
asked to come over I was told that there<lb/>
was nothing the matter with Andrus<lb/>
he was simply cranky, the boy couldn't<lb/>
tell me his troubles he only cried, but<lb/>
he was in great pain I could see that<lb/>
so I brook quarrantine and <unclear>race</unclear> up to see<lb/>
Dr Ames and told him that Andrus was<lb/>
very sick and that Dr Pinto had not been<lb/>
down there since the previous morning I<lb/>
tried to tell the best I knew how he<lb/>
acted but I couldn't described well<lb/>
enough for the Dr. to diagnose his<lb/>
trouble. I knew if Dr Ames could come<lb/>
down Andrus would be all right so<lb/>
I asked Dr Ames if there wasn't <unclear>some</unclear><lb/>
way he could come down, he said<lb/>
I'm sick in <unclear>bed</unclear> myself, I suggested<lb/>
that he let me get help and we would<lb/>
carry him down to which he agreed<lb/>
I can't remember if it was M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Carthy<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06001182"/>
11<lb/>
or <unclear>Fanning</unclear> I got hold of but he<lb/>
came along and we went in and<lb/>
picked up the bed and started out<lb/>
when Miss Lewis came in (she was<lb/>
out while I spoke to Dr Ames) she tried<lb/>
to stop us so she could ask Maj. Stark<lb/>
but we kept going Dr Ames wouldnt<lb/>
let us walk over the <unclear>litle</unclear> bridge so<lb/>
went around, the railroad cut M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Carthy<lb/>
put his end of <unclear>bedd</unclear>inside of door I then<lb/>
pushed Dr. Ames alongside of Andrus, the Dr.<lb/>
found a carbuncle in his rectum (an ugly<lb/>
looking thing) I brought a scalpel and<lb/>
Dr Ames cut it, after geting the dirt out the<lb/>
boy felt at ease. Dr Ames rested a <unclear>litle</unclear> and<lb/>
we took <add>him</add> back. (Please read affidavit Miss<lb/>
Lewis sent upon request) Maj Stark was<lb/>
waiting! Miss Lewis say's Maj Stark was not<lb/>
pleased no because for about 5 minutes<lb/>
I got the worst calling down I ever had<lb/>
for taking his patient out visiting<lb/>
then he chased me out and <unclear>told</unclear> me<lb/>
to get down to where I belonged.<lb/>
The Majors anger was only temporary I<lb/>
was the last person he operated on at<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06001183"/>
12<lb/>
quemados he did that after he were<lb/>
relieved. he operated on me at 10 A. M.<lb/>
and left at one P. M. I did not have<lb/>
a chance to thank him for his kindness<lb/>
I have a letter from the War Dept stating<lb/>
that Maj. Stark commended me to the<lb/>
surg. Gen. Office for untiring attention<lb/>
to duty while nursing yellow fever at<lb/>
quemados I think it would have been</item>
<item><p>15) been better for all <unclear>concerned</unclear>if Gillen and<lb/>
<unclear>Latties<lb/>
hasnt</unclear> been there, they were the only females<lb/>
down there</p>
<p><del>15)</del> No Sir! If I had been I would have<lb/>
had no posible re<add>a</add>son to look for recognition</p></item>
<item>16) No Sir</item>
<item>17) yellow fever: Dr Ames told me the same<lb/>
at N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 He did not say that he had never had<lb/>
yellow fever but that he had handled so much<lb/>
of it at New Orleans and never got sick<lb/>
so he must be immune. After all the<lb/>
cases we had at N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 and one autopsy<lb/>
I did on a body brought in from the<lb/>
outside at N<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 1 Dr Ames told me that<lb/>
I must be an immune <unclear>too</unclear>as I did not<lb/>
get sick Everytime Maj. Reed came<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06001184"/>
Ac<lb/>
<unclear>IN to L</unclear><lb/>
13<lb/>
in he used to ask me how do you<lb/>
feel Lambert I think he expected me<lb/>
to get the fever</item>
<item>18) <unclear>I'n</unclear> 1914<lb/>
<del>19)</del> In Guatamala, I think Mrs Ames<lb/>
said he was Doctor for the <unclear>Am</unclear> fruit <unclear>be</unclear><lb/>
his wife and two children was down<lb/>
there with him Mrs Ames and children<lb/>
<del><unclear>not</unclear></del> went back home she was going<lb/>
to have her third baby when she<lb/>
arrived in New Orleans she received<lb/>
a telegram telling her the Doctor died<lb/>
two day's after she left. Black fever<lb/>
she called it</item>
<item>19) No Sir - no Sir</item>
<item>20) Only one night on Dr Carrolls case</item>
<item>21) <hi>Mrs Warner</hi> was never accross the rail<lb/>
road cut from the middle of sept to the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi><lb/>
of march when I sent everything up to<lb/>
the disinfection plant. <hi>I don't know if<lb/>
she nursed Dr Lezear but if she did small<lb/>
credit to her,</hi> Dr Ames told me Dr Lezear<lb/>
had been out off <unclear>bedd</unclear>when he was real<lb/>
sick they did not watch him properly</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
