<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06001084">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, April 5, 1954</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06001084</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1954-04-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lambert, Gustaf E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Carroll, Mrs. George</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Second Division Hospital, 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Army Corps (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1954-04-05">April 5, 1954</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06001084</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, April 5, 1954</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench has recently found four photographs in trunks belonging to the daughter-in-law of James Carroll. He would like Lambert's help in identifying buildings and people in the photographs.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1954-04-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, April 5, 1954</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06001084"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1954-04-05">April 5, 1954</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Gust E. Lambert<lb/>
17092 Lincoln Street<lb/>
Hazel Crest, Illinois<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Lambert:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sorry to hear that you have been ill but glad indeed that you are re-<lb/>
covering. I do not want to ask you to make a trip into town from a Chicago<lb/>
suburb just after you are recovered from pneumonia. Perhaps you can help me<lb/>
at the moment by correspondence.</p>
<p>I shall be in Chicago three different days. I shall be at the Conrad<lb/>
Hilton Hotel just for the day, Sunday, April 4; again just for the day on<lb/>
Friday, April 9 and on these two days I will be much too busy at medical<lb/>
meetings. But I shall be returning through Chicago with my 11-year old<lb/>
boy from the east on Thursday, April 15 and would certainly like to see<lb/>
you then if it can be arranged. If, by then, you are feeling well enough,<lb/>
you might come to town and join me for lunch perhaps or, if you are not<lb/>
feeling well and I can do it, I will come to see you; however as I say,<lb/>
I will have my boy with me and will have to take care of him.</p>
<p>Mrs. George Carroll, daughter-in-law of Doctor Carroll, recently permitted<lb/>
me to go through some old trunks. I found therein some very interesting<lb/>
material, especially four photographs, the likes of which I have not seen<lb/>
before. Two of them I am especially anxious for you to see. Two of these<lb/>
photographs were not identified. One was identified correctly and another<lb/>
one was wrongly identified. I am especially anxious for you to see these.</p>
<p>The one, marked on the back, &ldquo;A&rdquo;, is, I am positive, the yellow fever huts<lb/>
just across the railroad track from the post hospital. I have marked it up<lb/>
with ink.</p>
<p>Let us proceed with the objects from right to left. &ldquo;A&rdquo; is undoubtedly the<lb/>
little bridge across the LaPlaya railroad tracks. If so, &ldquo;K&rdquo; must be Building<lb/>
No. 115 as indicated on the map of the post hospital grounds facing page 51<lb/>
of General Truby's book, a copy of which I think you have; and &ldquo;L&rdquo; is un-<lb/>
doubtedly Building No. 117. I know that you have had trouble with your<lb/>
eyesight but I hope that with a magnifying glass you can examine this photo-<lb/>
graph carefully.</p>
<p>According to a model of the post hospital and the yellow fever huts made years<lb/>
ago by Alfonso Perez, which model is still at Carlisle Barracks, the bridge<lb/>
across the railroad track was between the two rows of yellow fever huts but<lb/>
nearer the row 114-120. I enclose a photograph of this model which I have<lb/>
cut in half as when it was set up at Carlisle Barracks for the purposes of<lb/>
this photograph, they set it up wrong. Therefore I have detached the yellow<lb/>
fever huts. railroad track and bridge - in other words, the second section of<lb/>
this model (it was on two separate boards). Although this model shows all<lb/>
the buildings very crowded together, nevertheless I am amazed to find how<lb/>
accurate the model is, as indicated by various photographs of these dif-<lb/>
ferent buildings. It is on the basis of this model that I have identified<lb/>
Building K as yellow fever hut No. 115 and Building L as yellow fever hut No. 117,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06001085"/>
Lambert<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 5, 1954<lb/>
Now, will you please consult the map on page 51 of General Truby's book.<lb/>
A being the bridge, B, in my opinion, is Building No. 105, the warehouse; C is<lb/>
Building 102; D (just behind E although it looks as if it might be part of E)<lb/>
is probably Building 101 and E is Building 111 with F, a little unmarked building,<lb/>
just to the left of it. In other words, E and F must be the disinfecting plant<lb/>
and your sleeping quarters. I wonder if you have ever seen this before and if<lb/>
you want one, I shall have another one made for you, enlarged. G, a dark building<lb/>
behind a white tent, is probably Building No. 99; H is Building 93. &ldquo;I&rdquo; would<lb/>
be yellow fever hut No. 113 and the little building on the horizon between the<lb/>
yellow fever huts 113 and 115, would probably be Building No. 96. I am most<lb/>
anxious for you to help me identify this.</p>
<p>Now for the people. There are at least nine and possibly two more in the group.<lb/>
I wonder if you could help me identify them. You will note that one man is in<lb/>
white uniform and I strongly suspect that's you. It must have been some oc-<lb/>
casion when you had 8 or more visitors at once and I suspect that it is a<lb/>
photograph taken when part of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Board took the members<lb/>
of the Havana Yellow Fever Board to see some of the experimental cases. It<lb/>
looks like a pretty formal occasion. At least it looks to me as if Figure No. 9<lb/>
has on a high silk hat. I am wondering if figure 3, 7 or 8 might be Walter Reed.<lb/>
Behind figure No. 1 in the white uniform (which I hope is you) you will see<lb/>
one man standing on the ground, Figure No. 2, and just to the right of the<lb/>
figure in which there may or may not be shown part of the body of someone just<lb/>
getting out of the rear of the doherty wagon. I am wondering if the tall<lb/>
figure, No. 4, in what looks like a rumpled uniform, might be Doctor Carroll<lb/>
and between him and figure No. 5, the stooping man in the middle wagon, I<lb/>
think one sees the back of the driver</p>
<p>Photo B. For comparison <unclear>with</unclear> Photo A, I am sending you Photograph B which I<lb/>
think I showed you some years ago. It is a newspaper photograph from a<lb/>
Springfield, Ohio, paper of April 11, 1905, a <unclear>photograph with</unclear> the words, &ldquo;Wards<lb/>
of the Isolation Yellow Fever Hospital, Columbia Barracks, Havana, Cuba.&rdquo; This<lb/>
photograph is pasted, with the clipping, in Mrs. Walter Reed's own scrapbook<lb/>
about her husband. Until seeing Mrs. Carroll's Photograph A, I could not be<lb/>
certain which of the yellow fever huts were in Photograph B, but viewing both<lb/>
pictures with a hand lens, I now believe that the huts in Photograph B are<lb/>
not the same as those in Photograph A. I suspect strongly that in Photograph B<lb/>
the hut on the right is No. 118, the one in the center is No. 116 and the little<lb/>
one on the left by the tree is No. 114. Now look at the horizon on the ex-<lb/>
treme left of this little newspaper photograph and you will see that something<lb/>
rises toward the left at an angle. Looking at the bridge on the extreme right<lb/>
in Photograph A, I have a strong suspicion now that this little angulation on<lb/>
the horizon on the left of Photograph B is the end of the bridge, and that if<lb/>
one holds Photograph B on the right next to photograph A, one has now two<lb/>
photographs showing the two different rows of huts, although neither photo-<lb/>
graph shows huts Nos. 119 and 120.</p>
<p>Another reason why I think the little building in the middle of Photograph B<lb/>
is not the same as the one in the middle of Photograph A (which I have marked<lb/>
Building K) is that in the front of the center building, Photograph B, there<lb/>
are on either side of the door two white cross-boards extending from the ground<lb/>
to the flooring and the building seems to be about as far off the ground at<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06001086"/>
Lambert<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
April 5, 1954<lb/>
its rear as it is at the front but comparing this with the center building<lb/>
(K), Photograph A, they don't quite look alike. First of all, there seems<lb/>
to be a different slope to the ground so that the rear of Building K is<lb/>
nearer the ground than the front. Furthermore, on the left of the door<lb/>
of Building K only one white bar can be seen from ground to floor and no cross<lb/>
bar. Unfortunately the comparable boards on the right of the door are hidden<lb/>
by the barrels.</p>
<p>So much for Photographs A and B but please compare them with Photographs C-1<lb/>
and C-2, which is the model which I have cut in half because the two dif-<lb/>
ferent sections of the model (on two different boards) were put together<lb/>
wrong by the photographer.</p>
<p>Now, please examine Photograph D. Mrs. Carroll loaned me this and on the back<lb/>
was written, &ldquo;Laboratory of Camp Lazear, property of Mrs. James Carroll.&rdquo; The<lb/>
writing is not that of Doctor Carroll. Now, there was no actual laboratory at<lb/>
Camp Lazear. There was a little mosquito laboratory attached to the rear of<lb/>
Building No. 2 and we know what that building looked like. Therefore this<lb/>
photograph is wrongly identified and I am sure it represents the laboratory, not<lb/>
at Camp Lazear, but at the post hospital at Camp Columbia. If so, it should be<lb/>
Building No. 89. (It is shown in Truby's book, page 51 and when you look at<lb/>
the Perez model of Building No. 89, it is identical in shape with the building<lb/>
in this photograph). Please note the little front door, the sloping roof, the<lb/>
cupola and, most important, in the rear an attachment which seems to be broken<lb/>
in the middle and rises to two different levels. With a hand lens you can see<lb/>
that Building No. 89 on the Perez model has two latticed windows, and that<lb/>
is exactly what shows in the rear on Photograph D. I think, therefore, this is<lb/>
the first photograph I have ever found of Walter Reed's laboratory at the post<lb/>
hospital at Camp Columbia. There seems to be a little pen or fenced-in area<lb/>
just beneath the last window on the right and on the horizon just above this<lb/>
there appears another distant building. Looking at the maps of Camp Columbia<lb/>
(a larger map than shown as Figure 10 of Truby's book) I identified it as<lb/>
one of the non-medical buildings of Camp Columbia.</p>
<p>One of the few things that I have never been able to agree on with General<lb/>
Truby was his identification of Figure 19 as Walter Reed's laboratory. I<lb/>
enclose the complete photograph from which Figure 19 was taken - a photograph<lb/>
of the Second Division Hospital, 7th Army Corps, Camp Columbia, April 1899,<lb/>
but if one looks on the horizon to the rear and to the right of this little<lb/>
center building, (labelled by General Truby as the surgery or Reed's labora-<lb/>
tory) one can see definitely the profile of General Lee's headquarters. I<lb/>
have carefully drawn two or three reconstructions and not one of them permits<lb/>
me to conclude that this building faced the same direction as Building No. 89,<lb/>
page 51. That is why I have never accepted it. General Truby thought that<lb/>
later it might have been turned on its axis, &ldquo;a simple thing to do,&rdquo; but why<lb/>
would anyone ask to have a building turned on its axis? Therefore, I am con-<lb/>
vinced all the more that Figure 19 (opposite page 87,), General Truby's book,<lb/>
was wrongly identified and that at long last we have found a photograph of<lb/>
Walter Reed's laboratory, namely Photograph B.</p>
<p>Mr. Lambert, were you at Camp Lazear at any time? Mrs. Carroll loaned me<lb/>
two additional photographs taken at Camp Lazear. One is an excellent one<lb/>
of the fomites Building No. 1, a better one than I have ever seen before,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06001087"/>
Lambert<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
April 5, 1954<lb/>
The other is even more important. It is the first photograph of Camp<lb/>
Lazear taken in the opposite direction of every other photograph I have ever<lb/>
seen. It has always puzzled me when visiting Camp Lazear as it is today,<lb/>
to note the irregularity of the terrain as compared to the apparent flat-<lb/>
ness of the old Army photographs of Camp Lazear. Of course Reed himself<lb/>
spoke of the &ldquo;little valley&rdquo; between Buildings One and Two and one old<lb/>
Army photograph does show this depression readily, but I have no doubt<lb/>
that when you visited Camp Lazear you were puzzled by the rough terrain.<lb/>
Of course a great amount of the roughness is due to the development, over<lb/>
the last 50 years or so, of the extensive quarries. This photograph shows<lb/>
the existence of the &ldquo;little Valley&rdquo; between Buildings One and Two, so rough<lb/>
that it does become quite irregular and almost hilly. That is why this one<lb/>
photograph pleases me so much, because it shows this irregularity of the<lb/>
land and, in addition, gives us another not-too-clear view of the unidentified<lb/>
building or ruins that were near Building No. 2, which are shown in one of<lb/>
the Army photographs, and the remnants of the ruins of which are still there<lb/>
even though Building No. 2 is gone. As I don't believe you were at Camp<lb/>
Lazear, I will not send you these two now, but if you were at Camp Lazear,<lb/>
I will bring them along and we can discuss them, perhaps in a couple of<lb/>
weeks (April 15) if I have the opportunity of visiting you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
