<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06001037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on Gustaf E. Lambert, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [November 1946]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06001037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Springer, Adolph F.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Driscoll, Daniel L.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McIntosh (Tex.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-00">[November 1946]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06001037</idno>
<title>Notes on Gustaf E. Lambert, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [November 1946]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean comments on Lambert's possible inclusion on the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-11-00">
<head>Notes on Gustaf E. Lambert, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [November 1946]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06001037"/>
<p>FROM GEN<unclear>.</unclear> J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>Memorandum in re<lb/>
The Statement of Gustaf E. Lambert, one time <unclear>Pvt. H. C.</unclear> at<lb/>
Columbia Bks. Cuba-</p>
<p>It is quite natural for a man who has done his duty<lb/>
bravely and faithfully in a difficult and dangerous<lb/>
situation, when he sees other men who had acted their<lb/>
parts, rewarded, while he is commended only but gets<lb/>
us substantial reward, is left out <add>to <unclear>have a grievance.</unclear></add> If he <unclear>broods</unclear> over it, the<lb/>
situation becomes intolerable and he loses sight of the<lb/>
essential conditions of such rewards- Facts are <unclear>forgitten</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>or</unclear> twisted out of true relation and he feels that an injustice<lb/>
has been done him- Such <unclear>seems</unclear> to be the case with Mr Lambert.<lb/>
When Congress in 1929 passed a bill giving pensions &amp; medals<lb/>
to the list of men who had been instrumental in the Reed<lb/>
demonstration of the agency of the mosquito in transmitting yellow<lb/>
fever the list was prepared for the H R committee by the<lb/>
Surgeon General of the Army after a consultation with Gen<lb/>
Kean and several of his assistants- Walter Reed and<lb/>
the members of his Board, the nine men who <unclear>underwent</unclear><lb/>
the very repulsive <unclear>fomites</unclear> experiments and the American<lb/>
volunteers who suffered attacks of yellow fever from experiments<lb/>
with infected mosquitoes &amp; blood <unclear>injections</unclear> were included- But<lb/>
it was realized that doctors and nurses who exposed themselves<lb/>
in the care of yellow fever cases in the line of duty should<lb/>
not be included in the list, however meritorious <unclear>their</unclear><lb/>
services had been- The reason was obvious: there would<lb/>
have been no limit to such a list-</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06001038"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>The object of the legislation was to reward <unclear>those</unclear> who actively<lb/>
participated in the experimental work- Those who cared for<lb/>
the sick or disinfected their clothes as a measure of routine<lb/>
sanitation were not included- These conditions excluded<lb/>
Dr. Roger Post Ames, and Privates Lambert, Springer and a<lb/>
number of others, who sought by special legislation to<lb/>
have their names placed on the Yellow Fever Roll of<lb/>
Honor- No applicant who was bitten but not infected was<lb/>
ever included, nor any man whose exposure was not gov-<lb/>
erned by the strict limitations of quarantine <unclear>-</unclear> and scientific <unclear>control.</unclear><lb/>
The efforts to disregard these necessary limitations have been<lb/>
numerous and some of them absurd, as in the case of a<lb/>
New York member of the H. R. who proposed as an additional<lb/>
member of the Roll of Honor an estimable doctor who<lb/>
had never been connected in any way with the <unclear>work</unclear> of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board, but had been on duty at Camp <unclear>Mon-<lb/>
tock on Long</unclear> Island treating the returning soldiers of the<lb/>
Santiago Campaign in 1898-</p>
<p>So much for the claims put forward in this statement<lb/>
of Gustaf Lambert, which seem worthy of a serious answer-<lb/>
The statement is however clouded by numerous errors and<lb/>
misstatements of which I will only notice a few, the object<lb/>
of which is not to advance the claim of the writer but to<lb/>
discredit me- I <hi>became ill of yellow</hi> fever before the Reed<lb/>
Board arrived in Cuba, namely June 21, 1900- and<lb/>
<hi>was treated in <del>the</del> a small <unclear>hut</unclear> in Yellow Fever section</hi> of<lb/>
the <hi>Post Hospital</hi> at Columbia Barracks, His account of<lb/>
my conversation and behavior is, as I recollect, without any<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06001039"/>
3<lb/>
foundation in fact- I have never expressed nor even <unclear>felt</unclear><lb/>
any dissatisfaction with my treatment during my illness-<lb/>
I certainly did not ask to have Lambert relieved from care<lb/>
of me and certainly did not have him sent away from<lb/>
Columbia Bks- He stated that he was sent away from<lb/>
Columbia Bks <unclear>about</unclear> the end of August 1901- But I ceased<lb/>
to be Chief Surgeon where Gen Fitzhugh Lee's Dept. was abolished about<lb/>
Nov. 15, 1900 and <add>I</add> went to duty of Gen. Wood's staff in May 1901<lb/>
so I had no connection whatever with movements of <unclear>Personnel</unclear><lb/>
at Columbia Bks after the latter date- I am equally innocent<lb/>
of moving Dr. Ames away from Columbia Bks. In fact<lb/>
my impression has been that he remained there until he<lb/>
was sent by War Dept Order to Fort M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intosh Texas-<lb/>
I has always entirely approved of his professional care of<lb/>
me and entertained him at my house-</p>
<p>As regards his army record I know of nothing to his discredit<lb/>
except the experimental <unclear>inpection</unclear> of Private Daniel <unclear>L. Dris-</unclear><lb/>
coll Co. F. 26 Inf at Fort M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Intosh Texas Nov. 9, 1903 by means<lb/>
of an infected mosquito- This did <add>not</add> advance in my way scientific<lb/>
knowledge of an already established fact, while it endan-<lb/>
gered a soldier's life and resulted in his permanent dis-<lb/>
ability and discharge from the service- It was not not<lb/>
however held against his claim to be included on the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Roll of Honor, for he never so far as I know ever made<lb/>
any such claim- Such a claim was made after his death by his<lb/>
widow but was disapproved by the Surgeon General of the Army<lb/>
on the ground that he had not become elegible, having been <unclear>neither</unclear><lb/>
a member of the Yellow Fever Board nor having been a case for<lb/>
experiment by the Board- Of course I never was Surgeon General or<lb/>
Acting Surgeon General of the Army nor did I have any personal<lb/>
prejudice against Dr. <unclear>Ames-,</unclear></p>
<closer>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
