<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06013001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Manuscript fragment: My Date with Walter Reed and Yellow Jack, by John J. Moran, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06013001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship">YES</term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Moran, Elida</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Pew, J. Howard</name>
<name type="person">Cespedes, Carlos Manuel</name>
<name type="person">Batista y Zaldivar, Fulgencio</name>
<name type="person">Grau San Martin, Ramon</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney</name>
<name type="person">Stewart, james</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Pogliotti, Luis</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Arlington National Cemetery, Arlington (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Goethals, George Washington</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Venezuela</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Quinta San Jose, Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Zunzunegui, Julian</name>
<name type="place">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="place">Hall of Fame, New York University, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>279 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06013001</idno>
<title>Manuscript fragment: My Date with Walter Reed and Yellow Jack, by John J. Moran, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This partial manuscript of Moran's autobiography describes his early life, military career, service as a sanitary inspector under Gorgas in Panama, marriage, and business ventures. He discusses his relationship with Hench and their search for the actual site of Camp Lazear, as well as the difficulties stemming from the Reed-Finlay controversy. The section of the draft covering the yellow fever experiments is missing.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Manuscript fragment: My Date with Walter Reed and Yellow Jack, by John J. Moran, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06013001"/>
<p><hi>MY DATE WITH WALTER REED<lb/>
AND<lb/>
&ldquo;YELLOW JACK&rdquo;</hi></p>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
Army Medical Museum and Library,<lb/>
WASHINGTON.</p>
<p>This is to certify that the bearer, Mr. John J. Moran, is a<lb/>
man of excellent habits and can be implicitly entrusted to perform<lb/>
whatever duty may be assigned him. He was in my employment for<lb/>
several months, as clerk and typewriter, and during this time per-<lb/>
formed his duties in the most satisfactory and painstaking manner.<lb/>
A man who volunteered, as he did, without hope of any pecuniary<lb/>
reward, but solely in the interests of humanity and medical science,<lb/>
to enter a building purposely infected with yellow fever, and there-<lb/>
by contracted an attack of the disease, should need no word of re-<lb/>
commendation from any one.</p>
<p>I feel confident, therefore, that he will give entire satis-<lb/>
faction to any one who may give him employment.</p>
<p>WALTER REED<lb/>
Surg., U. S. A.</p>
<p>Feb. 20, 1901.</p>
<p>As it was to turn out, Major Reed was leaving Cuba forever and, as fortune had<lb/>
it, with him enroute to New York were John R. Kissinger and I, his first two &ldquo;guinea<lb/>
pigs&rdquo;, Kissinger being on furlough while my immediate destination was Salem, N. J.</p>
<p>Our ship was the SS &ldquo;MORRO CASTLE&rdquo; of that day, a small vessel of the WARD LINE<lb/>
fleet. Before we lost sight of Havana we were ploughing into a choppy sea, increasing<lb/>
in intensity as we approached Cape Hatteras. As we rounded Hatteras our little steam-<lb/>
er pitched and rolled so that those who were not &ldquo;good sailors&rdquo; took to their cabins<lb/>
and remained there until the following day. It so happened that I did not miss a<lb/>
meal, much to the surprise and admiration of my table steward. I suspected that<lb/>
Major Reed was a little &ldquo;under the weather&rdquo; but I took care not to inquire when he<lb/>
appeared on deck, knowing that most people who suffer from seasickness prefer to hide<lb/>
that weakness, which is not a weakness at all but a matter in which a certain nerve<lb/>
plays an involuntary part.</p>
<p>As we were approaching New York Harbor, Major Reed invited me to follow him to<lb/>
the ship's saloon where he sat down before a writing desk while I took a seat opposite<lb/>
him. He then handed me the above letter, written in his own legible hand, saying &ldquo;I<lb/>
should have given you this letter before leaving Havana, but in my hurry to wind up<lb/>
my affairs in Cuba, and return to Washington, I forgot it. It may be of use to you<lb/>
some day&rdquo;. After thanking him, I read and re-read the letter. My admiration for him<lb/>
bordered on hero worship, hence my pride in receiving such a letter of commendation<lb/>
from him.</p>
<p>After three years in the army and seven months as a field clerk, I was returning<lb/>
to the States bound for other adventures. As I said good bye to Major Reed I didn't<lb/>
realize of course that I was never to see him again. I'd seen him near and far during<lb/>
the previous six months. I had volunteered to let him produce in me experimental<lb/>
yellow fever. This he had done by means of a &ldquo;special experiment&rdquo; which he reserved<lb/>
for me, and so far as I was concerned the event was an incident of the past. But it<lb/>
was an event which, as Reed himself told, might have ended my career at the age of<lb/>
24. It didn't end it but, in one way or another it influenced notably the rest of<lb/>
my life which began on <hi>March 15, 1876.</hi></p>
<pb n="2" id="f06013002"/>
<p>-- 2 --</p>
<p>I was born in the village of Cloughbrack, Galway County, Ireland, on the shores<lb/>
of Lough Mask, the youngest of three sons and two daughters, my parents being tenants<lb/>
of the absentee land owner and titled Lord Ardilaun, also the owner of the breweries<lb/>
which manufactured the the well-known beverage &ldquo;Guiness' Stout&rdquo;. In order to make<lb/>
both ends meet my parents, in common with those of our village, had to work late and<lb/>
early in order to pay the rent or else face eviction at the hands of the &ldquo;landlord's&rdquo;<lb/>
merciless agent. Every other year my father would cross over to England to work in<lb/>
one of the steel mills, helping out with remittances to pay the rent and to purchase<lb/>
fertilizers without which our crops of potatoes and grain would have been miserable<lb/>
failures. Even with all this toil and effort little or nothing could be laid by for<lb/>
a rainy day. Small wonder therefore that my brother and two sisters broke away from<lb/>
such a life of slavery, as they became of age, by emigrating to that Land of Promise<lb/>
and haven for the down-trodden of all nations, known simply as &ldquo;America&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The first to come to the United States was my sister Nancy, followed by Katie<lb/>
and my brother Martin. They were aided by two uncles on my mother's side who had<lb/>
settled down in Youngstown, Ohio, many years before. They furnished the &ldquo;passage<lb/>
money&rdquo;, later on to be paid back at the leisure of the recipients, a very common<lb/>
practice in Ireland in that day and generation when her sons were forced to emigrate<lb/>
or starve to death. It was an endless chain arrangement, so to speak. With their<lb/>
departure, we were two, my brother Michael and myself. Martin wanted us all to come<lb/>
to the United States but my parents considered themselves too old to start life anew<lb/>
in a distant land and in a world unknown to them. They would remain in Ireland for<lb/>
the rest of their days, watching with sorrow the departure, one by one, of their off-<lb/>
spring. But such was the tragedy of those <unclear>days for the enslaved</unclear> sons of the Emerald<lb/>
Isle, conquered but not absorbed by the ruthless British.</p>
<p>With my mother's consent, I wrote my brother Martin for passage money, since it<lb/>
was <hi>Michael's</hi> fate to remain with the old folks in their declining years, I being too<lb/>
young to be of much service on the little farm. I suspect that I was an American in<lb/>
embryo, for as soon as I learned my ABC's a juvenile biography of &ldquo;The Father of his<lb/>
Country&rdquo; became my dearest treasure and constant companion. I was sitting on pins and<lb/>
needles until I received my brother's reply, but it arrived in due time in the form of<lb/>
a postal money order addressed to my mother, with an additional amount for herself, I<lb/>
was too happy to notice my mother's anguish. I was her baby and she would never see me<lb/>
again, as she must have thought, while all I was thinking of was to be on my way. How<lb/>
thoughtless children are towards those who bring them into the world, and how selfish!</p>
<p>My first Great Day had arrived. I was to start for Queenstown, today known as<lb/>
Cobb, my port of embarkation, father to accompany me on the first leg of my journey,<lb/>
by jaunting-car to Ballinrobe where I would board a train to Queenstown. In memory I<lb/>
can still feel my dear mother's embrace as she held me to her bosom, murmuring<lb/>
&ldquo;macushla&rdquo; and now making no effort to hold back her tears which mingled with my own.<lb/>
For a fleeting moment I was on the verge of repenting when my father separated us, tell-<lb/>
ing me there was no time to lose. Sure, I would write to her often and long and I<lb/>
would come back to visit her some day, but I was never to see her again except in my<lb/>
dreams. Wanderlust had claimed me at an early age, so early that I did not even know<lb/>
its meaning. Boy though I was, I was old enough to hate the "Sassenach (the English),<lb/>
responsible in large measure for the ills of Ireland, a country which they did their<lb/>
level best to reduce to serfdom. Gaelic, my mother tongue, was to them only a dialect<lb/>
and could not be taught in the National Schools of Ireland, but it survived none the<lb/>
less through centuries of oppression. Truly, I owe very little to the English and it<lb/>
required World War II to wipe out that hatred. With its advent I ceased to hate them<lb/>
and to forgive but not forget.</p>
<p>Boarding the SS &ldquo;ETRURIA&rdquo;, I was soon on my way and greatly impressed by the<lb/>
immense body of water through which we were ploughing, mentally comparing it with the<lb/>
small freshwater lake on the shores of which I had first seen the light. Soon I was to<lb/>
know the meaning of seasickness. Within a few hours the nauseating odor of salt water<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06013003"/>
-- 3 --<lb/>
1886?<lb/>
Emigrated at age 10<lb/>
acted on me as an emetic. Sixty years have rolled by since that, my first ocean<lb/>
voyage, but I have not forgotten it. For four or five days mine was a case of &ldquo;all<lb/>
coming up and nothing staying down&rdquo;, but it was to be the first and last time for me<lb/>
to be seasick, although I have made a score of ocean voyages in the intervening<lb/>
years, some of them in comparative calm and others in semi-cyclonic weather. On one<lb/>
of the latter occasions over half of the officers and crew became seasick. Only those<lb/>
who have been seasick once can fully sympathize with fellow-travelers who suffer from<lb/>
that very disagreeable but not dangerous malady.</p>
<p>I landed at &ldquo;Castle Garden&rdquo;, at the foot of Battery Park, the &ldquo;Ellis Island&rdquo; of<lb/>
those days, my brother Martin having come on from Youngstown to meet me, a very much<lb/>
awed an bewildred youngster as I gazed on the sky-scrapers of lower Manhattan. Today,<lb/>
without blinking, I am no longer awed by the Empire State Building. Presently we were<lb/>
on our way to Youngstown. For a month or so my sister-in-law, a bonny Scottish dame,<lb/>
was very kind to me but when my brother was laid off indefinitely at the steel mill<lb/>
where he was employed as a master puddler, I sensed that I was one too many in his<lb/>
household. They had two children of their own and he was obliged to dig into his<lb/>
savings account. I did not want to be a bone of contention, so I decided to try at<lb/>
earning my own living, taking care that my sister-in-law's attitude towards me was my<lb/>
secret only. I was sensitive as a boy and I have remained sensitive as a man. Very<lb/>
much against my brother's wishes, I broke loose. My dreams of an education turned<lb/>
out to be dreams only.</p>
<p>I first tackled the owner of a grocery store on Federal Street, Youngstown's<lb/>
Broadway, taking note of the fact that he alone attended the customers. He was a<lb/>
strapping, good-natured Irishman by the name of Gillespie. He must have laughed up<lb/>
his sleeve when I told him I was looking for a job, but he didn't. He took me serious-<lb/>
ly. Sure, he could use me as an errand boy to carry packages to the curb or across<lb/>
the street to the buggies or phaetons of customers; also I could help in arraying<lb/>
canned goods on the shelves, see that labeled goods were arranged right side up. I<lb/>
was of real assistance to him and in a few months I blossomed out as a sales-body. I was<lb/>
happy in a way and proved to myself that I was not a burden to anyone. After four<lb/>
years with him I found myself out of a job. Lack of sufficient capital to start with<lb/>
and keen competition, he told me, obliged him to liquidate. He could do better as a<lb/>
salesman with Atlantic &amp; Pacific Tea Company and would go back to his old job there.<lb/>
To lighten the blow and my disappointment he made me a gift of $50.00, which I thought<lb/>
most generous. During those four years he had served as my banker and I had managed<lb/>
to save a few dollars every month.</p>
<p>With my $50.00 plus, I became one of the agents for a book titled "The Life of Li<lb/>
Hung Chang, a Chinese grandee. I was not taken very seriously by prospective customers<lb/>
but none the less I sold several volumes in house-to-house canvassing. My efforts to<lb/>
reach &ldquo;the lady of the house&rdquo; were often frustrated by the hired help, but I managed<lb/>
to crash the front door on more than one occasion to extoll the virtues of my book.<lb/>
Probably my youth and my Irish brogue were determining factors more than once in making<lb/>
a sale. Having exhausted the field for my book, as I thought, I refused an offer from<lb/>
the publishers to take on another book. My record so far had been that of a rolling<lb/>
stone, but I did gather a little moss and I steered clear of bad company. I had a well<lb/>
defined sense of right and wrong, &ldquo;mine&rdquo; and &ldquo;thine&rdquo;. Other boys could steal apples<lb/>
but I was never tempted to do so. &ldquo;He who would steal a pin would steal a bigger thing&rdquo;<lb/>
became part of my creed.</p>
<p>I now turned to the &ldquo;Help Wanted&rdquo; columns of &ldquo;THE VINDICATOR&rdquo;, one of Youngstown's<lb/>
two dailies, where I spotted an advertisement of a lady doctor requiring the services<lb/>
of a young boy in her office and to accompany her on her rounds. Although I arrived<lb/>
at an early hour, other candidates had been ahead of me. When my turn came and I stood<lb/>
before her, her ammusement at my gaelic accent was not assuring. I landed the job,<lb/>
however. My salary was to include room, board and laundry. Her name was Dr. Ida<lb/>
Clarke, a pioneer among her sex in those days in the field of medicine. Being one of<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06013004"/>
-- 4 --<lb/>
a family of three and wealthy, medicine with her was a hobby rather than a means to<lb/>
earn a living and although she could be selective in the matter of patients, she<lb/>
never commercialized her profession. It may well be that her prosperous patients<lb/>
paid their fair share of those whom she treated gratis. She was altruistic by nature<lb/>
and on many occasions not only were her services given free but an order for groceries<lb/>
was thrown in for good measure. I suspect that her profession filled a void in her<lb/>
life which might have been offset through matrimony. She remained a spinster all her<lb/>
life and appeared to find happiness in catering to the ills of women and children.</p>
<p>I am dwelling at large on the Clarke family, simply because they had a far-reach-<lb/>
ing effect on my own future conduct in life. I found them peculiar in only one<lb/>
respect. Neither the brother nor his two sisters ever married. The other sister,<lb/>
Alice, was more or less of an invalid. The brother, John H. Clarke, was an outstand-<lb/>
ing lawyer, handsome, winning personality and with hair prematurely gray, a brilliant<lb/>
orator and prominent as a member of the Democratic Party in his native state. In a<lb/>
then traditionally Republican state, he was nominated by his party as candidate for<lb/>
the U. S. Senate against Marcus Aurelius Hanna, the Republican nominee, and was defeat-<lb/>
ed. That was to be the first and the last time that he was to stand for an elective<lb/>
office. He owned the VINDICATOR and continued to own it until the day of his death.</p>
<p>When Woodrow Wilson became President he nominated Mr. Clarke to an Associate<lb/>
Justiceship of the U. S. Supreme Court, a position he resigned in order to campaign<lb/>
the nation for U. S. entry in The League of Nations, a vain sacrifice on his part.<lb/>
He then retired from Public life, confining his activities to editorial contributions<lb/>
to his own newspaper. By that time he was the last of his family, his mother and two<lb/>
sisters having passed away. Instead of returning to his old home on Bryson Street,<lb/>
he took up residence in La Joya, California, where he died in 1945, at the ripe old<lb/>
age of 88 years.</p>
<p>It was while I was in the service of the Clarke family that my self-education<lb/>
really started. I had access to the well-stocked family library and Dr. Clarke's<lb/>
suggestions as to the books which would best serve me was valuable. All my spare<lb/>
time was devoted to the acquisition of book knowledge. Instead of twiddling my thumbs<lb/>
at the doctor's office while she was examining a patient, I delved into a book on<lb/>
&ldquo;Materia Medica &amp; Therapeutics&rdquo;, a pastime which she found amusing but to which she<lb/>
made no objection. I had no time for recreation or amusements and less time to get<lb/>
into mischief, finding happiness in reading. My salary during those years was saved<lb/>
practically intact. But the time had come when I sensed that I had outgrown my use-<lb/>
fulness to the doctor. Also, I had other plans.</p>
<p>Seeking Mr. Clarke's advice I told him I wanted to prepare myself for a position<lb/>
in commercial life, which he thought a very good idea. Based on the amount I had saved<lb/>
he calculated that I could afford a two-year course at a small commercial college in<lb/>
the town of Rogers, Columbiana County, which he had recently visited as speaker at<lb/>
commencement exercises. Tuition, as well as room and board, he said, was moderate as<lb/>
compared with a similar school in Youngstown. He would write to Professor Bowman,<lb/>
the President, in my behalf and he would give me a letter to him when I should present<lb/>
myself for matriculation. The name of the college appealed to me: MOUNT HOPE COLLEGE.</p>
<p>Arrived at Mount Hope College, I started to concentrate on arithmetic, penmanship<lb/>
and bookkeeping, bent on making good use of my limited capital and unlimited time. Mr.<lb/>
Clarke had warned me that neither could be wasted. The course was continuous at opt-<lb/>
ion so that students so inclined could take vacations or study the year around. I<lb/>
elected continuous study, not being at all sure that I could complete the course with-<lb/>
in the two years, but I did. When my mind got muddled with too many figures, single<lb/>
an double entries, I fell back on my favorite pastime, reading. The town of Rogers,<lb/>
named after one of the trustees of the college, owed its existence to the school and<lb/>
was dependent on it and the surrounding farms. Aside from the occasional student re-<lb/>
unions, social life in the town was practically nil. It was an ideal place for study<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06013005"/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
extra sheet<lb/>
cf o data on<lb/>
p 5-6 <unclear>Mrs B Versim xx</unclear><lb/>
p 5 " " " x<lb/>
could spend a few days there and again head for Pittsburgh. It was the month of<lb/>
May, 1897. I registered at the Central Hotel and became one of not over a half<lb/>
dozen guests. The proprietor was clerk, cashier and manager all rolled in one.<lb/>
At that, he was not overworked. That evening he engaged me in conversation and<lb/>
he soon had my full story. Would I show him my diploma, which I had taken great<lb/>
care to mention? How would I like to take on the position of clerk, recently<lb/>
vacated? He was looking for a young man of my qualifications. Yes, I would<lb/>
accept it on trial, which he hoped would be permanent, at the same time assuring<lb/>
me that my duties would not be of a difficult nature. The hours would be long, as<lb/>
he told me, which I did not mind. The salary to start would be $30.00 a month<lb/>
with room, board and laundry.</p>
<p>Alas and alack, I was not destined to become a permanent resident of Beaver<lb/>
Falls. It was a rather dull town at that time of the year and the guests at the<lb/>
hotel were so few, and my duties so light, that I really felt ashamed to draw my<lb/>
salary, while the proprietor worried not at all. All I did was merely trying to<lb/>
keep busy. When I told him that I would be &ldquo;on my way&rdquo;, he was very much dis-<lb/>
appointed and that if it was a matter of salary he would willingly double it, but<lb/>
I stuck to my purpose. I instinctively knew that I would never be satisfied in<lb/>
such a small town as Beaver Falls, Pa. I reckon I was born to wander, having had<lb/>
an early start in life. I think my Beaver Falls friend had understood me. I have<lb/>
never forgotten how kind and considerate he was towards me.</p>
<p>Continuing on to Pittsburgh, I gave but little thought to the surprise that<lb/>
was in store for me in the city where I had hoped to take root. That eternal<lb/>
canopy of smoke and soot over the entire district convinced me in one day that<lb/>
I was not to become an honored citizen of the Smokey City. Too late, I regretted<lb/>
that I had not made a beeline for Cleveland. With no regrets, I left Pittsburgh<lb/>
and bought a ticket for Washington. The nation's capital was indeed a city to<lb/>
dream of, with its tree-lined, broad avenues, with no canopy of smoke or soot to<lb/>
shut out the rays of the sun. As I thought, there I could take root, although<lb/>
destiny had other plans for me, plans of which I could not then be aware.</p>
<p>I wanted to enlist in the 5th Cavalry, then stationed at Fort Myer, Virginia,<lb/>
close to the District limits, but to all intents and purposes a part of Washing-<lb/>
ton. Arriving at the Post one morning, headed for the Adjuntant's office, I was<lb/>
accosted by an army officer who rightly guessed that I was a candidate for enlist-<lb/>
ment. I soon discovered that he was Major William H. Arthur, Post Surgeon, and<lb/>
very much interested in having me change my plans for the Cavalry and enlist in<lb/>
the Hospital Corps instead. Would I please accompany him to his office at the<lb/>
hospital, near by? I told him I had a note of introduction for the commander<lb/>
of Troop B from Mrs. John A. Logan, widow of General Logan, then residing in<lb/>
Washington but formerly of Youngstown. I did not know Mrs. Logan but I did know<lb/>
that she was an intimate friend of Dr. Ida Clarke and her brother, John H. Clarke,<lb/>
prominent lawyer who was later appointed a justice of the Supreme Court by<lb/>
President Wilson. When I left Youngstown Dr. Clarke gave me a nice letter of<lb/>
recommendation so that Mrs. Logan, based on that letter, did not hesitate to give<lb/>
me a note of introduction to the commander of Troop B.</p>
<p>Major Arthur read Mrs. Logan's note and determined that the Hospital Corps<lb/>
should have me, and not the Cavalry. He was most eloquent in pointing out to me<lb/>
that I had a more brilliant future with the <unclear>HC</unclear> than I could ever have as a soldier<lb/>
of the line. I might even study medicine while serving in the Hospital Corps and<lb/>
thus aspire to a commission as a 1st lieutenant in the Medical Corps, after grad-<lb/>
uation. He mentioned two or three medical officers then in the Army who had<lb/>
studied medicine while in the Hospital Corps. I never presented Mrs. Logan's<lb/>
note. He gave me a letter to Captain George D. Deshon, commandant of the Hospital<lb/>
School of Instruction, Washington Barracks, and on July 3, 1897, I was sworn in<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06013006"/>
Extra sheet<lb/>
of <unclear></unclear> data on p 2 mss 5<lb/>
centrate his efforts on yellow fever, then raising havoc among American troops and<lb/>
personnel throughout the Island. Walter Reed was quartered within the Post Hospital<lb/>
grounds at Columbia Barracks, and established his laboratory there. I did not meet<lb/>
him until the first days of October, when I presented myself as a volunteer for<lb/>
his proposed series of experiments at Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>When I was discharged from the army, I immediately became a civilian clerk at<lb/>
General Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters, in Marianao, being accorded by Major Stark the<lb/>
unusual privilege of occupying the same room which I had while in military service.<lb/>
A room in the town of Marianao would have cost me $20.00 a month. I shared the<lb/>
room with Kissinger, my successor in the operating room, our room being at one end<lb/>
of the frame building which housed Major Reed's laboratory. Therefore, while I was<lb/>
now a civilian, I was up-to-date on the doings within the Post Hospital reservation.<lb/>
I had no occasion or opportunity to meet Walter Reed during July, August and<lb/>
September, although my friend, Major Stark, informed me of his mission in Cuba.</p>
<p>Prior to my advent at General Lee's headquarters, I had known that three of<lb/>
his staff officers had contracted yellow fever, viz: Majors Jefferson R. Kean,<lb/>
Chief Surgeon, Majors Cartwright and Edmunds, Chief Quartermaster and Inspector<lb/>
General, respectively. Major Kean happily recovered, but Majors Cartwright and<lb/>
Edmunds succumbed to the disease. All three roomed in the town of Marianao. So<lb/>
far as I can recall, no case of yellow fever had developed within the military<lb/>
reservation of Columbia Barracks, then occupied by the 7th Cavalry Regiment,<lb/>
commanded by Colonel Baldwin. In the city of Havana, headquarters of the Military<lb/>
Governor of Cuba (General Leonard Wood), the number of officers, soldiers and<lb/>
civilians attached to his staff, registered a still higher proportion of yellow<lb/>
fever cases. They were all Americans, of course, native Cubans being considered<lb/>
immune to the scourge. Americans and Spaniards were the favorite targets of<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Following the death of Major Peterson, one of General Wood's staff officers,<lb/>
at &ldquo;Las Animas&rdquo; Hospital and the suicide of his wife, some hours after his death,<lb/>
in a nurse's room at the same institution, conditions had reached a stage of near-<lb/>
panic. The sadness created by their untimely death brought sharply into focus the<lb/>
deadly nature of the disease. Other officers whose wives had come to Cuba to join<lb/>
them, hurriedly arranged for their return to the U. S. Cuba was an unsafe place<lb/>
then for American wives and daughters and their men folks insisted on their hurried<lb/>
departure, in many cases against their wishes, bravery being a feminine virtue<lb/>
comparable to the opposite species, as we all know.</p>
<p>No one was more deeply impressed and concerned with the conditions described<lb/>
than was the mild-mannered, gentle and God-fearing Walter Reed who came to Cuba to<lb/>
run down the microbe or &ldquo;germ&rdquo; responsible for yellow fever, a &ldquo;bug&rdquo; so elusive<lb/>
as to pass through through the finest laboratory filter, thus defying the best<lb/>
efforts of medical scientists to isolate it. &ldquo;Why not&rdquo;, thought Reed, &ldquo;look into<lb/>
Dr. Carlos Finlay's mosquito theory&rdquo;. As far back as 1881 Dr. Finlay began to<lb/>
experiment with a certain species of mosquito identified as the CULEX FASCIATUS,<lb/>
later called STEGOMYIA and definitely named AEDES AEGYPTI, its present day name.<lb/>
Very much against the advice of most of his colleagues, he called upon Finlay who<lb/>
at that time had but one believer in his theory, in all Cuba, Dr. Claudio Delgado,<lb/>
his laboratory partner. For 19 years Dr. Finlay expounded his theory to deaf and<lb/>
unbelieving ears. While his fellow-medicos did not ridicule him to his face, they<lb/>
did so between themselves. He had discovered the right mosquito but his technique<lb/>
was wrong. Walter Reed and his Army Board found the missing link.</p>
<p>see &para; 5</p>
<p>p 2 mss 5</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06013007"/>
<p><unclear>actual (revision?) of</unclear></p>
<p>pp 7-8 mss 5</p>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>And now, as they say in radio parlance, I come to &ldquo;the $64.00 question&rdquo;. The<lb/>
reader, if he has been able to follow me in my disjointed narrative, will have<lb/>
formed an opinion as to whether or not I have earned the right to arrive at definite<lb/>
cnclusions in a matter &ldquo;loaded with dynamite&rdquo; and which may have repercussions in<lb/>
Cuba which I do not invite, but which I must record if justice to the memories of<lb/>
two great men is to prevail. Since the Cuban and American medical fraternities<lb/>
have not been able to iron out their differences over the past 50 years, I shall<lb/>
endeavor to play the role of arbiter, with no leaning to one side or the other<lb/>
because of nationality, basing my statements on facts only.</p>
<p>Walter Reed's series of experiments at Camp Lazear converted Carlos Finlay's<lb/>
19-year-old theory into a living reality. That is an indisputable fact. The<lb/>
contribution of each to that happy event resulted in a partnership which can never<lb/>
be dissolved. It was a-share-and-share-alike partnership. Walter Reed was<lb/>
acclaimed by the Americas and nowhere more than in Cuba. In this first outburst<lb/>
of enthusiasm, his partner, Carlos Finlay, was slighted, but not overlooked by<lb/>
any manner of means. As a matter of fact, he could not be overlooked, at least<lb/>
not for long. That silent partnership and a complete understanding between the<lb/>
two scientists could not be dissolved. The findings at Camp Lazear were as much<lb/>
Finlay's as they were Reed's, although the work done there was exclusively directed<lb/>
by Reed, with Finlay's pet mosquito. Walter Reed himself, as I knew him, would be<lb/>
the last man on earth to deny Finlay his rightful share in the joint enterprise.</p>
<p>With the mosquito theory now no longer a theory, Major William C. Gorgas,<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer of Cuba, no longer the confirmed skeptic, set about organ-<lb/>
izing his cohorts to make war on the STEGOMYIA mosquito, up to that time considered<lb/>
a stinging nuisance only. Adult mosquitoes were to be destroyed by fumigation<lb/>
and their eggs, lacking still or stagnant water wherein to breed, would be convert-<lb/>
ed into harmless dust. Water containers, deposits and wells were to be screened<lb/>
or hermetically covered. Fines were imposed for harboring water containers in<lb/>
which wigglers or mosquito larvae were found, on house-to-house inspection. His<lb/>
task in Cuba happily finished, Walter Reed returned to Washington in February, 1901.</p>
<p>During 1901 and until his untimely death in November, 1902, Reed was the<lb/>
recipient of many honors on the part of scientific bodies and institutions of<lb/>
learning. Among the latter, the Universities of Harvard and Michigan awarded<lb/>
him honorary degrees - Harvard, that of A. M. and the University of Michigan, that<lb/>
of LL.D. His Harvard citation read as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of the University of Virginia, the army<lb/>
surgeon who planned and directed in Cuba the experiments which have<lb/>
given man control over that fearful scourge, Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>His remains were interred at Arlington National Cemetery and shortly after,<lb/>
a beautiful marble shaft was placed over his tomb and on it a bronze tablet<lb/>
bearing the following inscription, based on eleven of the words of the Harvard<lb/>
citation:</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D. of the University of Virginia.<lb/>
A. M. of Harvard University,<lb/>
LL.D. of the University of Michigan,<lb/>
Professor of Bacteriology, Army Medical School<lb/>
and<lb/>
Columbian University, Washington, D. C.<lb/>
&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge,<lb/>
Yellow Fever&rdquo;</p>
<p>Those eleven words have been the innocent cause of more bitter controversy, during<lb/>
the first half of the 20th Century, than any similar number of words in the annals</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06013008"/>
<p>alternate (revision?)</p>
<p>of pp 7-8 mss 5</p>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>Walter Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear converted a theory into a living<lb/>
reality. I use the term &ldquo;theory&rdquo; knowingly, because up to that time it had been<lb/>
looked upon as illusory by the scientific world and nowhere had it been more dis-<lb/>
credited than in Cuba, the country in which Finlay was born, the son of a British<lb/>
father and a French mother. Walter Reed, who had found the missing link, was<lb/>
acclaimed and the &ldquo;Camp Lazear Episode&rdquo; added another milestone to medical<lb/>
history. The carrier of a dreadful scourge could now be controlled and destroyed.<lb/>
The world press heralded the glad tidings with delirious enthusiasm. In this<lb/>
first outburst of joy, the name of Carlos Finlay was lost in the shuffle, at<lb/>
least for the time being. Overnight, so to speak, Walter Reed, the modest man<lb/>
of medicine, had attained immortality and a niche in The Hall of Fame.</p>
<p>With PROOF now displacing THEORY, Major William Crawford Gorgas, Chief Sanitary<lb/>
Officer of Cuba and no longer the confirmed skeptic, organized his campaign to<lb/>
make war on the STEGOMYIA mosquito, hitherto considered merely a stinging nuisance.<lb/>
Sanitary brigades were formed to seek out the culprit in its natural habitat, the<lb/>
domestic atmosphere where man lived and had his being. That insect depended<lb/>
principally on human blood for its existence. Its proboscis could penetrate the<lb/>
tender skin of the human and in no time at all reach a small vein or capillary. It<lb/>
was eminently a household or domestic insect. It became essential, therefore, to<lb/>
first destroy the adult mosquito by fumigation, then to deprive it of its favorite<lb/>
breeding place, viz: still or stagnant water. House-to-house inspections and<lb/>
compulsory screening of water containers became the order of the day and fines<lb/>
were imposed for possessing or harboring uncovered water containers containing<lb/>
wigglers or mosquito larvae.</p>
<p>His task in Cuba happily finished, Walter Reed returned to Washington in<lb/>
February, 1901. Until his untimely death in November, 1902, he was the recipeant<lb/>
of many honors on the part of scientific bodies and institutions of learning,<lb/>
including Harvard and the University of Michigan. His remains were interred at<lb/>
Arlington National Cemetery. A bronze tablet on his monument bears the following<lb/>
inscription, based on his Harvard University citation:</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D. of the University of Virginia.<lb/>
A. M. of Harvard University,<lb/>
LL. D. of the University of Michigan,<lb/>
Professor of Bacteriology, Army Medical School<lb/>
and<lb/>
Columbian University, Washington, D. C.<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge,<lb/>
Yellow Fever.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Harvard University citation reads as follows: &ldquo;<hi>Walter Reed, graduate of<lb/>
the University of Virginia, the army surgeon who planned and directed in Cuba the<lb/>
experiments which have given man control over that fearful scourge, yellow fever.</hi>&rdquo;</p>
<p>Those eleven words <hi>&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge, Yellow<lb/>
Fever</hi>&rdquo;, inscribed on Walter Reed's monument have been the innocent cause of more<lb/>
bitter controversy, over a period of almost half a century, than any eleven words<lb/>
in the annals of medicine - a bitterness born in the mind of a Cuban doctor of<lb/>
that day. That doctor was certainly not Carlos Finlay. The venemous attack on<lb/>
Reed and his memory had taken root so that, one by one, the Cuban doctors who knew<lb/>
Reed personally and admired him for his work at Camp Lazear, either succumbed to the<lb/>
unilateral claims for Finlay or faced ostracism. That was the situation as explained<lb/>
to me on May 2, 1940, by one of the few living Cuban medicos who knew Reed well and<lb/>
appreciated his work and what it meant to the Island of Cuba in the critical year<lb/>
of 1900. He is no longer alive and out of respect to his memory I am not giving<lb/>
his name. What he told me was strictly confidential.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f06013009"/>
<p>alternate to p7 mss 5</p>
<p>-- 7 --</p>
<p>Now, that the open-minded reader has formed an opinion as to whether or not<lb/>
I am authorized to arrive at conclusions in a matter &ldquo;loaded with dynamite&rdquo;, I<lb/>
shall endeavor to enter the Sanctum Sanctorum of medical science, to convince the<lb/>
members of that noble profession of an error, correction of which they have side-<lb/>
stepped for almost 50 years. Since the Cuban and American doctors have not been<lb/>
able to iron out their differences, I, the layman, am undertaking the self-imposed<lb/>
role of arbiter, forgetting for the nonce that I am an American citizen residing<lb/>
in a country whose people I admire for their virtues, with tolerance for their<lb/>
faults - a country whose people have honored me personally and to a degree far<lb/>
beyond my merits.</p>
<p>I think it was in the years 1903-1904 that a monument was placed over the<lb/>
tomb of Walter Reed, in Arlington National Cemetery, where his remains had been<lb/>
interred upon his untimely death in November, 1902. A bronze tablet on the monu-<lb/>
ment bears the following inscription, based on the citation of Harvard University<lb/>
in conferring upon him the honorary degree of A. M., some months before his death:</p>
<p>&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge,<lb/>
Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Harvard University citation read as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of the University of Virginia, the army surgeon<lb/>
who planned and directed in Cuba the experiments which have given man<lb/>
control over that fearful scourge, yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A young Cuban doctor who had been one of Dr. Finlay's severest critics, prior<lb/>
to the experiments at Camp Lazear and the results there obtained, became overnight,<lb/>
so to speak, Dr. Finlay's self-appointed champion and Walter Reed's bitter enemy.<lb/>
He was no shining light in his profession but he was an astute politician, knowing<lb/>
how to play on the sentiments of his countrymen and with a deep knowledge of their<lb/>
temperament and their intense nationalism. The epitaph over Reed's tomb in Arling-<lb/>
ton gave him his cue. Was not that epitaph a denial of Finlay's share in The Con-<lb/>
quest of Yellow Fever? On the surface, and only on the surface, it was. To the<lb/>
young convert, it had a deeper and more sinister meaning, viz: that the innocent<lb/>
and now immortal Reed had robbed Finlay of his glory.</p>
<p>The prominent members of the Cuban medical fraternity who had witnessed the<lb/>
transformation of Finlay's theory into a living reality were silenced or brow-beaten<lb/>
into silence by the vehemence and virulence of this young physician, if they dared<lb/>
to do justice to Reed and his memory. They were threatened with ostracism in their<lb/>
profession and one of them actually underwent that stain. He lived to regret that<lb/>
he had stood up for Reed. Others followed the course of least resistance. They<lb/>
kept their councel to themselves, neglecting to mention Reed when they were called<lb/>
upon to laud Finlay</p>
<pb n="10" id="f06013010"/>
<p>-- 8 --</p>
<p>Dating from 1904, the campaign of defamation against Reed gained momentum and<lb/>
in this Year of Our Lord, 1950, the all-out claims for Finlay have become a national<lb/>
conviction. In May, 1948, when the Fourth International Congresses of Tropical<lb/>
Medicine and Malaria convened in Washington, one the matters on its agenda was that<lb/>
of holding commemorative exercises in honor of Reed, the program decided upon bear-<lb/>
ing the title:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Exercises to Commemorate the Demonstration by<lb/>
Walter Reed<lb/>
of the Mosquito Transmission of Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Cuban delegates to the Congresses strenously objected to the wording and<lb/>
implied meaning involved in the program's title, with the solid backing of the<lb/>
medical societies of Cuba and the Cuban press. It threatened to become an inter-<lb/>
American incident. A compromise was reached with the Cuban delegates who reluctant-<lb/>
ly agreed to accept Reed as Finlay's <hi>collaborator</hi>. With this grudging concession<lb/>
on the part of the Cubans, I had visions of an amicable understanding of the half-<lb/>
century-old controversy. Sorry to record that I was over-optimistic. No such luck.<lb/>
Eleven days later, the fireworks started in a virulent article, authored by a Cuban<lb/>
medico and published in &ldquo;BOHEMIA&rdquo;, a weekly news-magazine of large circulation,<lb/>
under the following title:</p>
<p>&ldquo;FINLAY'S WORK WAS NOT A THEORY<lb/>
NOR WAS REED HIS COLLABORATOR&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The author, in his article, stripped Walter Reed of any share in The Conquest<lb/>
of Yellow Fever, stating that he merely &ldquo;confirmed&rdquo; what Finlay had already &ldquo;proved&rdquo;.<lb/>
Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear were referred to as &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; and entirely<lb/>
&ldquo;unnecessary&rdquo;. Reed, he goes on to state, had &ldquo;no scientific background&rdquo; and there-<lb/>
fore could not &ldquo;feel the emotions of the real scientist&rdquo;, inferring that he was a<lb/>
mere salaried automat, carrying out instructions of General Wood, Military Governor<lb/>
of Cuba. He charges Reed with &ldquo;bad faith&rdquo; in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;, read before<lb/>
The American Public Health Association, in Indianapolis, in October, 1900. Was any<lb/>
voice raised in Cuba or in the United States in defense of Reed, his memory and his<lb/>
work? Those who should have done so - members of Reed's profession - remained<lb/>
discreetly silent. For this complacency on part of the American medical fraternity<lb/>
there are a number of contributing reasons, a few of which I can explain.</p>
<p>First, was the meager credit given to Finlay on the heels of Reed's conclusive<lb/>
experiments at Camp Lazear, indirectly started by Finlay and finished by Reed. The<lb/>
result was a Finlay-Reed accomplishment. In the intervening years, American medicine<lb/>
and American public opinion have bent backwards to correct those first impressions<lb/>
but fishbone in the throat of the Cubans still remains. Then there is the matter<lb/>
of a difference in temperaments, with the Spanish or Latin temperament uppermost in<lb/>
the Cubans, a people who are intensely nationalistic, proud as they are, and as<lb/>
they should be, of their Spanish forefathers. The present generation in Cuba is<lb/>
now steeped in their all-out claims for Finlay, with no consideration for Reed.</p>
<p>Cuban medicos, in their contact and association with their opposites in the<lb/>
U. S., have extolled the glory of Finlay, soft-pedalling the mention of Reed and<lb/>
not mentioning him at all, except as a member of the Army Board, without pronouncing<lb/>
his name. In Cuba, he is rarely if ever mentioned by name and when he is so<lb/>
mentioned it is only to defile his memory. They have taken good care to glorify<lb/>
Finlay in Latin America and other European countries, but in so doing they vilify<lb/>
Reed and his memory. American medicos visiting Cuba laud Finlay and refrain from<lb/>
lauding Reed, but no Cuban medico visiting the U. S. has ever lauded Reed. Their<lb/>
resentment against him borders on hatred, an untenable position if facts and common<lb/>
justice can be lightly brushed off and ignored. I have often asked one and another<lb/>
of them if they thought Major Reed came to Cuba to &ldquo;confirm&rdquo; Finlay's theory, and<lb/>
whether or not they had ever read his instructions from the Surgeon General of the Army.<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06013011"/>
-- 8 --<lb/>
of medicine. They were not authored by Walter Reed or any member of his family<lb/>
nor by any member of the Army Medical Corps. They were expressed by President<lb/>
Eliot of Harvard University, a non-medico.</p>
<p>It is possible, but doubtful, that the Cuban medical fraternity would have<lb/>
been satisfied if the wording of the Harvard citation had read as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of the University of Virginia, the army<lb/>
surgeon who, with Doctor Carlos Finlay, planned and directed in Cuba<lb/>
the experiments which have given man control over that fearful<lb/>
scourge, Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>They, however, interpreted the words of the epitaph as a unilateral claim for<lb/>
Reed and a denial of Finlay's share in the Camp Lazear demonstrations.</p>
<p>Then began the venemous attacks on Reed and his memory, initiated by a young<lb/>
Cuban medico who, until the day of his death, denied Reed any part in The Conquest<lb/>
of Yellow Fever. Ignoring all the facts, he gave Walter Reed credit only for<lb/>
&ldquo;confirming&rdquo; what Finlay had fully proved. Yet this same young doctor was one of<lb/>
Finlay's severest critics prior to the Camp Lazear Episode. It may be interesting<lb/>
to quote here from a letter written to Dr. Aristides Agramonte by Major Reed, on<lb/>
May 25, 1900, on the official stationery of the War Department, Surgeon General's<lb/>
Office:</p>
<p>&ldquo;An order issued yesterday from the War Department calls for<lb/>
a board of medical officers for the investigation of acute infectious<lb/>
diseases occurring on the Island of Cuba. The board consists of<lb/>
Carroll, yourself, Lazear and the writer. It will be our duty, under<lb/>
verbal instructions from the Surgeon General, to continue the investi-<lb/>
gation of the causation of yellow fever.&rdquo; ..........................</p>
<p>The Cuban doctors who knew Walter Reed well and admired him for his work at<lb/>
Camp Lazear passively allowed his detractor to continue his campaign of defamation.<lb/>
At first he had less than a half dozen followers, but gradually, he gained addicts,<lb/>
using nationalism as a weapon. His unilateral claims for Finlay swayed and engulf-<lb/>
ed the Cuban doctors, silencing and brow-beating those who would do justice to<lb/>
Reed. Finally, when his claims had been accepted nationally, he threatened ostra-<lb/>
cism for any medico who would espouse Reed's cause. One of the most prominent<lb/>
of Reed's friends - and he had many when he left Cuba - suffered ostracism for his<lb/>
defense of Reed. He finally succumbed to the detractor, as he personally informed<lb/>
me in 1928. Another friend of Reed's informed me that he, too, did not dare come<lb/>
out in defense of Reed, fearing reprisals. He happened to be one of Finlay's<lb/>
very close friends and associate. Those two Reed admirers have passed on to their<lb/>
reward. I shall respect their confidence by not naming them.</p>
<p><unclear>Agramonte??</unclear></p>
<pb n="12" id="f06013012"/>
<p>extra sheet<lb/>
Probably alternate<lb/>
to p 8 mss 5</p>
<p>-- 9 --</p>
<p>&ldquo;a voice in the wilderness&rdquo;. During 19 long years, Finlay's mosquito theory had<lb/>
but one believer, his disciple and laboratory assistant, Dr. Claudio Delgado, a<lb/>
Spanish doctor.</p>
<p>During 1901 and until his untimely death in November, 1902, Walter Reed was<lb/>
the recipient of many honors on the part of scientific bodies and institutions<lb/>
of learning. Among the latter, the Universities of Harvard and Michigan awarded<lb/>
him honorary degrees - Harvard that of A. M. and the University of Michigan that<lb/>
of LL.D. His Harvard citation read as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Walter Reed, graduate of the University of Virginia, the<lb/>
army surgeon who planned and directed in Cuba the experiments<lb/>
which have given man control over that fearful scourge, Yellow<lb/>
Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>His remains were interred at Arlington National Cemetery. Shortly after, a<lb/>
beautiful marble shaft was raised over his tomb and on it was placed a bronze<lb/>
tablet bearing the following inscription:</p>
<p>Walter Reed, M. D. of the University of Virginia.<lb/>
A. M. of Harvard University,<lb/>
LL.D. of the University of Michigan,<lb/>
Professor of Bacteriology, Army Medical School<lb/>
and<lb/>
Columbian University, Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge,<lb/>
Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Those eleven words, practically quoted verbatim from the Harvard citation,<lb/>
have been the innocent cause of more bitter controversy on the part of the Cuban<lb/>
medical fraternity, over the past 50 years, than any other eleven words in the<lb/>
annals of medicine. By a strange coincidence, the initiator of the campaign of<lb/>
bitterness against Reed and his memory was a leader in ridiculizing Finlay, up<lb/>
to the Camp Lazear Episode. Now he became Finlay's self-appointed redeemer and<lb/>
champion, interpreting the epitaph on Reed's monument as a denial of Finlay's<lb/>
part in The Conquest of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>The venemous attack on Walter Reed began to take root so that, one by one,<lb/>
the group of doctors who knew Reed well and admired him for his work at Camp Lazear<lb/>
either succumbed to the detractor's unilateral claims for Finlay, or were coerced<lb/>
into silence by threats of ostracism. I was not in Cuba during those years -<lb/>
1902-1905, but the situation was explained to me on May 2, 1940, by one of the<lb/>
few Cuban medicos then alive, one who knew Reed well and appreciated his<lb/>
work and what it meant to the Island of Cuba, in the critical year of 1900. One<lb/>
of Reed's medico friends who did not &ldquo;follow the course of least resistance&rdquo;,<lb/>
but defended him suffered ostracism. The detractor denied Reed any part in the<lb/>
final conquest of yellow fever, other than that of &ldquo;confirming&rdquo; what he claimed<lb/>
Finly had already &ldquo;proved&rdquo;.</p>
<p><unclear>Albertini</unclear></p>
<p>The venemous attacks on Reed were saturated with such terms as &ldquo;trying to<lb/>
rob Finlay of his glory&rdquo;, lacking a &ldquo;scientific background&rdquo;, the Camp Lazear drama<lb/>
was classed as &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; and entirely unnecessary, &ldquo;incapable of feeling the<lb/>
emotions of the real scientist&rdquo;, strongly suggesting that Reed was &ldquo;just a salaried<lb/>
automat, carrying out the orders given him by General Wood&rdquo;. It is inconceivable<lb/>
that men of medicine could fall for such slanderous propaganda, giving no consider-<lb/>
ation to facts then fresh in the minds of every Cuban physician.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f06013013"/>
<p>-- 16 --</p>
<p>During three years in the Army and one year in civil life I had saved $1,800.00,<lb/>
denying myself many little luxuries and some that were not luxuries. Now, it was a<lb/>
case of &ldquo;all going out and nothing coming in&rdquo;. Within a very few months I was forced<lb/>
to the conclusion that the four-year budget I had so carefully prepared was long on<lb/>
optimism, notwithstanding my frugality. What between room and board, textbooks and<lb/>
other essential material, I was spending at the rate of $80.00 per month or $720.00<lb/>
for the college year of nine months. There was no certainty that I could find a job<lb/>
for the other three months of the year since Charlottesville was not even a city in<lb/>
those days. Had the University had a small hospital I might have qualified for a<lb/>
temporary position there. It boasted of a dispensary only with, perhaps, a half-dozen<lb/>
beds. I was certainly in a quandary.</p>
<p>One of the few luxuries I could afford was the Sunday edition of the New York<lb/>
Journal &amp; American. A full-page advertisement of the Grace Oil Company, illustrated<lb/>
with derricks, gushers and all, attracted my attention. I read and re-read it. The<lb/>
company had a limited number of shares for sale to the public, first come first served,<lb/>
and the favored ones would get in on the ground floor, the company having oil rights<lb/>
in the bonanza field known as &ldquo;Spindle Top Heights&rdquo; near Beaumont, Texas. Shares were<lb/>
sure to quadruple in value within the year. Like one of those &ldquo;born every minute&rdquo;, I<lb/>
swallowed the bait, hook, line and sinker. Without consulting anyone I invested $500.<lb/>
in the venture, hoping I would not be too late. Promptly I received beautifully<lb/>
engraved stock certificates for 2,000 shares and a letter of congratulation for my<lb/>
foresight, the letter adding that the available number of shares had been over-sub-<lb/>
scribed as my letter was being dictated. Then followed monthly reports, not so<lb/>
optimistic, gradually preparing for the sad news, the last one reporting that brackish<lb/>
water had invaded the company's oil wells. By this time I was more than half prepared<lb/>
for the worse. The Grace Oil Company turned out to be an aggregation of swindlers.<lb/>
I swallowed my bitter pill in silence, not wishing to have anyone know that I was so<lb/>
gullible. Toward the end of the college year I told Dr. Barringer the sad story. If,<lb/>
he said, I had only consulted him! It was now a case of &ldquo;Good bye to that M. D.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Asked what my plans were, I told Dr. Barringer I had none. He drew a letter out<lb/>
of a pigeon-hole in his desk, saying &ldquo;Read this. It may interest you&rdquo;. I read the<lb/>
letter twice. It was short and concise. It was signed by a Mr. Thomas P. Spencer,<lb/>
a native of Lynchburg, Virginia. He wanted Dr. Barringer to give him a list of young<lb/>
men who were to leave the University that year and did not expect to return. He had<lb/>
an interesting offer to make to such of them as were willing to go to Richmond to meet<lb/>
him for a personal interview, at the Hotel Jefferson, date of his arrival there given.<lb/>
In case his offer should not be acceptable to candidates, or the candidates not accept-<lb/>
able to him, railroad fare and hotel expenses would be guaranteed by him. Place of<lb/>
employment would be New York City, nature of duties not stated but declared by him to<lb/>
be such as to lead to a promising and profitable career. I decided to look into it.</p>
<p>At this time a transcedental event was in the making at the University, one which<lb/>
I could not miss even though I knew that I <del><unclear>know</unclear></del> was not to come back for the '02-'03<lb/>
session. That event involved that time-honored institution held sacred by generations<lb/>
of U.Va. students and known as &ldquo;The Honor System&rdquo;. The students themselves were the<lb/>
guardians of the Honor System and once they were satisfied that a student <unclear>had</unclear> cheated<lb/>
the violator accepted their verdict and would &ldquo;fold up his tent like the Arabs&rdquo; and<lb/>
silently abandon the University, never to return. However, for the first time, a<lb/>
student who had violated the Honor System had ignored the order to leave and elected<lb/>
to fight it out, employing a noted criminal lawyer to defend him before the student<lb/>
body. On the day of the trial all college activities were suspended, with every<lb/>
student present. The jury was composed of nine members of the faculty. Proofs that<lb/>
Mr. P--e had left the examination room and had gone to his room outside the University<lb/>
grounds, remaining there for fifteen minutes, were absolute. Further, shortly after<lb/>
abandoning his room, the student &ldquo;committee&rdquo; entered it and found his textbook open<lb/>
at the tell-tale page which answered a very difficult question on his final examination.</p>
<pb n="14" id="f06013014"/>
<p>-- 17 --</p>
<p>Although Mr. P--e's counsel made an eloquent plea in his behalf and shedding<lb/>
crocodile tears in the bargain, Mr. P. was found guilty of violating the honor<lb/>
system and the whole student body wildly applauded the verdict. It was my impress-<lb/>
ion that it was the first time in the history of the University that a violator of<lb/>
The Honor System had challenged the findings of a &ldquo;Student Committee&rdquo; entrusted with<lb/>
its guardianship. The fact that he was a member of one of the FFV (First Families<lb/>
of Virginia) did not help. On the contrary it was considered incumbent upon him to<lb/>
hold that distinction without blemish. I have never forgotten the impression that<lb/>
that incident made on me. My memories of The Honor System are just as keen as are<lb/>
those of the Serpentine Walk, the Rotunda and the Lawn. I bade good bye to good old<lb/>
Virginia with deep and sincere regret.</p>
<p>I kept my date with Mr. Spencer who informed me that he had just been appointed<lb/>
general manager of the Metropolitan Office of the Travelers Insurance Company, of<lb/>
Hartford, at 31 Nassau Street, New York, which had recently added life insurance to<lb/>
its lines of accident and casualty insurance. Mr. Spencer was a convincing talker<lb/>
and soon had me won over so that I began to share his enthusiasm. It was because of<lb/>
his outstanding success as an insurance solicitor with the Northwestern Mutual Life<lb/>
that Travelers had selected him for their top man in New York. But I soon found that<lb/>
life insurance was a tough game, especially in the highly competitive City of New<lb/>
York and for one of the most competetive commodities in that market. It was a comm-<lb/>
odity which did not appeal to a man's stomach or vanity. He had to be lectured on<lb/>
his duty to posterity - parents, wife and children, with never a thought that the<lb/>
Grim Reaper might be waiting for him around the corner, leaving his loved ones to<lb/>
look out for themselves. Given an opportunity, the insurance solicitor could drive<lb/>
in that hard, cold fact, but in those days the value of life insurance was barely<lb/>
understood by the average man. It was in its infancy.</p>
<p>Mr. Spencer's first class of &ldquo;recruits&rdquo; numbered 30 men, all ranging in age<lb/>
between 25 and 30. We were all allowed a modest drawing account against future<lb/>
commissions. One by one and month after month our ranks registered casualties, not-<lb/>
withstanding daily lectures by Mr. Spencer on perseverance and &ldquo;stick-to-it-iveness&rdquo;,<lb/>
a term which he dearly loved. The more sensitive souls felt discouraged and humili-<lb/>
ated at being kicked out of offices and office buildings. In common with book agents,<lb/>
the insurance solicitor was looked upon as a nuisance by elevator operators, office<lb/>
boys and secretaries, all in league to frustrate his efforts to reach the presence of<lb/>
the boss. Thanks to the efforts of Mr. Spencer, I managed to survive the crucial<lb/>
period. Two years had rolled by before I could afford a vacation. All through the<lb/>
scorching night-and-day heat of July and August, I stuck to canvassing for insurance<lb/>
prospects. I was now an experienced insurance solicitor, needing no lectures or en-<lb/>
couragement from Mr. Spencer. I had a nice renewal income from policies in force.</p>
<p>I left for the Midwest in June, 1904, where I expected to spend three months, to<lb/>
include July and August and do a lot of reading and loafing, for a change. In less<lb/>
than three weeks I received a letter from Colonel Gorgas, written "On Board the SS<lb/>
&ldquo;Allianca&rdquo;, of the Panama Railroad Steamship Company, dated June 22, 1904, offering<lb/>
me a position as sanitary inspector on the Panama Canal, Colonel Gorgas being then<lb/>
on his way to assume the position of Chief Sanitary Officer. His letter read &ldquo;If you<lb/>
desire this position I would like to have you at once. ......... I am authorized to<lb/>
pay you a salary of $100.00 a month. ....... Present this letter to the Panama Rail-<lb/>
road Steamship Co. at 24 State Street, who will give you transportation. Your pay will<lb/>
commence from the date of sailing.&rdquo; I thought the matter over for a week and finally<lb/>
decided to relinquish economic independence for &ldquo;The Call of the Tropics&rdquo; and wander-<lb/>
lust, much to the consternation of Mr. Spencer. I forestalled the arguments which I<lb/>
knew he would make, telling him my decision was not made overnight, but after a week's<lb/>
reflection and debate with my own thoughts and conscience. Being foot loose and fancy<lb/>
free, the consequences would be mine and mine only. He made no further effort to<lb/>
hold me.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f06013015"/>
<p>-- 18 --</p>
<p>No one knew better than I that, from a material pint of view, I was making a<lb/>
capital error. I saved what I could out of the wreck. I sold my prospect cards for<lb/>
twenty-five cents each to one of the few survivors of the original class of 30<lb/>
&ldquo;recruits&rdquo;, index, file and all, about two thousand in number. My contract with<lb/>
Travelers stipulated that if for three succesive years I should fail to bring in<lb/>
any new business, my account would be liquidated and my contract cancelled. An<lb/>
office employee would attend to collection of premiums on the business I had in<lb/>
force. In the meantime I had cabled Colonel Gorgas my acceptance of his offer and<lb/>
on July 19, 1904, I boarded a steamer for Colon, thus becoming one of the pioneers<lb/>
on the Panama Canal, all 1904 men being so considered, years later.</p>
<p>As a sanitary inspector my first assignment was in the Colon district but present-<lb/>
I was induced to switch to a clerkship at Colon Hospital, a position I resigned in<lb/>
January of 1905, confinement within the four walls of an office not being to my liking.<lb/>
Accepting a reduction in salary, I again became a sanitary inspector, with no break in<lb/>
my service. Presently I was transferred to Panama City for fumigation work, a yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic being then in full swing there. The plan mapped out by Colonel Gorgas<lb/>
included wholesale fumigation of the city from one extreme to the other. We were two<lb/>
sanitary inspectors in joint charge of a sanitary brigade of 400 men, the other being<lb/>
William J. Murphy of Harpers Ferry, West Virginia. Our force included two score fore-<lb/>
men and sub-foremen, carpenters and cartmen. The rank and file of our brigade had had<lb/>
no previous experience in fumigation work but we wre fortunate in having two Cuban<lb/>
foremen who had served under Gorgas in Havana. As a matter of fact my own experience<lb/>
had been limited to isolated fumigations of hotels and private residences where Americ-<lb/>
ans had been taken down with yellow fever.</p>
<p>Murphy suggested and Colonel Gorgas approved the idea of adopting a uniform to<lb/>
serve us as an emblem of authority and to distinguish us from the average civilian,<lb/>
so we decided on a modified naval officer's uniform, with no insignia. Pure linen<lb/>
drill was cheap in those days, so was tailoring and laundry charges. Once more I was<lb/>
back in uniform, but this time I could shed it when I pleased, something I could not<lb/>
do in the army. We were authorized by the Panamanian government to take over the<lb/>
&ldquo;Plaza del Triumfo&rdquo; (Triumph Plaza) for our equipment. It was a much-neglected and<lb/>
bare &ldquo;Plaza&rdquo;, with no shade trees, plants or benches, one block back of Central Ave-<lb/>
nue, the main artery of Panama City. We had the whole-hearted cooperation of Doctor<lb/>
Manuel Amador Guerrero, first president of the young republic, which one of our young<lb/>
wits had nicknamed &ldquo;The Peanut Republic&rdquo;, because of its small size. In like manner<lb/>
we had the support of Don Francisco de la Ossa, Mayor of the city. Our authority under<lb/>
the Panama Canal Treaty was practically absolute in everything related to public health,<lb/>
but we rarely had to invoke our rights, since the authorities backed us in entire good<lb/>
faith. That mild-mannered gentleman, Colonel Gorgas, imbued his subordinates with a<lb/>
spirit of patience and tolerance towards the natives, having more faith in persuasive<lb/>
measures than in &ldquo;The Big Stick&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Panamanians observed our movements with mixed curiosity and trembling. By this<lb/>
time they had had practical demonstrations of our clean-up methods, which included dis-<lb/>
infection of cesspools and oiling of stagnant inside of and around buildings. Our<lb/>
stocks included hundreds of cast-iron pots, of the tripod variety, for burning sulphur<lb/>
and pyrethrum with safety. Pots of the &ldquo;legless&rdquo; class had to be set on cobble-stones.<lb/>
Our stock of pyrethrum or Dalmatian Powder was enormous, followed by sulphur, the most<lb/>
efficient of the two but limited in use because of the corrosive action of its fumes on<lb/>
metals and mirrors. Next in importance came wood alcohol to start burning of the fumi-<lb/>
gating agents. We used sulphur fumigation only in outhouses, stables and in dwellings<lb/>
an shacks of the poorer classes where its fumes could do little damage.</p>
<p>Most of the natives considered our work more of a nuisance than a benefit. Had not<lb/>
Panama been a plague-ridden strip of tropical country since the year ONE? Did those<lb/>
&ldquo;Americanos&rdquo; think they could wipe out yellow fever, bubonic <unclear>plague</unclear>, malaria and other<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06013016"/>
-- 19 --<lb/>
scourges at which the French had failed? Diplomatically we would ask them if they<lb/>
did not know how Gorgas had wiped out yellow fever in Cuba. One in a hundred did know<lb/>
but the rest did not. Those who knew of Walter Reed's experiments, followed by Gorgas'<lb/>
campaign of mosquito extermination in Cuba were few and far between, and even the few<lb/>
had not grasped its significance. But, like the Cubans, they were to learn, it being<lb/>
our business to give them practical lessons.</p>
<p>When we wre all set we started our wholesale fumigation at a point known as &ldquo;Las<lb/>
Bovedas&rdquo;, the old, walled section of the city, three or four blocks removed from &ldquo;Plaza<lb/>
de la Catedral&rdquo; or Cathedral Square. Day after day, our motley crews of Jamaicans and<lb/>
other West Indian negroes became more and more efficient. Taking every building in our<lb/>
stride, we presently reached Cathedral Square and its surrounding specialty shops and<lb/>
near-by department stores. Here we instinctively knew that we could expect opposition<lb/>
to our work. Following the Gorgas policy we would try to sidestep trouble and allay<lb/>
the fears of the merchant class. First on our list of stores was the haberdashery of<lb/>
Carlos Muller, a small but well-stocked shop which catered to the elite of Panama. I<lb/>
was courteously received by the owner. Yes, he had been expecting our visit. With not<lb/>
a little concern, he told me he feared fumigation would damage, perhaps ruin, his stock<lb/>
of fabrics, much of which was of the snow-white variety. I told him that responsibil-<lb/>
ity would be ours and that we were prepared to guarantee him against loss for any item<lb/>
of merchandise which might suffer damage from pyrethrum fumes. Could I obtain such a<lb/>
promise in writing? Certainly, I could, previous authority to that effect having been<lb/>
given by Colonel Gorgas. I would obtain such a promise, in letter form, from the Chief<lb/>
Sanitary Officer. We knew that the results of that first fumigation of a commercial<lb/>
establishment would have a far-reaching effect on similar fumigations. Satisfied, Mr.<lb/>
Muller had no further objections.</p>
<p>I set the hour for fumigation to suit Mr. Muller's convenience. We could take over<lb/>
the store from 11:00 A. M. to 1:30 P. M. At my suggestion, Mr. Muller laid out on the<lb/>
counters a number of delicate fabrics, bolts of linen and silk, all to be partly unfold-<lb/>
ed so that any taint or stain could be detected by comparison with the unexposed folds.<lb/>
Would Mr. Muller be kind enough to notify some of his business friends whose fears<lb/>
might be similar to his own, so that they could see for themselves that the pyrethrum<lb/>
smoke would not affect their wares.? Certainly, he would be glad to do so. Fumigation<lb/>
was to last the customary two hours, the additional half hour being consumed in sealing<lb/>
cracks and crevices and sweeping up afterwards. Promptly on the hour I took charge of<lb/>
the shop. The number of doors and windows being few, sealing was comparatively simple<lb/>
and rapid. With the proper number of cast-iron pots, each with its quota of pyrethrum<lb/>
powder, we were now all set. But I was taking no chances, so I decided to set fire to<lb/>
every other pot only. It was not a simulated job but it came close to being just that.<lb/>
I considered it justifiable, in view of the fact that so much depended on the results.<lb/>
I knew from experience that an almost imperceptible brown stain would show up on the<lb/>
snow-white fabrics if I carried out a full-fledged fumigation and that Mr. Muller and<lb/>
his friends would be sure to notice it.</p>
<p>It was now my problem to remove the pots and get them out of the way before the<lb/>
arrival of Mr. Muller and his friends. For that reason, I cut the duration of the<lb/>
fumigation from two hours to an hour and three-quarters. With a cart at hand, I had<lb/>
the pots removed, placing a burnt pot on top of each of those which had not been set<lb/>
off. Our sweepers got into action. Examining the insects in the sweepings they appear-<lb/>
ed to be dead, although they might have been just stunned. Cockroaches were still<lb/>
kicking and had to be liquidated, but in the sweeping-up process no mosquito could<lb/>
survive. All the sweepings were dumped into a garbage can and covered with waste<lb/>
paper to which we applied a match. Our fumigation turned out to be a bullseye, with<lb/>
not a shade of brown visible on any of the exposed articles. Mr. Muller and his friends<lb/>
were happy and no further letters from Colonel Gorgas would be required. Our course<lb/>
was clear from there on, so far as mercantile establishments were concerned.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f06013017"/>
<p>-- 20 --</p>
<p>In fumigating residences, however, our path was not exactly strewn with roses<lb/>
but there were thorns aplenty. The natives found a thousand and one reasons for<lb/>
postponing the &ldquo;fatal day&rdquo; for fumigation, while our task was to advance rapidly at<lb/>
any cost. Sickness in the family was their most effective weapon, but we had made<lb/>
provision for that. We had a Panamanian doctor on our payroll to investigate every<lb/>
such case and he was authorized to offer the stricken member of the family free<lb/>
ambulance and hospital treatment at Santa Tomas Hospital, with its competent medical<lb/>
staff. In 95 cases out of a hundred, sickness was simulated, so we would return to<lb/>
the house and complete arrangements for an early morning hour, after the family had<lb/>
had their light tropical breakfast. They could visit friends or relatives until the<lb/>
afternoon, when our work would be finished. In all truth, our task required diplomacy<lb/>
and tact and I am sure we merited their good will. Latin Americans are a courteous<lb/>
and hospitable people but they are extremely sensitive.</p>
<p>The yellow fever epidemic's banner year was 1905. The French Administration<lb/>
Building in Panama City was then occupied by the Isthmian Canal Commission and its<lb/>
300 employees. They roomed in hotels, boarding houses and private residences. When<lb/>
three of them died from yellow fever within a two weeks' period, a full-fledged panic<lb/>
was in the making and the few outbound steamers were crowded with employees. Had<lb/>
accomodations been available, the exodus would have been general. I thanked my lucky<lb/>
star that I was immune. One employee who had arrived in Colon never set foot on<lb/>
Panama soil, refusing to land and remaining aboard until the steamer returned to New<lb/>
York. His was an extreme case however. By and large, the Americans then employed on<lb/>
the Panama Canal were a valiant aggregation and imbued with the pioneer spirit.</p>
<p>It had its beginning when I was arranging for a day and hour to fumigate the resi-<lb/>
dence of Doctor Manuel Coroalles, then absent in New York, accompanied by his wife,<lb/>
where he had gone to consult a specialist. His daughter, Elida, the eldest of five<lb/>
sisters was nominally in charge of the house. My interview with her was strictly in<lb/>
line of duty but there and then I lost my heart to her and she has been caring for it<lb/>
ever since. Her name as well as her surname were far from common. As a matter of fact<lb/>
I have never met any one with that surname in any Latin American country that I have<lb/>
visited. In Cuba, where Doctor Coroalles was born, the only two bearing that surname<lb/>
are his two sons and their sons. But to get on with this transcedental event in my<lb/>
life. On the evening of the day I first met her, I called to make sure that there<lb/>
would be no misunderstanding as to the day and hour for the fumigation, and again the<lb/>
following evening. On the third evening I proposed marriage to her and was tentatively<lb/>
accepted. She told me that in the absence of her parents a formal engagement could not<lb/>
take place. It was in May, 1905. In the meantime she had confided the great news to<lb/>
her married sister and the sister consulted her husband, who carried on a quiet invest-<lb/>
igation of my person and precedents, following which he requested to meet me. He appear-<lb/>
ed to be satisfied that my intentions were entirely honorable. Her four sisters and<lb/>
the married one were solidly in my favor.</p>
<p>About the middle of July her parents returned and the dreaded interview with her<lb/>
father was to be faced. In pretty much of a flurry and no little apprehension, I met<lb/>
her parents. Her father, still in delicate health, left me to the tender mercies of<lb/>
her mother, who spoke English very well. Elida sat in the parlor with one or two of<lb/>
her sisters, while I sat on the balcony with my prospective mother-in-law. I talked<lb/>
about everything, including the weather, except what was uppermost in my mind. Finally,<lb/>
in desperation, she blurted out &ldquo;Mr. Moran, are you in love with me or with my daughter&rdquo;<lb/>
That broke the ice and I was no longer tongue-tied. I was to return the following day<lb/>
for my answer, after talking the matter over with here husband. With no suspicion on<lb/>
my part that the family preocupation was as to whether or not I had any matrimonial<lb/>
impediments, I came back for the verdict. I faced the doctor and I fancied I saw an<lb/>
expression of antagonism there. He spoke no English and I was not much of an expert<lb/>
in Spanish. He could read French and English well but could not speak the latter.<lb/>
Could I get a letter from Colonel Gorgas to the effect that I was a fit partner for<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f06013018"/>
-- 21 --<lb/>
his daughter? Certainly, I could. I lost no time in calling on the Colonel for<lb/>
the letter. Smiling broadly, the Colonel remarked that Latin American families<lb/>
always insisted that foreigners aspiring to marry one of their daughters should<lb/>
furnish proofs of celibacy.</p>
<p>Jokingly, Colonel Gorgas remarked &ldquo;I do not know whether you are married or not,<lb/>
Mr. Moran, but I will take a chance on it&rdquo;. Calling a stenographer, he dictated a<lb/>
letter to &ldquo;To Whom it May Concern&rdquo;, certifying that to the best of his knowledge and<lb/>
belief I was an unmarried man and that he had known me since 1901 as a man of irre-<lb/>
proachable character. Handing me the letter, I hastened to deliver it to my prospect-<lb/>
ive father-in-law. Upon reading the letter he frowned, having expected a letter<lb/>
addressed to him personally. Very well, I would call on the Colonel for the form of<lb/>
letter he wanted. Sheepfacedly, I again called on the Colonel who gave me the accept-<lb/>
able modification in a new letter, which proved entirely satisfactory.</p>
<p>I wanted to get married at once, but it could not be. The bride's trousseau could<lb/>
not be ready in less than three weeks. We first met on May 26 and we were married on<lb/>
August 10th, after a record courtship of less than three months. The old adage, &ldquo;marry<lb/>
in haste and repent at leisure&rdquo;, has never had any meaning in our case. In our forty<lb/>
odd years of married life we have seen many a union go on the rocks among our own<lb/>
friends and our respective families. Elida's family, by the way, was a numerous one<lb/>
with two sons and nine daughters. Her father was a Cuban exile who, shortly after<lb/>
graduating as a medico, was forced to leave his native country for participating in a<lb/>
conspiracy against the Spanish regime, first going to New York and eventually settling<lb/>
down in Panama City, having never renounced his Cuban citizenship. A year after our<lb/>
marriage he passed on to his reward. When he was on his deathbed and knowing that his<lb/>
days were numbered, he called me to his side to tell me to take good care of his<lb/>
daughter, adding that she was the noblest of his eleven children, sweet-tempered and<lb/>
profoundly religious but extremely sensitive to unmerited reproach. She has been all<lb/>
that in my life, God bless her, and very much more. She deserved a better life part-<lb/>
ner than myself, I am sure, but she has graciously overlooked my many imperfections.<lb/>
We have never had a serious misunderstanding and but few trivial ones, nor are we<lb/>
likely to have any for the rest of the journey.</p>
<p>During the months of wholesale fumigation I had some interesting experiences, one<lb/>
of which may be worth recording. Due to the heart-breaking pace we had set for our-<lb/>
selves and the tension of our work, I was admitted to Ancon Hospital twice, suffering<lb/>
from my old enemy, malaria. All fever patients admitted to the hospital were screened<lb/>
through the yellow fever ward. I would patiently explain to the doctor that I was<lb/>
immune to yellow fever and while filling out my admission slip he would look up and<lb/>
say &ldquo;Oh, YES?&rdquo;, then call the orderly, saying &ldquo;Take Mr. Moran to the yellow fever ward&rdquo;<lb/>
Arriving there I was placed in a screened cage. During the yellow fever epidemic,<lb/>
Colonel Gorgas never failed to visit the yellow fever ward every morning before going<lb/>
to his office. Accompanied by the nurse in charge, he would stand before my cage and<lb/>
say &ldquo;Mr. Moran, what are you doing here?&rdquo;. &ldquo;They would not believe me, Colonel, when<lb/>
I told them I was immune&rdquo;. Smiling, he would turn to the nurse and say &ldquo;Miss .......,<lb/>
please have Mr. Moran removed to Ward 15&rdquo;, the malarial ward. The foregoing dialogue<lb/>
was repeated within the short space of a few months. Only a few of the doctors on the<lb/>
Isthmus knew that I had been one of Walter Reed's guinea pigs. Colonel Gorgas was one<lb/>
of them, of course.</p>
<p>By the end of 1905 yellow fever was no longer a menace on the Isthmus of Panama.<lb/>
Fumigations were rare and Colonel Gorgas authorized me to take an overdue combination<lb/>
honeymoon and vacation. When I returned I was given charge of the Culebra district as<lb/>
sanitary inspector. A new administration building had been built on a hill overlooking<lb/>
the famous &ldquo;Culebra Cut&rdquo;, housing the Chief Engineer and his corps of assistants, Mr.<lb/>
John F. Stevens, being then Chief Engineer of the Panama Canal, with Mr. J. G. Sullivan<lb/>
Assistant Chief Engineer. It was here that I came near meeting my &ldquo;Waterloo&rdquo; at the<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f06013019"/>
-- 22 --<lb/>
hands of Mr. Sullivan, Acting Chief Engineer in the absence of Mr. Stevens. It came<lb/>
about this way; Between the towns of Culebra and Empire there was a swamp known as<lb/>
&ldquo;Lirio Swamps&rdquo;, so named because of the myriad of water-lilys growing in its center.<lb/>
It was quite extensive and it had a quicksand base. To reach the stagnant water in<lb/>
its center was a problem, and the oiling of stagnant water to prevent mosquito breed-<lb/>
ing was one of the principal tasks of a sanitary inspector. Lirio Swamps was in real-<lb/>
ity a mosquito hatchery. By deepening an already existing ditch at one end of the<lb/>
swamp I decided that we could draw off most of the stagnant water, but to do that it<lb/>
would be necessary to turn a small quantity of water into the canal for a few days<lb/>
while our men deepened the ditch, using wheelbarrows to haul out the excavated dirt,<lb/>
the banks of the ditch being too high to permit of shovelling it. The ditch was origin-<lb/>
ally dug by the French and intended to carry off the overflow, following heavy rains,<lb/>
so it might not flow into the canal and impede excavation work. They were not interest-<lb/>
ed in mosquito control, aside from screening the more luxurious residences of their top<lb/>
executives, while the rank and file of their employees could get along as best they<lb/>
could by using mosquito nets over their beds or cots.</p>
<p>After consultation with the Chief Sanitary Inspector he gave me his OK after look-<lb/>
ing over the site of our proposed operations. Since they involved diversion of a small<lb/>
quantity of water into the canal, it was understood that our work should be rushed.<lb/>
We knew the Engineering Department would be sure to call a halt on our activities, once<lb/>
discovered and reported. We had selected a propitious moment, in that the swamp water<lb/>
was very low, following a few weeks of dry weather. Our men worked like beavers for<lb/>
two days, but an inquisitive foreman happened along, inquiring what we were up to and<lb/>
by what authority we were diverting water into the canal. During those two days I was<lb/>
conveniently &ldquo;absent&rdquo; from Culebra, my foreman reporting to me surreptitiously at night.<lb/>
I had no doubt that trouble was brewing for me and that sooner or later I would be<lb/>
called upon to explain my &ldquo;audacious&rdquo; act. Two days after we had finished our job I<lb/>
received a letter from Mr. Sullivan, addressed to me personally. The letter opened<lb/>
with: &ldquo;Imagine my surprise ..........&rdquo;, then recited the capital sin I had committed,<lb/>
winding up with: &ldquo;I am giving you this opportunity to explain instead of asking for<lb/>
your instant dismissal from the service.&rdquo; I would have been entirely willing to explain<lb/>
and justify my actions to Mr. Sullivan, but his veiled threat left me no other alter-<lb/>
native than that of striking back, regardless of consequences.</p>
<p>Instead of giving Mr. Sullivan the explanation he so crudely demanded, I wrote him<lb/>
a biting, if not sarcastic, letter, informing him that he would receive an explanation<lb/>
from the head of my department in due time, to whom his letter had been forwarded thru<lb/>
proper channels, adding that since he was &ldquo;making a mountain out of a mole-hill&rdquo;, I was<lb/>
not obliged to see his &ldquo;mountain&rdquo;, my imagination being too narrow to reach such fan-<lb/>
tastic heights. I took great care to make my letter personal, avoiding titles of any<lb/>
kind, assuring him that the little fish could give a good account of itself before the<lb/>
big fish succeeded in swallowing it and that, in the meantime, another big fish could<lb/>
come to my assistance.</p>
<p>Ten days later, Mr. Sullivan's letter brought an energetic reply from Colonel<lb/>
Gorgas, strictly official and addressed to the Chief Engineer, deploring &ldquo;the tone<lb/>
and language used&rdquo; to reprimand one of his subordinates, adding that if the inspector<lb/>
had committed a fault the matter should have been reported to him for appropriate act-<lb/>
ion; that if he was to maintain discipline within his own organization, letters of this<lb/>
nature would nullify his efforts. I was not furnished with a copy of Colonel Gorgas'<lb/>
letter but I saw it later on. I also learned of Mr. Sullivan's reaction when he receiv-<lb/>
ed it, as I had several friends in the Chief Engineer's office to satisfy my curiosity.<lb/>
My informant told me that Mr. Sullivan literally &ldquo;hit the ceiling&rdquo; when he read it.<lb/>
To the best of my knowledge the duel ended there and then.</p>
<p>In a way I was sorry for my passage at arms with Mr. Sullivan. He was an able<lb/>
railroad engineer, having served on the Great Northern with Mr. Stevens, returning<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f06013020"/>
-- 23 --<lb/>
to that Company shortly after Colonel Goethals took over as Chairman of the Panama<lb/>
Canal Commission and Chief Engineer. That was the last I heard of him until I read<lb/>
of his death a few years ago. He was accustomed to straight-from-the-shoulder methods<lb/>
and I knew that his letter to me grated on my mild-mannered chief, who could deny a<lb/>
request and have the petitioner leave his office almost as happy as if the request<lb/>
had been granted. Mr. Sullivan made &ldquo;Much Ado About Nothing&rdquo;, since the quantity of<lb/>
water we had diverted into the canal was so insignificant that it was absorbed by the<lb/>
earth or evaporated within a few hours, causing less damage than would a ten-minute<lb/>
shower. I had no intention to step on the toes of the engineering department, but I<lb/>
was morally certain that if I had asked for permission to accomplish that part of my<lb/>
job, it would have been denied. I drained off considerable stagnant water, with no<lb/>
damage to the canal, thus limiting a mosquito-breeding area.</p>
<p>As I have already stated, I resigned on July 13, 1906, to manage my brother-in-<lb/>
law's jewelry store in the city of Panama, while he was recuperating in his native<lb/>
Switzerland. He having reneged on the terms of our partnership, I divorced myself<lb/>
from his business at the end of February, 1907. Our parting was entirely devoid of<lb/>
any ill-feeling on my part. I could not see things his way and after all the business<lb/>
was his. I had served him in need and at a time when I could have driven a hard<lb/>
bargain with him and have him like it. Had it not been that his wife and mine were<lb/>
sisters I might not have broken my service with the Sanitary Department except at a<lb/>
commensurate price.</p>
<p><unclear>Where</unclear></p>
<p>On March 1, 1907, with a break in service of less than eight months, I was welcom-<lb/>
ed back in the Sanitary Department by Colonel Gorgas. I informed him that I would<lb/>
prefer a position other than that of sanitary inspector, an underpaid position as<lb/>
compared with work of equal responsibility in other departments of the Canal. For a<lb/>
short time I was employed on property records in the Colonel's office, where I<lb/>
advanced rapidly. Seven months later, Colonel Gorgas sent for me one morning and in<lb/>
the sixty seconds it required to reach his private office I was speculating as to<lb/>
whether I was in for a reprimand, or what. Hitherto, my duties concerned his execu-<lb/>
tive officer, Major Champ C. McCulloch, of the Army Medical Corps, a fine, upstanding<lb/>
Texan. The Colonel informed me that he was very much worried about affairs at the<lb/>
Medical Storehouse, in Colon. The Auditor of the Panama Canal had recently rendered<lb/>
a report indicating a shortage of $60,000.00 at the Storehouse. He had Captain<lb/>
Shanton, Chief of Police of the Canal Zone, make an investigation with the result<lb/>
that no trace of irregularities on the part of the storekeeper could be established.<lb/>
He and Major McCulloch had talked the matter over and they had agreed on me to solve<lb/>
the mystery. &ldquo;Go in and see the Major about it and then come back to see me&rdquo;, he said.</p>
<p>Major McCulloch was expecting me and dismissed the stenographer to whom he was<lb/>
dictating. Well, how did I feel about it? I told him I was flattered by the con-<lb/>
fidence they had in me, but doubted my ability to unravel the apparently inexplicable<lb/>
shortage. If I should fail, and thus disappoint them, I would be worse off in my own<lb/>
opinion than if I had never undertaken it. The Major replied &ldquo;You have an excellent<lb/>
reputation for figures and detail and those are the qualifications necessary in clear-<lb/>
ing up this mess - if it can be cleared. All we expect of you is to do your best and<lb/>
we are sure you will do just that&rdquo;. As a matter of fact I was not very keen on the<lb/>
assignment but I could not very well sidestep it, so I accepted it. The Major conti-<lb/>
nued &ldquo;As you know, Dr. W.....s is bonded for $10,000.00 and he will remain on the pay-<lb/>
roll until his property accounts are cleared up. You will have full charge and we want<lb/>
you to help him all you can to get out of the mess he has created for himself. So far,<lb/>
there is not a scrap of evidence that he has unlawfully disposed of government property.<lb/>
Your salary for the present will remain the same but I can assure you that if you make<lb/>
good, you will be receiving $250.00 a month within two years.&rdquo; Knowing Major McCulloch<lb/>
as I did, I hadn't the slightest doubt that he spoke in good faith. Family quarters<lb/>
would be assigned me within the Colon Hospital grounds and later on a Type 17 house<lb/>
<pb n="21" id="f06013021"/>
-- 24 --<lb/>
(one family) would be built for me near the Medical Storehouse. It was, and I lived<lb/>
in it happily for seven years.</p>
<p>When I presented my credentials to my harried predecessor, he received me with<lb/>
open arms, but not so his five office assistants who looked upon me as more or less<lb/>
of an intruder. They had expected a change in storekeepers and probably calculated<lb/>
that one of their own number would be trusted with the job, hence it was entirely<lb/>
natural that they would have a veiled resentment against an outsider. There was no<lb/>
open hostility towards me, however, so I decided to act unconcerned. I was there to<lb/>
do a job and intended to do it and the weeding out of trouble-makers could be done<lb/>
later if I found it necessary. Within 24 hours after my arrival, I had the key to<lb/>
the situation. Dr. W. had converted a six-man office force into a one-man organiza-<lb/>
tion. He delegated no responsibility to any of his assistants. The most trivial out-<lb/>
going required his OK before it could be mailed. His desk was littered with &ldquo;pending&rdquo;<lb/>
business. In filling requisitions, each man checked his own work from the issue clerk<lb/>
to the packing list, to the stock-cards clerk and to the invoice clerk - four separate<lb/>
steps which each employee should have checked with another. I gave it the name of the<lb/>
&ldquo;double-checking system&rdquo;, a system as old as the hills.</p>
<p>Feeling sure that my trail would lead to a &ldquo;paper shortage&rdquo;, I came to the con-<lb/>
clusion that a re-check of three years' issues of medical supplies would unearth a<lb/>
startling series of discrepancies and solve the riddle which had so worried Colonel<lb/>
Gorgas. In the meantime, current business could not be neglected. Stocks had to be<lb/>
replenished through orders on the Medical Supply Depot of the Army, in New York, which<lb/>
served as our purchasing agent. Hospitals and dispensaries had to be supplied from our<lb/>
stocks. At the end of three months the paper shortage of $60,000.00 was reduced to<lb/>
$800.00. That amount represented items which had been destroyed or dumped without<lb/>
action of The Board of Survey without whose authority of &ldquo;Inspected &amp; Condemned&rdquo; credit<lb/>
could not be taken on the stock cards. Every hospital and dispensary to whom supplies<lb/>
had been issued in excess of quantities receipted for was obliged to sign a receipt<lb/>
for same. Some of the district physicians demurred because &ldquo;this happened while Dr.<lb/>
thus-and-so was in charge of the dispensary&rdquo;, but we proved by the packing lists and<lb/>
other data that the supplies had been shipped.</p>
<p>Strange enough, comparatively few report errors in their favor and fewer yet who<lb/>
will not report them, if short-shipped. In our case it was all government property and<lb/>
would be used legitimately in any event. All parties concerned were, no doubt, inher-<lb/>
ently honest but had not stopped to think that some one would be called upon, sooner or<lb/>
later, to account for the over-shipped-and-not-receipted-for items. When it came to<lb/>
government property, to receive something without signing for it was considered a fair<lb/>
game. Those who feel that way in such matters are personally honest in 99 cases out<lb/>
of a hundred and would never think of cheating an individual. Finally, we had scraped<lb/>
the barrel clean, but that $800.00 would become a claim against the bonding company if<lb/>
the Panama Canal administration could not be induced to absorb the amount, a claim<lb/>
which I thought would not be a just one, especially in view of the fact that it concern-<lb/>
ed a three-year period, during which no audit had been made. Also, it would have<lb/>
resulted in barring Dr. W. from occupying a bonded position in future. The fact that<lb/>
he was a victim of his own ineptitude and lack of system or coordination, rather than<lb/>
a proved appropriator of government property, was an extenuating circumstance.</p>
<p>I personally pleaded his case with Colonel Gorgas, who explained to me that Colonel<lb/>
Goethals, the Chairman &amp; Chief Engineer, was the only man on the Isthmus who had author-<lb/>
ity to pardon or &ldquo;write off&rdquo; the $800.00 shortage and clear the negligent employee's<lb/>
bond. I then requested permission to personally take up the case with Colonel Goethals,<lb/>
to which he readily agreed. I had met Colonel Goethals just once, a week or so after<lb/>
his arrival on the Isthmus, when the University Club held a reception in his honor.<lb/>
As I was only one of a hundred or more whom he met on that occasion, he would not, of<lb/>
course, remember me. I calculated that a personal explanation would be more effective<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="f06013022"/>
-- 25 --<lb/>
than a long letter, an opinion with which Colonel Gorgas was in complete accord. I made<lb/>
an appointment with Colonel Goethals through his executive secretary and a few days<lb/>
later I was received by him. When he realized that my mission was in behalf of some<lb/>
one else, and not my own, he graciously heard me through my brief summary of Dr. W's<lb/>
unfortunate predicament, listening carefully until I had finished. He had the reput-<lb/>
ation by this time of being a &ldquo;Benevolent Despot&rdquo;, but eminently just and but little<lb/>
influenced by personalities and position. Once convinced that a complaining day labor-<lb/>
er's cause was just, he did not hesitate to over-rule the head of his department, but<lb/>
woe unto the man who would appeal to him without having reason on his side. For him<lb/>
and his ilk, there was a steamer out of Colon once a week and he would be sure to be<lb/>
on it. I left with his assurance that a brief letter for the record would result in<lb/>
a pardon for Dr. W., classifying him in my mind as very human.</p>
<p>Returning to Colon, I informed Dr. W. that he would soon be free to leave the<lb/>
Isthmus, with no stigma on his record. Poor fellow, I felt very sorry for him. The<lb/>
pent-up emotions and mental agony of several months now gave way to joy and that boon<lb/>
of the afflicted - tears. He broke down and cried like a baby. Who could blame him?<lb/>
He was an honest man but he was assigned a position for which he was not qualified.<lb/>
Like most medicos, he was not much of a business man. I heard from him, on and off,<lb/>
for the succeeding two or three years. He had gone back to New Orleans and reported<lb/>
that he was making headway in his profession. I have always been happy to know that<lb/>
I was instrumental in a small way in his rehabilitation.</p>
<p>The records of the Panama Canal will show that my administration of the Medical<lb/>
Storehouse was successful, but they will not show the thousands of dollars I saved the<lb/>
Government in the judicious ordering and distribution of medical supplies. Efficiency<lb/>
in Government service is based on the employee's ability to account for property he<lb/>
receives and issues. Initiative tending to cut down waste and increase economy is<lb/>
rarely rewarded as it should be. More than once I have been criticized for question-<lb/>
ing what looked to me to be excessive quantities of a given drug called for on a<lb/>
requisition. Colonel Gorgas backed me up in insisting that hospitals and dispensaries<lb/>
call for a month's supply of drugs and chemicals, so that I could form an &ldquo;experience<lb/>
table&rdquo; of receipts and issues, and so that an item of current use would not be mono-<lb/>
polized by the few to the detriment of the many, but permitting special requisitions<lb/>
to be placed at any time for an exhausted item. Every district physician had his<lb/>
special hobbies in prescribing. His successor would have his own hobbies, with the<lb/>
result that the dispensary shelves were cluttered with inactive drugs and specialties.<lb/>
I had all such &ldquo;inactives&rdquo; turned into the storehouse, instead of ordering similar<lb/>
items from the U. S. Through doing so, I was not encroaching on any doctor's pre-<lb/>
rogative. It was a calculated economy.</p>
<p>In the meantime, the years rolled by and I waited for the promised increase in<lb/>
salary. Much to my own detriment, I had waited too long. Major McCulloch, the man<lb/>
who made me the promise, had long ago returned to garrison duty in the States and<lb/>
Colonel Gorgas had apparently overlooked me. Without my knowledge, a list of permanent<lb/>
salaries had been prepared at the instance of the Congressional Committee for Canal<lb/>
appropriations, so that my then salary and position was covered by legislation. I was<lb/>
left out in the cold. I took my case up to Colonel Gorgas. He recommended that I be<lb/>
given the increase, using a standard form for that purpose, which merely stated that<lb/>
&ldquo;The nature of this man's service is such that he deserves this increase&rdquo;. When that<lb/>
sterotyped form reached Colonel Goethals, he promptly returned it &ldquo;Disapproved&rdquo;, in-<lb/>
viting attention to the fact that my salary had been legislated for by Congress. I<lb/>
asked for permission to argue my case with him, which was freely granted. Although<lb/>
admitting that I had earned the increase, Colonel Goethals informed me that it would<lb/>
be most difficult to put it through. He approved it for the balance of the fiscal<lb/>
year, including April, May and June - three months only. The injustice to me had been<lb/>
unwittingly done by the head of my department. The promised raise never materialized.</p>
<pb n="23" id="f06013023"/>
<p>-- 26 --</p>
<p>That Colonel Gorgas was sincere in his efforts to right a wrong, I have no doubt.<lb/>
As a matter of fact, he was very much concerned about it, so much so that in order to<lb/>
make amends for his failure to include my name, position and salary, on the permanent<lb/>
list, he offered to recommend me anew for the increase, based on my connection with the<lb/>
yellow fever experiments carried out by Walter Reed in Cuba, an offer which I refused.<lb/>
I told him that if an increase in my salary could not be justified on the merits of<lb/>
my work, I would prefer to have the matter dropped. In looking over the permanent list<lb/>
of his department, prior to signing it, he probably had forgotten a promise which must<lb/>
have been discussed with him by Major McCulloch some three years earlier. He deplored<lb/>
my failure to remind him of that promise at an earlier date. To that I replied that I<lb/>
had never requested an increase in salary in the seven years I had been on the Canal,<lb/>
having always felt that no pressure should be brought to bear on the head of my depart-<lb/>
ment in such matters. Personally, I have never taken kindly to requests for increases<lb/>
in salary by those employed under me. If they deserved an increase I was the first to<lb/>
recognize it. By that same token I have never asked for a salary increase for myself.<lb/>
The promise made to me by Major McCulloch was entirely spontaneous and voluntary on<lb/>
his part. It was conditional on my making good and when I had made good I expected the<lb/>
promise to be made good.</p>
<p>With the Canal completed in 1914, the army of 50,000 men employed in its construct-<lb/>
ion was disbanded and the necessary small force to opearate it came into being. Med-<lb/>
ical supplies were reduced accordingly and the large medical storehouse was abandoned.<lb/>
A new storehouse was built close to Ancon Hospital with about one-fourth the floor<lb/>
space of the Colon building. The Chief Quartermaster at that time was Major Robert E.<lb/>
Wood, later Brigadier General and actually chairman of the board of directors of Sears<lb/>
Roebuck &amp; Company. He recommended that medical supplies be made a section of the<lb/>
general <unclear>strehouse</unclear> at Balboa, which I opposed, for good and sound reasons, firmly backed<lb/>
by Colonel Gorgas' successor, Colonel Charles F. Mason, Chief Health Officer, the title<lb/>
of Chief Sanitary Officer having been abolished. By this time Goethals and Gorgas had<lb/>
been promoted to Majors General, in recognition of their eminent services on the Panama<lb/>
Canal. Major Wood insisted on his plan and invited me to Culebra to talk the matter<lb/>
over. I frankly informed him that a Medical Section of the General Storehouse would<lb/>
be an &ldquo;orphan&rdquo; if its control should be taken away from the Chief Health Officer. Not<lb/>
so, with a storekeeper directly responsible to him and to him only. He still insisted.<lb/>
&ldquo;Very well, Major Wood,&rdquo; I said, &ldquo;you can name your own man to take charge. I am not<lb/>
going to be an obstacle to the carrying out of your plans. I will stay long enough<lb/>
to turn the job over to the man you select&rdquo;. That was not a part of his plan, as he<lb/>
told me. &ldquo;General Goethals wants you to be in charge&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;hold off until I can<lb/>
talk to him&rdquo;. The General over-ruled him, hence the new storehouse. Although I<lb/>
opposed him, General Wood has always been my very good friend.</p>
<p>On June 30, 1915, I resigned permanently from the service in order to go into<lb/>
business for myself in the City of Panama, an opportunity presenting itself which I<lb/>
could not pass up. My French brother-in-law was an army reservist who had been given<lb/>
a year to arrange his affairs in Panama and join the colors. The year was up and, much<lb/>
as he tried, he had not been able to sell his jewelry store. Meantime, he had reduced<lb/>
his stock to the bone, replenishing it in driblets only. He was denied an extension.<lb/>
In his predicament, he thought of me, knowing that I had a little knowledge of the line<lb/>
with my other brother-in-law, the Swiss, whose store was located in the same block. He<lb/>
sent for me and we talked the matter over. He calculated the inventory value of his<lb/>
stock at $25,000.00. I told him I was not his man. Well, how much cash could I raise?<lb/>
I told him I had $5,000.00 and could probably raise an equal amount among my American<lb/>
friends, which I would not do because I might be risking their money. He knocked me<lb/>
flat when he told me he would sell me the business with that amount as an initial pay-<lb/>
ment. He had another card up his sleeve. &ldquo;So far as you and I are concerned, you<lb/>
must let it be known that you have paid me in full&rdquo;, he said, "otherwise you will be<lb/>
unable to obtain credit. You will sign promissory notes for $20,000.00, with no<lb/>
maturity dates, to be paid in installments and at your leisure from profits. If you<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="f06013024"/>
-- 27 --<lb/>
should fail, I alone will be the loser, but if you manage the business wisely neither<lb/>
of us will lose. I did not much like the idea of some day making a false statement to<lb/>
a bank from which I might seek credit, but in the end he convinced me that my indebted-<lb/>
ness to him was purely one of honor.</p>
<p>I now became the proud owner of a very decrepit and run-down business. In the<lb/>
deal, I had two advantages. My jewelry store had the best location of four in that<lb/>
line in my block, it being located on the corner of Central Avenue and 8th Street. Good<lb/>
Will had cost me nothing, but it was an undoubted asset. The stock was at least fifty<lb/>
percent riff-raff. It had a dingy show window, old-fashioned show cases and an uneven<lb/>
concrete floor. From current sales, I enlarged the show window, replacing the ordinary<lb/>
glass with plate-glass. I ordered a horse-shoe display case from Grand Rapids, Michi-<lb/>
gan. I had the front half of the floor converted from concrete to granite, but I could<lb/>
not afford to have the rear half replaced. Looking over my out-of-date stock, I dis-<lb/>
covered that some of it had been there for over ten years. My French friend did not<lb/>
believe in &ldquo;sacrifice&rdquo; sales. Within six weeks I decided to convert all dead stock<lb/>
into dollars and cents, segregating all such items and marking them with former prices<lb/>
in black and new prices in red ink. My predecessor never showed prices in numbers, nor<lb/>
did any of my competitors, using letters only to show cost and selling price. I was<lb/>
now all set for my experiment.</p>
<p>I placed a half-page advertisement in the Panama &ldquo;Star &amp; Herald&rdquo;, a combination<lb/>
Spanish-English daily, heading it in bold type &ldquo;LIQUIDATION SALE&rdquo; To Make Room for<lb/>
New Merchandise Now on Order in the United States and Europe. For the present, $10,000.<lb/>
worth would be disposed of, first come, first served. The result far exceeded my most<lb/>
optimistic expectations. The Panamanians flocked to my store, picking out silver-plated<lb/>
articles for present and future wedding and birthday gifts. I had calculated that 10%<lb/>
of cost would cover my advertising spree, and it did. Within two months I had converted<lb/>
shop-worn odds and ends into real cash which, needless to say, I badly needed. Christmas<lb/>
was the jeweler's harvest time in those days, so I had to prepare for it.</p>
<p>I had opened my account in the Panama Branch of the Commercial National Bank of<lb/>
Washington, D. C., but recently opened, the manager being Mr. Rolfe E. Bolling, brother-<lb/>
in-law of President Woodrow Wilson who had married his sister, Mrs. Galt, nee Bolling.<lb/>
I now thought the time was ripe to sound out Mr. Bolling on the matter of commercial<lb/>
loans. Yes, Mr. Bolling had been quietly observing my progress and sales methods. He<lb/>
would not make me a loan but he would be pleased to cover my merchandise invoices, up<lb/>
to $5,000.00, documents to come through the bank for acceptance or payment on sight. In<lb/>
that way, he told me, you will not be paying interest on idle money. Exactly the form<lb/>
of credit I needed. I was badly in need of diamonds and platinum-faced jewelry, so I<lb/>
placed a most unusual order for $10,000.00 worth of diamonds, ranging in size from one-<lb/>
half to two carats, on the firm of B. H. Joseph &amp; Co., Birmingham, England. Due to the<lb/>
War, our Amsterdam connection for diamonds was unable to sell us stones. While the<lb/>
Birmingham firm were not diamond merchants, but large diamond users, they very kindly<lb/>
accepted my &ldquo;blind&rdquo; order and had the diamonds shipped from London for their account.<lb/>
I made it clear that I was asking for a favor and that I knew in advance I would have<lb/>
a square deal at their hands. About ten days before Christmas I received the diamonds.<lb/>
I have never forgotten that firm. They were manufacturers of platinum-faced gold<lb/>
jewelry and knew my predecessor well. I was one of their loyal customers while I was<lb/>
in the jewelry business. By the end of January, 1916, I had sold every stone at an<lb/>
average profit of 15%, all my customers being Canal Zone employees.</p>
<p>By this time, Mr. Bolling doubled the bank's loans against invoices. I took on<lb/>
an industrial partner, an experienced watch repair man and engraver, whose services I<lb/>
badly needed, especially for American-made movements, my Swiss watch-repair man being<lb/>
unable to properly repair and adjust American watches, my American partner being at an<lb/>
equal disadvantage in repairing and adjusting Swiss watches. I now had a balanced<lb/>
force and I was well on my way, with an up-to-date stock. Within my first year, I was<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="f06013025"/>
-- 28 --<lb/>
in position to pay off $5,000.00 of my indebtedness to the Frenchman and was enjoying<lb/>
credit from all of my predecessor's suppliers, being no longer considered a novice in<lb/>
the line. Had the United States not participated in World War I, it is more than<lb/>
likely that I would still be in business in Panama City. It was in early 1917 that I<lb/>
felt I could take a little vacation, the Christmas rush being over. My better half<lb/>
and I had long desired to see one of the famous Mar de Gras of New Orleans, carried out<lb/>
with great splendor that year. From there we crossed over to Cuba to meet members of<lb/>
her family whom I had not personally met before. While in Havana, in February, 1917,<lb/>
I could see the hand-writing on the wall, feeling certain that the U. S. would be in-<lb/>
volved in the War before many months. I had made up my mind to &ldquo;do my bit&rdquo;, come what<lb/>
might. I cut my vacation short, once more, returning to Panama forthwith. In April,<lb/>
we were in the War up to our necks. What to do!</p>
<p><unclear><hi>Ford</hi></unclear></p>
<p>My industrial partner was a comparatively young man but he was wearing a wooden<lb/>
leg, hence could not serve in the armed forces. I was 41 and a safe distance away<lb/>
from draft age. I informed him that I would sell out my business and head for the<lb/>
Army. Did he know of any likely buyer? He asked me not to look for a buyer for a<lb/>
week or ten days, that he, himself, might be able to engineer the deal in conjunction<lb/>
with his wife, a graduate nurse, who had recently come into a legacy of ten or fifteen<lb/>
thousand dollars. His share of the profits could not be retired from the business,<lb/>
according to our contract, his salary being sufficient to cover the expenses of both.<lb/>
Assisted by the bank, they were able to buy me out to within $5,000.00 of the necessary<lb/>
amount. We agreed that the sales document was to be dposited in escrow with the<lb/>
Commercial National Bank, with the obligation that all his business was to be with that<lb/>
bank until the $5,000.00 should be paid, in two yearly installments. Between one thing<lb/>
and another, I was not free to leave Panama until the end of 1917. By this time, my<lb/>
friend Bolling had resigned as manager of the Commercial National and had been named a<lb/>
vice-president of the Chatham &amp; Pheonix National Bank, in New York, being succeeded by<lb/>
a Mr. George Shaeffer, a lawyer. He was a novice in the banking game.</p>
<p>After all my affairs had been placed in order I called on Mr. Shaeffer, informing<lb/>
him that I wanted a draft on Paris for the equivalent in French francs of $15,000.00,<lb/>
payable to the order of Elie Lacroisade, my French brother-in-law, divulging for the<lb/>
the first time the terms upon which I had acquired the jewelry store. Mr. Shaeffer got<lb/>
red in the face and said &ldquo;Why, you crook. You never informed this bank that you owed<lb/>
any such amount&rdquo;. It was now my turn, so I told him that he would have to live a long<lb/>
time to surpass me in honor and honesty, adding that if he did not want to sell me the<lb/>
draft there were two other banks who would be glad to make the commission. He then<lb/>
controlled himself and apologized for his fit of ill temper. Admitting that, on the<lb/>
surface, he was right in charging me with withhoding from the bank information of such<lb/>
vital importance, I proceeded to give him a lesson in banking which I hoped would serve<lb/>
him and his bank in future.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Now, Mr. Shaeffer&rdquo;, I told him, &ldquo;You are a lawyer, recently turned banker, but a<lb/>
moment ago you forgot it and turned judge. How much credit to you suppose your bank<lb/>
would have extended me, had I told Mr. Bolling my exact worth? I will answer that<lb/>
question for you. NOT ONE PENNY. In that case, my survival in what you now know to be<lb/>
a prosperous business would have been extremely doubtful. You jumped at conclusions<lb/>
instead of seeking motives. Those motives, let me assure you, were entirely honest and<lb/>
honorable. Your branding me as a &ldquo;crook&rdquo; might have led to a serious incident, for I<lb/>
was perfectly justified in letting you have it between the eyes. That, as you know,<lb/>
would not have redounded to your credit, for a bank is not a place for a free-for-all<lb/>
and your superiors in Washington would be sure to take cognizance of it, since I would<lb/>
have taken pains to fully inform them of the incident. Having honestly liquidated my<lb/>
business, I would have nothing to lose, whereas you might lose your job. Furthermore,<lb/>
I made a voluntary confession where I was not obliged to make any confession at all.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I had thoroughly tamed Mr. Shaeffer and had forgiven but not forgotten the vile<lb/>
<pb n="26" id="f06013026"/>
-- 29 --<lb/>
epithet he applied to me. It was the first and last time in my life that my honesty<lb/>
was to be questioned. It is strange that the servile and cringing upstarts of yester-<lb/>
year are those most prone to offend the dignity of man when they attain power and<lb/>
abuse it, while at the same time they are the &ldquo;Yes-men&rdquo; of presidents and executives,<lb/>
afraid to stand up for their own convictions, if they have any. Such, I imagine, was<lb/>
Mr. Shaeffer, as he faced the humbly-born and intended victim of his wrath, but not so<lb/>
meek as he had imagined. He was not yet sure that I would not report him to his main<lb/>
office in Washington. He was profuse in his apologies, a little too profuse, perhaps.<lb/>
I purchased my draft on Paris and bid him good bye, never having occasion to call on<lb/>
him after that. I did know, of course, that he remained with the bank until the<lb/>
Commercial National turned over its Panama Branch to the American Foreign Banking<lb/>
Corporation, a World War I infant, which in turn liquidated its business in Latin<lb/>
America.</p>
<p>While closing my affairs in Panama, General Gorgas, then Surgeon General of the<lb/>
Army, offered me a commission in the Sanitary Corps, for service as Medical Supply<lb/>
Officer in the Department of Panama, which I declined, having no desire to remain in<lb/>
the Canal Zone, &ldquo;cooling my feet&rdquo; all through the War. I wanted service overseas, but<lb/>
not in Panama. The best part of a year had rolled by and here I was, still twiddling<lb/>
my thumbs. My better half, God bless her, would travel with me as far as she could,<lb/>
so at last we were off to New York, she hoping that I would not be sent overseas,<lb/>
while that was what I secretly craved. A fellow-passenger on the same steamer,<lb/>
employed at the Gatun Locks, had a mission similar to my own - to get into uniform.<lb/>
We arranged to go to Washington together. Arrived in New York we found the army<lb/>
uniform very much in evidence, but when we arrived in Washington a man out of uniform<lb/>
attracted attention, so much so that my Gatun friend and I felt rather sheepish in our<lb/>
civilian attire. He was to call on a Canal Zone friend, now an emergency officer,<lb/>
while I planned to call on General Gorgas and General Goethals, the latter being then<lb/>
Assistant Chief of Staff, in charge of Purchase, Storage and Traffic.</p>
<p>The Act which had advanced all army officers of long service on the Panama Canal<lb/>
two grades in rank, also permitted them to be placed on the retired list, regardless<lb/>
of their age, was taken advantage of by General Goethals, but on the outbreak of War<lb/>
they all returned to active service. Colonel Robert E. Wood had retired with his new<lb/>
rank and had entered the service of the Barber-Asphalt Company. He, too, was then<lb/>
back in service with the rank of Brigadier General and Acting Quartermaster General<lb/>
under Goethals. I first paid my respects to General Gorgas, my old chief of Canal<lb/>
days. While I knew he was a very busy man and could be seen only by appointment, I<lb/>
was sure he would grant me an interview. It required a little diplomatic insistence<lb/>
to have him informed that I was in the building and wished to see him. Within a quarter<lb/>
of an hour he received me, gracious and amiable as always. I explained to him what I<lb/>
was in Washington for and that it was my intention to enter the Quartermaster Corps,<lb/>
counting on the assistance of General Goethals. &ldquo;I think we can take care of you in<lb/>
the Sanitary Corps&rdquo;, he said. &ldquo;Go down and see Colonel Darnall and tell him I sent<lb/>
you. When you get through, come back and see me.&rdquo; I could not offend him by telling<lb/>
him I did not want to get into the Sanitary Corps. A non-medico, I knew, would be<lb/>
neither fish nor flesh in that corps.</p>
<p>To get to see Colonel Carl R. Darnall was more difficult for me than it had been<lb/>
to see General Gorgas. Major Schwartz, Colonel Darnall's aide, wanted to know the<lb/>
nature of my business with him. I told him I was there at the instance of General<lb/>
Gorgas, whom I had just visited. &ldquo;Ah, but I must know what the object of your visit<lb/>
is&rdquo;, he said. Briefly, I told him. What experience did I have and what was my special-<lb/>
ty. Not in very good humor by this time, I told him that I had served three years in<lb/>
the hospital corps, three years as sanitary inspector on the Panama Canal and eight<lb/>
years as medical storekeeper. It did not impress him. &ldquo;Suppose you received an order<lb/>
for 250 cc's of laudanum, what would you supply?&rdquo; By this time I was boiling mad but<lb/>
I gave him the correct answer. Forestalling further questions, I told him &ldquo;And now,<lb/>
<pb n="27" id="f06013027"/>
-- 30 --<lb/>
Major Schwartz, you can go to hell with my compliments. Tell Colonel Darnall what<lb/>
you please, but I will tell General Gorgas what I think of you&rdquo;. Too late, he tried<lb/>
to have me wait, but the die had been cast.</p>
<p>Back to General Gorgas' office, I informed him that Major Schwartz wanted to put<lb/>
me through the third degree before allowing me to see Colonel Darnall. &ldquo;Oh, yes&rdquo;,<lb/>
remarked the General, &ldquo;he is a retired hospital steward but too much inclined to serve<lb/>
as a mentor for Colonel Darnall. Why not go back and see the Colonel, who is entirely<lb/>
innocent in this matter?&rdquo; Thanking him for his good intentions, I declined, feeling<lb/>
that I had closed the door in that quarter and that Major Schwartz would be only too<lb/>
glad to &ldquo;put a nail in my coffin&rdquo; at the first opportunity if I should accept a<lb/>
commission in the Sanitary Corps. I was not conceited enough to think that Colonel<lb/>
Darnall would transfer or demote his &ldquo;watchdog&rdquo; on my account. That was to be the last<lb/>
time I was to see General Gorgas alive. My old friend of Canal days passed away in<lb/>
London, on July 4, 1920, while enroute to West Africa to investigate yellow fever, I<lb/>
being then in France.</p>
<p>That same morning I called at General Goethals' office in the State, War and Navy<lb/>
Building. I was received by his civilian secretary, whose business it was to forestall<lb/>
the efforts of any &ldquo;small fry&rdquo; from storming the Sanctum Sanctorum of the General. He<lb/>
was sorry, but the General was then <hi>in conference</hi> and could not be disturbed. Would I<lb/>
kindly request an appointment in writing? I was rapidly &ldquo;catching on&rdquo;, so I informed<lb/>
him that my business was personal and urgent and my time in Washington limited, so he<lb/>
passed me on to one of the General's aides. He, too, was sorry but the General could<lb/>
not be disturbed then. I told him I was an old friend of General Goethals and that I<lb/>
was sure he would receive me if my card was sent in to him. Well, he would be seeing<lb/>
the General around noon and would see to it that my call would be made known to him,<lb/>
making note of my hotel and room number on the card which I left with him. With that<lb/>
assurance I returned to &ldquo;The New Willard Hotel&rdquo;, not so new when I registered there in<lb/>
1940. My Gatun friend and I had lunch together at a Childs' restaurant, after which we<lb/>
meandered around, taking in the Washington Monument and other famous landmarks.</p>
<p>I returned to the hotel around four o'clock in the afternoon and upon asking for<lb/>
my room-key the desk clerk handed me a memorandum which read that I was to call up<lb/>
General Goethals' office not later than 7:00 P. M. Very much excited, I did so at<lb/>
once. The civilian secretary answered the phone, informing me that General Goethals<lb/>
had received my card and would be glad to see me. Arriving at the building, I was<lb/>
halted by the guard, with a demand for my pass. I then learned that admission to the<lb/>
building after 4:00 P. M. was limited to men in uniform and civilians with an official<lb/>
pass. I asked the guard if he would please phone the General's secretary, which he did.<lb/>
This time I was received with a deference which was absent on the occasion of my morning<lb/>
visit. The secretary must have thought I was a Very Important Person. I followed thru<lb/>
a maze of offices until I was in the presence of &ldquo;The Man Who Dug the Panama Canal&rdquo;.<lb/>
I apologized for the intrusion, knowing that he was a very busy man. I remained stand-<lb/>
ing until he told me to be seated, adding that he would be glad to relax for an hour<lb/>
or so and talk to an old-timer like myself. He asked me question after question about<lb/>
&ldquo;The Big Ditch&rdquo; and the incessant slides into the Culebra Cut, his old friends still on<lb/>
the Isthmus. Some I could answer and some I could not. I could see that he was in a<lb/>
reminescent mood. Finally, he asked me if there was anything he could do for me.</p>
<p>Telling General Goethals that I had sold out my business in order to get into<lb/>
uniform, he remarked &ldquo;It is too bad you could not get up here six months ago. Then I<lb/>
could have obtained a a major's commission for you within 24 hours, now it will require<lb/>
five or six weeks and your age and experience entitles you to that rank&rdquo;. Telling him<lb/>
that time was of more importance to me than rank, I suggested that a 1st lieutenancy<lb/>
would be entirely satisfactory. &ldquo;Oh, no&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;I cannot recommend you for anything<lb/>
less than a captaincy. That rank should be yours within a week if you can pass the<lb/>
physical examination. Your old friend from Panama, Major McCulloch, now Colonel, has<lb/>
charge of physical examinations at the Army Medical School and I am sure he will be<lb/>
<pb n="28" id="f06013028"/>
-- 31 --<lb/>
glad to rush you through.&rdquo; Before leaving him I told him I was surprised that he was<lb/>
not overseas with General Pershing. With a sad note in his voice which I shall never<lb/>
forget, he said &ldquo;Mr. Moran, they think I am too old to stand the gaff. No one in<lb/>
Panama ever thought so, as you well know&rdquo;. That was true. I was sorry I had mentioned<lb/>
the matter. I suspected that he was too big and prominent to suit the powers that be.<lb/>
When he was building the Panama Canal he was the biggest man in the Army, in charge of<lb/>
the biggest job undertaken by by any nation in the world up to that time, a job the<lb/>
estimated cost of which was without precedence, the then fabulous sum of $375,000,000.<lb/>
Preceding him as Chief Engineer were two civilians, the first John F. Wallace, the<lb/>
second John F. Stevens. Both had quit in disgust because their best efforts had been<lb/>
thwarted by a cumbersome Isthmian Canal Commission, with headquarters in Washington.<lb/>
President Roosevelt (the first) dissolved the Commission and turned the job over to<lb/>
the Army's Corps of Engineers, appointing one of its most capable members to the dual<lb/>
position of Chairman of the Panama Canal Commission and Chief Engineer of the Panama<lb/>
Canal, the appointee being Lieutenant-Colonel George W. Goethals, who had graduated at<lb/>
the head of his class at West Point, in 1880. The reorganized Commission would have<lb/>
its headquarters on the Isthmus and not in Washington.</p>
<p>The following morning, I was once more obliged to break through the barriers in<lb/>
order to talk to Colonel McCulloch, who was also glad to see me. He had a corps of<lb/>
young army doctors at his command to examine candidates for a commission, but he first<lb/>
wanted to have a long talk with me. On second thought, he decided that I had best have<lb/>
my physical examination first and then I would feel more at ease, our chat to be post-<lb/>
poned until that ordeal was over with. I passed with flying colors in everything except<lb/>
my vision, which could be remedied by wearing appropriate glasses. Frowning, he told<lb/>
me that my examination papers could not be forwarded until that defect was corrected.<lb/>
He was sorry, but after a moment he said &ldquo;Moran, I think I can trust you. When you go<lb/>
back to New York take your prescription to the Medical Center Building, where you will<lb/>
find a number of reliable occulists. Have one of them re-check your prescription and<lb/>
supply you with name of of his favorite optician. In the meantime, I will forward your<lb/>
examination papers. Here in Washington the occulists and opticians are working over-<lb/>
time and you might not have your glasses in less than a couple of weeks. There are<lb/>
very few for whom I would do this, but I know you will not let me down.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We now had our long chat, which lasted until noon and continued through the lunch<lb/>
hour. He regretted that I was side-stepping the Sanitary Corps for the Q. M. Corps,<lb/>
but I think he understood my reasons. In the Sanitary Corps I would be with medical<lb/>
officers but not of them. The increase in salary which he had promised me was injected<lb/>
into our talk. &ldquo;They gave it to you, alright, I hope&rdquo;. &ldquo;No&rdquo;, I said. &ldquo;It is a long<lb/>
story, water over the dam&rdquo;. Sensing that it would not be a fair question, I did not<lb/>
ask him if General Gorgas knew of his executive officer's promise, the General being<lb/>
then head of his department. Colonel McCulloch was the manner of man whom one could<lb/>
not forget. He was the soul of honor, frank and likable. Had he been a little less<lb/>
unselfish and a little more aggresive, he would have been a brigadier general at that<lb/>
time instead of a colonel. He was of too independent a nature to play &ldquo;office politics&rdquo;<lb/>
or pull wires. One of the most considerate that I have ever been associated with.</p>
<p>Now back in New York I was making good my promise to Colonel McCulloch. My glasses<lb/>
had not yet been <unclear>deliveree</unclear> to me when I received the following telegram from the Adjutan<lb/>
General of the Army: YOU ARE APPOINTED CAPTAIN QUARTERMASTER CORPS NATIONAL ARMY WIRE<lb/>
ACCEPTANCE GIVING FULL NAME AND RANK AND REPORT WITHOUT DELAY DEPOT QUARTERMASTER NEW<lb/>
YORK CITY FOR DUTY. MCCAIN THE ADJUTANT GENERAL. This was followed by the regular<lb/>
printed order, signed by General Peyton C. March, Chief of Staff. Once more, Johnny<lb/>
Moran was &ldquo;in the Army now&rdquo;, this time as a captain instead of a &ldquo;buck private&rdquo;, but<lb/>
I was an officer without a uniform for a few days, a matter easily remedied.</p>
<p>I was fortunate enough to be recommended to an &ldquo;army tailor&rdquo; on Governors Island<lb/>
He was a Pole by birth. I brought along my own olive drab material. He proudly boasted<lb/>
<pb n="29" id="f06013029"/>
-- 32 --<lb/>
that when General Henry C. Corbin was stationed on the Island as Commanding General of<lb/>
the Department of the East, he made all his uniforms for him. Seeing my predicament,<lb/>
I aroused his sympathy and he promised to give me priority for at least one of the<lb/>
uiforms I needed. He refused my offer of a bonus for rapid service, thus shaming me<lb/>
for having made it. He was a good soul and to me a friend in need.</p>
<p>I reported to the Depot Quartermaster on May 31, 1918, and was immediately assigned<lb/>
to the Warehousing Division, on Governors Island, under Major Lew E. Willson, Officer in<lb/>
Charge, a man I knew well on the Isthmus of Panama, as chief clerk at the Mount Hope<lb/>
Depot for Material &amp; Supplies. After a conference with him, he induced me to take over<lb/>
Finance &amp; Accounts, instead of warehousing duties which would have been much more to my<lb/>
liking. He explained that invoices covering several million dollars remained to be<lb/>
certified for payment, some of them dating back to the first months of the War. Absolute<lb/>
proof of delivery was impossible to obtain, since the officers and enlisted men who had<lb/>
received the supplies or equipment were no longer within reach, or if they were, they<lb/>
would not remember just what they had signed for at the Army Piers. In the early days<lb/>
of the War, suppliers actuated by patriotic motives had handed over to the Army equip-<lb/>
ment and supplies worth thousands of dollars, in exchange for the flimsiest form of<lb/>
receipt signed by an officer who might be a second lieutenant or a a major general. We<lb/>
had a force of 100 civilian clerks working on those old invoices, in addition to current<lb/>
ones. One finance officer after another sidestepped the responsibility of certifying<lb/>
vouchers unaccompanied by a signed sales slip or memorandum receipt. Yet the Chief of<lb/>
Finance was anxious to clear such invoices for payment, convinced that 99 out of every<lb/>
100 of them were correct and just.</p>
<p>I adopted the system of inviting the merchants concerned to bring along such data<lb/>
and evidence as they had, such as carbon copies of remissions, remission blocks, etc.,<lb/>
and on more than one occasion I visited their offices to check entries made on their<lb/>
books. Using a little natural psychology during those interviews helped me to determine<lb/>
whether or not the creditor was acting in good faith. I am sure I certified vouchers<lb/>
of this class to the amount of several hundred thousand dollars during the four months<lb/>
June to September, 1918. I have never felt any twinges of conscience in the matter.<lb/>
Those patriotic merchants had waited much too long for payment of their accounts against<lb/>
the Government and I saw no good reason for following the course of least resistance, to<lb/>
their detriment, by shuffling their bills and passing them on to the next man. I simply<lb/>
used common sense and imagining myself in their place. However, it was a relief to me<lb/>
when on October 2, 1918, I received a telegram from General Wood, Acting Quartermaster<lb/>
General, to meet him at the Hotel Sevilla in New York, that evening. I did not have the<lb/>
slightest idea as to what was in store for me, but I imagined it involved my transfer<lb/>
to some other point. I was merely speculating, of course.</p>
<p>I was at the hotel well ahead of the scheduled hour, watching the revolving door<lb/>
through which General Wood was to enter. It was the first time I was to face after our<lb/>
memorable interview in Culebra, when he was Chief Quartermaster on the Panama Canal.<lb/>
I stood to &ldquo;attention&rdquo; before him but after shaking hands with me he motioned me to be<lb/>
seated and got down to brass tacks. &ldquo;Moran, he said, I am pulling you out of the Ware-<lb/>
housing Division. I need you more in the Inspection Branch of the Clothing &amp; Equipage<lb/>
Division than I do in the Warehousing Division. You have done an excellent job there<lb/>
but your new assignment will be a much more ticklish one. The recent &ldquo;raincoat scanadal&rdquo;<lb/>
has aroused the ire of General Pershing and clothing inspection in general has been far<lb/>
from what it should be. Too many of our officers in that Division are New Yorkers and<lb/>
I am sorry to say that they have not taken their work seriously. Too many parties and<lb/>
banquets have been given by clothing contractors to inspection officers, thus putting<lb/>
them under obligations to them, with consequent laxity in their work, to the detriment<lb/>
of the service&rdquo;. I heard him through, thinking hard all the time.</p>
<p>Now it was my turn. I told him that I had absolutely no qualifications for the<lb/>
duties he had in mind for me. He met that statement with another, to the effect that<lb/>
<pb n="30" id="f06013030"/>
-- 33 --<lb/>
he would have a technical man accompany me until such time as I thought I could get<lb/>
along on my own, adding: &ldquo;Your native shrewdness will help you in catching on within<lb/>
a month or two. What is more important, I know you are as straight as a string. I have<lb/>
known you too many years to have any doubts about your honesty and devotion to duty&rdquo;.<lb/>
Those were complimentary words indeed, spoken by the dynamic Robert E. Wood, and I was<lb/>
as grateful as I was surprised for the frank and sincere manner in which they were<lb/>
expressed. All I could do was to thank him and tell him I would do my very best to<lb/>
merit his confidence in my new assignment. He then told me that he was transferring<lb/>
Major Williams from the Boston office to take charge of the New York Division, adding<lb/>
that he was an expert in the inspection of clothing. I have never forgotten the words<lb/>
&ldquo;native shrewdness&rdquo; and &ldquo;straight as a string&rdquo;.</p>
<p>From the day I was commissioned, I never lost hope of &ldquo;wiggling my way&rdquo; into over-<lb/>
seas service. I could not very well have broached the matter to General Wood, on the<lb/>
heels of his very complimentary remarks, but I had sold out my business to enter the<lb/>
Army and get &ldquo;Over There&rdquo;. Major Willson had forestalled my every effort to &ldquo;get on the<lb/>
list&rdquo;, which I could not do without his consent. He knew that my better half was<lb/>
opposed to my asking for overseas service. If ordered to go, that would be a different<lb/>
matter. About this time, I learned that another Canal Zone friend of mine, Dave Wolver-<lb/>
ton, was on duty in the Q. M. General's office and could probably arrange to get my<lb/>
name on the list, so I wrote him a personal letter to that end. Captain Wolverton did<lb/>
not reply but within ten days Major Willson, now executive officer to the Depot Quarter-<lb/>
master, sent for me and showed me a telegram from Washington inquiring if the services<lb/>
of Captain Moran could be spared for &ldquo;extended field service&rdquo;, which was understood to<lb/>
men overseas service. Following office practice, the telegram was signed "R. E. Wood,<lb/>
Acting Q. M. General.</p>
<p>Major Willson smiled, saying &ldquo;Johnny, I can see your fine Italian hand in this<lb/>
matter. You know as well as I do that General Wood never read this telegram. As a<lb/>
matter of routine, his name is signed to all such documents. If I tell the Depot<lb/>
Quartermaster the facts in your case, I know what his reply will be&rdquo;. I begged him to<lb/>
slip my name through for approval and conveniently forget what he knew. Altogether,<lb/>
there were seven or eight names included in the telegram. &ldquo;By the way&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;it<lb/>
will ruin your chances for promotion, and I happen to know that you are in line. As<lb/>
you may know, the Commander in Chief frowns on promotions for officers about to be sent<lb/>
overseas.&rdquo; I told him that promotion was the least of my worries. Effective October<lb/>
26, 1918, I was relieved from duty as a clothing inspector. I had an interesting three<lb/>
weeks in that line of work, visiting sweat-shops and some that were not. Due to the<lb/>
shakeup contractors were watching their steps.</p>
<p>Three times I was ordered to Hoboken to embark, finally sailing on the &ldquo;Mauretania&rdquo;,<lb/>
enroute to Liverpool, <hi>the armistice overtaking us on the high seas</hi>. The wartime black-<lb/>
out was rigidly enforced all the way across and we were escorted by British warships<lb/>
upon nearing the English coast. Arriving in Liverpool we entrained to Winchester and<lb/>
nearby Camp Winnals Down, where we remained for four days, then on to Southhampton to be<lb/>
ferried across to Le Havre on the SS &ldquo;St. Charles&rdquo;, which I recognized as the &ldquo;Harvard&rdquo;,<lb/>
sister ship of the &ldquo;Yale&rdquo;, which used to ply between New York and Boston, commanding<lb/>
most of the passenger traffic hitherto enjoyed by the slow-moving steamers of the Joy<lb/>
Line. Having made a trip on the Harvard at one time, she now seemed to me like an old<lb/>
friend. She had been given the wartime name of &ldquo;St. Charles&rdquo;.</p>
<p><unclear>Now</unclear></p>
<p>At Le Havre my large, square manila envelope containing my Qualification or Effici-<lb/>
ency Card was taken up by the Adjutant of U. S. troops there, and its seals broken. Con-<lb/>
tents of those envelopes were sacred and any officer guilty of breaking the seals in<lb/>
order to &ldquo;peep&rdquo; at his efficiency record would be courting trouble, a court-martial<lb/>
offense, plainly printed on the envelope itself. Much to my surprise, I learned for<lb/>
the first time that I was an expert finance officer, indicated by a celluloid clip, one<lb/>
of many such clips of different colors. It was a National Cash Register system, adopted<lb/>
by the Army for the rating of officers. &ldquo;So your are an expert finance man&rdquo;, said the<lb/>
<pb n="31" id="f06013031"/>
-- 34 --<lb/>
Adjutant. Frankly, I told him that it was news to me. But that celluloid clip was as<lb/>
conspicuous as a sore thumb. He remarked that the Depot Quartermaster in New York must<lb/>
have had a reason for putting it there. Promptly I was packed off to the Q. M. Casual<lb/>
Depot at Camp Clayton, Chateau-du-Loir, where I remained two weeks, and from there to<lb/>
Bordeaux, for temporary duty in the office of the disbursing quartermaster, Major<lb/>
Calkins, a banker in civil life, as he informed me. He was delighted to have me as his<lb/>
assistant and planned to have me with him permanently. When I informed him that my<lb/>
qualification card was in error, he just smiled and said &ldquo;Captain, I don't blame you<lb/>
for trying to break away from disbursing. It's a dog's life, especially over here. I<lb/>
have my heart in my mouth most of the time. If one of my assistants makes an over-pay-<lb/>
ment, miscalculates an officer's pay voucher or pays unauthorized commutation to a<lb/>
soldier, I am held accountable. Disbursing has its compensations and no one can compel<lb/>
me to honor any voucher unless I am satisfied that it will stand the Comptroller's<lb/>
scrutiny, but years may roll by before I know what I may be in for&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I started in with Major Calkins as a general utility man and for the first time in<lb/>
my life I handled currency for the Government. I much preferred checking vouchers of<lb/>
every description. My stay with Major Calkins was to be of short duration, as it turned<lb/>
out, for I was obliged to enter Base Hospital No. 6, near Bordeaux, Beau Desert Hospital<lb/>
Center. Base Hospital No. 6 was a Massachusetts General Hospital Unit. There they<lb/>
filled my stomach with barium sulphate and had it X-Rayed. The diagnosis was that of<lb/>
a duodenal ulcer, and the verdict that I be D'd back to the United States to enter<lb/>
Walter Reed Hospital for an operation, which I strenuously opposed, telling the Major<lb/>
surgeon in charge of my ward that I'd be ashamed to return to the U. S. within a month<lb/>
after my arrival in France, but the doctor was adamant. What I needed, he said, was an<lb/>
operation and they were not doing any major operations in France if they were not of<lb/>
an urgent nature, which mine was not. I asked him if he would object if I should<lb/>
appeal over his head to the Commanding Officer of the hospital. Not at all, he said,<lb/>
but he doubted very much that the Colonel would override his recommendation. The<lb/>
commanding officer was Colonel Warren LaVerne Babcock, as I took pains to inquire.</p>
<p>I had no difficulty in having an interview with Colonel Babcock and stating my<lb/>
case. He lost no time in telling me that he could not disregard the Major's decision<lb/>
in my case and that, in any event, it was for my own good. I then decided to play my<lb/>
last card, not knowing whether it would turn out to be the ace of trump or the deuce.<lb/>
I asked him if he was familiar with Walter Reed's work and whether or not he had read<lb/>
Dr. Howard A. Kelly's &ldquo;Walter Reed &amp; Yellow Fever&rdquo;. Yes, he had it read it many years<lb/>
ago. &ldquo;But why do you ask, Captain&rdquo;, he said, seeming a little annoyed by my question.<lb/>
Did the Colonel recall the names of any of Major Reed's human guinea pigs? Sorry, but<lb/>
he did not. &ldquo;I am sorry too, Colonel, but I hoped you would, since I happen to be one<lb/>
of them&rdquo;. Quick as a flash he said &ldquo;Yes, I now recall Major Reed's reference to &lsquo;a<lb/>
plucky Ohio boy by the name of Moran&rsquo;. Are you the man?&rdquo;, my reply being &ldquo;Yes, Col-<lb/>
onel&rdquo;. &ldquo;Well, he said, a man who did what you did is entitled to every consideration<lb/>
at my hands and at the hands of every member of the medical profession. So far as I<lb/>
am concerned you shall have your wish, but please let me consult Major....... He will<lb/>
be here directly, so take a seat.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Ten minutes later, the Major entered and upon seeing me he must have sensed that<lb/>
he was called by the Colonel on my account. Colonel Babcock lost no time in explain-<lb/>
ing who I was, adding that he had no objection to my remaining in France, but that<lb/>
final decision is &ldquo;up to you&rdquo;. With a broad smile the Major said he was in entire<lb/>
accord. Extending his hand, he congratulated me, telling me that he was proud to have<lb/>
had me as a patient. They both advised me to have the operation performed upon my<lb/>
return to the U. S. and that they were sure I would have the best of treatment at the<lb/>
hands of the surgical staff of Walter Reed General Hospital, &ldquo;but&rdquo;, added the Colonel,<lb/>
&ldquo;don't forget to tell them who you are&rdquo;. I returned to Major Calkins' office, very<lb/>
happy and a little bloated with my own importance and the praise of which I had been<lb/>
the recipient. Thirty years have rolled by and my gastric ulcer is still with me. Two<lb/>
days later I was on my way to Mars Hospital Center, spending Christmas Day, 1900, on<lb/>
He must mean Xmas 1918<lb/>
<pb n="32" id="f06013032"/>
-- 35 --<lb/>
the &ldquo;American Special&rdquo;, operated by the Army and for the Army, with military personnel.<lb/>
I had a good Christmas dinner aboard the train, but Mars-sur-Allier was not on its<lb/>
route, so I was obliged to take a French train for part of the distance, arriving at<lb/>
my destination on December 27th. I was now disbursing on my own, but fortunately I<lb/>
had a &ldquo;broken-in&rdquo; Second Lieutenant and several sergeants as assistants. After check-<lb/>
ing the contents of six field safes, I signed over for the funds, all in French<lb/>
francs, thus clearing my predecessor of that part of his accountability. He was to<lb/>
wind up his affairs as of December 31, 1918, and I took over as of January 1, 1919.</p>
<p>I was soon to discover that the commanding officer of the Hospital Center, Col.<lb/>
George A. Skinner, Medical Corps, had been accustomed to order certain payments in a<lb/>
more or less arbitrary manner, such as indicating amounts of commutation of rations<lb/>
to be paid to evacuees from the 14 wards of the Center, a matter strictly within the<lb/>
province of the disbursing officer who in the last analysis would be accountable to<lb/>
the Comptroller of the AEF and the Chief Finance Officer. Commutation rates might<lb/>
vary from 45 cents a day to $2.00, depending on circumstances, interpretation of the<lb/>
regulations governing such rates being left to the decision of the disbursing officer.<lb/>
If he should pay $2.00 a day where only 60 cents was authorized, he would be charged<lb/>
back with the difference when his vouchers should be examined by the Chief of Finance<lb/>
and, ultimately, by the Comptroller. Only an Act of Congress could relieve a paying<lb/>
officer from personal responsibility for over-payments or shortage of cash. That was<lb/>
why disbursing officers found their duties to be considerable of a nightmare. Re-<lb/>
sponsibility for government funds has always been personal, never official. Most of<lb/>
those I met overseas, especially old-timers, played &ldquo;safe&rdquo;, frequently at the expense<lb/>
of the soldier.</p>
<p>The first time I questioned an order of Colonel Skinner to pay an outgoing con-<lb/>
valescent so much a day for commutation of rations to his destination, I immediately<lb/>
called on him in person requesting that he make his order official and over his own<lb/>
signature, when I would gladly comply, explaining to him that any responsibility in-<lb/>
volved, when and as the payment should be passed upon by the Comptroller, would be his<lb/>
and not mine. I knew and he knew that as commanding officer of the Center, he was per<lb/>
si my commanding officer in all matters of a military nature, but not in matters in-<lb/>
volving the funds entrusted to me. He was a regular army officer of many years'<lb/>
service. During my tenure at the Center he made no more attempts to interfere with<lb/>
commutations. My talk with him was most courteous and respectful, admitting that my<lb/>
attitude was correct. Unfortunately, I had occasion later on to tread on Colonel<lb/>
Skinner's toes, when he tried to commandeer the Cadillac car I had assigned me.</p>
<p>In the AEF we had cars for three categories, viz: Fords for officers to and in-<lb/>
cluding the rank of captain; Dodges for majors to colonel, inclusive, and Cadillacs<lb/>
for generals. Disbursing quartermasters and disbursing officers, regardless of their<lb/>
rank, were entitled to the safest and best transportation in the army, because of the<lb/>
personal responsibility involved. The Cadillac was considered to be the safest and<lb/>
most reliable. Colonel Skinner had tried to have a Cadillac assigned to him but had<lb/>
not been successful. Desiring to visit Nevers one day, I phoned the motor transport<lb/>
officer to send me my car. &ldquo;Sorry, Captain&rdquo;, he replied, &ldquo;but the Colonel ordered me<lb/>
to send him your car this morning&rdquo;. &ldquo;He knew it was assigned to me, did he not&rdquo;, I<lb/>
replied. &ldquo;Yes, I told him&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;but he came back at me, stating that the command-<lb/>
ing officer of the Center was more entitled to a Cadillac than Captain Moran&rdquo;. Colonel<lb/>
Skinner had not said a word to me. With all due respect to him, I made up my mind to<lb/>
fight for my rights. I telegraphed the Chief Finance Officer in Tours, informing him<lb/>
that my Cadillac had been taken over by Colonel Skinner, without my knowledge or<lb/>
consent. Would he please have the matter looked into? The following day, the<lb/>
Commanding General of Intermediate Section wired Colonel Skinner to release Cadillac<lb/>
car No. --------, assigned to Captain Moran as disbursing officer at the Center. In a<lb/>
way, I was sorry that the colonel acted as he did. I called on him to tell him that<lb/>
he would be welcome to my car for any trips outside the Center which he wished to make,<lb/>
after consultation with me, since I used it only three or four times a week. Before<lb/>
I left the Hospital Center, he called on me for the car for a three-day trip.</p>
<pb n="33" id="f06013033"/>
<p>-- 36 --</p>
<p>A few months after my arrival at Mars Hospital Center, one hospital unit after<lb/>
another was disbanded, most of their personnel bidding goodbye to France and entrain-<lb/>
ing for an embarkation port for transportation to the U. S. to be demobolized. Sensing<lb/>
that a disbursing officer was no longer necessary at what was left of the Center, I<lb/>
notified the Chief Finance Officer in Tours that effective with the end of April, the<lb/>
few troops still there could be paid monthly by the disbursing officer at Nevers.<lb/>
Agreeing with me, he instructed me to close my accounts there and report to him in<lb/>
person. I was no longer interested in remaining in France and hoped to be relieved<lb/>
from further overseas duty. With my accounts in order, I reported to the Chief Finance<lb/>
Officer, telling him of my desire to return to the U. S. His answer was that he need-<lb/>
ed good disbursing officers &ldquo;cleaning up&rdquo; thousands of odds and ends, such as French<lb/>
claims, etc., etc., and that I had made a good record, remarking &ldquo;I have a number of<lb/>
men who do not want to go home but they will have to go, as I want to hold on to good<lb/>
men only. I will neeed you for the present. We will find another station for you<lb/>
before you are much older.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I was then ordered to report to the Intermediate Section Quartermaster at Nevers<lb/>
for temporary duty as disbursing officer during the absence sick in hospital of Captain<lb/>
E. I. Edwards Jr., son of the then Governor of New Jersey. He returned to duty during<lb/>
the first week of May, again assuming his duties, but Colonel Sheen, Quartermaster of<lb/>
Intermediate Section, told me to continue and await a new assignment. In the first two<lb/>
days after Captain Edwards' return I had a little argument with him about a very<lb/>
trivial matter. A sergeant on duty at a railroad station three miles out of Nevers<lb/>
came into the office for his weekly commutation money and it so happened that the<lb/>
previous day commutation payments had been transferred to the commissary officer on<lb/>
the outskirts of the city. It being late in the afternoon, that office would be closed<lb/>
before the sergeant could arrive there. I overheard his arguments with the sergeant<lb/>
who was attending him, so I suggested that he speak with Captain Edwards, explaining<lb/>
how important it was to him to collect his commutation money that day and return to his<lb/>
station. He pleaded with the captain but to no purpose as he reported back to me.<lb/>
Telling him to wait for me, I went to see Captain Edwards in his behalf. He told me<lb/>
very abruptly that he had already decided that matter. I then told him that officers<lb/>
like him were responsible for much of the neo-communism that was cropping out in the<lb/>
Army, adding that I would personally pay the sergeant's commutation money from funds<lb/>
I still had at my disposal. Captain Edwards told me &ldquo;I have a notion to have you court-<lb/>
martialed for your disrespectful words and actions&rdquo; &ldquo;Go ahead&rdquo;, I replied, &ldquo;if you<lb/>
dare. You have a good witness in that grinning 1st, Lieutenant sitting across the desk<lb/>
from you&rdquo;. He did not try, but I learned later that he had reported me to Colonel<lb/>
Sheen. Returning to the outer office, I had a commutation sheet made out for the rail-<lb/>
road sergeant. He left the office happy.</p>
<p>On May 24, 1919, I was ordered to Bourges (Cher), Central Records Office, as dis-<lb/>
bursing officer. Before leaving Nevers I paid my respects to Colonel Sheen. He told<lb/>
me he knew of my tiff with Captain Edwards, but would I mind telling him all about it.<lb/>
In a few words I told him my side of the story. His smile and handshake assured me<lb/>
that he approved my words and action. I was highly pleased with myself, for Colonel<lb/>
Sheen had himself disbursed in his days, being a regular army officer of long service.</p>
<p>Arriving in Bourges, I found a state of affairs bordering on anarchy. A group of<lb/>
hoodlums from Brooklyn and the East Side of New York had established a &ldquo;little Russia&rdquo;<lb/>
at the old French post where Central Records Office personnel were quartered, causing<lb/>
no end of worry to Colonel David L. Stone, commander of U. S. troops there. One of the<lb/>
causes for their discontent was that my predecessor had not been accustomed to pay<lb/>
them until the 15th of the month. My first payday was to cover the month of June.<lb/>
Colonel Stone sent for me, stating that the communists were planning to stage a dis-<lb/>
orderly demonstration for July Fourth. Could I possibly arrange to pay the troops<lb/>
on July 3rd, thus nipping the movement in the bud. I told him I thought I could, if<lb/>
company commanders could get their payrolls to my office on the morning of July 1st.</p>
<pb n="34" id="f06013034"/>
<p>-- 37 --</p>
<p>Returning to my office, I talked to my picked detachment of payroll men, headed<lb/>
by Sergeant F. A. Weiland and a number of men who had served with him at Metz Hospital<lb/>
Center, taking them all into my confidence and repeating Colonel Stone's concern about<lb/>
what the communists were brewing. I felt sure of their whole-hearted cooperation and<lb/>
knew they would not fail me, although I had been their commanding officer for a bare<lb/>
two weeks. The first time I entered the large office where they had their desks they<lb/>
all stood at attention. I told them I wanted that practice discontinued, which did<lb/>
not lessen their respect for me. On the contrary, they realiezed that I was not one<lb/>
of those who would deliberately cross the street in order to have a couple of enlisted<lb/>
men salute me. Many officers were guilty of that sin but none of them were West Point-<lb/>
ers. By that I do not intend to cast any reflection on volunteer or emergency officers.<lb/>
By and large, they were not &ldquo;saluting demons&rdquo;, but their number was sufficient to<lb/>
create an unsavory class distinction.</p>
<p>All my force worked like beavers for two solid days and until two o'clock in the<lb/>
morning, barely taking sufficient time off for their meals, so that on the morning of<lb/>
July 3rd we notified company commanders to &ldquo;come and get it&rdquo;, with bills and small<lb/>
change all arranged so that their men could be paid off the exact amount due each.<lb/>
Every man in the garrison received his pay on July 3rd and the communist parade was<lb/>
knocked into a cocked hat. Colonel Stone sent the adjutant to thank me for complying<lb/>
so effectively with his wishes. I told the adjutant to please inform Colonel Stone<lb/>
that my detachment of loyal assistants were entitled to the credit. Colonel Stone was<lb/>
retired as Major General on August 30, 1940. I am sure he vividly remembers that<lb/>
incident. He and every member of his staff were my warmest friends.</p>
<p>It was in June, 1919, that I deemed it wise to call on Mr. Lurtin R. Ginn,<lb/>
Assistant Comptroller of the Treasury, Paris, for decision on a matter which had been<lb/>
giving me not a few sleepless nights. Over a period of five months, I had been paying<lb/>
soldiers commutation of rations on 3-day leaves to Paris, including travel time from<lb/>
station to Paris and return, under provisions of General Order 14, G. H. Q. That<lb/>
General Order was issued by General Pershing with the object of affording every man in<lb/>
the A. E. F. a chance to see Paris before returning to the U. S. He intended to do<lb/>
away with the practice of glutting Paris with men in uniform, many of whom had been<lb/>
accustomed to lose themselves in the gay capital. Under that General Order they were<lb/>
obliged to check in and out of Paris within the three days. Other disbursing officers<lb/>
interpreted the Order as limiting the soldier to three days' commutation of rations,<lb/>
no allowance being made for reasonable travel time. The Major paymaster at Gievres<lb/>
was one of them. He told me I would be in the army for the rest of my life to liquid-<lb/>
ate the over-payments I had made on 3-day leaves to Paris. I was certainly worried.</p>
<p>When I called on Mr. Ginn and stated my case he frankly informed me that 3-day<lb/>
leaves to Paris did not include commutation of rations for travel time and that my<lb/>
interpretation of that paragraph of G. O. 14, G. H. Q. was in error. I argued with all<lb/>
the eloquence I could command that a soldier on authorized leave could not be deprived<lb/>
of his rations in kind or their equivalent in the form of commutation. The soldier's<lb/>
company commander did not draw rations for him during the nine to five days of his<lb/>
absence. The Commander-in-Chief limited his stay in Paris to 3 days, for a very<lb/>
definite reason, but made no mention of travel time, which might be two days, four or<lb/>
six, depending on the distance of his station from Paris. Mr. Ginn, while I waited,<lb/>
told me he would consult with G. H. Q. by telephone. In the meantime I had my fingers<lb/>
crossed<unclear><del>.</del></unclear> He argued my case for me as I had stated it to him. G. H. Q. informed him<lb/>
that my interpretation was correct. Mr. Ginn then congratulated me. In his decision,<lb/>
dated June 30, 1919, to the Commander-in-Chief, A. E. F., payment of the commutation<lb/>
of rations for travel time was authorized and promulgated throughout the A. E. F. My<lb/>
nightmare was ended. I owe a debt of gratitude to Mr. Ginn. He might well have denied<lb/>
me an opportunity for reconsideration of my case, leaving me with the only recourse of<lb/>
a special Act of Congress for relief and pardon of several thousand dollars in over-<lb/>
payments. In France his decisions were as valid as were those of the Comptroller of<lb/>
of the Treasury in the United States. His powers were almost absolute.</p>
<pb n="35" id="f06013035"/>
<p>-- 38 --</p>
<p>I was very happy indeed with the moral victory I had obtained as a result of my<lb/>
visit to to the Comptroller. I might have followed the course of least resistance<lb/>
and &ldquo;played safe&rdquo;, as did the other disbursing officers who had unwittingly despoiled<lb/>
thousands of soldiers of their just rights. My victory, however, came too late to<lb/>
benefit only a handful of the soldiers still in France, nine-tenths of the A. E. F.<lb/>
having returned to the United States to be mustered out and by this time back in<lb/>
civil life. I had killed two birds with one stone. First, I was not to become the<lb/>
sorry exception among disbursing officers in the A. E. F. to make unauthorized pay-<lb/>
ments, with its train of disagreeable consequences. Second, I had the infinite<lb/>
satisfaction of knowing that I had not cheated any soldier out of his just rights,<lb/>
rights which a generous country was entirely willing to extend to him and as intended<lb/>
by his Commander-in-Chief, General John J. Pershing.</p>
<p>It was now nearing the end of August, 1919, with my chances of returning home<lb/>
being excellent, since I was an emergency officer and with no desire to remain over-<lb/>
seas. In view of the fact that the nature of my duties was more personal than<lb/>
military, I had been unable to avail myself of the 15-day leave which all officers<lb/>
had been entitled to. To do so, I would have been obliged to close my accounts<lb/>
temporarily and request that an officer be sent to relieve me. Since I entered the<lb/>
army in order to do my bit, I did not intend to complicate matters for the Chief<lb/>
Finance Officer in order to take a vacation. When I finally closed out my accounts<lb/>
I was offered a 15-day leave by the Chief Quartermaster, with permission to go to<lb/>
Ireland, by way of England, an offer which sorely tempted me but which I refused, my<lb/>
desire to get back to my little wife being stronger than that of visiting the land<lb/>
of my birth. On September 9, 1919, I reported at Brest for transportation to the<lb/>
U. S. and on the 19th I arrived at Hoboken, leaving immediately for Washington to<lb/>
report to the Director of Finance, where I hoped to get a clearance. There I was<lb/>
informed that my accounts might not be audited for at least a year. As it turned<lb/>
out, three years rolled by before I received a final clearance.</p>
<p>Instead of going to a demobilization <add>Camp</add> to be mustered out, I was authorized to<lb/>
be discharged at Governor's Island <del>instead</del>, effective October 1, 1919. The follow-<lb/>
ing day I entered the service of the Mercantile Bank of the Americas, the ill-fated<lb/>
institution which came a cropper in the post-war depression of 1920-1921, when all<lb/>
Latin American products, principally sugar and coffee, ruined the MBA and weakened<lb/>
many other banks. In preparation for a suitable berth in the tropics, I remained in<lb/>
the New York office until April, 1920, when I was sent to Maracaibo, Venezuela, and<lb/>
from that city to the interior town of Valera, State of Trujillo, as branch manager<lb/>
of the Mercantile Overseas Corporation, a wholly-owned subsidiary of the Mercantile<lb/>
Bank of the Americas. Business in that section of Venezuela was 90% German controll-<lb/>
ed. For years they had monopolized everything between Maracaibo and the Colombian<lb/>
border, trading drygoods and hardware for coffee, cacao, hides and other native<lb/>
products. They invoiced their German-made products on a six months' basis, with an<lb/>
additional two months &ldquo;respiro&rdquo; (breathing spell), terms foreign to American export-<lb/>
ers, yet under such long-term credits they grew rich and powerful. They were past<lb/>
masters at the art of dealing with the natives. It was almost impossible to wean<lb/>
away from them any worth-while accounts. The one article of American manufacture<lb/>
which they were never able to displace was the Collins machete, a long, bellied knife<lb/>
used for cane-cutting and like purposes, still the favorite in every Latin American<lb/>
country. American influence in Venezuela was then practically nil.</p>
<p>The Germans were not interested in Venezuelan crude oil but American oil compan-<lb/>
ies were then entering that field in proper fashion, production being then in its<lb/>
infancy and confined to the British. Among the American pioneers were Sun Oil Company<lb/>
and Standard of New Jersey, with a number of mushroom companies following in their<lb/>
trail, all American-backed. The two American major oil companies were pock-marking<lb/>
the country with their concessions. For every such concession the Venezuelan<lb/>
<pb n="36" id="f06013036"/>
-- 39 --<lb/>
government reserved to itself an adjoining plot of equal size, thus relieving it of<lb/>
drilling costs, while participating in production of the American companies through<lb/>
sale of the reserved plots in any given field. The entire country was then an oil-<lb/>
man's paradise and potential as a petroleum producer beyond the dreams of the most<lb/>
optimistic geologist. It was while I was in Valera that I first came in contact with<lb/>
the Sun Oil Company geologists, for whom we acted in the interior as bankers, and it<lb/>
was there that I first met one of the Pew family, Mr. J. Edgar Pew, in charge of Sun<lb/>
production, who traveled on mule-back throughout the Cordilleras of Venezuela, the<lb/>
natives according him such homage as &ldquo;The Dictator&rdquo; only could command, but for a<lb/>
very different reason, since Mr. Pew's was spontaneous and genuine and the &ldquo;Dictator's&rdquo;<lb/>
forced or simulated. He was none else than General Juan Vicente Gomez, who graduated<lb/>
into the presidency from leader of a mule caravan, following the fall and exile of<lb/>
the notorious Cipriano Castro. It was simply a case of a super-tyrant succeeding a<lb/>
small-fry one, with this difference: Cipriano was educated, while Juan Vicente could<lb/>
hardly read or write.</p>
<p>I was not long in Venezuela when I learned that our whole organization was composed<lb/>
of rank amateurs, commencing with the Home Office at 44 Pine Street, New York. During<lb/>
World War I, it grew up like a mushroom, taking on misfits right and left, mostly men<lb/>
with no business experience but rich in fantastic and unworkable theories. When the<lb/>
post-war depression got under way it had overtaken them before they realized it and<lb/>
then began the stampede. The bank had been caught in a trap, resulting in the most<lb/>
colossal failure of all times, past or present, on the American continent, since it<lb/>
affected a score or more of other American banks, stockholders in that ill-fated<lb/>
venture, the Guaranty Trust Company being one of them. The MBA had as a nucleus the<lb/>
&ldquo;Banco Nacional de Nicaragua&rdquo;, jointly controlled by the New York banking houses of<lb/>
Brown Brothers and Seligman, a profitable venture and well managed. The small force<lb/>
of trained men was entirely inadequate to train and form such an ambitious force and<lb/>
program to cover all Latin America. It requires more than a will to form an efficient<lb/>
business organization. Furthermore, it cannot be done overnight. It must be progress-<lb/>
ive and coordinated. The MBA made the capital error of forming a subsidiary company<lb/>
to purchase merchandise which it hoped to exchange for local products, principal of<lb/>
which were coffee, cacao and hides, later adding sugar to the list. Its Mercantile<lb/>
Overseas Corporation served as a funnel for the bank's funds, buying all manner of<lb/>
merchandise at inflated prices, later to be sold at a heavy loss. Another capital<lb/>
blunder was that of advancing 50% to 60% of current market prices of tropical products<lb/>
which could not be sold without the consent of the owner. Coffee, for instance, for<lb/>
which the bank had advanced to the owner 10&cent; per pound was selling in the N. Y. market<lb/>
for as low as 8&cent;, yet the bank could not dispose of it without the consent of the own-<lb/>
er who gambled at the expense of the bank for an advance which did not materialize.</p>
<p>Finally, the banks which had financed the MBA took over control, first ordering<lb/>
the management to liquidate its mercantile business and save what it could out of the<lb/>
wreck, all concerned to devote their time and energies to collections. Of the millions<lb/>
represented by accounts receivable, not more than 25% was ever collected. The bank<lb/>
paid its creditors in full. Mismanagement was not alone responsible for the bank's<lb/>
failure. It might not have been so disastrous if the men in the field had had the<lb/>
support of the Home Office, since many of them were not merely time-servers or theor-<lb/>
ists. Initiative, unless it was born in the Home Office, was frowned upon. Long-<lb/>
distance management, if comprehensive, is healthy and encouraging. Otherwise, it is<lb/>
usually fatal. When I was in Valera I placed an order for ten-penny nails, specifying<lb/>
that they should be put up in pound packages, explaining that nails had never been sold<lb/>
loose in the interior of the country. They were to be packed in 100-lb. boxes so that<lb/>
two cases would make the proper load for transportation on mule-back, one case on each<lb/>
side. Much to my surprise the order was filled in 100-lb. kegs, and loose. The pur-<lb/>
chasing agent, in his office on the 15th floor of 44 Pine Street, knew better than we<lb/>
did what would sell to the natives. What foolishness, calling for nails put up in 1-lb<lb/>
packages, while loose nails in kegs cost much less! In order to dispose of them we<lb/>
had to take a loss of 30% on the shipment. An excellent example of mismanagement.</p>
<pb n="37" id="f06013037"/>
<p>-- 40 --</p>
<p>Called in to Maracaibo, I was shown the hand-writing on the wall by the General<lb/>
Manager, one of the best judges of coffee in Latin America. He told me to return to<lb/>
Valera and dispose of our stocks of merchandise, including hardware, textiles, fine<lb/>
French brandies, etc., for cash. He was a master at blending coffees but no merchand-<lb/>
izer. He told me to be in no hurry and that he expected to remain in Maracaibo for<lb/>
another year at least, while I was in a hurry to divorce myself from the payroll. I<lb/>
was not much older when an official liquidator, formerly with the Nicaragua branch,<lb/>
appeared on the scene. He started with the Valera branch, intending to take in later<lb/>
Merida, Tovar and San Cristobal, leaving Maracaibo to the last. His instructions<lb/>
were to sell everything for cash, regardless of price, the point being to liquidate<lb/>
with the least possible delay. I was just as anxious as he was to close and get out,<lb/>
not that I wanted to desert a sinking ship if there was any chance of salvaging it.<lb/>
He arrived at night and we made our plans for the following morning. We set out bright<lb/>
and early and during that day we visited every promising prospect in the town, being<lb/>
able to place a maximum of $1,500.00 out of an estimated inventory of $30,000.00, on<lb/>
which we were ready to take a loss of 40%. The liquidator was sorely disappointed.<lb/>
Our prices were attractive but all merchants were overstocked. What could I suggest?</p>
<p>I recommended a clearance sale which would be attractive to consumers, our ware-<lb/>
house to be converted into a retail establishment, with my Italian-born assistant mana-<lb/>
ger to supervise the selling. He was a bonded employee, but aside from that I had<lb/>
faith in his honesty. The liquidator gladly accepted my recommendation, adding &ldquo;but<lb/>
what do you expect to do?&rdquo; I told him that I was ready to leave for Maracaibo, as<lb/>
soon as I could dispose of my household furniture, and leave for New York on the first<lb/>
steamer out of Maracaibo, with my better half who had shared my lot in that primitive<lb/>
interior town. &ldquo;Well&rdquo;, he replied, &ldquo;I am glad to run across one man who is anxious to<lb/>
remove himself from the payroll. The Big Boy in Maracaibo wants to hold on to his<lb/>
$1,000.00 a month indefinitely. He told me that his Power of Attorney and contract<lb/>
cannot be terminated by any liquidator, so I have cabled New York to straighten him<lb/>
out&rdquo;. I was patting myself on the back. While I had no position in sight, that was<lb/>
the least of my worries. I wanted to be freed from an outfit which I had hoped could<lb/>
use my services until I should reach retirement-age, and here I was, contemplating a<lb/>
new start. Yes, I wanted to forget it all, the sooner the better.</p>
<p>My plans for a quick get-away, however, were knocked into a cocked hat by the<lb/>
liquidator. The stocks at Merida and Tovar were under my general supervision but the<lb/>
agent and manager, respectively, reported direct to Maracaibo. &ldquo;Come to think of it&rdquo;,<lb/>
said the liquidator, &ldquo;I don't believe I can do the job as well as you can. Besides,<lb/>
I think I had better stay close to Maracaibo and watch &ldquo;the old man&rdquo;. I'm very much<lb/>
afraid he will make trouble for us before we can pry him loose. For that reason, I<lb/>
hope you will stay on long enough to close up the Merida Agency and the Tovar branch.<lb/>
By the time you have done that, you can come in to Maracaibo or go on to San Cristobal<lb/>
and pry loose the branch manager there, another time-server. At one time he was a high-<lb/>
powered man in the New York office, so to get rid of him they sent him to Venezuela,<lb/>
where he has been acting as a &ldquo;shoo-fly&rdquo; <unclear>man</unclear> for the general manager ever since, all<lb/>
the time busy in undermining the Big Boy in Maracaibo and planning to succeed him.<lb/>
Now, he knows the game is up, so he will freeze on to his job as long as he can possibly<lb/>
do so. They have no use for him in New York but they have handed me the job of getting<lb/>
rid of him, so there you are.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I told my friend that I would accept the task of liquidating Merida and Tovar but<lb/>
not San Cristobal, making it a condition that I would be given a free hand to dispose<lb/>
of the stock in both places on the best available terms, adding that I would advise<lb/>
him by telegram, prior to closing, if circumstances permitted. He told me to write<lb/>
out my own conditions and that he would sign the document. Leaving Valera the<lb/>
following day on my mission, at three o'clock in the morning, not at all an unusual<lb/>
hour for mule-back travel in Venezuela, I was well on my way by 9:00 A. M. As a<lb/>
matter of fact, I had reached the base of the Timotes Paramo at that hour, ascending<lb/>
that mountain slowly and painfully for three solid hours, then crossing its bleak<lb/>
<pb n="38" id="f06013038"/>
-- 41 --<lb/>
flat top for another hour and a half. Mountain travel in Venezuela was then an art,<lb/>
in addition to being a means of earning a livelihood for traveller and guide. Woe<lb/>
unto him who would attempt to cross the &ldquo;Paramos&rdquo; or &ldquo;Cordilleras&rdquo; of the country<lb/>
without an expert guide or &ldquo;asistente&rdquo;, as the natives call them, for if he should<lb/>
get lost it would be a case of goodbye<unclear>.</unclear> Expert guides use certain landmarks in<lb/>
crossing the Paramos, there being no trails or paths to guide the novice, with no<lb/>
sign of human habitation. Usually they are canopied by a cold and penetrating fog.<lb/>
For the first-trip traveller it is an experience never to be forgotten. One instinct-<lb/>
ively feels closer to his Creator. The natives pick up a certain leaf upon entering<lb/>
the Paramo, placing it between their lips to prevent chapping, which I thought ridi-<lb/>
culous on my first such trip, very much to my sorrow. Within a matter of a couple of<lb/>
hours my lips were beautifully cracked, but not on this trip. I had learned my lesson.<lb/>
Needless to record that trips involving the crossing of Paramos in Venezuela were<lb/>
usually of an urgent nature, most travellers electing the longer way around, taking<lb/>
passage on the side-wheelers which touched the port towns bordering on Lake Maracaibo,<lb/>
there to be met by their guides with mule packs and mounts.</p>
<p>Every Maracaibo salesman covering interior towns must have his expert guide to<lb/>
care for his mount and the two or three pack mules which carry his samples and personal<lb/>
baggage. They all have to make hay <hi>before</hi> the sun shines, the opposite of the adage,<lb/>
their best hours being between three and nine o'clock in the morning, three of those<lb/>
six hours being travelled in pitch darkness, with their safety depending on the sure-<lb/>
footedness of that trusty quadruped, the mule, with its natural instinct to sidestep<lb/>
pits, crevices and other dangerous obstacles. The rider has to look out for bent or<lb/>
overhanging branches on the trail or path, while the mule will take care of the dangers<lb/>
in the path itself. Except for short daylight trips, the horse is never used and the<lb/>
mule is rarely used for pleasure trips unless it is an exceptional specimen. The<lb/>
average traveller in those days could not afford the rocking-chair variety of mule<lb/>
flesh, since the price would be $500. to $600., with cargo mules costing from $100. to<lb/>
$200., depending on age and other conditions. A fine horse could be purchased for $150.</p>
<p>Now we have crossed the mountain and starting to descend into the valley of Merida,<lb/>
my first scheduled stop, meeting our first human habitation, a stopping place where we<lb/>
can have lunch, feed and rest our mules. The sun was burning hot while we crossed the<lb/>
Paramo, and it is still hot. Within two hours we were on our way again, gradually<lb/>
descending all the way to the town of Merida, where we arrived around eight o'clock at<lb/>
night. I then felt that I was entitled to a cocktail before my dinner, so I hastened to<lb/>
the hotel bar. The bartender told me he did not know how to prepare a cocktail. Well,<lb/>
I would show him how. Did he have ice, cognac. Italian vermuth and Angostura bitters?<lb/>
He had no shaker, however, but I managed to mix a very tasty cocktail, carefully<lb/>
measuring all the ingrediants, including sugar, for the benefit of my open-mouthed<lb/>
pupil. Would he take one with me? He certainly did, remarking that it tasted like<lb/>
an excellent &ldquo;refresco&rdquo;, or soft drink. I had to remind him that, with all its apparent<lb/>
mildness, it would not serve as a soft drink. French cognac, I knew was the favorite<lb/>
Venezuelan drink, with beer next, with wines for dinner. Then followed dinner, to which<lb/>
I did justice. Although I was dog tired, I could not go to bed, so I looked up our<lb/>
agent, Don Pio Nono Picon, having been baptized &ldquo;Pius IX&rdquo;, a name for which he was in<lb/>
no way responsible. I inferred that he was of Italian descent. Briefly, I told him of<lb/>
the object of my mission. We agreed to talk it over the following morning.</p>
<p>I arose early next morning and walked to the balcony of my room to enjoy a view of<lb/>
the &ldquo;Sierra Nevada&rdquo;, or snow-capped mountain, unscaled by any human, so far as the old-<lb/>
est inhabitant of Merida knew, so I was informed. It appeared to be so near that one<lb/>
could reach its base in an hour, yet it required two days to reach the edge of that<lb/>
mass of ice, on mule-back and return. I knew that the ice I had used for my cocktail<lb/>
had come from that source, there being no iceplant in Merida. Our agent had informed<lb/>
me that money was so scarce in the town that it would be impossible to dispose of our<lb/>
stocks, but we could make the rounds anyway. It was just a repetition of my Valera<lb/>
<pb n="39" id="f06013039"/>
-- 42 --<lb/>
experience. Merchants were overstocked and sacrifice prices were no inducement. Our<lb/>
agent was financially sound. He was the owner of coffee plantations and had ware-<lb/>
houses full of that grain which he could not sell, with prices tumbling day after<lb/>
day. His business was unencumbered. He owned a caravan of 100 pack mules, easily<lb/>
worth $250.00 each, but no cash. He had a clean record with the company and had<lb/>
religiously reported sales from the consigned stock, remitting proceeds on maturity<lb/>
dates, with no simulated excuses. I proposed that he take over all the stock on<lb/>
a six months basis, giving us a mortgage on his 100 mules. The 40% discount which<lb/>
I offered him was an incentive, so he agreed. I notified the liquidator by telegraph<lb/>
and followed it up by letter. It was the best we could do, so why hold of for the<lb/>
impossible, cash being out of the question. Within a week, I was on my way to Tovar<lb/>
to dispose of the stock, office furniture and fixtures of that branch.</p>
<p>Arriving in Tovar I went into a huddle with our sub-manager, a young man of<lb/>
Italian parentage but born in Venezuela. I sensed that we would have tough sledding<lb/>
before we could fold up our tents. One firm in the town controlled practically<lb/>
everything in it and owned vast extensions of land to within a radius of 50 miles of<lb/>
Tovar. The stocks of their mercantile warehouses was estimated at $200,000.00. That<lb/>
firm had resented our entry into their field from the day we first opened up there,<lb/>
looking upon us as intruders. My plan now was to concentrate on that firm, making no<lb/>
effort to sell to the local merchants. I knew that if I called on any of them, the<lb/>
information would be relayed to my prospective buyer, which would be sure to hurt my<lb/>
chances. But how to arrange for an interview, since I was not acquainted with any of<lb/>
the three men forming their board of directors. Our sub-manager had met one of them<lb/>
so I arranged to meet him. I explained my mission to Tovar, stating that we wanted<lb/>
to close shop there with the least possible delay. Our entire stock would be mere<lb/>
chicken feed for his company. We were liquidating and getting out of the mercantile<lb/>
business in Venezuela. He promised to place the matter before his two partners. Two<lb/>
days went by and no hint as to their intentions. I marked time during those two<lb/>
days while I took inventory and prepared an invoice with our laid-down costs in one<lb/>
column and our sacrifice prices in the other, based on a 30% discount for cash.</p>
<p>Again calling at the firm's office, I inquired as to their verdict. No, they had<lb/>
not arrived at a decision as yet. I politely suggested a meeting with the three,<lb/>
which was granted. I told them we had no intention of interfering with their busi-<lb/>
ness but that we were obliged to act and act quickly. If they would not take over<lb/>
our stock, we would use our own warehouse as a retail store and find a number of<lb/>
holes-in-the-wall in the town, selling direct to consumers. That would upset their<lb/>
market as wholesalers and would demoralize the business of retailers in the town for<lb/>
some time to come. I made it clear to them that we had no axe to grind with them but<lb/>
liquidation of our stocks was imperative. I could be very eloquent and convincing<lb/>
in an audience of six or less, so I pleaded as I had never done before with those<lb/>
three directors. I recall that one of the three, named &ldquo;Jaime&rdquo; (James), was the key<lb/>
man and the one to be convinced. He said little but listened closely to what I had<lb/>
to say. They went into a huddle for about five minutes and &ldquo;Jaime&rdquo; informed me that<lb/>
they would take over our stocks, including furniture and fixtures. They would give<lb/>
me a check dated 15 days in advance, payable in Maracaibo, which was entirely satis-<lb/>
factory, knowing that it was as good as gold. Checking of our inventory was effected<lb/>
in one day. The reserve which they maintained up to that time disappeared and their<lb/>
inherent hospitality became manifest. They invited me to their club and instructed<lb/>
the manager to treat me as a member, explaining that I would be their guest for some<lb/>
days and that I would have my meals there. The club was small but it was well stocked,<lb/>
and the food excellent and well cooked. They had invited me to lunches and dinners<lb/>
which I reciprocated, but when I called for my account on the eve of my departure, the<lb/>
manager informed me that &ldquo;el se&ntilde;or Jaime&rdquo; had given him strict instructions to the<lb/>
effect that he was not to accept payment from me. I told him that &ldquo;Jaime&rdquo; was not<lb/>
there just then and would be none the wiser. His reply was: "El se&ntilde;or Jaime never<lb/>
forgets, Sir, and he probably would not forget to show me the door if I disobeyed his<lb/>
instructions. Would he accept a gratuity for himself and his assistants? I had to<lb/>
press hard for that concession but he finally accepted.</p>
<pb n="40" id="f06013040"/>
<p>-- 43 --</p>
<p>I regret that I cannot recall the name of that Tovar firm and the surname of<lb/>
&ldquo;Jaime&rdquo; (James) but I have not forgotten their hospitality after I had once gained<lb/>
their confidence. None the less, although they were big fish in a small pond, they<lb/>
lived pretty much of a primitive life with which they were apparently happy, a life<lb/>
which I am sure would not appeal to me, rover that I was. From Tovar I decided to<lb/>
return to Valera by a less trying route, by way of Santa Barbara, a point of call for<lb/>
the side-wheeler which would land me at La Ceiba. My guide was to return by the<lb/>
route over which we had travelled to Tovar, with my mount, his own and the pack mule.<lb/>
The side-wheelers had no accomodations for beasts of burden. The captain suggested<lb/>
that I would be more comfortable on board the steamer than I would be at the &ldquo;posada&rdquo;<lb/>
(boarding house). Like most interior towns Santa Barbara had no hotel. Although I<lb/>
had a mosquito net over my berth, it served more as a trap than a protection against<lb/>
the insects, so that I could neither rest nor sleep. I had had a similar experience<lb/>
in a hotel in Colon, back in 1904. I was glad when daylight set in so that I could<lb/>
have a chance to hit back at my tormentors.</p>
<p>We wre under way before six o'clock in the morning, following the Maracaibo Lake<lb/>
coast to La Ceiba, a port of call only. A primitive railroad, with a wood-burning<lb/>
locomotive and cars with hard benches plied between La Ceiba and Motatan, for travell-<lb/>
ers entering the State of Trujillo. I had telegraphed from Santa Barbara to Valera<lb/>
to have one of the only two jitneys in the town meet me at Motatan, both &ldquo;Overlands&rdquo;.<lb/>
Locally, it was considered a miracle that they survived those daily trips between<lb/>
Valera and Motatan, rolling over dirt roads and frequently over the edge of nowhere.<lb/>
Overnight, the road would be washed away at crucial points by torrential rains, making<lb/>
it necessary to explore the road on mule-back before renewal of motor transportation.</p>
<p>Fortunate for me, the road to Valera was clear that day, for I had developed a<lb/>
high fever on the train, which I thought was an attack of malaria. Upon my arrival<lb/>
in Valera I had to take to my bed. Also it was my good fortune that the medical<lb/>
director of Sun Oil Company, Dr. de Bellard, had his headquarters in Valera. Before<lb/>
his arrival Valera had no graduate doctor, only a &ldquo;practicante&rdquo; or non-graduate. Dr.<lb/>
de Bellard was a graduate of Tulane and was the only American doctor registered in<lb/>
Venezuela in those days. When Sun Oil Company engaged his services he had a lucrative<lb/>
practice in Caracas. I was on very friendly terms with him and his mother, a fine old<lb/>
Spanish lady, God bless her memory. My better half sent for him and I had his constant<lb/>
care from the start and until I had passed the crisis. Only after I was well conva-<lb/>
lescent was I informed that I had contracted a nice case of typhus. In the meantime,<lb/>
Dr. de Bellard was hurriedly called to Caracas to attend to the wife of the Sun rep-<lb/>
resentative in Venezuela who had been taken suddenly ill. Before leaving, he called<lb/>
in &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo; Marmol, the practitioner, giving him explicit instructions as to what to<lb/>
do and what not to do and leaving him the the keys to his medicine cabinets. A few<lb/>
days after his departure I had a relapse. The liquidator in Maracaibo sent a &ldquo;nurse&rdquo;<lb/>
(who was no nurse at all) to assist my wife. She packed her back to Maracaibo on the<lb/>
following steamer. I pulled through by the grace of God and the devoted care of my<lb/>
better half and Dr. de Bellard's mother. That, I think, was the narrowest escape I<lb/>
had up to that time. Had Dr. de Bellard not been in Valera I am morally certain that<lb/>
it would have been a case of &ldquo;Good Bye Johnny&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Now back to health and 20 lbs. lighter, I set about arranging my affairs for clear-<lb/>
in out of Venezuela. My sub-manager had made very good progress in disposing of our<lb/>
stocks during my absence and my illness. I was fortunate in locating a buyer for our<lb/>
household furniture for two-thirds of its cost to me. My partner in exile, however,<lb/>
had the troublesome task of packing our seven pieces of baggage, a matter in which I<lb/>
have never been very much of an expert. I left Valera forever in the last week of<lb/>
November, 1921, planning to reach Panama for Christmas and then on to New York. Mr.<lb/>
Cohen, the liquidator, had other plans for me. He wanted me to help dispose of the<lb/>
Maracaibo stocks but I prevailed upon him to desist, arguing that I had done my fair<lb/>
share. He was a very considerate and understanding man. He adjusted my salary and<lb/>
<pb n="41" id="f06013041"/>
-- 44 --<lb/>
accrued leave; transportation to New York, including customary tips, also reimbursing<lb/>
me for the net loss on my household furniture, an item which my contract of employ-<lb/>
ment did not specify. He explained that it was company policy to provide branch<lb/>
managers with rent-free, furnished quarters, a little matter which my Maracaibo boss<lb/>
had conveniently overlooked. He would not reimburse me for the rent I had paid for<lb/>
my house in Valera, adding that I could claim it upon reporting to the New York<lb/>
office. I never claimed it, however, since no mention of it was made in my contract.</p>
<p>After stopping off at Panama for a few weeks, I continued my trip to New York<lb/>
where I arrived in January, 1922. Of the 15 floors which the MBA occupied when I<lb/>
left for Maracaibo, twelve had been vacated and were being rented. The large force<lb/>
had been reduced to skeleton size. Others had been sent out as liquidators. Of my<lb/>
old friends there only Mr. Todd, the personnel officer, was left. Asking me if I had<lb/>
any plans for the future I told him that I did not. &ldquo;How would you like to take over<lb/>
as one of the bank's liquidators&rdquo;, he said, adding that the position would be good for<lb/>
a year and a half to two years. The Maracaibo liquidator (Mr. Cohen) had written the<lb/>
Home Office of my exceptional services and assistance to him. &ldquo;The salary, he said,<lb/>
would be better than that which I had been receiving as branch manager&rdquo;. I told him<lb/>
that such work had no appeal for me. I would, however, appreciate his good offices<lb/>
in helping me line up with some going concern doing business in Latin America where<lb/>
my knowledge of Spanish would be an asset. He would be glad to do so. &ldquo;Come back<lb/>
tomorrow, he said, and I may have good news for you&rdquo;.</p>
<p>My friend evidently got busy, for the next day he had arranged for an interview<lb/>
with the vice-president of Compa&ntilde;ia Petrolera &ldquo;El Agwi&rdquo;, subsidiary of Atlantic Gulf<lb/>
&amp; West Inddias S. S. Company (Ward Line), owners of oil wells and a refinery in the<lb/>
State of Veracruz, with headquarters in Tampico. Salary and conditions of employment<lb/>
being satisfactory, I accepted a position to take charge of the warehouse at the<lb/>
company's Tecomate refinery in the state of Veracruz. Before leaving New York I was<lb/>
warned that men employed in New York for service in the Tampico oil fields were<lb/>
generally not welcome to the Mexican management of the company, but I did not let<lb/>
that deter me. Sure enough, upon reporting to the general manager in Tampico, I<lb/>
sensed from the coolness of my reception that I would not be the recipient of any<lb/>
special favors, made more patent still when I reported to the superintendent of the<lb/>
refinery, but I was there to serve the company. I had no chip on my shoulder and I<lb/>
was not seeking trouble, but I would certainly resent any form of persecution. I was<lb/>
informed that for the present there was no family cottage available for me, so I was<lb/>
assigned a room in the bachellor quarters, which I considered fair enough.</p>
<p>Ten days after my arrival one of the family cottages was vacated and I was tipped<lb/>
off that it was to be assigned to one of the superintendent's favorites. I went to<lb/>
his office and in his absence I told the chief clerk that I was eligible for the<lb/>
cottage and would he please inform the boss that I had called to see him about the<lb/>
matter. The following day I was cited to meet the superintendent who informed me<lb/>
that a man who had been on the job several months ahead of me would have priority.<lb/>
His family was living in Tampico but wanted to come to Tecomate. He was a clerk in<lb/>
the commisary store. I argued that I had been promised family quarters by the vice-<lb/>
president of the company who knew of my married status and encouraged me to have my<lb/>
wife accompany me. One of the cottages was intended for the incumbent of the position<lb/>
to which I had been appointed. With very poor grace he told me I could have the house.<lb/>
He made very little effort to conceal his displeasure. I knew then that I would have<lb/>
to watch my step from there on.</p>
<p>I stood for petty annoyances for some time but I knew I was a marked man and that<lb/>
sooner or later life at the refinery would interfere with my peace of mind and the<lb/>
efficiency of my work. My New York sponsor visited Tecomate on an inspection tour<lb/>
and was quatered in the superintendent's big residence. I requested permission to see<lb/>
him, which was very reluctantly granted. He was glad to see me, adding that it was<lb/>
his intention to see me before he left. I explained my predicament to him, which did<lb/>
<pb n="42" id="f06013042"/>
-- 45 --<lb/>
not at all surprise him. &ldquo;They probably think you were sent here to spy on them&rdquo;,<lb/>
he said, adding that his own hands were tied within a vicious circle and that he was<lb/>
sorry to have been a party to placing me in such a lion's den. A few days after he<lb/>
left I resigned. The Ward Line company eventually lost a neat little fortune in its<lb/>
petroleum venture, which goes to prove that "a cobbler should stick to his last.</p>
<p>I had had several invitations to visit one of my associates at Maracaibo who had<lb/>
resigned before the crash and was then in Mexico City. He had formed a company to<lb/>
handle Firestone tires and Sunoco lubricants in Mexico. We had gone to Venezuela<lb/>
together. &ldquo;Now that you are foot loose once more, he said, why not take a chance with<lb/>
me?&rdquo; I was entirely willing. He needed me to open branches in Monterrey and Guada-<lb/>
lajara. I opened the branch at Monterrey and turned it over to a Mexican manager<lb/>
within a year. Now I was ready to open a branch in Guadalajara. I had barely started<lb/>
when the &ldquo;de la Huerta revolution&rdquo; broke out with the State of Jalisco falling into<lb/>
the hands of the rebels. Our position there became untenable so I returned to Mexico<lb/>
City where conditions were not much better. We could sell tires and lubricants to<lb/>
the government if we wanted to gamble, a luxury which we could not afford. I helped<lb/>
prepare our year-end balances. We were considerably in the red. I decided to divorce<lb/>
myself from the payroll. My friend, Captain Carl B. Schmidt, was a born optimist<lb/>
when it came to Mexico. The fact that the revolution which had overthrown Porfirio<lb/>
Diaz had ruined his father meant nothing in his young life. He begged me to stay on<lb/>
with him, even charging me with disloyalty. I told him that ruse would not work so<lb/>
I left with his blessing. Our 14-day voyage on the SS&ldquo;Zulia&rdquo; of the Red D Line had<lb/>
resulted in a friendship which has never dimmed. That little 1500-ton tub remains<lb/>
green in my memory. Not many years later she was swallowed by the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
<p>Upon leaving Mexico I headed for Los Angeles, California, having no desire to<lb/>
face the rigurous winters of the East after a residence of twenty years in the tropics.<lb/>
I thought perhaps I could settle down there permanently but I soon came to the con-<lb/>
clusion that I did not fit into the picture after so many years doing missionary work<lb/>
in Latin America. Three months in Los Angeles sufficed to convince me that I was in<lb/>
the wrong pew, so I decided to return to Cuba, my first love, arriving there in early<lb/>
1924. I succeeded in obtaining a few contracts from the Public Works Department of the<lb/>
Cuban government, then headed by President Alfredo Zayas, for which I had been partia-<lb/>
ally paid when General Machado took over. He refused to pay any contractor who had<lb/>
not collected before Zayas left office. Calling all unpaid contractors to a conference<lb/>
he offered us 50% of the amounts due us. I told him I could not accept any such offer<lb/>
since my maximum profit was 25%, which was true. Some of them accepted his offer.<lb/>
Probably they could afford it as but few had been working on such a narrow margin as<lb/>
I had. I did learn a lesson, however. I deposited the certificates of acceptance of<lb/>
the jobs I had finished with my bank, intending to have my claim added to the Floating<lb/>
Debt rather than collect at a loss. A year later my claim was bought by someone who<lb/>
thought he could collect at par. He paid me 85%. I never discovered who he was as<lb/>
I was then in Mexico.</p>
<p>I had my fill of government contracts, following my interview with Machado. In<lb/>
the meantime, the revolution in Mexico had been squashed and business began to pick<lb/>
up in that revolution-ridden country and my good friend Schmidt was continually urging<lb/>
me to join him, finally cabling me a definte offer of $500.00 a month to open a branch<lb/>
in Tampico, where Firestone was the only one of &ldquo;The Big Four&rdquo; not represented in that<lb/>
active oil city. Leaving my better half in Havana, I accepted the offer, intending to<lb/>
send for her after starting the branch. I reported to my friend in Mexico City who<lb/>
had already placed an order for a carload of tires. Until arrival of the tires I was<lb/>
to study the situation in Tampico and look around for prospective dealers. By agree-<lb/>
ment of all tire importers, maximum discounts to dealers and oil companies were 15%<lb/>
on list prices to consumers. In Mexico City it was 25%. I soon discovered that con-<lb/>
fidential discounts had demoralized the tire business in Tampico, the principal offend-<lb/>
er being a well-known European brand which was giving an additional 5% on list prices<lb/>
which never appeared on the invoices, hence almost impossible to trace. With infinite<lb/>
<pb n="43" id="f06013043"/>
-- 46 --<lb/>
patience and tact I proved it to my own satisfaction. It so happened that the Ford<lb/>
Agency in Tampico, Universal Motor Company, welcomed the entry of Firestone in that<lb/>
hitherto-neglected field. All their cars had Firestones as original equipment, but<lb/>
for oil-fields service the four-ply tires were a failure and Ford owners insisted on<lb/>
six-ply or heavy duty tires. In practically every instance the agency was obliged to<lb/>
change the original equipment and sell the tires for city use. The agency had no tire<lb/>
of its own but was one of the principal purchasers of the heavy duty types. The joint<lb/>
managers of the company were sold on Firestones but I could not give them the 5% extra<lb/>
discount, nor was I convinced that they were actually receiving it. Could I see the<lb/>
credit notes issued by the distributor of the European tire? They had no objection.<lb/>
I was shown the tell-tale evidence and the corresponding entries on their books. Would<lb/>
they allow me to have photostatic copies made? They would, with the condition that I<lb/>
meet the secret discount. That, of course, I could not do. Would they be willing to<lb/>
show the evidence to a represenative from the Firestone office in Akron? They certain-<lb/>
ly would. They were anxious and I was perfectly willing to let them have the exclusive<lb/>
franchise for Tampico and the oil fields.</p>
<p>I reported my findings to Mexico City, well knowing that Akron would insist on<lb/>
written evidence in such matters as secret or unauthorized discounts. I suggested that<lb/>
Akron be informed that I had actually seen the written evidence but that the recipients<lb/>
of the extra discount were unwilling to surrender the incriminating credit notes, or to<lb/>
have them photographed; that it concerned a prospective customer whose monthly purchases<lb/>
averaged $6,000.00; that no time should be lost in having a confidential agent from the<lb/>
Home Office visit Tampico and verify the statements I had made. Within ten days I<lb/>
was visited by the assistant export manager, who immediately accompanied me to the <lb/>
office of Universal Motor Company where he confirmed my statements. Following his<lb/>
return to Akron we were placed in position to meet the extra discount. My carload of<lb/>
tires was about to arrive and I had obtained the necessary permits for opening the<lb/>
branch, but I had no intention of going through with it if I could line up the Ford<lb/>
distributor, now more anxious than ever to take over Firestone. I had sounded Captain<lb/>
Schmidt about such an arrangement, pointing out that the branch would be sure to be<lb/>
a losing venture for at least two years, what with rent and a top-heavy payroll, but he<lb/>
was bent on operating the branch, cost what it might. I made no further effort to<lb/>
convince him, but I was fully determined to carry through the deal with Universal Motor<lb/>
Company, even at the cost of easing myself out of a position and salary which I wanted<lb/>
and needed. My original Power of Attorney from the Mexican Trading Corporation had<lb/>
never been rescinded, therefore I could sign any notarial document in its name.</p>
<p>I closed the deal with Universal Motor Company, naming them exclusive distribut-<lb/>
ors for the State of Tamaulipas and the oil fields. I received cash for 1,800 tires<lb/>
and tubes (the entire carload), with 90-day credits to apply to future orders. We made<lb/>
an 8% net profit on the carload. After the contract was signed and notarially sealed<lb/>
I wired Captain Schmidt of my action, inquiring if I should take the next steamer out<lb/>
of Tampico to Havana. His reply was short and incisive. &ldquo;Who the hell told you you<lb/>
were going back to Cuba. Close the branch officially and come along to Mexico City&rdquo;.<lb/>
That was just like Captain Schmidt. It was the first and the last time that I refused<lb/>
to obey his specific instructions in such a flagrant manner but I have never had any<lb/>
twinges of conscience on account of the course I followed. Had I carried out his<lb/>
instructions I am morally certain I should never have forgiven myself for failing to<lb/>
safeguard his interests.</p>
<pb n="44" id="f06013044"/>
<p>-- 47 --</p>
<p>That was one of the best deals that I ever made for my friend, for myself or for<lb/>
anyone else. Instead of risking a loss of $750.00 a month we stood to make a profit of<lb/>
$950.00 a month, Mexican money or $475.00 American currency. What with competition so<lb/>
keen among the &ldquo;Big Four&rdquo; in the Mexican oil fields, we, as the last of the four to<lb/>
enter that field, would have to sacrifice profits for volume, and we were not in busi-<lb/>
ness for our health. Captain Schmidt saw the point after I explained the situation to<lb/>
him. But there was Guadalajara, again! A branch there would be once more in order,<lb/>
now that the Southern Pacific had completed its line from the American border to that<lb/>
city through the states of Sonora, Sinaloa and Nayarit, three states in which we were<lb/>
never able to make satisfactory connections. That was to be my new assignment and I<lb/>
arranged for an exploratory trip to the border before opening the Guadalajara branch.<lb/>
As had happened at Monterrey, I turned the branch over to a Mexican manager within a<lb/>
year, handling tires and lubricants and operating a model lubrication service. I picked<lb/>
the young son of an ex-banker as manager before I had ever met either of them. I knew<lb/>
the father by reputation only. When I called on him and introduced myself he was dumb-<lb/>
founded when I told him I had designs on one of his four sons to serve as my understudy.<lb/>
It was a new experience to him but he apparently liked it. Two days later, I met the<lb/>
son who had been elected by the family to serve as my understudy. His name was Guill-<lb/>
ermo Kunhardt, son of a German father and a Venezuelan mother. He had personality and<lb/>
he was well educated. He could count on the influence of his father and his wide<lb/>
acquaintance in that part of the country.</p>
<p>While young Kunhardt was learning the business, I paid him $50.00 a month. Within<lb/>
two months of intensive training I appointed him manager at a salary of $200.00 a month<lb/>
and travel expenses. He turned out to be a success and remained with the company for<lb/>
several years, judging from letters I had from Captain Schmidt after I left Mexico to<lb/>
return to Cuba permanently, which happened on or about the first of March, 1928. Having<lb/>
known the Sun Oil Company people in Venezuela, I asked for the Sunoco franchise for all<lb/>
Cuba, sensing that they were far from satisfied with the gallonage which they were<lb/>
getting through their branch. The best I could get was the City of Havana, and that for<lb/>
motor oils only, industrial oils excluded. It was not much but I accepted it, intend-<lb/>
ing to add tires to that line. I started out big, renting a service station on the<lb/>
Malecon and adding two hydraulic lubrication elevators to my activities, the first such<lb/>
service to be installed in Cuba. By the time I was ready to do business, I had invested<lb/>
$6,000.00 in lubrication equipment, gasoline pumps and tanks, tire racks, office furni-<lb/>
ture, etc., with $600.00 in a one-day advertising splurge in the Havna newspapers and<lb/>
weeklies. Up to this time I had paid cash for everything in the line of equipment,<lb/>
taking the corresponding discounts.</p>
<p>I was making headway rapidly when, two weeks after I got started, the Cuban Govern-<lb/>
ment dropped a monkey-wrench into my machinery. The Public Works Department wanted to<lb/>
remove the unsightly street cars from the Malecon, the pride of the Havanese, and before<lb/>
I knew it they began to pull up the rails in front of my service station and practically<lb/>
closing it. My customers were obliged to drive through an alley in the rear of my<lb/>
place for gasoline and service. The road in front of my station was blocked to traffic<lb/>
for three months. In the meantime, I was paying $500.00 a month in rent. The only con-<lb/>
solation I had was the Neon sign set up in front, in orange and blue, telling car owners<lb/>
that Sunoco was a motor oil and not a salad oil. The branch had never advertised the<lb/>
brand. I tried to flood-light the building but that was expensive advertising, with<lb/>
electric current at 17&cent; per KWH. Today it is 9-1/3&cent;. I was practically bankrupt after<lb/>
six months, when along came my Mexican associate of other days, Carl B. Schmidt. He<lb/>
was on his annual visit to Philadelphia and Akron.</p>
<p>I told him my tale of woe, feeling sure it would not fall on deaf ears. &ldquo;You're<lb/>
already broke, Johnny, but let's try to figure out something. Suppose I get Mr. J.<lb/>
Howard Pew to close the Havana branch, what increase in gallonage can I promise him in<lb/>
your behalf?&rdquo; The branch volume did not exceed 75,000 gallons a year, I was quite<lb/>
sure. I told him that starting with January 1, 1929, I could double that volume. I<lb/>
<pb n="45" id="f06013045"/>
-- 48 --<lb/>
managed to convey some of my optimism to the man to whom I was looking to be my<lb/>
savior. I looked him in the eye, expecting a smile of ridicule which would have<lb/>
been entirely justified, considering the mess I had made of things, but it was not<lb/>
there. He might have had his doubts, but if he had any they did not show. He was<lb/>
too noble and too sincere a friend to doubt my own sincerity, without calculating<lb/>
that a man in my desperate condition might resort to subterfuge and promises impo-<lb/>
ssible of fulfillment in order to save himself. I had concrete evidence of his<lb/>
nobility of character one day in Mexico City when a dray-horse pulling a heavy load<lb/>
slipped to the pavement and broke its leg, a block distant from our office. A crowd<lb/>
had formed around the dumb and helpless animal, so out of curiosity we wanted to see<lb/>
what it was all about. Pushing his way through the crowd, Captain Schmidt realized<lb/>
what had happened. He asked the owner to shoot the poor beast and put it out of its<lb/>
misery. With tears in his eyes, the man replied that he could <add>not</add> afford to lose his<lb/>
horse. Schmidt asked him how much a horse to replace him would cost. He replied<lb/>
&ldquo;cien pesos, se&ntilde;or&rdquo; (100 pesos, Sir). &ldquo;You wait for me here, Johnny&rdquo;, said Schmidt.<lb/>
&ldquo;I'll be back in a moment.&rdquo; Back he came with his automatic and a hundred pesos in<lb/>
gold coin ($50.00), handing the money to the cartman. The crowd, now larger, watch-<lb/>
ed and murmured as he shot the animal through the head. One shot sufficed. I venture<lb/>
to say that every Mexican there present never forgot that incident. I have never<lb/>
forgotten it either. At that time of his life Captain Schmidt was not very flush<lb/>
with money.</p>
<p>But to return to Schmidt's Havana visit with me. We sat down and drew up a plan<lb/>
which he thought might appeal to the president of Sun Oil Company, Mr. J. Howard Pew.<lb/>
It included the formation of a corporation with a capital of $25,000.00 and to be<lb/>
named Compa&ntilde;ia Sunoco de Cuba. My own investment of approximately $8,000.00 in the<lb/>
unfortunate venture would be my share in the new company. If I could find another<lb/>
party with $7,000.00, my friend would invest $10,000.00 to complete the $25,000.00.<lb/>
I induced a Cuban friend to come in with us, providing we could obtain the franchise<lb/>
for the whole Island. He did not have the amount available at the moment but he could<lb/>
arrange it within 60 days. Within a week I received a cable from Schmidt to the<lb/>
effect that Mr. Pew had approved our plan and had issued instructions to the Regional<lb/>
Manager in Jacksonville to meet with us on a given date, in Havana, accompanied by his<lb/>
auditor, to transfer the stocks of the Branch to the new company. My spirits rose as<lb/>
if by magic. Once more I could vision a new lease on life for me in the offing, thanks<lb/>
to my good friend.</p>
<p>The Regional Manager, Mr. Paul H. Harrison, arrived and we set about taking<lb/>
inventory of the Branch stocks and such items of office furniture and equipment as<lb/>
we could use. Schmidt told me that Mr. Pew had accepted my promise of doubling volume<lb/>
within a year with &ldquo;a little more than a grain of salt&rdquo;, but hoped I would try for that<lb/>
goal. He thought I was being over-optimistic but he was impressed by my friend's<lb/>
confidence in my ability to put it across. Mr. Harrison was held in high esteem at the<lb/>
Philadelphia office, an esteem which he no doubt merited, but for us he turned out to<lb/>
be very much of a Shylock. Among the lubricants which he insisted we take over were<lb/>
several barrels of grease shipped to Cuba in 1919, the first year the Branch was opened.<lb/>
They were wooden barrels, a war-time substitute for metal drums, but for nine years<lb/>
they had been religiously carried on inventory at original cost. We opened one of the<lb/>
barrels only to discover that the oil or lubricating agent had leaked out through the<lb/>
seams, leaving the contents a soapy mass. We pointed out that it would not be fair to<lb/>
saddle us with worthless material which we would eventually be obliged to haul to the<lb/>
garbage dump at our expense, an expense which we were willing to assume, if not invoiced<lb/>
to us. Our efforts were in vain, for the regional manager insisted on his &ldquo;pound of<lb/>
flesh&rdquo;. As a matter of fact, he was over-zealous and in such a petty matter failed to<lb/>
reflect the Live-and-let-Live policy of his Company. Within six months the Cuban<lb/>
company was removed from the jurisdiction of Jacksonville and placed under the Foreign<lb/>
Sales Department, where it properly belonged. That was a relief to me.</p>
<pb n="46" id="f06013046"/>
<p>-- 49 --</p>
<p>The year 1929 was to be my banner year in more ways than one. Here I was, in my<lb/>
48th year but with the spirit and enthusiasm of a youth of 25. I had made a promise<lb/>
which I was morally bound to make good and I had a date with history of which I had<lb/>
never dreamed. As far back as 1902, my old friend of yellow fever days, Major Jeffer-<lb/>
son Randolph Kean, of the Army Medical Corps, became the advocate for Congressional<lb/>
recognition of Walter Reed and his brood of human guinea pigs. With a tenacity of<lb/>
purpose and actuated by the most altruistic of motives, he did not falter in his<lb/>
efforts during those 27 years. In February, 1929, he had the great satisfaction of<lb/>
seeing his missionary work crowned with success. It is to that noble son of Virginia,<lb/>
more than all the others combined, that those connected with the yellow fever experi-<lb/>
ments owe everlasting gratitude. As one of the three survivors, I pay homage to my<lb/>
friend and benefactor for his consistent devotion to our cause. Our good friend is<lb/>
is still in the land of the living, having been retired many years ago with the rank<lb/>
of Brigadier General.</p>
<p>There it was. The Act of February 28, 1929. &ldquo;Participants in Yellow Fever Invest-<lb/>
igations in Cuba. The Secretary of War, Hon. Elihu Root, in his annual report, 1902,<lb/>
said with reference to the conquest of yellow fever in Cuba in 1900-1901: The brilli-<lb/>
ant character of this scientific achievement, its inestimable value to mankind, the<lb/>
saving of thousands of lives, and the deliverance of the Atlantic seacoast from constant<lb/>
apprehension, demand special recognition from the Government of the United States. The<lb/>
Congress has, in concurrence with his opinion, by an Act approved February 28, 1929,<lb/>
authorized and directed the Secretary of War to publish annually in the Army Register<lb/>
a Roll of Honor on which shall be carried the following names, and to define in appro-<lb/>
priate language the part taken by each of these persons in the yellow fever invest-<lb/>
igation in Cuba.&rdquo; The same Act provided that a gold medal be presented to each person<lb/>
named in the Roll, or to the representatives of those who have died." An annuity of<lb/>
$1,500.00, for the rest of their natural lives, was also made to the survivors and to<lb/>
the widows of those who had died prior to the passage of the Act. The Roll of Honor<lb/>
includes the names of the four members of the Army Yellow Fever Board and the 18 men<lb/>
who volunteered for the experiments.</p>
<p><hi>I QUOTE MY OWN ENTRY ON THE ROLL OF HONOR</hi>:</p>
<p>JOHN J. MORAN was employed as a clerk at the department<lb/>
headquarters at Marianao, Cuba. He there did clerical<lb/>
work for Major REED and became interested in the work<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Board. He and KISSINGER were the<lb/>
first to volunteer for the conclusive series of experi-<lb/>
ments at Camp Lazear. He was bitten on November 26 and<lb/>
29, by infected mosquitoes, but without result. On Dec-<lb/>
ember 21, 1900, he twice visited the mosquito room, and<lb/>
again next day, and was repeatedly bitten. On Christmas<lb/>
Day he became ill, and suffered a well marked and severe<lb/>
attack of yellow fever. MORAN refused to accept the<lb/>
bonus which was given by the Governor of Cuba to each<lb/>
volunteer, stating that he was glad to be able to do this<lb/>
service to humanity. He was discharged from the service,<lb/>
July 2, 1900, with character excellent. He served for<lb/>
some years at Panama during the construction of the Canal,<lb/>
and was commissioned a captain in the United States Army<lb/>
(Emergency Forces) during the World War.</p>
<p>Moran, John J. B-Ireland<lb/>
15 Mar. 76. Capt. Q.M.C.N.A.<lb/>
27 May 18; hon. dis. 1 Oct.<lb/>
19. -- Pvt. and actg. hosp.<lb/>
stewd., Hosp. Corps 3 July<lb/>
97 to 2 July 00. B. C. S.<lb/>
Mount Hope Coll. 96.</p>
<p>(Copied from the<lb/>
Roll of Honor,<lb/>
Official Army<lb/>
Register for 1947)</p>
<p>The foregoing tribute of a grateful nation is one of which any man might well be<lb/>
proud. Applied to me by my adopted country, I am doubly proud and grateful, especially<lb/>
in that the ROLL OF HONOR will be published as long as we have an Army. My entry will<lb/>
be complete and closed when notation of the date of my death may be in order. For that<lb/>
final notation I have long ago been ready. Amen.</p>
<pb n="47" id="f06013047"/>
<p>-- 50 --</p>
<p>Captain Schmidt and I had promised Mr. Pew a volume of 150,000 gallons for the<lb/>
year 1929. We actually made it a little over 170,000. We were riding high for that<lb/>
year. In early 1930 Mr. M. L. Newhall, Foreign Sales Manager, paid us a visit. Taking<lb/>
advantage of his presence in Havana, I showed him a list of of worthless material and<lb/>
obsolete equipment which the Jacksonville regional manager had forced us to accept. It<lb/>
amounted to less than $800.00. Without comment, he asked for a copy of the list. say-<lb/>
ing he would look into the matter on his return to Philadelphia. I sensed that as a<lb/>
matter of delicacy he refrained from criticism. A few weeks after his return to the<lb/>
home office, we received a credit memorandum for a little over $5,000.00, it having<lb/>
come to light that the stock invoiced to us had been over-priced. For that act in<lb/>
righting a wrong I owe a debt of gratitude to Messrs. Pew and Newhall. Mr. Pew<lb/>
recently retired as President of Sun Oil Company. Mr. Newhall resigned his position<lb/>
with the Company several years ago to become executive vice-president of the Berwind-<lb/>
White Coal Mining Company.</p>
<p>In the year 1930 we increased our gallonage to to 190,000 and Mr. Pew was so<lb/>
favorably impressed with our progress that I was instructed to look for a suitable<lb/>
site for a small bulk-plant for both motor oils and gasoline. I located an ideal site<lb/>
of 5,000 square meters and the Engineering Department had drawn up blueprints for the<lb/>
proposed plant. As I was about to execute an option on the plot, an unexpected turn<lb/>
in political conditions in Cuba discouraged the Company from going ahead with the pro-<lb/>
ject, postponing it for a year or two. With the assassination of Rafael Trejo, a<lb/>
young University of Havana student, by the hired assassins of General Machado, dictator-<lb/>
president of Cuba, conditions had reached an ugly stage. The University was closed by<lb/>
order of the tyrant and the student body went underground. For the succeeding three<lb/>
years, bombs on the one hand, assassinations and reprisals on the other, became the<lb/>
order of the day. Business just marked time. General Machado's &ldquo;Porra&rdquo; or secret<lb/>
police had a continuous field-day, the innocent falling with the guilty. It was a case<lb/>
of &ldquo;an eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth&rdquo;. Finally, on August 12, 1933, the day<lb/>
of reckoning for Machado had arrived and the dictator &ldquo;flew the coop&rdquo;, never again to<lb/>
see his native land alive.</p>
<p>Business could now try to get back to normal after a three years' nightmare, so<lb/>
most of us thought when the gentle and mild-mannered Carlos Manuel de Cespedes took<lb/>
over as Provisional President. In less than a month he was deposed, as were the commi-<lb/>
sioned officers of the National Army of Cuba. Headed by Sergeant-stenographer Fulgencio<lb/>
Batista and a hand-full of other non-commissioned officers, the regular army officers<lb/>
were &ldquo;requested&rdquo; to hand over the army, which they meekly did, thinking it more or less<lb/>
of a joke, a capital error on their part. They should have realized that insubordin-<lb/>
ation and mutiny are dangerous playthings. The rank and file of the army were disci-<lb/>
plined soldiers and had the officers assumed the responsibility vested in them, I would<lb/>
now be recording a different story. True, the National Army officers should have weed-<lb/>
ed out of their ranks those who had participated in the dictator's ruthless and repress-<lb/>
ive measures, but they hesitated too long. By and large, those officers were good men,<lb/>
career officers with no interest in politics, strictly army men and nine out of ten<lb/>
opposed to Machado. It is inconceivable that such a turn-over could be brought about<lb/>
without firing a shot, but that is exactly what happened. If they wanted to establish<lb/>
a unique record in military history, they certainly had succeeded, but subsequent events<lb/>
indicated that such was not their object.</p>
<p>They now retired to their homes, but within a few days they became unwelcome guests<lb/>
at the Hotel Nacional, occupying two floors of the building. It did not suit Sergeant<lb/>
Batista (now Colonel) to have that well-trained miniature army entrenched in such a<lb/>
fortress, so he had the hotel surrounded by a strong guard. Presently, they had the<lb/>
hotel all to themselves, with the management and other personnel abandoning the building<lb/>
They operated the elevators and did their own cooking. Telephone service had been cut<lb/>
cut off. Their supplies were running out and not replenished. Slowly, they were<lb/>
being starved to death, so they decided to make a break for liberty and to fight. They had<lb/>
<pb n="48" id="f06013048"/>
-- 51 --<lb/>
been promised outside assistance by other groups of sympathizers who had fought Machado<lb/>
and his regime and had accepted Carlos Manuel de Cespedes, son of &ldquo;The Father of His<lb/>
Country&rdquo;, as the man most likely to bring order out of chaos and to consolidate all<lb/>
factions in supporting a program for economic recovery and to end civil strife. The<lb/>
&ldquo;Coup of the 4th of September&rdquo;, as that episode is known in the history of Cuba frus-<lb/>
trated that noble attempt. Aside from the part played by individual officers, addicts<lb/>
of Machado in his repressive measures, the National Army officers had remained neutral.<lb/>
They had contributed nothing to the downfall of the dictator, neither had they helped<lb/>
him, with one notable exception, the Chief of Staff and a handful of officers imbued by<lb/>
selfish motives.</p>
<p>Those who had participated in &ldquo;The 4th of September Coup&rdquo; included the Student<lb/>
Federation of the University of Havana and Dr. Ramon Grau San Martin, professor of<lb/>
physiology and a prominent medico, together with other semi-radical elements not in<lb/>
accord with the selection of Cespedes, principally because <unclear>Summer</unclear> Welles, Special Envoy<lb/>
of the State Department had backed his candidacy. U. S. Imperialism was flourished as<lb/>
the underlying factor in the selection of Cespedes. &ldquo;Yankee Imperialism&rdquo; had become<lb/>
a favorite slogan for newsmen and orators and is still effectively wielded, notwith-<lb/>
standing the &ldquo;Good-Neighbor&rdquo; policy initiated by President Roosevelt and fostered by<lb/>
him until the day of his death. University students and the other civilian malcontents<lb/>
realized that the Cuban Army's support was necessary in order that the &ldquo;Coup&rdquo; might<lb/>
succeed. They also knew that the National Army officers would not second any such<lb/>
movement. But there was Sergeant Batista, expert stenographer to the deposed Chief of<lb/>
Staff. He had learned a few things while employed in that confidential capacity. He<lb/>
also knew that he had not become rich on his salary of Chief of Staff, a modest one in<lb/>
those days of intense depression in Cuba.</p>
<p>When Sergeant Batista made common cause with the civilian groups I have no doubt<lb/>
he was not actuated by personal ambitions only. He had a little of the idealist in his<lb/>
makeup. After all, he risked more than the civilians, in that his insubordination<lb/>
might have led to an end of his existence, there and then. Regardless of what he had<lb/>
done before or since, he must be credited with an uncommon degree of courage. He dis-<lb/>
claimed any ambition for rank, stating that he would head the newly baptized &ldquo;Consti-<lb/>
tutional Army&rdquo; as Sergeant Batista. It is to be presumed, of course, that he knew such<lb/>
an anomaly could only be temporary. His civilian associates had different ideas, for<lb/>
within a week he was promoted to Colonel and Chief of Staff by the five-man government<lb/>
which succeeded Cespedes and which lasted less than a week, after they had decided it<lb/>
would not work. The other four members induced Dr. Ramon Grau San Martin to assume the<lb/>
Presidency, which he did with some reluctance, so it was said.</p>
<p>Now, with rank and status appropriate to his position, Colonel Batista set about<lb/>
building up personal loyalty to him in the Constitutional Army, being most solicitous<lb/>
of their welfare. He saw to it that they were well uniformed and well fed, little<lb/>
matters which count much with soldiers. Other Cubans might feel the pinch of hard<lb/>
times but not the army. Colonel Batista could now blossom into the &ldquo;Strong Man&rdquo; and<lb/>
dictator which he voluntarily relinquished eleven years later. He assumed powers which<lb/>
Machado never had, but along different lines. Many of &ldquo;the cream of the cream&rdquo; of<lb/>
Havana society bowed and kowtowed to him. He had come far.</p>
<p>The break for liberty of the imprisoned army officers was planned for the first<lb/>
week of October but the civilian and other groups which had promised to join them had<lb/>
apparently failed to coordinate their efforts. Also, it is to be assumed that Colonel<lb/>
Batista had been tipped off by one of their supposed friends. The guard surrounding<lb/>
the hotel had been doubled and the vicinity had been well illuminated, which had its<lb/>
disadvantages. The shooting began before daybreak, the sentries being the first vict-<lb/>
ims. They were picked off, one after another, by the sharp-shooting officers, l i k e<lb/>
<pb n="49" id="f06013049"/>
-- 52 --<lb/>
flies. That first skirmish was supposed to be the signal for the friends of the<lb/>
beleaguered officers to enter the picture, but instead of their friends Colonel Batista<lb/>
had formed a cordon around the neighborhood of the hotel, taking care to keep out of<lb/>
range of the sharp-shooters.</p>
<p>The Hotel Nacional, built on the site of an old Spanish battery, could not be<lb/>
stormed while the officers' supply of ammunition held out, except at a prohibitive<lb/>
price in human lives. They had an ample supply of rifles and machine guns and con-<lb/>
siderable ammunition. No shots were wasted. Colonel Batista and his advisers decided<lb/>
to bombard the hotel with artillery fire, his cannons being placed out of range of the<lb/>
besiegers, the hotel forming an ideal target. Fire was concentrated on the two foors<lb/>
of the hotel known to to be occupied by the officers. Damage to the building was the<lb/>
least of the Colonel's worries. That was a matter which the hotel owners, the insurance<lb/>
companies and the Cuban Government could settle in the distant future. For him it was<lb/>
the course of least resistance. The Cuban Navy endeavored to assist in the bombardment<lb/>
from the harbor but its fire was woefully ineffective and out of line with the target,<lb/>
due in part to the small size of the units engaged and their small armament. After<lb/>
several trials the gunboats retired from the scene.</p>
<p>The heavy artillery brought in from &ldquo;El Campamento de Columbia&rdquo;, now known as<lb/>
&ldquo;Ciudad Militar&rdquo; (Military City), had better luck. After a few wild shots the gunners<lb/>
established their range and for four hours the hotel was subjected to a continuous<lb/>
bombardment, the two floors occupied by the officers being hit with devastating effect.<lb/>
Finally, that valiant band of career officers, with their ranks decimated, had no other<lb/>
alternative than that of surrendering or perishing. About four o'clock in the after-<lb/>
noon they hoisted a white flag in token of surrender, descending to the hotel lawn with<lb/>
their arms raised above their heads. It was very much of an uneven battle and an in-<lb/>
glorious one for both sides. It was said that some of the officers were shot in cold<lb/>
blood on the hotel lawn by some of the victors, immediately after the surrender, to<lb/>
avenge the death of their comrades, especially those known to be sharp-shooters. As<lb/>
there were no civilian witnesses, it is presumed that the survivors were responsible<lb/>
for the rumors. One by one, the survivors were eventually released, retiring to a<lb/>
life of oblivion and to commence anew in other activities, a sorry alternative for<lb/>
career officers who were educated and trained for army life.</p>
<p>With elimination of of the National Army officers, the new army dropped even its<lb/>
name. Henceforth it was to be known as the &ldquo;Constitutional Army&rdquo;, although there was<lb/>
nothing constitutional about it. In reality it was &ldquo;The Fourth of September Army&rdquo;,<lb/>
with its &ldquo;4th of September banner&rdquo; being accorded the same honors as the lone-star<lb/>
Cuban flag, so far as the military was concerned. With his consolidation of the army,<lb/>
Colonel Batista promptly nullified the influence of the Student Federation in the civil<lb/>
government of Dr. Ramon Grau San Martin, by this time President in name only. Unwilling<lb/>
to accept dictation from Colonel Batista, Dr. Grau resigned the presidency and went into<lb/>
exile. Batista then appointed Colonel Carlos Mendieta as provisional president after<lb/>
he was assured that orders from Camp Columbia would be scrupolously obeyed. For the<lb/>
following eleven years the erstwhile sergeant-stenographer was Cuba's &ldquo;Strong Man&rdquo;,<lb/>
culminating in his election to the presidency, in 1940, but still holding the army in<lb/>
the hollow of his hand. In the 1944 election he could have imposed his chosen success-<lb/>
or on the country. He did not, however, a large item in his favor. Instead, he<lb/>
allowed the voters to express their choice, free of any governmental or military inter-<lb/>
ference, with the result that his former enemy, Dr. Ramon Grau San Martin was elected<lb/>
by an overwhelming majority.</p>
<p>While Batista was President of Cuba he had himself promoted from Colonel to Major<lb/>
General. Being now a millionaire, he assisted at the inauguration of Dr. Grau, then<lb/>
graciously removing himself from the Cuban scene. He would travel throughout Latin<lb/>
America and gather material for a book of &ldquo;Impressions&rdquo; which he would publish later<lb/>
on. He would return to Cuba a year later, but four years have rolled by and he is<lb/>
<pb n="50" id="f06013050"/>
-- 53 --<lb/>
still in voluntary exile, d e e m i n g it the better part of wisdom to stay away from<lb/>
Cuba, having taken up residence in Daytona Beach, Florida, where he keeps in touch with<lb/>
events in his native country. In the 1948 elections he was elected a senator of the<lb/>
republic and he may return to occupy his seat in the Senate, where he will enjoy legis-<lb/>
lative immunity. He has many friends in Cuba but he also has many enemies. In a<lb/>
country where there are so many trigger-happy men wandering around, life in the U. S.<lb/>
for opulent General Batista is much more secure. With all his faults, however, Batista<lb/>
is not lacking in personal courage and it may well be that he will face any danger that<lb/>
may be in store for him. The opinions I have here expressed are merely those of a<lb/>
neutral bystander. Although I am a foreigner in Cuba, I have been an interested obser-<lb/>
ver in Cuban events since 1928. That, of course, is quite natural. Personally, I have<lb/>
ever been accorded the hospitality for which Cubans are famous towards &ldquo;the stranger in<lb/>
their midst&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But to get back to business! The depression which hit the U. S. during the Hoover<lb/>
regime affected Cuba doubly so, with its one-crop mainstay - sugar - being a dearth in<lb/>
the one market upon which it had always depended. Cuba has considered tourist business<lb/>
as its second crop and tobacco as third in importance. A depression in the U. S.<lb/>
affected all three. Nor was Cuba the only Latin American country in the doldrums.<lb/>
Mexico was hard hit, as my associate there took pains to inform me. The Mexican peso<lb/>
which could be converted into dollars at the rate of two to one when I left the country<lb/>
in 1928 could now be exchanged only at the rate of four to one. The principal stock-<lb/>
holder of Compa&ntilde;ia Sunoco de Cuba wrote to inform me that he could not buy dollars with<lb/>
which to pay off his indebtedness to Sun Oil Company, except at a prohibitive rate of<lb/>
exchange, hence he would be obliged to transfer his interest in the Cuban company to<lb/>
Sun, if they should be willing, the proceeds to be credit to his account. At the moment<lb/>
of writing he owned one-half of the stock, or 125 shares, then having a book value of<lb/>
$115.00 a share. The company sent an auditor from Philadelphia to look us over before<lb/>
deciding on the deal. Being satisfied that we were solvent, they took over Captain<lb/>
Schmidt's half interest at par. That was in 1931. The Sun company then became my<lb/>
partner. At the end of that year we were in the red but they stood nobly by me. Three<lb/>
years later the Cuban company was bankrupt and I turned in my holdings as treasury<lb/>
stock. That was not much of a sacrifice since it was worth less than $25.00 a share.</p>
<p>With my stock turned in I offered to resign so that Sun would be free to appoint<lb/>
a manager of their own choosing. They refused to accept it, adducing that I was the<lb/>
victim of economic conditions, at the same time extending me a vote of confidence. I<lb/>
continued to carry one. At that, our position was no different than that of the average<lb/>
importer and our percentage of loss much lower than most. The company continued to<lb/>
supply me with all the lubricants I called for and I was not pressed for remittances.<lb/>
I was to keep them informed and instructed to watch my credits carefully. In those days<lb/>
there were no good credit risks and every sale on credit was a risk, but we were obliged<lb/>
to extend credit or close out, an alternative which the Sun company was opposed to.<lb/>
They knew, of course, that our situation was not unique. Many importers, subsidiaries<lb/>
of American companies, retired their representation from Cuba for own account, naming<lb/>
distributors to represent their products.</p>
<p>In 1934 I was called to Philadelphia for consultation. I suspected that the call<lb/>
was just an excuse to give me a vacation which I would not take on my own account. I<lb/>
happened to arrive in New York on a Monday morning and called up a friend who I had<lb/>
known in Mexico. Much to my surprise he asked me if I had come to New York to see<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;, authored by Sidney Howard. It was all news to me. He informed me that<lb/>
the play had its initial performance the preceding Saturday night in the Martin Beck<lb/>
Theatre, recommending that I secure a copy of the TIMES, Sunday edition. James Stewart<lb/>
was playing the part of Sgt. John J. O'Hara, the name the author had given me in the<lb/>
play, as being more Irish than Moran. I called on the director and he very promptly<lb/>
<pb n="51" id="f06013051"/>
-- 54 --<lb/>
invited me to that evening's performance, which I gladly accepted, very curious to<lb/>
see myself on the stage in the person of Jimmy Stewart, then a rising young actor<lb/>
who was later to blossom into stardom. After the performance I was introduced to him<lb/>
and to the other members of the cast. I thought his brogue was much thicker than my<lb/>
own and wondered where he got it. They all seemed surprised at my timidity, since I<lb/>
was extremely vocal in the play, with my quotations from Shakespeare and my lording<lb/>
it over Kissinger. Guthrie McClintic, the director, suggested I meet the press but I<lb/>
rebelled. Sidney Howard had left for Europe. Preparatory to writing the play he had<lb/>
spent three days in Havana with me. That was in early 1932. When he returned to New<lb/>
York he wrote me:<lb/>
&ldquo;....... I had a great time in Havana, thanks to you<lb/>
and I am very grateful. You helped my job a lot but<lb/>
knowing you is more important than the job ........<lb/>
Please give my best to all the gentlemen leaning<lb/>
against the bar at the American Club and to your wife<lb/>
and to those Spanish speaking Kathleen Mavourneen<lb/>
nieces of yours. ......&rdquo;</p>
<p>Mr. Howard had reference to my wife's nieces, Eudora and Patricia O'Shaughnessy,<lb/>
whose mother was Cuban and whose father was an American. Greater was Sidney Howard's<lb/>
surprise when he learned that their father's name was Phil Sheridan O'Shaughnessy,<lb/>
named after his godfather, General Phil Sheridan of Union Army fame. I have ever<lb/>
been proud of the friendship of Sidney Howard, scenarist and playwright of &ldquo;Yellow<lb/>
Jack&rdquo;, least of his products, and &ldquo;Gone With the Wind&rdquo;, his most outstanding success.<lb/>
I mourned his untimely death, just as was about to reach the zenith of his fame. He<lb/>
was killed by his own tractor while enjoying his hobby of &ldquo;gentleman-farmer&rdquo;. I met<lb/>
his widow for the first time at Washington and Jefferson College, in 1940, when the<lb/>
Jesse W. Lazear Laboratory Building was inaugurated, among the invited guests being<lb/>
Mrs. Polly Damrosch Howard, daughter of the famous Walter Damrosch. Student talent<lb/>
reproduced her husband's play, &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. Kissinger and this narrator were award-<lb/>
ed citations as &ldquo;heros and benefactors of humanity&rdquo;, thanks to the initiative of Dr.<lb/>
Philip S. Hench, of the Mayo Clinic, also an honored guest and the recipent of an<lb/>
honorary degree, Doctor of Science.</p>
<p>Two years before (1938) &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; had been filmed and screened by MGM and<lb/>
I had been asked permission for the use of my real name instead of &ldquo;O'Hara&rdquo;, to be<lb/>
shown on the screen at the beginning or at the end of the picture, as one of the five<lb/>
human guinea pigs impersonated in the play, the other four being Cooke, Folk, Jernigan<lb/>
and Kissinger. I had no objection. Robert Montgomery impersonated me in the screened<lb/>
version. As Sergeant John J. O'Hara his brogue was perfect, but he dropped it on one<lb/>
or two occasions. The picture as a whole was poorly directed and the characters very<lb/>
much distorted, which was not true of the well-directed stage edition. The directors<lb/>
of the film had been handed a lot of misinformation by self-styled experts, within<lb/>
easy reach. Charles Coburn impersonated Finlay to perfection but he unwittingly spoil-<lb/>
it by wearing a monocle instead of spectacles. No one had ever seen Finlay use a<lb/>
monocle in Cuba. Dr. Agramonte's &ldquo;broken English&rdquo; was another blunder. His English<lb/>
was as fluent as his Spanish, having lived in the U. S. from age 7 to 25., graduating<lb/>
in medicine at Columbia University in 1892, being a classmate of Dr. Lazear. MGM<lb/>
management, however, and not the directors of the film was responsible for the glaring<lb/>
errors appearing in the thrown-together product. Lewis Stone, as Walter Reed, played<lb/>
his part to perfection, as usual.</p>
<p>But to get back to earth again. The prosperity for which Cuba had been waiting<lb/>
for ten long years came along at last, with the outbreak of World War II, when her<lb/>
sugar became one of the essentials for armies in the field, and much more so after<lb/>
Pearl Harbor and the entry of the U. S. in the world conflict. Poverty was forgotten<lb/>
and &ldquo;the dance of the millions&rdquo; was on. Overnight, so to speak, the peons on sugar<lb/>
<pb n="52" id="f06013052"/>
--- 55 ---<lb/>
cane fields and sugar-mill workers and their families were sporting expensive jewelry,<lb/>
wearing fifteen and twenty dollar hats, with similar prices for shoes. Plantation and<lb/>
sugar-mill owners were paying off their mortgages and building palatial residences and<lb/>
selling their ill-cared-for houses of depression days at fancy prices. Seven years<lb/>
after Pearl Harbor the orgy goes merrily on. Houses which could have been purchased<lb/>
for $10,000.00 in 1938 now sell for as much as $50,000.00. The Cubans are a happy and<lb/>
care-free people. They know that life will come to an end some day, so why not get the<lb/>
most out of it now. Let posterity look out for itself and the devil take the hind-<lb/>
most. Laying something by for a rainy day does not worry the average Cuban. There are<lb/>
no better spenders in the world than the people of this &ldquo;Gem of the Sea&rdquo;. The words<lb/>
&ldquo;Eat, drink and be merry, for tomorrow ye may die&rdquo; must have been inspired by a Cuban.<lb/>
For a year-around climate Cuba may be equalled but not surpassed. It is a paradise<lb/>
for the rich as well as the poor, but God alone takes care of the white-collar or<lb/>
salaried employee. He was better off before the war than he is now. Then, he could<lb/>
buy a pound of butter for forty cents and a pound of lard for fifteen cents. Today,<lb/>
prices of both have quadrupled, but his salary has not even doubled. Beef and rice cost<lb/>
four times pre-war prices.</p>
<p>After Pearl Harbor, our own troubles began. We had added pneumatic tires and tubes<lb/>
to our one line of lubricants. In early 1942, that additional line was frozen and<lb/>
strictly rationed for the duration, leaving us again with our one line. There was never<lb/>
any real shortage in that line, unlike other petroleum products, such as gasoline, gas<lb/>
oil and fuel oil. Our four strong competitors had either one or all four products and<lb/>
the available supply of the three rationed products was never sufficient. Our customers<lb/>
were informed, always by word of mouth, that if they expected their quota of the ration-<lb/>
ed products, lubricants would have to be included. It was a case of &ldquo;you scratch me and<lb/>
I'll scratch you&rdquo;. The policy of &ldquo;live and let live&rdquo; was an unknown quantity to those<lb/>
very patriotic American companies. We had nothing to &ldquo;trade&rdquo;, with the result that we<lb/>
became a war orphan, losing every worth-while customer we had. Our Home Office under-<lb/>
stood our situation but could do nothing about it, written evidence of the unfair com-<lb/>
petition being impossible to obtain. Such unfair practices were, of course, prohibited,<lb/>
but woe unto the customer who would certify under oath that they existed. Reprisals<lb/>
would be sure to follow. Our Home Office encouraged us to do our best under the circum-<lb/>
stances, with not a word of complaint or criticism.</p>
<p>Our utter helplessness would be galling to a man much less sensitive by nature than<lb/>
I am. Ruthlessness, sugar-coated or raw, has always been abhorrent to me. With the<lb/>
cost of living in Cuba doubled, I was given an unsolicited increase in salary which I<lb/>
promptly refused, not because I could not use it but because I did not deem it a fair<lb/>
burden on a business that was operating in the red. A sharp reprimand from the Home<lb/>
Office reminded me that it was a decision of the management and not open to argument,<lb/>
so I swallowed my pride, and with it my idealism and my sense of what was just and what<lb/>
was not. During an 18-year relationship with Sun Oil Company it was to be my first<lb/>
and last reprimand. During that period, by the way, I had not asked fornor received an<lb/>
increase in salary. In 1931, I voluntarily reduced my own salary when we were affected<lb/>
by a depression in Cuba. From that year on I could not change it without consent of<lb/>
the Home Office.</p>
<p>With the war now well over and having reached the biblical age of three-score-and-<lb/>
ten, I decided to retire from business life. With no understudy acceptable to the<lb/>
Management to succeed me, it was decided to dissolve and liquidate Compa&ntilde;ia Sunoco de<lb/>
Cuba, the representation to be handed to a distributor of my election. Magnanimous,<lb/>
as usual, the board of directors voted me a most liberal retirement allowance. Consider-<lb/>
ing that the Cuban subsidiary had been very much of a headache to the company, also a<lb/>
failure, I tried to frustrate it. The company had different views. It was a case of<lb/>
idealism against realism and the latter won out. I would certainly be an ingrate if I<lb/>
should fail to appreciate such generosity. Some corporations do have souls and I am<lb/>
convinced that Sun Oil Company is one of them, although I have not always thought so.</p>
<pb n="53" id="f06013053"/>
<p>-- 56 --</p>
<p>It happened in early <unclear>1943</unclear> while I was in Philadelphia on a business trip. I was<lb/>
asked to give a brief talk on my yellow fever experience on Lowell Thomas' radio pro-<lb/>
gram but it has had its repercussions to this day. With fear and trepidation I accept-<lb/>
ed the invitation, thinking of the shame which would be mine if I should get stage-<lb/>
fright or stumble before my invisible audience, many of whom would be members of the<lb/>
Sun Oil Company family, previously tipped off. I rehearsed my part for an hour with<lb/>
a shadow-writer until he was satisfied that I could be trusted to face the microphone.<lb/>
When the crucial moment had arrived, Lowell Thomas gave me my cue, he asking the<lb/>
questions and I reading from the script. I tried to be as imperturbable as that master<lb/>
commentator, a vain hope, but I was not altogether a failure, judging from the number<lb/>
of letters I received later, some of them addressed to the station but most of them<lb/>
addressed to me in Havana, with no street address, but simply &ldquo;John Moran or John J.<lb/>
Moran, Havana, Cuba&rdquo;. Al told, I received over 300 letters and I acknowledged receipt<lb/>
of those I felt to be disinterested. Several young men wrote me for employment in<lb/>
our company, thinking I was the head of a large force. I personally typed the replies<lb/>
but it required three months' spare time to finish the job.</p>
<p>One letter reached me in July, <unclear>1937</unclear>, from one who had not heard my short talk on<lb/>
the radio. It was from Dr. Philip S. Hench, of the Mayo Clinic, Rochester, Minn. and<lb/>
from which I quote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I understand that you recently gave a talk on the radio, and I hope<lb/>
that the address that I am using is correct. I would appreciate it very<lb/>
much indeed to be permitted to see a copy of your script. I should like<lb/>
so much to visit you sometime to hear your interesting side-lights and<lb/>
experiences with this work, and I regret that I did not know you were in<lb/>
Havana, as I was there just about three months ago. ...................<lb/>
I am interested in preparing a little article for our local staff meeting<lb/>
on the yellow fever work, and I am interested to know your whereabouts<lb/>
and present occupation.&rdquo;</p>
<p>That letter led me to know one of the noblest personalities that it has been my<lb/>
good fortune to have ever met, in his profession or outside of it. In my heart he<lb/>
occupies a place with that venerable figure, General Jefferson Randolph Kean, Carl B.<lb/>
Schmidt and my late lamented friend, John A. Lloyd, at the time of his death Director,<lb/>
Foreign Department of Sun Oil Company. It is mainly due to the dying wish of Johnny<lb/>
Lloyd that I have undertaked to write my &ldquo;memoirs&rdquo; of yellow fever days. Probably one<lb/>
of the last letters he was to write was mailed to me in Philadelphia in the afternoon<lb/>
of June 19th, apparently unaware that he was marked by the grim reaper. He succumbed<lb/>
to a heart attack the next day, June 20th, mourned by the entire Sun Oil Company<lb/>
family and a host of friends. The company lost one of its most devoted and loyal<lb/>
officers. His sudden passing left me stunned. He was my sincere friend.</p>
<p>That innocent-looking letter from Dr. Hench has led to investigation and research<lb/>
on his part that will eventually result in a History of Yellow Fever so complete and<lb/>
accurate that it will be monumental, for he has been marshalling data now over a period<lb/>
of eleven years, temporarily interrupted while he served as Colonel in the Medical<lb/>
Corps of the Army during World War II. I take great pride in the fact that I was in-<lb/>
directly instrumental in a small way to have him undertake a task for which he is<lb/>
eminently fitted. He hopes to have his book published in 1950, the 50th anniversary<lb/>
of Walter Reed's yellow fever experiments in Cuba. My dearest wish would be to live<lb/>
long enough to receive an autographed copy of the first edition of my friend's book.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench and I have corresponed regularly over the years. Through his question-<lb/>
ing of me, he knows more about me than I do myself. He has made many trips to Havana<lb/>
since 1940 when he first decided that he must see for himself the site of Walter Reed's<lb/>
expirements. In the Spring of that year I had the honor of meeting him and his charm-<lb/>
ing wife, Mary Kahler Hench. Their visit to Havana was to be a combination vacation,<lb/>
<pb n="54" id="f06013054"/>
-- 57 --<lb/>
with side excursions on his part to the site of Camp Lazear, where yellow fever had<lb/>
come to me in the form of a Christmas gift. When I took up residence in Cuba, in<lb/>
1928, and renewed acquaintance with Dr. Agramonte, I told him I would like to visit<lb/>
once more the site of Camp Lazear and he offered to take me out there &ldquo;one of these<lb/>
days&rdquo;, but due to a series of circumstances the offer failed of realization. In 1930,<lb/>
with the University of Havana closed, Dr. Agramonte joined the staff of Louisiana<lb/>
State University, as professor of tropical medicine, so I lost the opportunity.</p>
<p>Dr. Agramonte was probably the only man in Cuba at that time who could go<lb/>
direct to the site of Camp Lazear and point it out with certainty. When Doctor<lb/>
Hench arrived on the scene, what had once been an isolated farm had been converted<lb/>
into a sub-division for laborers' cottages, in part, with the rest of the land and<lb/>
its top-soil supplying a nearby brick-plant with earth suitable for that industry,<lb/>
and a limestone quarry then in operation. In the meantime, the Cuban Government<lb/>
was moved to memorialize Camp Lazear, but where was it located. An old doctor<lb/>
living in Marianao thought he had the answer, locating the site back of the<lb/>
Military Hospital, where the Post Hospital of American days had stood. It was a<lb/>
false site, of course, but no one in authority questioned the verdict of the old<lb/>
doctor. While medical men in authority knew I had returned to Cuba and was then<lb/>
living in their midst, none of them sought my advice. The false site was officially<lb/>
declared to be a National Monument and Lieutenant-Colonel Edgar E. Hume, of the<lb/>
Army Medical Corps, representing the Medical Corps of the Army, came on from Wash-<lb/>
ington at the invitation of the Cuban Government, to assist at its dedication. For<lb/>
that purpose, a temporary, sheet-zinc, signboard had been raised on the supposed<lb/>
site of Camp Lazear, one side of which bore a rough inscription of its historic<lb/>
significance. I was not invited to the ceremony of dedication, hence I did not<lb/>
intrude.</p>
<p>Future plans for a real memorial contemplated conversion of the false site into<lb/>
a small park, but nothing had been done to that end up to the time Dr. Hench arrived<lb/>
on the scene. It was then that we were shown for the first time the plot of ground<lb/>
on which Walter Reed was supposed to have carried out his series of experiments.<lb/>
Upon looking it over, Doctor Hench said to me &ldquo;Johnny, is the Military Hospital<lb/>
built on the site of the Post Hospital of your days?&rdquo; I replied in the affirmative.<lb/>
&ldquo;Then&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;this cannot be the site of Camp Lazear, If I am not mistaken,<lb/>
Walter Reed said it was a mile or more removed from the Post Hospital, while this<lb/>
is within fifty yards of it&rdquo;. We both agreed there and then that the selected site<lb/>
was a false one.</p>
<p>But where was the true site of the experimental camp? I certainly did not<lb/>
have the answer, but Dr. Hench did. I was totally lost and confused. I was depo-<lb/>
sited in Camp Lazear on November 20, 1900, paying little attention to distance or<lb/>
direction on my way there, remaining at the camp until December 25th, when I had a<lb/>
free ambulance ride to the yellow fever hospital, caring little about my surround-<lb/>
ings as I lay on a stretcher. I was not of much help to Doctor Hench and I was<lb/>
not a little ashamed of myself. But was that master-researcher discouraged? Not<lb/>
at all. I could vision how much of a vacation Doctor and Mrs. Hench were to have<lb/>
on that visit to Havana. He was in his element and enjoying himself wonderfully,<lb/>
while she was the most patient of little ladies, an ideal spouse for an inquisitive<lb/>
and determined medico to whom obstacles were only appetizers for conquering and<lb/>
reaching his goal. I marveled at his tenacity of purpose. Trails which meant<lb/>
nothing to me were highly important to him. They had their place in his final<lb/>
analysis. On many occasions he tripped me up on my own home grounds. Had he not<lb/>
chosen medicine, I am sure he would have been as great a lawyer as he is a doctor.<lb/>
And I want it understood that I am not using that word &ldquo;great&rdquo; lightly, for in his<lb/>
special field he is one of the most famous medicos in the U. S.</p>
<pb n="55" id="f06013055"/>
<p>--58----</p>
<p>By a stroke of good fortune we met the man who had sold the Cuban Government the<lb/>
plot of land which was designated as the site of Camp Lazear and declared a National<lb/>
Monument. He was selling building lots on that part of the sub-division which had not<lb/>
been set aside by the government. Dr. Hench read to him from an article written by Dr.<lb/>
Agramonte and published in the December, 1915, issue of The Scientific Monthly, in<lb/>
which he stated:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I was therefore favorably impressed with the seclusion offfered by<lb/>
a spot situated a short distance from the main road, in a farm named San<lb/>
Jos&eacute;, belonging to my friend Dr. Ignacio Rojas, of Havana. Major Reed<lb/>
decided upon this place after looking at many others in the neighborhood.&rdquo;<lb/>
Our new friend, Mr. Luis Pogolotti, informed us that the site we were looking at was<lb/>
never owned by Dr. Rojas, since the deeds he had in his possession made no mention of<lb/>
him as a former owner. He knew the Rojas family and the San Jos&eacute; farm, his brother<lb/>
having purchased a section of the farm around 1907. The family had disposed of the<lb/>
farm with exception of two or three blocks surrounding the farm house which they con-<lb/>
tinued to use as a summer residence and known as the &ldquo;Quinta San Jos&eacute;&rdquo;. He gave Dr.<lb/>
Hench the city address of Dr. Rojas' widow and he lost no time in calling on the old<lb/>
lady and her daughter, being informed that they would be glad to assist him in his<lb/>
mission.</p>
<p>Mrs. Rojas, of course, remembered all about the experimental camp, stating that<lb/>
she could see the tents in the distance from the balcony of her bedroom on the second<lb/>
floor of the farm house. She thought she could point out the site to us, although she<lb/>
had not visited that part of the farm in many years. By this time Dr. Hench felt that<lb/>
he was treading on solid ground and his enthusiasm was contagious. Mrs. Rojas led us<lb/>
to the spot where she thought Camp Lazear had existed but she could tell us nothing as<lb/>
to the fate of the two small frame houses which were known to have been left standing<lb/>
when the camp was abandoned in 1901. Dr. Hench had employed a photographer for several<lb/>
days running, taking views which might <unclear>dovetail</unclear> with those taken of the camp after it<lb/>
was set up, but to no purpose. We aroused the curiosity of the natives to such an<lb/>
extent that one of them was bold enough to inquire the nature of our business. His<lb/>
name was Zunzunegui. He was the owner of a limestone quarry and lime-kiln which his<lb/>
father had leased in 1907 from Dr. Rojas. Included in the lease was the use of two<lb/>
small wooden buildings. His three children had been born in one of them and it was<lb/>
still standing. The other was blown over in the 1926 cyclone and was converted into<lb/>
kindling wood.</p>
<p>Mr. <unclear>Zunzunegui</unclear> led us to what was at one time &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; for infected<lb/>
bedding and clothing. We had passed by it several times, not once suspecting that<lb/>
it was what we were looking for. A lean-to kitchen had been built against it and a<lb/>
small room had been added to one end of it. A partition had been built across the<lb/>
original 20' x 14', one-room structure. Once inside, however, any doubts we might<lb/>
have had as to its identity were soon dissipated. There was the stove-pipe hole in<lb/>
the ceiling of one corner, the nature of the ceiling itself, the tongued-and-grooved<lb/>
boards, the double wall. What was left of it could have well been tagged: &ldquo;Built in<lb/>
U. S. A.&rdquo;. A charcoal vendor and his family occupied the &ldquo;shack&rdquo;, for that is what<lb/>
it had degenerated into.</p>
<p>Now armed with indisputable proof, we visited Dr. Domingo Ramos, prominent in<lb/>
public health spheres but then Secretary of Defense in the Batista administration.<lb/>
That very elusive gentleman had so many and such varied duties that he could never be<lb/>
depended on to keep an appointment, since he invariably accompanied the President on<lb/>
his excursions. Finally Dr. Hench succeeded in seeing him for a fleeting five minutes<lb/>
during which he indicated that absolute proofs would be necessary before the &ldquo;false<lb/>
site&rdquo; could be discarded, especially since the old doctor who had pointed it out as<lb/>
the &ldquo;true site&rdquo; insisted that we were interlopers. Any man less determined than Dr.<lb/>
Hench would have given up in disgust, since it was patent that the authorities liked<lb/>
the false site much better than the real one. It was close to the Military Hospital<lb/>
<pb n="56" id="f06013056"/>
-- 59 --<lb/>
while the other was a mile or more distant and in squalid surroundings. With commend-<lb/>
able patience Dr. Hench assembled the necessary proofs in the form of photographs and<lb/>
photostatic copies, including entries made by Dr. Rojas in his Day Book &amp; Journal, the<lb/>
whole arranged in a neatly-bound volume which he delivered to Dr. Ramos and which was<lb/>
ceremoniously deposited in the Finlay Institute. With that done the true site of Camp<lb/>
Lazear was officially acknowledged, but Dr. Hench was far from through. His fight for<lb/>
a memorial to be built on the site of the experimental camp has gone merrily on to<lb/>
this day, with an unshaken faith on his part.</p>
<p>Finally Dr. Hench's enthusiasm was stimulated when, in 1947, &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo;<lb/>
was officially declared a National Monument. In April, <unclear>1948</unclear>, an appropriation of<lb/>
$50,000.00 was made for a memorial to include its restoration and to create a park<lb/>
around it, but so far nothing has been done to protect the shell of the original build-<lb/>
ing and the few timbers and boards which have withstood the ravages of time, the<lb/>
elements and dry-rot. The tentative plans contemplate duplication of &ldquo;Building No. 2&rdquo;<lb/>
(the mosquito building) where it originally stood. From 1940 on, Dr. Hench attended<lb/>
to repairs to &ldquo;Building No. 1&rdquo; but after it was declared a national monument repairs<lb/>
could be made only by the Cuban authorities. It is not at all certain that the<lb/>
appropriation made by the Cuban government last April has been situated and made<lb/>
available by the Minister of Finance, hence execution of the projected memorial may<lb/>
depend on the new administration which took over on October 10, 1948, headed by Dr.<lb/>
Carlos Prio Socarras, the new Cuban President. In the meantime Dr. Hench remains<lb/>
optimistic. I trust he will not be disappointed.</p>
<p>And now comes the most painful part of my self-imposed task. That part, bitter<lb/>
as it may taste to many of the present generation of Cuban doctors, is one which I<lb/>
cannot shirk. Without it those recollections of mine would not be worth recording.<lb/>
Since I am one of the few living witnesses and actors of the drama which was enacted<lb/>
at Camp Lazear between November 20, 1900 and February 15, 1901, I claim the right to<lb/>
an opinion on the respective parts played by Finlay and Reed in what has generally been<lb/>
referred to as &ldquo;The Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. The fact that my relations with Reed<lb/>
were more or less intimate, while I had seen Finlay only twice, does not mean that my<lb/>
opinion will not be impartial. I have been thoroughly in accord with the Cubans in<lb/>
their glorification of Finlay but I am certainly not in accord with them when, in<lb/>
glorifying that fine old gentleman, they vilify Reed and his memory. Surely the man<lb/>
who helped free the Island of Cuba from a centuries-old scourge deserves the ever-<lb/>
lasting gratitude of the Cuban people. That gratitude was his in a generous measure<lb/>
immediately following the experiments at Camp Lazear. But less than two years had<lb/>
expired when personal ambitions for notoriety, professional jealousy and exaggerated<lb/>
nationalism were brought into play with the avowed purpose of dimming his work.</p>
<p><unclear>Vernon A</unclear><lb/>
P.S.H.</p>
<p>It is entirely true that the American people in their enthusiastic applause of<lb/>
Walter Reed and his conclusive experiments had for the moment failed to link Finlay<lb/>
with his accomplishments, but so had the rest of the world. The fact that Dr. Finlay<lb/>
had identified the right species of mosquito as the yellow fever carrier was in itself<lb/>
a notable achievement and without which Major Reed's experiments might never have taken<lb/>
place. By that same token, Dr. Finlay's theory might have continued to be &ldquo;a voice in<lb/>
the wilderness&rdquo; for the rest of his natural life, had it not been for the advent of<lb/>
Walter Reed. Wishful thinking and commodious generalities cannot change those simple<lb/>
truths into fancy or fiction.</p>
<p>Now let us get to the root and origin of the Cubans' negation of Reed and their<lb/>
all-out or unilateral claims for Finlay. It germinated in and incubated in the mind<lb/>
of one man with a very definite purpose, which was not exactly to exalt Finlay at the<lb/>
expense of Reed but to satisfy his own personal ambitions for honors which, as a doctor,<lb/>
he could never have obtained in the field of medical science. To that end, he set<lb/>
himself up as the defender of Finlay and the detractor of Reed. It suited his purpose<lb/>
to play on nationalism as his best weapon so that, gradually, he came to actually hate<lb/>
<pb n="57" id="f06013057"/>
-- 60 --<lb/>
Walter Reed and all his works, with a hatred which he delighted to proclaim by word<lb/>
and pen until the day of his death. So potent was his influence at one time that<lb/>
those of his countrymen who would do justice to Reed did not dare combat his unilateral<lb/>
claims for Finlay, with one exception which I will mention later. With passage of the<lb/>
years his tirades against Reed and his memory increased in bitterness.</p>
<p>In the field of medicine he pertained to the French school of thought and practice,<lb/>
a minority in his day as it is now, since the majority of Cuban doctors follow the<lb/>
newer or American school. There again he deftly played the game of nationalism. He<lb/>
had married a <hi>French</hi> lady and Dr. Finlays mother was a Frenchwoman. Being more of a<lb/>
politician than a doctor, when the party to which he pertained came into power he was<lb/>
given a diplomatic post in Paris, where he remained for several years. He craved honors<lb/>
at the hands of the French, so the approaching centenary of Finlay's birth was his<lb/>
golden opportunity to proclaim to the world that Reed was an imposter. He then wrote<lb/>
his euology of Finlay and his travesty on Reed in a book titled &ldquo;CARLOS J. FINLAY - SON<lb/>
CENTENAIRE&rdquo;. It is assumed that French scientists did not realize that they were being<lb/>
victimized. Up to that time they had considered Finlay and Reed as collaborators. But<lb/>
surely it could not be doubted since the author was a man of diplomatic status and a<lb/>
graduate in medicine. No American in Paris at the time raised his voice in defense of<lb/>
Reed. With characteristic complacency they remained silent, secure in the knowledge<lb/>
that Reed's immortality was safe in the hearts of his countrymen.</p>
<p><del><unclear>I told<lb/>
nto</unclear></del></p>
<p>Now Reed's detractor could vision the French honors which he had so devoutly<lb/>
craved. His dreams were soon to become a reality for <del><unclear>soon</unclear></del> he was accorded their<lb/>
highest honors. In the meantime he saw to it that the torch of hatred against Reed<lb/>
should not be quenched in Cuba. His handful of diehards were urged to continue the<lb/>
campaign of defamation which he had so deftly fathered. It is almost inconceivable<lb/>
that one man could swerve or stultify the convictions of even a small group of prof-<lb/>
essional men to such an extent as to create a fear of ostracism in them if they should<lb/>
venture to do justice to Reed. Sad to state that it was all too true. Two Cuban<lb/>
doctors informed me that their professional status would be placed in jeopardy if<lb/>
they should champion the cause of Reed. Both knew Finlay and Reed well and had followed<lb/>
closely the latter's work at Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>Back in 1939, when the film &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo; was being exhibited in Cuba for the first<lb/>
time, I was invited by the Rotary Club of the city of Havana to a session at which the<lb/>
yellow fever episode and Finlay were to be discussed. Also an invited guest was Reed's<lb/>
detractor, that being the first time I had seen him. Only a few days before I had<lb/>
received a letter from General Kean wherein he favored me with his recollections of a<lb/>
banquet given in honor of Finlay on December 22, 1900, to which General Wood, Major<lb/>
Reed and himself were invited. The speaker of the evening was Dr. Juan Guiteras, the<lb/>
noted yellow fever expert. General Kean went on to state that Dr. Guiteras proclaimed<lb/>
the experiments at Camp Lazear as a joint Finlay-Reed achievement, with an equal<lb/>
division of the glory between the two. At my request, the secretary of the Rotary<lb/>
Club made a running translation of General Kean's letter for the benefit of those not<lb/>
familiar with the English language. No sooner had he finished than Reed's detractor<lb/>
demanded the floor, denying Reed any part in the conquest of yellow fever. To link<lb/>
Reed's name with Finlay was sacrilege, he said, completely ignoring General Kean's<lb/>
statements. Reed and his Army Board, he said, merely confirmed what Finlay had already<lb/>
proved.</p>
<p>Some years later, when Dr. Hench happened to be at the Finlay Institute, he learned<lb/>
that Reed's detractor was in the building and he expressed a desire to meet him, so we<lb/>
were presented to him. He knew, of course, that I was one of Walter Reed's experiment-<lb/>
al subjects and he had not forgotten the letter I had caused to be read at the Rotary<lb/>
Club session. Instinctively, I knew he did not like me and when we mentioned the name<lb/>
of Reed I noticed that same look of resentment which he displayed at the Rotary Club<lb/>
meeting. He referred to the experiments at Camp Lazear as &ldquo;the Finlay experiments&rdquo; but<lb/>
he abstained from launching into his customary diatribes against his memory.</p>
<pb n="58" id="f06013058"/>
<p>-- 61 --</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the venemous attacks of Reed's detractor were not confined to<lb/>
Cuba and France. His small corps of disciples had been spreading his gospel to many<lb/>
other Latin American countries, to the point of saturation. While his followers in<lb/>
Cuba were few, like communists they were excellent propagandists and able to silence<lb/>
the majority through the use of communistic tactics, with nationalism as a cloak.<lb/>
Those who were willing to do Reed justice bowed to the will of a minority, thus follow-<lb/>
ing the course of least resistance. One of them, however, did not bow to the opinion<lb/>
of Reed's defamers. He was Dr. Aristides Agramonte, the Cuban member of the four-man<lb/>
Army Board of Medical Officers headed by Major Reed. In the December, 1915, issue of<lb/>
&ldquo;THE SCIENTIFIC MONTHLY&rdquo; he wrote an article titled &ldquo;The Inside History of a Great<lb/>
Medical Discovery&rdquo;, from which I quote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In 1881, Dr. Carlos Finlay, of Havana, in an exhaustive paper read<lb/>
before the Royal Academy of Sciences, gave as his opinion that yellow<lb/>
fever was spread by the bites of mosquitoes &lsquo;directly contaminated by<lb/>
stinging a yellow fever patient (or perhaps by contact with or feeding<lb/>
from his discharge)&rsquo;. This latter view he held as late as 1900, which,<lb/>
although correct in the main fact of the transmission of the germ from<lb/>
a patient to a susceptible person by the mosquito, the MODUS OPERANDI,<lb/>
as he conceived it, was entirely erroneous.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay, unfortunately was unable to produce experimentally a<lb/>
single case of fever that could withstand the mildest criticism, so<lb/>
that at the time when the Army Board came to investigate the causes of<lb/>
yellow fever in Cuba, his theory, though practically the correct one,<lb/>
had been so much discredited, in a great measure by his own failures,<lb/>
that the best-known experts considered it as an ingenious, but wholly<lb/>
fanciful, one and many thought it a fit subject for humorous and sar-<lb/>
castic repartee. Finlay also believed, erroneously, that repeated<lb/>
bites of contaminated insects might protect against yellow fever and<lb/>
that the mosquitoes were capable of transmitting the germ to the next<lb/>
generation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Following publication of that article Dr. Agramonte became a target for the viru-<lb/>
lent attacks of Reed's master-detractor and his handful of diehards. They branded him<lb/>
as a traitor to Finlay and to Cuba. At that time Dr. Agramonte was professor of<lb/>
bacteriology and experimental pathology in the University of Havana. Walter Reed's<lb/>
detractor and his aides continued to hound him in every possible manner, subtly en-<lb/>
deavoring to discredit him with his own students, who upon graduation would be expect-<lb/>
ed to join the anti-Reed clique. Outright ostracism was planned but did not prosper,<lb/>
cooler heads visioning an international scandal in any such measure, but the campaign<lb/>
of persecution to which he was subjected interfered with his peace of mind. When the<lb/>
University of Havana was closed by Machado, in 1930, it was a relief to him to go into<lb/>
exile, hence he accepted appointment to the chair of tropical medicine in the Louisiana<lb/>
State University, where he died on August 18, 1931, at the age of 63. His name, with<lb/>
those of Walter Reed, Jesse W. Lazear and James Carroll, is appropriately inscribed on<lb/>
the ROLL OF HONOR of the War Department, in Washington, and will be published in per-<lb/>
petuity in the Official Army Register, a fitting tribute to a Cuban who would not<lb/>
allow nationalism to obscure his sense of scientific justice. His memory should be<lb/>
cherished by Cubans and Americans alike.</p>
<p>How well the campaign of defamation against Reed is still bearing fruit was demon-<lb/>
strated in connection with the FOURTH INTERNATIONAL CONGRESSES OF TROPICAL MEDICINE<lb/>
AND MALARIA, at their meetings in Washington, D. C., in May, 1948, during which<lb/>
<pb n="59" id="f06013059"/>
-- 62 --<lb/>
a Reed Commemoration Meeting was held on May 12th, to be followed on May 20th by the<lb/>
unveiling of a Bust and Tablet for Walter Reed in the Hall of Fame of New York<lb/>
University, where a niche had been reserved for him many years ago. Both ceremonies<lb/>
drew protests from the Cuban medical bodies, registered through the Cuban delegates<lb/>
attending the Congresses, vigorously resenting the honors to be accorded to the<lb/>
memory of Reed and the title of the program which read as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Exercises to Commemorate the Demonstration by<lb/>
Walter Reed<lb/>
of the Mosquito Transmission of Yellow Fever&rdquo;.</p>
<p>To avert an Inter-American incident a compromise was reached, the Cubans agreeing<lb/>
to accept Reed as Finlay's collaborator. With this concession on the part of the<lb/>
Cubans it would appear that the 48-year-old controversy was amicably settled. Far from<lb/>
it. Walter Reed's defamers would accept no such verdict. Eleven days later there was<lb/>
published in &ldquo;BOHEMIA&rdquo;, a Cuban weekly news-magazine of wide circulation, a virulent<lb/>
article, authored by a Cuban doctor, under the following title:</p>
<p>&ldquo;NI &lsquo;TEORIA&rsquo; FUE LA OBRA DE FINLAY,<lb/>
NI REED SU COLABORADOR&rdquo;<lb/>
(Finlay's Work was not a Theory, nor was Reed his Collaborator)<lb/>
The author immediately proceeds to strip Walter Reed of any part worth mentioning in<lb/>
the yellow fever drama, charging him with BAD FAITH in his &ldquo;Preliminary Note&rdquo;, read<lb/>
before the American Public Health Association, in Indianapolis, in October, 1900. He<lb/>
refers to Reed's experiments at Camp Lazear as &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; and entirely unnecessary,<lb/>
flatly stating that the cases of Lazear, Carroll and Dean &ldquo;confirmed&rdquo; what Finlay had<lb/>
already &ldquo;proved&rdquo;. With all due respect to the author, the skeptics who out numbered the<lb/>
believers 1,000 to 1 were not convinced by those three cases, for the very good reason<lb/>
that the circumstances under which they were bitten by infected yellow fever mosquitoes<lb/>
were not conclusive from a scientific point of view.</p>
<p>I am a living witness to the fact that there was nothing theatrical about the<lb/>
series of experiments carried out by Walter Reed at Camp Lazear. Major Reed was not<lb/>
the manner of man to risk human lives for &ldquo;staged&rdquo; fame or personal prestige. The<lb/>
author denies Reed the right to be classed as a scientist because, as he puts it, he<lb/>
lacked a scientific background. Reed, he says, was a salaried medical officer and was<lb/>
obliged to obey orders of his superiors, therefore he could not feel the emotions of<lb/>
the real scientist. He strongly infers that Reed was a mere automat and only carried<lb/>
out the experiments at the instance of General Wood, Military Governor of Cuba. That<lb/>
is not true. He consulted with General Wood as he did with General Kean and others of<lb/>
his own corps, but he was responsible only to General George M. Sternberg, Surgeon<lb/>
General of the Army, whose instructions to him were broad and entirely discretionary.<lb/>
General Wood merely supplied the funds necessary for carrying out the experiments.</p>
<p>In conclusion, I want to make my own position clear. I accord equal honors to<lb/>
Carlos J. Finlay and Walter Reed. Their work in life has earned them a place among<lb/>
the immortals in the field of medical science. Americans, I am sure, will continue<lb/>
to honor the memories of both. All they expect of the Cubans is to refrain from<lb/>
defaming Reed when they honor and glorify Finlay. The comparative sizes of Cuba and<lb/>
the United States of America do not figure in this matter. If Walter Reed had been<lb/>
born in Cuba and Carlos J. Finlay in the United States their individual or joint<lb/>
achievements would remain the same, since those who have contributed to the progress<lb/>
of medical science belong to no country in particular but to the entire world. For<lb/>
that reason, whether the Cubans like it or not, history will link the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever as a FINLAY-REED accomplishment.</p>
<pb n="60" id="f06013060"/>
<p><hi>MEDALS &amp; CITATIONS</hi>.</p>
<p>p 63</p>
<p>
February 26, 1916. Awarded Diploma and Medal of the &ldquo;ORDEN DEL LIBERTADOR&rdquo;, Fourth<lb/>
Class, by the Government of Venezuela, generally known in that<lb/>
country as &ldquo;EL BUSTO DE BOLIVAR&rdquo; and/or &ldquo;EL BUSTO DEL LIBERTADOR&rdquo;.<lb/>
First country to honor me with its Condecoration.</p>
<p>February 28, 1929. Special Congressional Medal of Honor, known as &ldquo;THE WALTER REED<lb/>
MEDAL&rdquo; awarded to the four members of the U. S. Army Board of<lb/>
Medical Officers and the eighteen volunteers for yellow fever<lb/>
experiments carried out at Camp Lazear, Cuba, in 1900-1901.</p>
<p>May 12, 1940. &ldquo;THE CARLOS J. FINLAY MEDAL&rdquo; in the Grade of &ldquo;Gran Oficial&rdquo; or<lb/>
&ldquo;Grand Officer&rdquo;. Awarded by the Cuban Government and presented<lb/>
to me at the Cuban Embassy in Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>October 26, 1940. CITATION as &ldquo;A HERO AND BENEFACTOR OF HUMANITY&rdquo; by Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson College, Washington, Pa. Elected an Honorary<lb/>
Alumnus of the College at the same time.</p>
<p>August 20, 1948. Medal of &ldquo;HONOR AL MERITO&rdquo; (Honoring Merit), known as the &ldquo;ESSO&rdquo;<lb/>
Medal. Awarded and presented by the Standard Oil Company of<lb/>
Cuba, at Radio Center, Havana, Cuba, at a special ceremony.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
