<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06107001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: Colonel Alexander N. Stark, by J.M. Phalen, October 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06107001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-10-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Phalen, J. M.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ireland. M. W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-10-00">October 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06107001</idno>
<title>Article: Colonel Alexander N. Stark, by J.M. Phalen, October 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This article, which appeared in the "Military Surgeon," is a biographical sketch of Stark. Truby, a friend of Stark, adds his own evaluation to illustrate his talents and character.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-10-00">
<head>Article: Colonel Alexander N. Stark, by J.M. Phalen, October 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06107001"/>
<opener>
<hi>COLONEL ALEXANDER N. STARK</hi><lb/>
Comments by <hi>Gen Truby</hi><lb/>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f06107002"/>
<p><hi>COLONEL ALEXANDER N. STARK</hi></p>
<p>The article by Col. J. M. Phalen about Col. Stark in<lb/>
the Military Surgeon for October, 1941 is a splendid one and I<lb/>
approve of all that Phalen said.</p>
<p>I can add very little to that except to bring out some<lb/>
little pecularities as well as <del>to</del> the sterling qualities which<lb/>
were so characteristic of Stark.</p>
<p>He and I became great friends and during all of our<lb/>
associations never had any trouble of any kind. For some reason<lb/>
or other, my early experiences as an assistant in surgery, where<lb/>
I had had considerable practical training, appealed to him.</p>
<p>Stark was liked by nearly everyone. He was friendly,<lb/>
full of humor, always willing to help others, thoroughly loyal<lb/>
and true to all of his friends, and a hard worker.</p>
<p>He was very brilliant as a student, had a fine memory<lb/>
and therefore was exceptionally well up on the theoretical part<lb/>
of medicine and surgery. His early education did not include a<lb/>
college course and his medical course was probably only two or<lb/>
three years at the University of Virginia. Clinics and practical<lb/>
work there could not have been extensive in such a small city.<lb/>
He took a short Post Graduate course in Medicine in New York;<lb/>
and no internship that I know of, so his practical experience in<lb/>
surgery was very limited when he entered the Corps in the spring<lb/>
of 1893. His service in Texas, likewise, did not give him much<lb/>
opportunity to do surgical work, which was what he wanted most.<lb/>
It was not until he came to Columbia Barracks late in 1899 that<lb/>
he found himself in a position to actually do surgical work on a<lb/>
rapidly increasing scale. During all these years, he had kept up<lb/>
his reading of anatomy and surgery and was well prepared from a<lb/>
theoretical standpoint.</p>
<p>When he came to Columbia Barracks late in 1899, he and<lb/>
I promptly formed a harmonious team with a sincere desire to<lb/>
cooperate in perfecting ourselves in surgery. Emergency surgery<lb/>
we had to do as there was no one else present better qualified.<lb/>
Stark in his work was at times apt to be too radical, while I<lb/>
was too conservative as the result of training under a very<lb/>
careful and great surgeon. We both realized our short comings<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06107003"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
and therefore Stark would frequently say, &ldquo;What would you do,<lb/>
Truby?&rdquo; or some similar statement. He also welcomed any of my<lb/>
suggestions and in that way we became a good team. Before any<lb/>
unusual operation, Stark would always read up the details in our<lb/>
surgical books and tell me to do the same.</p>
<p>The surgical service grew rapidly becamse of Stark's<lb/>
enthusiasm. He hunted for cases in all fields including<lb/>
gynecology and found them. Everybody liked Stark and his<lb/>
ability as a surgeon soon was known by everybody in the Post.<lb/>
His results were good and he was undoubtedly the best operating<lb/>
surgeon then in Cuba.</p>
<p>I left him in November, 1900 and did not see him again<lb/>
until I joined him at West Point. He was doing much important<lb/>
surgery there and promptly asked for me as his assistant. We<lb/>
had a great service there and the people of the Post were most<lb/>
enthusiastic about Stark and his work. His results were fine.<lb/>
In about a year I was promoted to Captain and was ordered to<lb/>
Alcatraz Island, California, as Surgeon. The Surgeon General's<lb/>
Office did not approve of having two Captains at West Point.<lb/>
Stark and Col. Havard both requested that I be left there but<lb/>
it was disapproved.</p>
<p>I did not see Stark again until 1908 at American Lake,<lb/>
Washington, where manoeuvres were being held. Stark was then<lb/>
a Major and on duty there as Camp Sanitary Inspector. I was a<lb/>
Captain and in command of the Field Hospital. When I and my<lb/>
outfit arrived, Stark was waiting on our camp site to welcome<lb/>
me, and with him was an officer with instructions as to the<lb/>
location of the Field Hospital camp.</p>
<p>I then indicated to the First Sergeant the point where<lb/>
our flagpole would be located. Then Stark and I sat on boxes<lb/>
and watched these specially trained men pitch the tents. The<lb/>
flagpole was the guiding point which determined all other points<lb/>
needed in the systematic arrangement of our camp hospital.<lb/>
The speed and precision of the work greatly impressed Stark<lb/>
and so he told me. (I am sending you <del>under separate cover</del> a<lb/>
<hi>report of that camp with remarks by Stark on my work.)</hi> Please return.</p>
<p>After 1908, I never saw Stark again. When he had his<lb/>
final illness at Hollywood, Calif., he telegraphed me at the<lb/>
Letterman Hospital where I was then in command stating that he<lb/>
wanted to be admitted for treatment. I sent an immediate reply<lb/>
urging him to come but he passed away before he could be moved.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06107004"/>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>I have written this frank story to help you get my<lb/>
view of some of the things Stark did - like the Ames letter.<lb/>
I hope that it will help you to understand things you want to<lb/>
know about him. I do want you to consider the unpleasant<lb/>
details as <unclear><hi>confidential.</hi></unclear> The good things, like the negro<lb/>
story, you can use if you desire.</p>
<p>Stark was one of the best and most loyal friends I<lb/>
have ever had. He had a much higher regard for me than I<lb/>
deserved. Probably because the two of us were such opposites.</p>
<p>He became a very excellent surgeon, one of the best the Army has<lb/>
produced.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
