<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, September 15, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Wood, Laura</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Early, Jubal</name>
<name type="person">Hunter, David</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Slocum, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="place">Liberty (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Bedford (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Sidney (Neb.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-15">September 15, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115024</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, September 15, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Wood is delighted with the material Hench has sent her for her book on Reed. She comments on the differences between the stories of Kissinger and Moran. She is trying to piece together Reed's early career. She is grateful for his offer to review her manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-15">
<head>Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, September 15, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115024"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
1338 19th St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1941-09-15">September 15, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am, as you can well imagine, simply delighted with the ma-<lb/>
terial you have sent me, and am also very conscious of your<lb/>
generosity in making available to me the results of so much<lb/>
of your own work, which I shall, of course, use in accordance<lb/>
with your requests. I am ashamed not to have answered your<lb/>
letters more promptly, but between being very busy and slight-<lb/>
ly ill, I couldn't quite make it before today. My present<lb/>
intentions are to make a final spurt to clear up what research<lb/>
remains, and then scurry up to Cape Cod the beginning of the<lb/>
month and go into <unclear>seclusion</unclear> for a bit at the place of some<lb/>
friends - whom you, incidentally, may know or know of: Dr.<lb/>
Sidney Schwab of St. Louis. I always expect, foolishly, that drs know each other.</p>
<p>Have your seen General Truby's memoir yet? It is most inter-<lb/>
esting, particularly in its account of Reed's actions, remarks,<lb/>
etc. and for the description of the officer's living quarters<lb/>
at the hospital and the army map showing the location of all<lb/>
the hospital buildings.</p>
<p>Mr. Moran, with whom I have had some correspondence, had told<lb/>
me that the I salute you story was legend, which I was rather<lb/>
glad to hear because I don't like it - it seems to me to have<lb/>
a touch of <del><unclear></unclear></del> pomposity and theatre about it quite<lb/>
uncharacteristic of Reed, who was, I gather, a charming and<lb/>
graceful man not given to fancy gestures. I am still, however,<lb/>
trying to find the precise circumstances of Moran's and Kissin-<lb/>
ger's volunteering. General Kean tells me that Mr. Kissinger<lb/>
is too ill to write letters, so I haven't attempted to commun-<lb/>
icate with him. Mr. Moran tells me that his and Mr. Kissinger's<lb/>
recollection of their volunteering are radically at variance,<lb/>
and that since the story is already current, he is willing to<lb/>
let it stand, on the theory that it doesn't make much difference.<lb/>
According to Truby's memoir K was first, thereby greatly cheer-<lb/>
ing Reed, who was feeling dubious about the Spaniards, and Moran<lb/>
immediately after. Mr. Moran, however, thinks he was first. He<lb/>
sent me a very interesting memorandum which I shall send to you<lb/>
for your files when I have finished, if you would like to have it.</p>
<p>I am trying to <del><unclear></unclear></del> determine precisely Reed's various residen-<lb/>
ces during his childhood through the records of the Virginia<lb/>
Methodist Conference. It's not particularly important, of course,<lb/>
where he lived when as a little boy, but rather interesting and<lb/>
completes the record. So far as I can judge now he must have<lb/>
lived at Liberty (now Bedford) near Lynchburg, in June 1864, when<lb/>
the bitterly hated General Hunter - who was himself a Virginian<lb/>
and who showed the most extraordinary venom and fury in his dep-<lb/>
radations through the Vally - was chased through there by Jubal<lb/>
Early with a considerably inferior force. The episode of the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115025"/>
stolen horses the following spring took place in Brunswick<lb/>
County which must have been uncomfortably close to the theatre<lb/>
of operations - i.e. the siege of Petersburg. Also I think I've<lb/>
turned up another unimportant but mildly interesting episode<lb/>
which took place <del><unclear></unclear></del> when he was staioned in Nebraska across the<lb/>
border from Cheyenne: a book, so I am told, about an extra-<lb/>
ordinary old ruffian, Old Jules, who was a homesteader in<lb/>
Wyoming, mentions that he was injured and taken to the nearby<lb/>
Army post, Camp <del><unclear>Sindey</unclear></del> Sidney, where he was treated by Dr. Reed.<lb/>
I haven't checked this yet, but hope<del><unclear></unclear></del> it's true - it makes a<lb/>
good story and is the kind of thing I need.</p>
<p>Carroll's letters were interesting, I thought, for certain spe-<lb/>
cific details of their movements - for instance, I had wondered<lb/>
who was with Reed when he and others watched Moran get bitten<lb/>
by in the infected mosquito building. Poor fellow, he seems to<lb/>
have felt inferior and touchy, to judge from his satisfaction<lb/>
that Slocum addressed him as &ldquo;Carroll.&rdquo; Also, Agramonte's<lb/>
account of the experiments and episodes connected with them <del>are</del><lb/>
is very good.</p>
<p>I'll see what I can do about getting to look at Mrs. Reed's ms<lb/>
again - I think I am suffering fully as much from her illness as<lb/>
she, by now. (I hope that doesn't sound callous - I'm actually<lb/>
much <add><unclear>more</unclear></add> sorry for her illness than <del><unclear></unclear></del> bothered about my incon-<lb/>
venience.) As a matter of fact, I'm a little relieved, too,<lb/>
that you didn't send me your copy, because if I saw it, it would<lb/>
be hard not to draw on it, and I'd feel uneasy about not having<lb/>
her permission,- all this aside from the complete folly of jeo-<lb/>
pardizing your relations with the Reeds, which are so much more<lb/>
important. I'll ask my <unclear>published</unclear> if they'd be interested in<lb/>
her ms, just in case.</p>
<p>Your offer to go over my ms when it is complete pleases me very<lb/>
much indeed, and I shall regard it as a great additional kind-<lb/>
ness if you will. The idea had already crossed my mind, but I<lb/>
have already imposed on you so much that I would not have sug-<lb/>
gested it for that reason. I simply can't tell you how keenly<lb/>
I appreciate your very generous cooperation in all of this.<lb/>
I'll take the utmost care of your material and not keep it un-<lb/>
duely long.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially,</salute>
<signed>Laura Wood</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
