<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, August 25, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Lawrence] Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Donnally, H. H.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-25">August 25, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115014</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, August 25, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench has selected the items which he thinks will help Wood to write her  book on Reed. He offers to read her manuscript when she has finished writing.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-25">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, August 25, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115014"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-25">August 25, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have spent the weekend going over my rather voluminous data on the<lb/>
yellow fever experiments and have selected what I think will be helpful to<lb/>
you. I am sending some of it either by separate post or by express. I enclose<lb/>
a list of the material being sent and also a list of letters, photographs and<lb/>
papers which I have but which seem to me either relatively useless for your<lb/>
purposes or which you can readily obtain on loan either from the Library of<lb/>
Congress or from the Surgeon-General's Library. Let me comment about the various<lb/>
items.</p>
<p>The letters of Dr. Lazear to Mrs. Lazear were loaned me by Mrs. Lazear<lb/>
who permitted me to take photostatic copies. There are only three of them but<lb/>
they are very revealing as they show that in the early stages of the work Lazear<lb/>
had more faith in the mosquito work than any of his colleagues, a fact later<lb/>
attested to in letters by Agramonte (see my W. and J. and my Cleveland talks)<lb/>
and by Carroll (in his letters of June 23, 1906 to Kelly and of Sept. 26, 1906<lb/>
to Latimer). I am sure Mrs. Lazear will not mind your having them as she gave me<lb/>
permission to use them any way I wished. They have never been published except<lb/>
in my own two papers and if you prefer to put onto me the responsibility for your<lb/>
using them you can merely do so by citing my papers as reference. Incidentally,<lb/>
my Cleveland talk will be published in the October Hygeia. These are the only<lb/>
letters Mrs. Lazear ever got from Dr. Lazear mentioning his work. If you care<lb/>
to, you might drop Mrs. Lazear a note asking permission directly to use the letters.<lb/>
That may please her and give you an interesting contact. Her address is 116 East<lb/>
Padre Street, Santa Barbara, California.</p>
<p>I am sure that Gen. Kean will have no objections to your using the three<lb/>
letters he recently gave me--the one from Reed to Sternberg and the two from Reed<lb/>
to himself (Kean). I have frankly &ldquo;censored&rdquo; both, not passing on to you certain<lb/>
personal data critical of persons some of whom are still living. That data would<lb/>
be of no earthly use to you in writing a book for children. I think the letter<lb/>
of Sept. 25, 1900 from Reed to Kean shows Reed's kind spirit admirably and also is<lb/>
a reflection of the wonderful personality of Lazear. May I suggest that, here<lb/>
again, to keep everything in order, you phone Gen. Kean and get his direct per-<lb/>
mission should you desire to quote the letters (I will send him a copy of this<lb/>
letter).</p>
<p>I am on less safe ground when I lend you part of Miss Blossom Reed's manu-<lb/>
script, that part which contains Reed's letters to his family from 1900-1901. Mrs.<lb/>
Reed has long desired to publish them, connecting the letters with running comments.<lb/>
She has been disappointed in having her manuscript turned down by at least one<lb/>
publisher (largely because, I believe, the early letters are too personal for the<lb/>
general reader and the connecting comments too brief). (Incidentally, is there a<lb/>
possibility that your own publishing house might publish them? They would make only<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115015"/>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
August<lb/>
a small book and one which could sell relatively inexpensively.) In preparation<lb/>
for the Cleveland affair (unveiling of the painting &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;)<lb/>
Mr. Kellogg borrowed Miss Reed's manuscript and asked me to read it over to select<lb/>
a choice letter to be read by General Ireland at the unveiling. I was fascinated<lb/>
by the letters--the early ones are so quaint (but very personal, being what might<lb/>
be called his love letters to his fiance and later his wife) and reveal his wonder-<lb/>
ful character, his ambitions, his ability to undergo hardships, etc. I do hope<lb/>
you can get to read them. One of them, telling of the terrors of a long wagon<lb/>
journey with his wife in Indian territory enroute to a new post is thrilling--<lb/>
real pioneer stuff.</p>
<p>I was more interested, naturally, in the letters which concerned the Cuban<lb/>
period. Some of them have already been published; others have not. They contained<lb/>
quite a few data on disputed dates, his comings and goings, etc., so that when I<lb/>
met Miss Reed I asked if I might copy those letters (from 1900-1901) to have as<lb/>
background information but <hi>not for me to publish as letters.</hi> Naturally it would be<lb/>
most unfair for me to publish what she has collected and hopes to publish herself.<lb/>
She readily gave me that permission. Even so I would not let you have my copy<lb/>
were it not that you have been unable to see Miss Reed yourself and were it not for<lb/>
the fact that Generals Kean and Lawrence Reed have both given me their tacit consent<lb/>
to help you in every way possible. I will ask you, of course, to respect Miss Reed's<lb/>
wishes in this matter and will expect you to use the letters only as background in-<lb/>
formation, and so that you may check your dates. More than that would be unfair to<lb/>
Miss Reed. But I feel sure that when you finally <unclear>get</unclear> to see her she will be as<lb/>
gracious to you as she was to me and will be glad that you are (as I am) honoring<lb/>
her father.</p>
<p>You will find items 2 and 3 (p. 3 of the enclosure) very helpful--Gen.<lb/>
Kean's memoranda re Reed. I am sure he will permit you to use it--<unclear>much</unclear> of it has<lb/>
been published previously. But you will also ask him about this directly.</p>
<p>With a little concern I also send you photostats of two little known articles<lb/>
which are very controversial, that by Donnally and that by Hemmeter. They are full<lb/>
of inaccuracies and were written in an unhappy spirit--in an effort to <unclear>laud</unclear> Carroll<lb/>
at the expense of his colleagues. Concerning the merits of this argument I will<lb/>
waste no space in this letter. I ask of you to use them wisely and the main reason<lb/>
I send them at all is that the one contains many of Carroll's letters therein with<lb/>
some useful dates. But even the letters themselves contain some errors of fact.<lb/>
One or two are obviously dated wrong (a simple thing to do). The special order #22<lb/>
(page 159) omits Agramonte's name; the error was corrected in special order #122,<lb/>
issued the same day but not cited herein. I have seen the original order #122.<lb/>
The letter of Aug. 27, <hi>1900</hi> was of course written in <hi>1901.</hi> There are certain names<lb/>
misspelled here and there (e.g. Wamer for Warner, p. 162). Reed's movements are not<lb/>
correctly noted in the letter of Sept. 18, 1900. The letter of Sept. 23, 1900 infers<lb/>
that Agramonte was away when Lazear died, an inference contradicted by other evidence<lb/>
I have. Carroll's letter of Sept. 28 saying &ldquo;Lazear died tonight&rdquo; is obviously<lb/>
wrongly dated since Lazear died Sept. 25 (the bronze tablet at Hopkins nothwith-<lb/>
standing:) I have a copy of the official death certificate, etc. These and other<lb/>
errors were allowed to slip into the articles by Hemmeter and some of the statements<lb/>
were later vigorously denied in a letter from Agramonte to Hemmeter (which is too<lb/>
personal for publication).</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06115016"/>
<p>Miss Laura Wood</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>August</p>
<p>I suggest therefore that you use only such data in this article which<lb/>
you can confirm from other sources, and as you and I agreed in our previous<lb/>
correspondence you are not interested in the unhappy controversy that occurred<lb/>
<hi>after</hi> the great work was finished.</p>
<p>Of special interest is Agramonte's 1915 Scientific Monthly article. It<lb/>
gives many interesting details not published elsewhere, but it too apparently<lb/>
contains some factual errors. Remember it was written 15 years after the events<lb/>
took place. There is some question as to the veracity of the story about Dean's<lb/>
inoculation (p. 210) and the supposed conversation which Agramonte overheard. I<lb/>
have no right to doubt that if this version was rather fictional, Agramonte had<lb/>
some honorable reason for handing it out. But at least two times elsewhere Agra-<lb/>
monte wrote that Lazear carried on the first two inoculations &ldquo;unknown to the<lb/>
other Board members.&rdquo; So you'd better not reproduce that part of the story.</p>
<p>Permit me to ask you to read my report to Dr. Ramos (Cuban Minister of<lb/>
Defense) in confidence. For reasons which I haven't yet found out (but suspect)<lb/>
Ramos does not want this report to be published quite yet. Regardless of his<lb/>
reasons I have my own reason for asking you not to quote it (except the allusions<lb/>
to it and the brief comments I have already published in my Washington and Jeffer-<lb/>
son and Cleveland talks). My reason is the simple selfish one that I want to<lb/>
publish it myself soon in a medical historical journal. But I do want you to see<lb/>
it because it contains a very carefully authenticated synopsis of &ldquo;what happened<lb/>
when&rdquo; at Columbia Barracks and at Camp Lazear. I think this synopsis will be<lb/>
helpful to you.</p>
<p>As you will see I am <hi>not</hi> sending you the originals or copies of the <unclear>10</unclear><lb/>
letters of Carroll, the 2 of Mrs. Carroll, and the 9 of Reed which were part of<lb/>
the collection of material which Dr. Kelly gave me. The reason is simple--I<lb/>
doubt if they will be helpful. The 2 or 3 which Kelly thought of value he pub-<lb/>
lished in his third edition (as noted herein). The others contain practically<lb/>
nothing of value and nothing new that isn't published in detail elsewhere. If<lb/>
you want copies I can have them made for you, either typewritten or photostated.<lb/>
You probably know better than I do how much a typist would charge for copying<lb/>
29 average length (1-2 page) letters. I regret that I would have to ask you to<lb/>
pay for this as this is our busiest season (Aug.-Sept.) and we are swamped with<lb/>
work. Our poor secretaries can take on no extra work in hours. But I frankly<lb/>
believe it would be wasted money. Then why don't I mail them to you? As source<lb/>
material for a book they are of little value (so little that Kelly didn't use<lb/>
them) but as letters of &ldquo;historical&rdquo; or sentimental interest they are sufficiently<lb/>
valuable that I don't want to trust them to the mails especially since they are<lb/>
really not mine but on &ldquo;permanent loan&rdquo; to form a part of my growing collection.</p>
<p>The photographs cited you can obtain readily (I believe at cost) from the<lb/>
U. S. Army Museum. If you want a copy of Camp Lazear and Bldg. No. 1 as we re-<lb/>
discovered it this year I'll gladly send it with an appropriate description.</p>
<p>By all means consult all of the references on page 6 (enclosure). You<lb/>
probably know of many of them already. Incidentally the story that Reed said,<lb/>
&ldquo;I salute you&rdquo; to Moran and Kissinger is a legend and had no basis in fact. I<lb/>
have that repeatedly and directly from both Moran and Kissinger. It's an appealing<lb/>
story which you might repeat as a <hi>legend</hi> and perhaps handle as I did by quoting<lb/>
the remark, &ldquo;If Reed didn't salute them, he should have.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06115017"/>
<p>Miss Laura Wood</p>
<p>- 4 -</p>
<p>August</p>
<p>I hope you will forgive me for having delayed so long in sending<lb/>
this data. I do want to help you even though in a way I might selfishly<lb/>
like to keep the data for my own forthcoming book on the whole story. But<lb/>
beyond any personal desire regarding my own book I have the desire to honor a<lb/>
gallant group of men and if I can help you spread their story so much the better.<lb/>
Furthermore I have accepted much of the material I have been given, not for my-<lb/>
self but as a custodian, the material to be available eventually to all <hi>critical</hi><lb/>
(but sympathetic) historians.</p>
<p>May I make this suggestion. I have found errors in every published work<lb/>
on the subject, even a few in the official Senate Document so carefully supervised<lb/>
by Major Kean. It is impossible for me to send you the (actually) hundreds of<lb/>
pages of &ldquo;original&rdquo; material I already have, material collected by voluminous<lb/>
correspondence and interviews. But I will gladly receive a copy of your pre-<lb/>
liminary draft and go over it carefully to see if dates and deeds conform to<lb/>
data which I consider authoritative. I do not propose to suggest that I criticize<lb/>
your manuscript. I will merely tell you where you can check this or that point that<lb/>
looks wrong to me.</p>
<p>In closing may I say that I too have had the same happy experience you<lb/>
have had. If all retired or un-retired generals were as marvelous as the <unclear>trio</unclear><lb/>
Kean-Truby-Ireland &ldquo;life would be beautiful&rdquo;!</p>
<p>Please guard my photostats and reprints--in most cases I have sent you<lb/>
my only copy. Return them at your &ldquo;earliest convenience&rdquo; but use them fully.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Best wishes.</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
