<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115128">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, June 5, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115128</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-06-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, Wiliam S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="place">Barbados</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-06-05">June 5, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115128</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, June 5, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench comments on Wood's manuscript. He hopes that she will acknowledge the Reeds in her foreword.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-06-05">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, June 5, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115128"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-06-05">June 5, 1942</date>
</dateline>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
230 South 19th Street<lb/>
Philadelphia, Pa.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I feel that I have let you down by delaying my reply so long, but I had<lb/>
a very hectic time recently. I have just heard that I have passed my army exam-<lb/>
ination but have no idea how soon I will be called to active duty.</p>
<p>I think your manuscript is excellent and I have very few comments to make.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>201: You say that the disease was carried in Spanish ships to the<lb/>
Barbadoes in 1864. Then you continue as if in chronological sequence to mention<lb/>
that it hit Havana in 1649. Is one of these dates wrong?</item>
<item>Page 202: You say one attack usually produced immunity. I thought that<lb/>
one attack of true yellow fever always produced immunity and that the confusion<lb/>
arose because people who thought they had had yellow fever occasionally later<lb/>
got true yellow fever. Are you sure that the word &ldquo;usually&rdquo; should be left in?</item>
<item>Page 203: &ldquo;The untended sick lay in the same room with the decomposing<lb/>
dead until they died themselves.&rdquo; Your meaning is perfectly clear but the nearness<lb/>
of the word &ldquo;they&rdquo; to &ldquo;the decomposing dead&rdquo; suggestes that the decomposing dead<lb/>
died themselves:</item>
<item>Page 213: &ldquo;On May 24, 1900 the Adjutant General issued the order&rdquo; etc.<lb/>
I found in the Archives Building, in the file on Read, Item No. 325807, records of<lb/>
the Surgeon General's office that the order was originally issued May 23, apparently.<lb/>
It was reissued on the 24th. I believe there are some minor differences in the<lb/>
wording of these two orders. This is of no importance for your book but I will<lb/>
have to work this out for my own manuscript. I have Sternberg's order of May <hi>23</hi> to<lb/>
the A.C. I think the latter issued the order May 24.</item>
<item>Page 222: Your imaginary conversation between Reed and Lazear in which<lb/>
Reed says &ldquo;I'll have a talk with Carter.&rdquo; According to General Kean's letter to<lb/>
me of August 20, 1941, Carter got sick and left Cuba on July 23, before the mos-<lb/>
quito work really began. General Kean sent me a copy of a letter that he had from<lb/>
Dr. Carter's daughter dated November 12, 1928 giving this information. In Kean's<lb/>
letter to me of Sept. 19, 1941 he said that Reed had no connection with Carter<lb/>
except that he had read a magazine article of Carter's. I should personally imagine<lb/>
that if Reed did read this article of Carter's and if Carter were still there the<lb/>
natural thing would have been for Reed to go and see him but I have been unable<lb/>
to prove to my satisfaction that they ever did actually discuss the matter and I<lb/>
seem to recall a letter which I believe Thayer of Hopkins wrote Mrs. Lazear in which<lb/>
he intimated that it was Lazear who had read Carter's paper and appreciated its<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115129"/>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
June 5, 1942<lb/>
significance. There was no indication that Reed had actually seen Carter. Do<lb/>
you have the facts right on this point?</item>
<item>Page 233-234: You indicate that when Carroll was inoculated, Lazear<lb/>
first held the test tube and that Carroll was actually holding it while the<lb/>
mosquito bit Carroll. I have wondered about that and imagine you based your<lb/>
remarks on Agramonte's article in the December 15 Scientific Monthly, bottom of<lb/>
Page 221. I have read something about this somewhere else but can't lay my<lb/>
hands on it at the moment. The wording was vague and one could not conclude who<lb/>
was actually holding the tube when the mosquito bit Carroll. Since Lazear at this<lb/>
time was the one most interested and responsible for these experiments, I advised<lb/>
Cornwell to have Lazear holding the tube in the Wyeth painting. Are you any more<lb/>
sure of this story than I am?</item>
<item>Page 239: Speaking of Dean you say, &ldquo;He had been outside of Camp Columbia<lb/>
only once in the last fifty-seven days.&rdquo; On page 210 of Agramonte's article,<lb/>
Agramonte says that Dean &ldquo;had not left the military reservation for nearly two<lb/>
months.&rdquo; I don't remember the details given by General Truby in his story about<lb/>
Reed's questioning Dean and offering him money to admit that he had gone out of<lb/>
the camp. My recollection is that Dean denied he had been out of the camp. Where<lb/>
did you get the basis for the statement that he had been out once?</item>
<item>Page 251: &ldquo;The Spaniards, whose only duty was to gather stones off the<lb/>
ground for a low wall about the Camp&rdquo; etc. In Agramonte's article, page 234, he<lb/>
says of the Spanish immigrants, &ldquo;Their only work was to pick up loose stones from<lb/>
the ground.&rdquo; He makes no mention of any stone wall. From various sources I have<lb/>
heard that a fence was around Camp Lazear but most of the men who lived there whom<lb/>
I have interviewed do not remember any fence, none have mentioned the wall and<lb/>
none of the army photographs or those in Kelly's book show any fence or wall.<lb/>
Are you sure there was one?</item>
<item>Page 267. In interviewed Lambert in Chicago again for the second time about<lb/>
two weeks ago. He does not believe the part of Andrus' story that Andrus took Reed's<lb/>
place. I discussed this with General Truby in Washington a couple of weeks ago and<lb/>
Truby thinks Andrus is correct. Lambert said that they would not have kept Forbes'<lb/>
blood around for two or three days, waiting for someone to decide to take it. I<lb/>
reread Andrus' story last night and he does not infer that the blood had been already<lb/>
taken from Forbes. So far as I can see from your story and that of Andrus, it does<lb/>
not conflict with the scientific necessity of drawing blood from Forbes during the<lb/>
first three days of his illness.</item>
</list></p>
<p>I shall be interested to hear when the book will appear. I sincerely hope<lb/>
that in your foreword you are going to say also how nice Blossom and Walter Reed's<lb/>
families have been to you even though you found them a little difficult. I am sure<lb/>
they will be much pleased to have you acknowledge publicly that they are the salt of<lb/>
the earth and have helped you tremendously even if it isn't quite true.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
