<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115073">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, February 3, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115073</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-02-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wormley, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Lawrence] Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Fort Snelling, St. Paul (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Library, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">National Archives, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-02-03">February 3, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115073</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, February 3, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Wood that the Surgeon General's library had no record of the Reed-Lazear notebook ever being catalogued. He suggests she visit Reed's family members for permission to use Walter Reed's letters.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-02-03">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, February 3, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115073"/>
<opener>
Y. F.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-02-03">February 3, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am returning to you the four photostated pages from the<lb/>
Lazear-Reed notebook as I now have my own copy. Let me thank you again for<lb/>
your real kindness in letting me know of this book. By the way, if you ever<lb/>
find no further use for your four photostats, I would like to have them,<lb/>
especially that on page 37. They made my photostats very hastily and many<lb/>
of them are very sloppy. My photostat of page 37 is not nearly as good as<lb/>
yours.</p>
<p>I spent a morning at the Surgeon General's library and we could<lb/>
find no evidence that this notebook had ever been catalogued. The chief librar-<lb/>
ian was out but Dr. Mayer, the librarian responsible for cataloging all the<lb/>
books spent some time with me. He was greatly interested in the book and its<lb/>
history. He seemed very gratified when I promised to let him have my photostats<lb/>
so that they could make themselves a copy for their library. He seemed satis-<lb/>
fied to consider the matter closed and therefore I told him a lot of what Dr.<lb/>
Malloch had told me. On his assurance that the matter was closed, I inquired<lb/>
as to whether a man by the name of Wormley had ever worked there. A colored man<lb/>
by that name used to work in the Surgeon General's office, in the medical de-<lb/>
partment but as I understand it, not for some years. Dr. Mayer estimated that<lb/>
he must be in his fifties now, so that he might be a relative of Dr. Lowell<lb/>
<unclear>Cheatban</unclear> Wormley who was in the directory. The latter was born in 1906 and is<lb/>
the man whose name you and I both found in the directory. Dr. Mayer told me<lb/>
it is quite possible that the old notebook might well have been thrown out.<lb/>
Like us, he was a little suspicious of the whole thing but not inclined to press<lb/>
matters. The question now is whether Dr. Wormley is the man who actually sold<lb/>
the book or the man who was an intermediary between the seller and Malloch.<lb/>
Malloch sent me the following note: &ldquo;In November, 1931, Dr. - -, an interne at<lb/>
the - Hospital, told Dr. - that <unclear>he</unclear> had Walter Reed's notebook of cases of<lb/>
yellow fever. Before Dr. - brought the book to me, I heard, third-handed, that<lb/>
when he was working as a medical student one summer at the Army Medical Library,<lb/>
he had rescued the book from an ash barrel...&rdquo; I think Malloch is going to get<lb/>
in touch with Wormley to see if he has any more Reed material.</p>
<p>Before leaving, Mrs. Hench and I called your home once Tuesday<lb/>
evening about 5:30 and twice Wednesday, but no one was at home.</p>
<p>May I urge you strongly to do two things: (1) By all means call<lb/>
in person on Mrs. Blossom Reed and her mother. She may not have the copies of<lb/>
the letters in Washington but you should meet her and her mother anyhow and if<lb/>
you find that the reception is a friendly one (and I sincerely believe it will be)<lb/>
you may be able to make some such statement as the following: &ldquo;Am I correct in<lb/>
my understanding that you let Dr. Hench make a copy of many of these letters? If<lb/>
so, would you be willing to let me write him and ask him to lend me his copy since<lb/>
yours is not in Washington?&rdquo; With her authorization I shall be glad to lend it to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115074"/>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
February 3, 1942<lb/>
you. Perhaps it is too late now to bother about that. (2) By all means, if you<lb/>
haven't already done so, go to the Archives Building and see Mr. R. R. Critchfield<lb/>
in the old records division of the Adjutant General's office. They have the per-<lb/>
sonal report files of Walter Reed showing his complete whereabouts throughout his<lb/>
entire army career with each report signed in his own handwriting. These were<lb/>
monthly reports. They are in much greater detail than the synopsis of his where-<lb/>
abouts as generally given out by the War Department. General Reed, Walter Reed's<lb/>
son, believes that his father was at Fort Snelling from May or June, 1891 to<lb/>
September, 1892 and in St. Paul from September, 1892 to September, 1893. I didn't<lb/>
have time to check these dates with Reed's monthly reports but you will find all<lb/>
of that data in one file. I don't know whether mentioning my name will help or<lb/>
hurt you. Critchfield wasn't very helpful at first until General Ireland put some<lb/>
pressure on him in my behalf. Because of this he was very nice at the last but<lb/>
nevertheless he may have resented Ireland's interference in my behalf and I think<lb/>
it might be best for you merely to say that you are writing up the life of Walter<lb/>
Reed, have had some help from the Reed family and others and you understand that<lb/>
the personal record file is in their office. You will be allowed to copy some of<lb/>
this material and have it censored by Critchfield. They are very wary about<lb/>
photostats.</p>
<closer>
<salute><unclear>Sincerely</unclear>,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
