<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115111">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, March 23, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Wood, Laura</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115111</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Alice</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Apache (Ariz.)</name>
<name type="place">Richmond (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-23">March 23, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115111</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, March 23, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Wood returns material, which Hench had loaned to her, and discusses her manuscript. The publication delay permits her to do more research on Lazear. Wood comments on a Reed family legend that is almost certainly apocryphal.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-23">
<head>Letter from Laura Wood to Philip Showalter Hench, March 23, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115111"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
1338 19th St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1942-03-23">March 23, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I'm sending you today by insured express the material you<lb/>
so kindly lent me - so long ago. I checked it against the<lb/>
list you made out at the time, and believe that I've re-<lb/>
turned everything. I sent also the Senate Document. If I<lb/>
need one later when I do some more checking I can probably<lb/>
find one in some medical library in Philadelphia. I in-<lb/>
cluded copies of a couple of letters from Reed to his father,<lb/>
copies of which Alice Reed let me have. They aren't of any<lb/>
value, just indicate that he had developed a little geneol-<lb/>
ogical interest. Also I sent a letter I received from Dr.<lb/>
William Howard, which I thought you might like to have for<lb/>
your <del><unclear></unclear></del> collection. It is a very nice and sweet letter<lb/>
about Reed, and since it is from a rather important man I<lb/>
thought it might interest you.</p>
<p>Now that publication has been pushed off until Fall, I'll<lb/>
have a chance to give Lazear more credit than I did. I<lb/>
can't help thinking that the rest of the doctors on the<lb/>
board were practically blind to take no interest in the<lb/>
mosquito theory when he was probably pushing it all the<lb/>
time in conversations.</p>
<p>Thank you for your sketch of the course of the Quemados epi-<lb/>
demic. I shan't of course use it except for reference - my<lb/>
own, I mean.</p>
<p>The Register of Medical Officers you refer to must be what<lb/>
I saw, too. Big books, kept in longhand, accounting for all<lb/>
the orders and moves of each medical officer from year to<lb/>
year? I've looked up Reed's from start to finish. One thing<lb/>
of interest that I found is that the family legend about the<lb/>
trip from Camp Apache to the Union Pacific tracks - 700 miles,<lb/>
27 days and all the rest of it, - is almost certainly apochry-<lb/>
phal. He was exactly two weeks getting from Apache to Rich-<lb/>
mond, where he went on leave. There's even a letter in his own<lb/>
hand dated May 27th (he started out on the 10th) from Richmond<lb/>
asking for an extension of his leave. I don't doubt that at<lb/>
one time or another he took such a trip, but I'm pretty sure<lb/>
it wasn't then, especially since there was no sense on earth<lb/>
in going out such a hard way when the Santa Fe Trail was com-<lb/>
paratively easy.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06115112"/>
<p>I'm ashamed to say that I've never written to Mrs. Lazear, but<lb/>
now that I have this unexpected breathing space I'm going to.<lb/>
It is a little hard to allow how much of a hero Lazear was<lb/>
without making Reed look a bit dumb, I think.</p>
<p>From April 1st on my address will be: 230 South 19th St.,<lb/>
Philadelphia. As you may judge, we found a place to live.<lb/>
It is on Rittenhouse Square, in a surprisingly ugly yellow<lb/>
brick mansion, with red sandstone trim, now converted into<lb/>
apartments. Since it is directly across the square from the<lb/>
SEC Crosby will have no transportation problems.</p>
<p>I'll let you know from time to time of the progress of my<lb/>
confection through the publisher, and shall also let you see<lb/>
the revisions I make about Lazear. And of course I'll send<lb/>
you one the minute it comes out.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Laura Wood</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
