<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115026">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, September 19, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115026</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Lawrence] Walter L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, [Blossom] Emilie M.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-19">September 19, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115026</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, September 19, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is pleased that the material he sent to Wood will be helpful. He comments on how to treat the Moran-Kissinger controversy regarding who volunteered first. Truby believes that Agramonte has written an article with errors, but Hench is not certain who is correct.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, September 19, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115026"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-09-19">September 19, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
1338 Nineteenth St. N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am glad that you expect my material to be helpful and I am indeed<lb/>
sorry that my conscience would not permit me to send you Major Reed's letters.<lb/>
I sincerely hope that you can still see them, not only the ones pertaining to<lb/>
1900 - 1901, but his earlier letters. I wrote to General Reed asking for further<lb/>
permission from him or as an alternative asking him if I could send to his sister<lb/>
a letter, a carbon copy of which I sent to him. I have not heard from him and<lb/>
suspect that he doesn't even want me to write to her. Just why they are protecting<lb/>
her so assiduously, I don't know.</p>
<p>I saw General Truby's original manuscript but it has been revised ex-<lb/>
tensively and I understand I am to see the revised copy shortly. What I saw<lb/>
was most interesting. We had quite a lively discussion about the location and<lb/>
identification of the buildings at Camp Columbia until I was lucky enough to<lb/>
find an old map which settled the matter. I imagine it was a copy of this map<lb/>
which he showed you. I have had extensive visits and correspondence with Moran<lb/>
and Kissinger and as you did, I found a discrepancy in their story. Both of<lb/>
these men are entirely <unclear>honest</unclear>, I am sure, but it is merely a matter of memory,<lb/>
and I don't think we can even trust General Truby as to who was first. Certainly<lb/>
Moran would know better than Truby. I believe that the best solution to the<lb/>
problem is to do what all other writers have done--to avoid this controversy<lb/>
and to lump the two men together as having volunteered together. After three<lb/>
years I have been unable to get the men to agree, even though I got them both<lb/>
in a hotel room at Washington and Jefferson last year.</p>
<p>Miss Blossom's Reed's letters I believe would give you many details<lb/>
about Reed's earlier residences. I have the book &ldquo;Old <unclear>Jules</unclear>&rdquo;. As you say,<lb/>
it is not particularly important but it was mildly interesting.</p>
<p>Let me repeat my offer to go over your manuscript. I shall be very<lb/>
glad to do it and indeed very interested to do it. Let me warn you that General<lb/>
Truby believes that Agramonte's article in the Popular Science Monthy has many<lb/>
errors in it. Who was right, Agramonte or Truby, I cannot entirely judge.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115027"/>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
September 19, 1941<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. Let me give you the results of my efforts to determine just who<lb/>
were present when Moran was first subjected to the experiments in Bldg. 2. Do you<lb/>
have Senate Document <unclear>822</unclear>, the official compilation of the yellow fever work? On<lb/>
pages 10, 86 and 100 of this document it mentions two controls only being on Side A<lb/>
(the mosquito-free side). These two controls were apparently non-immune volunteers<lb/>
but they have never been identified. Moran doesn't recall who they were. On page<lb/>
100 Reed says that the <hi>two controls</hi> continued to sleep in that room at night. On<lb/>
page 99 Reed mentions <hi>two controls</hi> and <hi>one other non-immune</hi> who were on the opposite<lb/>
side of the screen from Moran. Apparently this &ldquo;<hi>other non-immune&rdquo;</hi> was Reed himself.<lb/>
Apparently he merely entered the mosquito-free side of the room briefly for the pur-<lb/>
pose of seeing Moran bitten. This data I found in Agramonte's scientific Monthly<lb/>
article Dec. 1915, on page 235 (bottom) where it says, &ldquo;During this time <hi>two other<lb/>
men and Major Reed</hi> remained in the other compartment, separated from Moran....etc.&rdquo;<lb/>
(This is why Miss Hallock had three figures drawn in the left box of the diagram<lb/>
on p. 21 of the enclosed Metropolitan Life Insurance Company's pamphlet. But the<lb/>
events pictured in Figures 1 and 3 on p. 21 never occurred, despite Gorgas' garbled<lb/>
version given on p. 243 of the Senate Document).<lb/>
But in Miss Reed's manuscript I found still another version of the incident.<lb/>
In the letter written by Reed to his family supposedly dated <hi>Dec. 26</hi>, 1900 Reed<lb/>
describes Moran's experiment and says, &ldquo;I stood with Dr. Carroll and Dr. Ames on<lb/>
the other side (of the screen) at the place marked &ldquo;B&rdquo; and saw the insect light...etc.<lb/>
Bed marked &ldquo;B&rdquo; is being occupied by <hi>a non-immune</hi> who sleeps within one foot of the<lb/>
screen, breathing the same air as in room with bed &ldquo;A&rdquo; (infected room). <hi>This young<lb/>
non-immune</hi> is quite well, but the young fellow (i.e. Moran) who went in on the 21st<lb/>
was suddenly stricken today at noon (just <hi>four days</hi> after he entered and was bitten)<lb/>
with a sharp attack of what promises to be yellow fever....etc.&rdquo;<lb/>
Obviously there is an error. The supposed date of this letter is Dec. 26<lb/>
but I imagine the date has been misread and was really Dec. 25. Reed would hardly have<lb/>
made a mistake in dating a letter on Christmas Day and yet the letter <hi>must</hi> have been<lb/>
written then because (1) he speaks of Dec. 21 and then <hi>this noon</hi>, four days later..etc.<lb/>
(2) also a glance at the official record of Moran's case with his fever chart, etc.<lb/>
shows that Moran took sick (really) on Christmas Day, had a fever of 104 that after-<lb/>
noon but did <hi>not</hi> have a fever that high on the 26th.<lb/>
One must conclude that there may have been, not two but perhaps five persons<lb/>
in the mosquito-free side of Bldg. #2 when Moran was being bitten on the other side.<lb/>
These were Drs. Reed, Carroll, Ames and at least one and probably two non-immune<lb/>
volunteers. Why Reed should only mention one (&ldquo;this young non-immune&rdquo;) in the letter<lb/>
to his family where everywhere else it speaks of two non-immune volunteers I do not<lb/>
know. It's just one more of the scores and scores of contradictions I've already<lb/>
found in the various official and unofficial records of the experiments. One is almost<lb/>
tempted to complain that although the results of the experiments were clear as crystal<lb/>
and the experiments themselves meticulously done, the records regarding incidental<lb/>
details were rather sloppily kept (or poorly remembered later).<lb/>
P.S. Hench, M.D.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
