<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06116090">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes on Philip Showalter Hench's speech entitled "Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever," [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06116090</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Roper, Laura Wood</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Malloch, Archibald</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Gawne, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Seth, Miss</name>
<name type="person">Sweitzer, Charlotte C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06116090</idno>
<title>Notes on Philip Showalter Hench's speech entitled "Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever," [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This typescript deals with Hench's discussion of the recently discovered notebook containing the lab notes of Lazear and Reed. Hench credited Laura Wood with the discovery. The speech was given before the American Association of Obstetricians, Gynecologists and Abdominal Surgeons.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Notes on Philip Showalter Hench's speech entitled "Walter Reed and the Conquest of Yellow Fever," [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06116090"/>
<p>Last night at the Hotel Kahler Dr. Hench gave an address on &ldquo;Walter Reed<lb/>
and the Conquest of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; before the American Association of Obstetricians,<lb/>
Gynecologists and Abdominal Surgeons. Dr. Hench has continued his studies on the<lb/>
history of this conquest having made several trips to Cuba where the discovery<lb/>
of the cause of yellow fever was made. Recently, two additional bibliographic<lb/>
&ldquo;finds&rdquo; have been made which Dr. Hench <del>mentioned</del><add><unclear>recalled</unclear></add> last night for the first time.<lb/>
Dr. Hench has been giving some assistance to Miss Laura Wood from Washington, D. C.<lb/>
whose book on the life of Walter Reed is soon to appear. In November Miss Wood,<lb/>
hunting for material concerning the conquest of yellow fever, learned that there<lb/>
was an unidentified notebook in the New York Academy of Medicine containing notes<lb/>
on yellow fever experiments done in Cuba in 1900. It had been sold to the library<lb/>
presumably as Dr. Reed's notebook. A friend of Dr. Reed's had failed to identify<lb/>
the handwriting as that of Reed and the notebook had remained unidentified and with<lb/>
little <add>or no</add> attention paid to it.</p>
<p>The four members of the U. S. Army Yellow Fever Commission who discovered<lb/>
the cause of yellow fever were Dr. Walter Reed, head of the Board, Dr. James<lb/>
Carroll, Dr. Jesse Lazear and Dr. Aristides Agramonte. During the yellow fever<lb/>
experiments Dr. Lazear contracted experimental yellow fever and died, but his<lb/>
carefully kept notebooks gave to Dr. Reed the chief clue which permited Dr. Reed<lb/>
to extend and complete the work which incriminated the mosquito as the cause of<lb/>
yellow fever. Shortly after the work was completed Dr. Reed died in 1902. Many<lb/>
of his records and notebooks mysteriously disappeared from his office in Washington<lb/>
and have not <add>yet</add> been recovered.</p>
<p>In 1931, someone brought to <del>the</del> Dr. Malloch, librarian of the New York<lb/>
Academy of Medicine, a notebook which he had presumably rescued from an ash barrel.<lb/>
He thought it was Dr. Reed's laboratory notebook, but when Dr. Reed's name was not<lb/>
found therein the book was referred to a friend for identification. Studying the<lb/>
notebook rather <unclear>cursorily</unclear> he did not see Dr. Reed's handwriting in the earlier parts<lb/>
of the book and concluded that although the notebook obviously reported some experi-<lb/>
ments carried out by the yellow fever commission it was not one of Dr. Reed's lost<lb/>
notebooks. Noting the dates in the notebook, Miss Laura Wood concluded that it might<lb/>
have been written by Dr. Lazear and sent to Dr. Hench three or four photostat pages.<lb/>
Dr. Hench recognized the handwriting as that of Dr. Lazear, as Mrs. Lazear had given<lb/>
to Dr. Hench some of Dr. Lazear's letters. Dr. Hench finally obtained a complete<lb/>
photostatic copy of the notebook. The first hundred pages are in the handwriting<lb/>
of Dr. Lazear and are of special historical significance because they show that on<lb/>
the very day on which the announcement was made in Washington of the formation of<lb/>
the Army Yellow Fever Board, Dr. Lazear visited a yellow fever patient in Havana<lb/>
and collected mosquitoes from his room for examination, indicating that at that early<lb/>
date Dr. Lazear was on the right track. Dr. Lazear's notes are continued until<lb/>
September 13. Shortly after that he became fatally ill and died on September 25,<lb/>
a martyr to science. Pages 105 to 143 are in the handwriting of Dr. Reed, giving<lb/>
details of the experiments done on volunteer soldiers at Camp Lazear. These soldiers<lb/>
developed experimental yellow fever as a result of being exposed to the bites of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes. An interesting item was found in <del>the</del> one of the pages describing<lb/>
an experiment on a soldier not heretofore mentioned in official or medical documents.<lb/>
Dr. Hench has <unclear>showed</unclear> copies of the notebook to Mrs. Walter Reed and Dr. Reed's son<lb/>
and daughter, also to Mrs. Lazear, the widow of Dr. Lazear. They recognized the<lb/>
handwritings of Drs. Lazear and Reed and have completely authenticated the notebook.</p>
<p>In January, while visiting the relatives of Dr. Reed and Dr. Lazear in<lb/>
Washington, Dr. Hench was invited by Mrs. Gawne and Miss Seth to visit the boyhood<lb/>
home of Dr. Lazear at &ldquo;Windsor&rdquo; near Baltimore. In the attic were found five trunks<lb/>
belonging to Dr. Lazear's mother; they had not been opened since her death many years<lb/>
ago. In these trunks Dr. Hench found many photographs taken by Dr. Lazear during his<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06116091"/>
stay in Cuba, also many heretofore unpublished photographs of his boyhood, school<lb/>
and college life. Of greatest interest was the finding of 140 letters written by<lb/>
Dr. Lazear to his mother. Many of them described his experiences during post-<lb/>
graduate medical study in Europe. Forty of them were written during Dr. Lazear's<lb/>
yellow fever experiments, the last one being written on the very day when he became<lb/>
fatally ill. These letters <del><unclear></unclear></del> graphically illustrate Dr. Lazear's splendid<lb/>
character, his eagerness to learn scientific <del>proof</del><add>truth</add>, his critical appraisal of<lb/>
medical education in Europe and in this country, and constitute an important<lb/>
new source of material for <del>those</del><add>scholars</add> interested in the history of the conquest of yellow<lb/>
fever, one of the greatest medical <del>discoveries</del><add>accomplishments</add> of all time. It is <del>hoped</del><add>planned</add> that this<lb/>
collection of letters and other Lazear material <del>can</del><add>will</add> be kept intact in a <add>medical</add> museum in<lb/>
Havana or in this country.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
