<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115064">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, December 11, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115064</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-12-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Wilson, Louis B.</name>
<name type="place">St. Paul (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Minneapolis (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-12-11">December 11, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115064</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, December 11, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Wood that he does not know Reed's whereabouts in 1893. He suggests she contact Wilson. He notes that his book does not focus on individuals to the extent that her work does.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-12-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, December 11, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115064"/>
<opener>
Y. F.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-12-11">December 11, 1941</date>
</dateline>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
1338 19th Street N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am glad the Kelly books arrived. There is no particular hurry<lb/>
about returning the third edition.</p>
<p>Since I am writing the story of the Cuban episode from the human<lb/>
angle and not the story of any individual participant, I have not done much<lb/>
on the researches of any of the individual men. Therefore, I cannot help<lb/>
you much as to the whereabouts of Reed in 1893. However, Dr. Louis B. Wilson,<lb/>
Director Emeritus of the Mayo Foundation, can help you, I am sure. I am sending<lb/>
you a reprint of his which shows his connection with Dr. Reed in St. Paul. Yes-<lb/>
terday he gave me the following additional information after I permitted him to<lb/>
read your letter.</p>
<p>While still studying medicine, Dr. Wilson was teaching biology in the<lb/>
Central High School in St. Paul. On March 28, 1893 Dr. Wilson met Reed, who there-<lb/>
after used Wilson's microscope and laboratory. Dr. Wilson <hi>insists</hi> that Reed<lb/>
stayed in St. Paul until <hi>November,</hi> 1893. Dr. Wilson certifies to the date of<lb/>
March 28 because that is the date given by Reed himself in the reprint. August<lb/>
was vacation time for Wilson. Having met Reed in March, by May, 1893, Reed and<lb/>
Wilson began making throat swabs and worked on this during the summer time.<lb/>
They continued to work together even after Dr. Wilson's school started in Septem-<lb/>
ber, 1893, and worked together for three more months until Reed was transferred<lb/>
to Washington in November, 1893. Dr. Wilson said it is of course possible that<lb/>
Reed left town from time to time between March and November, 1893, but during those<lb/>
months at least he was officially in St. Paul. Reed had been at Hopkins before<lb/>
coming to St. Paul and may have gone to Hopkins after he left St. Paul. Dr. Wilson<lb/>
says that Sternberg did not send Reed to Hopkins in May, 1893. He may have made<lb/>
the arrangements at that time, but Wilson is sure that Reed did not go in that month.<lb/>
A few years later, in 1898, Reed returned to Minneapolis I believe to speak or at<lb/>
least attend a meeting there. Dr. Wilson thought it was the meeting of the American<lb/>
Public Health Association (do you know whether he attended that meeting?). At any<lb/>
rate, Reed was a house guest of Dr. Wilson in their home at 1004 <unclear>Como</unclear> Avenue at the<lb/>
corner of Sixteenth Street in Minneapolis. During their conversations, Reed inquired<lb/>
of Wilson as to whether Wilson would like to leave Minneapolis and join him in Wash-<lb/>
ington and do bacteriology in the Army Medical Corps. It so happened that Dr. Wilson<lb/>
and Dr. Westbrook were studying an epidemic of typhoid fever among the thirteenth<lb/>
regiment of Minnesota volunteers encamped at the State Fair Grounds in St. Paul.<lb/>
Wilson and Westbrook noted that latrines were close to the kitchens and they actually<lb/>
watched flies going from one to the other. They caught flies but were unable to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06115065"/>
Miss Laura Wood<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
December 11, 1941<lb/>
find typhoid bacilli thereon. Reed was much interested in this work and you<lb/>
know a little bit later he was put on the committee with Vaughan and Shakespeare,<lb/>
which proved the carrier ability of flies in typhoid fever. Dr. Wilson declined<lb/>
Major Reed's suggestion because he (Wilson) wanted to finish his work with West-<lb/>
brook. Dr. Wilson doesn't remember where Reed lived in St. Paul in 1893 but he<lb/>
had his laboratory in a government building on the south side of Third Street<lb/>
either at Roberts or Cedar Streets, St. Paul. The building has been torn down<lb/>
long since.</p>
<p>This is all Dr. Wilson could remember yesterday. He gold me that he<lb/>
would be glad to hear from you if he could help in any further way. I am sending<lb/>
him a copy of this letter in order that he can check up on me if I have misquoted<lb/>
him.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
