<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06115084">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, March 13, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06115084</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-03-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Wood, Laura</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Fforth, Stubbins</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Havard, V.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Lazear. Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, Wiliam S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-03-13">March 13, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06115084</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, March 13, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench comments on details in Wood's manuscript of her book on Reed. He reflects on the difficulties in planning his own book.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-03-13">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Laura Wood, March 13, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06115084"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-03-13">March 13, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Miss Wood:</salute>
</opener>
<p>First let me thank you sincerely for the fine copy of Kelly's book.<lb/>
When I sent you the advertisement about it I was afraid you'd think it was a not<lb/>
very subtle hint that you should replace the copy I sent you, but I assure you<lb/>
again that was not my purpose. I thought you might like to complete for yourself<lb/>
a set of the three editions thereof. And so I will continue to send you what ad-<lb/>
vertisements of them I can find. Meanwhile I will accept this copy with pleasure,<lb/>
not for myself but for the three-edition set I plan to give W. and J.</p>
<p>I have received your manuscript chapters 18 et seq., and have read it<lb/>
with much interest. I am delighted with it and congratulate you sincerely. I am<lb/>
very surprised about one thing, however, and that is that I thought you were writing<lb/>
a book for <hi>children,</hi> and my definition of children is kids under 15 years of age.<lb/>
From what I have read of your manuscript I would say its appeal would be, not for<lb/>
kids, but for young people of college age and indeed for laymen of all ages for that<lb/>
matter. I do think that much of it is over the heads of school-kids for whom I<lb/>
thought you were writing it. But that's just one man's opinion and if it sells<lb/>
better for grown-ups than for kids you should worry!</p>
<p>Just between us (and implying no hidden meanings whatever) I'm beginning<lb/>
to wonder seriously whether there is any use for me to write my story after that of<lb/>
Truby and that of yourself appears! But we shall see what we shall see, and if mine<lb/>
never sees the light of day I've had a whale of a lot of fun on it anyhow.</p>
<p>I do envy you one thing. In planning my own book I've debated and debated<lb/>
as to whether I should manufacture &ldquo;likely conversation&rdquo; out of more or less whole<lb/>
cloth or stick strictly to facts. Conversation does help tremendously but my whole<lb/>
background of scientific training has been to say nothing or write nothing that couldn't<lb/>
be absolutely <hi>proven.</hi> And who knows what Reed et al said to each other. You are<lb/>
not bound by such restrictions; hence your manuscript is lively with chatty conver-<lb/>
sation and I must say the conversation you've manufactured is infinitely more appro-<lb/>
priate to the characters involved than the highly dramatized and unnecessarily pro-<lb/>
fane conversations Sidney Howard manufactured for &ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. (Me thinks you<lb/>
borrowed with slight alterations one or two of his less purple conversation-pieces;<lb/>
am I right? But that's O.K.)</p>
<p>Now for some comments. I have made no attempt to edit it. That's not my<lb/>
function. I do think a sentence here and there could be smoothed up and their<lb/>
parsing made less complicated. But all in all it's swell. May I make some individual<lb/>
comments:</p>
<p>Chap. 18, p. 8: &ldquo;Fewer than 1000 Americans stopped bullets.....&rdquo; It<lb/>
is the conventional thing to say (as I did in one of my talks) that disease especially<lb/>
yellow fever killed more soldiers than did the bullets, but I confess I'm having a<lb/>
little difficulty in finding trustworthy statistics on the incidence of fatal wounds,<lb/>
non-fatal wounds, fatal and non-fatal yellow fever. The reports of the Surgeon-General<lb/>
for the years 1898-1902 are in my hands but did you run across any other dope on this<lb/>
point? Where did you get the reference to the sentence re 1000 Americans?</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06115085"/>
<p>Miss Wood</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>March 13, 1942</p>
<p>Chapt. 18, p. 10. Where did you get the reference to the &ldquo;only $20,000<lb/>
to spend&rdquo; on the medical corps? This is a very interesting chapter about a phase<lb/>
of Reed's life I've so far not interested myself in much, although recently I bought<lb/>
a fine copy of the detailed report of Reed, Vaughan and Shakespeare. Haven't had<lb/>
time to read it yet.</p>
<p>Chapt. 19, p. 26. I have always been thrilled with the paper of Stubbins<lb/>
Fforth. What a grand name! I've had his paper microfilmed. How nearly he found the<lb/>
secret!</p>
<p>Chapt. 19, pp. 30-31. There is a great and sudden change between the<lb/>
context on p. 30 and that on p. 31. On page 30 you are exploring the mind of<lb/>
Sternberg and showing why he decided to create the Board. Without interrupting<lb/>
devices <unclear>(**********)</unclear> or a new chapter head you suddenly plunge on page 31 to Reed<lb/>
on a boat down in Tampa. Some plunge! I do think the connection should be<lb/>
smoothed out.</p>
<p>Chapt. 19, p. 32. &ldquo;Quemados seven miles west of Havana.&rdquo; I've seen this<lb/>
variously stated as 9 kilometers west of Havana, 5 miles west, etc. etc. I've<lb/>
travelled it many times and measured it with the autometer but it all depends on what<lb/>
part of Havana is considered the measuring point. I've gotten so many figures myself<lb/>
I'm confused. For example, in the Senate Document 61, <unclear>pl</unclear> 10 McCaw speaks of Camp<lb/>
Lazear (in Quemados) as &ldquo;about 4 miles from Habana&rdquo;. On page 16 Kean says &ldquo;Camp<lb/>
Lazear----about 4 miles from Habana.&rdquo; On page 68 Reed et al speak of &ldquo;Habana, 6<lb/>
miles distant.&rdquo; In the Annual Report of Major General Leonard Wood for 1901 on<lb/>
page 6 (third chapter (?) - &ldquo;Roster of Troops&rdquo; etc.) it says &ldquo;Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Marianao Railroad Station, Quemados, 6 miles from Havana.&rdquo; In Agramonte's &ldquo;Inside<lb/>
History of a Great Medical Discovery,&rdquo; Scientific Monthly Dec. 1915 he says on the<lb/>
first page - &ldquo;Columbia Barracks---distant about 8 miles from the city of Havana.&rdquo;<lb/>
Somewhere else (I can't find the reference at the moment) Camp Columbia is referred<lb/>
to as 9 kilometers. Now 9 kilometers about 5.6 miles (am I right?). So why not<lb/>
accept Wood's statement and call it 6 miles instead of seven miles. (All this is<lb/>
much ado about not very much but it annoys me to see so many different distances<lb/>
given. It makes it harder to satisfy people that we have actually found Camp<lb/>
Lazear where it is).</p>
<p>Chapt. 19, p. 34. You suddenly shift scenes without adequate warning, ex-<lb/>
planation or interrupting typographical devices. One minute you are with Lazear,<lb/>
Reed et al on the verandah at Camp Columbia. A sentence later &ldquo;Sternberg (in<lb/>
Washington) seated behind his desk, nods agreement to Reed's conversation 1000 miles<lb/>
away. The inference is that Sternberg was in Quemados.</p>
<p>Chapt. 20, p. 39. Whose version are you taking re the spread of the<lb/>
epidemic in Quemados? You are apparently combining the version given by Reed (Senate<lb/>
Doc. p. 94) and that given in Kean's diary entry of June 8, p. 169, where he recapitu-<lb/>
lated the list of yellow fever victims Kean says the epidemic first started in #20<lb/>
Gen. Lee Street, then went to 102 Real and then to 89 Real, etc. Reed who wasn't in<lb/>
Havana then and who must have gotten this dope later from Kean or Lazear or Ames,<lb/>
said the epidemic began at 102 Real, then #20 Gen. Lee, then to a house (number not<lb/>
mentioned) right across the street. I have visited all of these houses and photographed<lb/>
each individually after finding out from old time residents that the numbers had not<lb/>
been changed. Reed's description as to 102 Real and then 20 Gen. Lee is obviously<lb/>
wrong. Unfortunately Kean was apparently wrong in placing the two Caesar brothers<lb/>
(who died) in 89 Real for I visited 89 Real and talked at length with one of its<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06115086"/>
Miss Wood<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
March 13, 1942<lb/>
inmates who had lived there for years and years, remembered the epidemic, etc. The<lb/>
Caesars never lived in #89. I think otherwise you'd better follow Kean's diary.<lb/>
Major Edmunds lived at #27 Gen. Lee St. which is <hi>not</hi> right across from #20 Gen. Lee<lb/>
St. but is actually across the street but 1 1/2 blocks nearer Camp Columbia (2 streets<lb/>
cross between #20 and #27 Gen. Lee. Major Kean had formerly lived in #27 himself.<lb/>
Right across from #27 Gen. Lee St. and 1 1/2 blocks from #20 Gen. Lee is #16 Gen. Lee<lb/>
where a Mrs. Fenn (according to Kean) or a Mrs. Muller (according to Dr. Angles) got<lb/>
yellow fever. (See the diagrams enclosed). I still haven't found the map of this<lb/>
epidemic--the house to house map made out by Ames (possibly with Lazear's help) which<lb/>
Reed borrowed. It is mentioned in several places, among them in a letter to Ames<lb/>
from Reed. But I did find in the National Archives a diagram which I microfilmed.<lb/>
I enclose a rough copy. It was from a Report of Major Havard to the Adjutant General,<lb/>
Division of Cuba, dated June 18, 1900.</p>
<p>I suggest that you don't worry about this. Perhaps you will let it go as<lb/>
you have it and I will finally straighten it out by putting together these various<lb/>
references after comparing them with Lazear's notes and some notes Miss Ames just<lb/>
sent me last week. But please don't publish these diagrams. I'd like to reserve them<lb/>
for my own study. Incidentally you say, &ldquo;Then it skipped to the <hi>square</hi> at the end<lb/>
of the <hi>block.</hi> You haven't quoted very clearly what Reed wrote on page 94, Sen. Doc.<lb/>
where he said &ldquo;to the distance of a square&rdquo;, etc. A square and a block are the same,<lb/>
aren't they?</p>
<p>Chapt. 20, p. 40. &ldquo;Turning off the Calzada Real into the hospital grounds<lb/>
......&rdquo; This gives the impression that the hospital grounds were next to or bounded<lb/>
by or at least very close to Calzada Real. As a matter of fact in some spots Calzada<lb/>
Real is 1/2 mile from the hospital grounds so I suggest you say &ldquo;Turning off the<lb/>
Calzada Real <hi>and proceeding onward</hi> to the hospital grounds&rdquo;......or some such.</p>
<p>Chapt. 20, p. 43. As to whether Carter's paper influenced Reed primarily<lb/>
or Lazear primarily I suspect that Reed didn't appreciate its significance until<lb/>
Lazear brought it forcibly to his attention by his work or by the notes in his<lb/>
(Lazear's) notebook. All I can do to help you is to inclose photostats of 3 letters<lb/>
sent to Mrs. Lazear by Dr. Thayer. (Please return these to me promptly as they are<lb/>
the only copies I have.)</p>
<p>I still <unclear>strongly</unclear> suspect that although Reed (when he first went to Cuba)<lb/>
may have already decided to investigate the mosquito theory <hi>sometime</hi> and <hi>somewhere</hi><lb/>
along the line, he wasn't impressed with this theory enough to put it first on their<lb/>
agenda and really wasn't impressed by it (even after the Pinar del Rio guardhouse<lb/>
affair) until Lazear had plugged away at it alone for quite awhile. Lazear apparently<lb/>
<hi>never</hi> had any use for the infectious theory and from the <hi>very beginning</hi> he tackled<lb/>
the mosquito idea.</p>
<p>Chapt. 21, p. 64. &ldquo;When he confided his suspicions to Kean, Truby and the<lb/>
other Board members.....&rdquo; Kean told me he never heard this idea from Reed, didn't<lb/>
know of Reed's suspicions until Truby told him just a few years ago (<hi>Better check<lb/>
this)</hi> I believe Trub wrote me (I can't find it today in the mass of correspondence<lb/>
I've had from him) that he believes Reed told his suspicions to only one or two<lb/>
(including Truby). Why not avoid specific names as I did on page 6 of the enclosed<lb/>
reprint (marked).</p>
<p>Chapt. 21, p. 67. I suppose you got this from Kean but I can't imagine<lb/>
one soldier addressing another as &ldquo;Ranny&rdquo; unless as you infer Lee had known Kean as<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06115087"/>
Miss Wood<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
March 13, 1942<lb/>
a child. Where did Lee know Kean's father? Is this conversation real (i.e. from<lb/>
Kean) or fabricated?</p>
<p>Chapt. 22, p. 74, paragraph 2. &ldquo;The <hi>non-immunes</hi> could go out on such<lb/>
necessary errands as getting supplies, etc...&rdquo; This is of course a slip. You meant<lb/>
the <hi>immunes.</hi> that is, the 3 immune members of the detachment (see Sen. Doc. p. 71).<lb/>
Reed et al specifically states (p. 71) &ldquo;A non-immune person having once left this<lb/>
camp, was not permitted to return to it under any circumstances whatever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Chapt. 22, p. 77. One version infers that one of the 3 (Cooke, Folk or<lb/>
Jernegan) vomited. I've never found out whether this is true and if so, who it was.<lb/>
All Reed says (Sen. Doc. 84) is that &ldquo;the odor was so offensive as to compel them to<lb/>
retreat from the house.&rdquo; You infer that Cooke was the one most affected. Do you<lb/>
know this for sure? It is one of the questions I plan to ask Cooke himself when<lb/>
I visit him this spring.</p>
<p>Chapt. 22, p. 79. It should be Bomiato, not Voniato (see Kean's paper<lb/>
&ldquo;Walter Reed, Dedication of His Birthplace&rdquo;-- in Military Surgeon, March, 1928,<lb/>
p. 301.</p>
<p>I wish I had time to go over your manuscript more carefully. But since<lb/>
you want it back almost at once I've only gone over it once. Please let me see<lb/>
a complete copy (galley proof or book) as soon as you can and if I can help more,<lb/>
please let me know. I just received the last batch of material I had photostated<lb/>
at the National Archives. In addition to Reed's personal file I found a most<lb/>
minute account of his whereabouts written in longhand by some clerk. Mr. Thomases<lb/>
found it for me--it is the Register of Medical Officers, Vol. 11. I couldn't find<lb/>
all the entries but pages 149, 150, 151 and 88 give Reed's whereabouts from Sept.<lb/>
1893 to his death. Doubtless the preceding data could be found, if you still want<lb/>
to check his earlier whereabouts in detail.</p>
<p>Have you ever corresponded with Mrs. Lazear? I don't imagine your book<lb/>
will satisfy Lazear's widow or relatives and of course it will make Carroll's<lb/>
son (nasty fellow!) see red once more (for the millionth time, I guess). I think<lb/>
you have given Lazear more credit than many writers but you have only hinted at the<lb/>
prime importance of his work during the first phases of the Board's work. But I<lb/>
can see that in a book on <hi>Reed</hi> you couldn't give Lazear the credit that I can,<lb/>
writing on the <hi>whole story</hi>, not on Reed's part alone.</p>
<p>Let me hear how things go and when the book is to appear, as I am anxious<lb/>
for an early copy. Will it be illustrated?</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
