<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06206001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April, 20, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06206001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-04-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">La Garde, Louis A.</name>
<name type="person">Spratling, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Magoon, Charles E.</name>
<name type="person">Davis, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Balch, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Shonts, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, C. A. L.</name>
<name type="person">Grunsky, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Straub, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Wheeler, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Curl, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">McCullough, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Furbush, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Taft, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Louise Young</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="place">Ancon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Colon (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-04-20">April 20, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06206001</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April, 20, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas writes about his administration of sanitary affairs in the Canal Zone and political machinations.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1905-04-20">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April, 20, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06206001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
ISTHMIAN CANAL ZONE<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH<lb/>
OFFICE OF CHIEF SANITARY OFFICER<lb/>
ANCON, CANAL ZONE<lb/>
<date value="1905-04-20">April 20, 1905</date>
</dateline>
Maj. J. R. Kean,<lb/>
Medical Corps, U.S.A.,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Kean:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letters of the 3rd and the 10th received.<lb/>
It seems to me that you and Gen. O'Reilly are very bloody<lb/>
minded in being so eager to get off the heads of LaGarde<lb/>
and Spratling, but seriously I think you are in the wrong.<lb/>
I think it would be very poor policy to move in the matter<lb/>
until I meet Judge Magoon and know something of my position.</p>
<p>What I would do, if I acted on my own judgment,<lb/>
would be this:</p>
<p>There is no pressing hurry in the matter and the<lb/>
question of a few weeks will make very little difference. I<lb/>
would wait until I had seen Judge Magoon, found out just what<lb/>
my position was and what his powers were, lay the matter be-<lb/>
for him and find out whether I would have his support. If I<lb/>
found that he was going to support me I would then write<lb/>
LaGarde and Spratling, telling them that, in my opinion, it<lb/>
was best for the work at large that their connection with<lb/>
it should be severed, and give them the opportunity of taking<lb/>
action on their own part. I would do this because it would<lb/>
be less of a reflection upon them and because it is what I<lb/>
would like to have done to me in similar circumstances.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06206002"/>
2:-<lb/>
If they did not act I would then write officially to Judge<lb/>
Magoon, recommending the change. For me to put in an official<lb/>
application now, not knowing how Judge Magoon would act,<lb/>
I think would be very unwise. If he should not support me<lb/>
it would leave me in the position of having two of my chief men<lb/>
on my hands openly antagonistic, and that would certainly<lb/>
weaken my discipline a great deal.</p>
<p>You write saying that I can communicate directly with<lb/>
Gen. O'Reilly and Judge Magoon. I have no official information<lb/>
of this. As far as I know I am still under General Davis<lb/>
as Governor.</p>
<p>These are my reasons, and I still think them very good,<lb/>
for not making application for the change now: I think<lb/>
if I made the application it should go through Gen. Davis,<lb/>
and he would merely forward it for the action of the commission;<lb/>
in Spratling's case I am quite sure entering an emphatic<lb/>
disapproval. With regard to LaGarde I believe he would support<lb/>
me. If Gen. O'Reilly thinks differently I herewith forward<lb/>
a letter to Judge Magoon, asking for the change, but unless<lb/>
Gen. O'Reilly is sure that it will receive Judge Magoon's support,<lb/>
I know it will be a mistake to put it in. Rest assured that<lb/>
I understand conditions down here better than either of you do<lb/>
and know about what I am talking.</p>
<p>Now as for Balch. I do not know what you and the<lb/>
General know about him, but I do not believe either of you<lb/>
know as much as I do. I roomed with him for two months down here<lb/>
and had to listen to him every day for that time. His great<lb/>
fault is that he talks morning, noon and night, Otherwise<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06206003"/>
3:-<lb/>
he is a capable man.</p>
<p>I do not understand from the President's letter that<lb/>
the government is to have a purchasing officer; as I under-<lb/>
stand it we are to merely have charge of our supplies after<lb/>
they get down here. Balch is honest, capable, energetic, and<lb/>
knows our wants and conditions down here and if Mr. Shonts<lb/>
wants a purchasing agent for medical supplies, I do not believe<lb/>
he could get as good a one as Balch. Certainly he would<lb/>
do a great deal better than the men who have heretofore done<lb/>
our purchasing. I think it would be very much better, as the<lb/>
work is in the War Department, to have our medical purveyor<lb/>
do the purchasing, but I would a great deal rather have Balch<lb/>
do it than to have it done as it is at present, but I have<lb/>
no particular interest in Balch and do not intend to make my-<lb/>
self a martyr for his sake and shall not urge him upon Judge<lb/>
Magoon. But here again I think you and Gen. O'Reilly are<lb/>
making up your minds without knowing the circumstances of the<lb/>
case. You can't, in Washington, judge for me down here. It<lb/>
is out of the question. Balch is a man of tolerably<lb/>
influencial political connections and a great talker, and<lb/>
while his letter is of the same character as Reed's, much<lb/>
exaggerated, he has data for everything he has said and could<lb/>
use it very disagreeably. I think it would be a very good<lb/>
piece of policy to tuck him away in some position where he<lb/>
could do good work and where it would be to his interest not<lb/>
to talk, but this concerned more the old Commission and I<lb/>
don't see that it is of much importance one way or the other<lb/>
now.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06206004"/>
<p>4:-</p>
<p>What I am grumbling about is that you and Gen. O'Reilly<lb/>
sit up in Washington criticising my soft heart, meaning my<lb/>
soft <hi>head</hi>, without knowing a damn thing about it (pardon the<lb/>
expression). Now I flatter myself that I am running this<lb/>
job pretty well. I am sorry the Secretary has formed an<lb/>
unfavorable opinion of me, but I rather think that is a result<lb/>
of the position I had to take, and I believe that if I remain<lb/>
here six months he will have changed his opinion. He knew<lb/>
nothing in the world of the Sanitary Department; did not ask<lb/>
10 words about it when he was down here. He derived his<lb/>
ideas entirely from Gen. Davis, and Gen. Davis' ideas were<lb/>
formed very naturally from his own standards. He and I<lb/>
differed in sanitary matters; he thought he knew all about it;<lb/>
I thought I knew all about it. As we were diametrically opposed<lb/>
in many things one of us had to be wrong. The Secretary<lb/>
heard his side of the question and naturally formed an un-<lb/>
favorable opinion of my work. If he had heard me alone he<lb/>
would have formed an equally unfavorable opinion of Gen.<lb/>
Davis' work. I am merely referring to the General in his<lb/>
official capacity now. He is a fine old fellow and I admire<lb/>
him and like him. I do not know anybody whom I look upon,<lb/>
taking all in all, as a higher type of man, but he is not a good<lb/>
administrator, and, in my opinion, not a good sanitarian, and I<lb/>
think it greatly to my advantage that he is not to remain as<lb/>
Governor.</p>
<p>I am inclined to think that the General has a very<lb/>
much higher opinion of me as an executive now than he had<lb/>
three months ago. I saw the storm coming and warned him time<lb/>
and time again. When I took charge, as things developed,<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06206005"/>
5:-<lb/>
I either had to acquiesce in the sanitary ideas of Gen. Davis<lb/>
and Mr. Grunsky, or be constantly advising pretty strongly<lb/>
in directions they did not like. I could see, from Cub<del><unclear>i</unclear></del>an<lb/>
experience, that in following the tack they were we would be<lb/>
exposed to a great <add>deal</add> of just criticism, and that to save myself<lb/>
I must get on record as advising differently. If I had joined<lb/>
in and acquiesced in all proposed I would have been thought<lb/>
a good sanitarian, but my career on the Isthmus would have<lb/>
now been ended. As it is, I am looked upon as a poor<lb/>
administrator, but still I am here, have accomplished the<lb/>
sanitary results I hoped for when I first came down, and these<lb/>
facts will very soon be recognized. I think,if you cast<lb/>
reflections upon the <del><unclear>r</unclear></del> consistency of my cardiac organ, you<lb/>
might at any rate give me credit for good judgment and<lb/>
diplomacy in my year down here, and balance my mushy heart<lb/>
but saying something about <unclear>good</unclear> firm cerebral tissue.</p>
<p>And now as to the positions here. Our force is full<lb/>
of ranking men; I have as many as I need, and cannot use any<lb/>
more. What I want is the young men who can get out on the<lb/>
line and do professional service. I do not want any more men<lb/>
that I cannot order around anywhere. For Ross's place I have<lb/>
recommended Carter. Carter has been doing the work since<lb/>
Ross left. I do not think you could give me a better man from<lb/>
the whole corps. I have asked for Straub with the idea of<lb/>
putting him up there. Stark's place as Health Officer<lb/>
of Colon is at present filled by Wheeler, who I think is doing<lb/>
the work very well, and all the lower positions caused by<lb/>
these changes have been filled by promotion. If Spratling goes<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06206006"/>
<del>7:-</del> 6<lb/>
I intend to put Curl in his place. If LaGarde goes I shall<lb/>
need somebody either in his place or Straub's. Now while<lb/>
you and Gen. O'Reilly know the men of our corps very much<lb/>
better than I do, I am not so sure that you know as well as<lb/>
I do the kind of men I need here; the fact is I know you don't.<lb/>
We are in the worst political kettle down here you every struck.<lb/>
My immediate success and reputation will depend altogether<lb/>
upon the personal impression I can make upon Judge Magoon, as<lb/>
they have depended in the past upon the personal impression<lb/>
I made upon Gen. Davis, so that of any one quality in the<lb/>
higher offices in my Department is very much the most important.</p>
<p>I know <unclear>M<del>u</del>Ccullough</unclear> well and know just what kind of a<lb/>
man he is. I could rely upon him for support just as I do<lb/>
upon Carter, and as for work, I flatter myself that I know<lb/>
Latin-American municipal sanitation about as well as anybody<lb/>
can. That may sound vain, but I think I am getting it down<lb/>
pat, and I do not want any man who will make anybody clean<lb/>
up his back yard; I want him to persuade him to clean up his<lb/>
backyard; that is the key to the business. My ideal Health<lb/>
Officer of Panama would <add>be</add> Furbush if I could get him.</p>
<p>Tell Gen. O'Reilly that in my opinion he need not be<lb/>
anxious about the work down here. It <hi>has been</hi> accomplished;<lb/>
I believe yellow fever has been eradicated, and I believe<lb/>
malaria has been controlled. As evidence of this I advance<lb/>
the health conditions of a considerable force of men who<lb/>
have been down here now a year, something like an average of<lb/>
4000 (we have at present nearly 9000 on the rolls), with only<lb/>
3 or 4 deaths from yellow fever and a death rate from all<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06206007"/>
<del>8:-</del> 7<lb/>
causes of less than 15 per thousand. If we <del>could</del> <add>can</add> keep it down to<lb/>
that the first year, I do not see why the same methods will<lb/>
not keep it down for the 2nd year, and the third, and the fourth.<lb/>
That it is not accidental one can see by comparing it with the<lb/>
first year of French work in which the French report a death<lb/>
rate of 67 per thousand, but I think I have pretty good<lb/>
evidence to know that it was considerably over 100 per<lb/>
thousand. There is no reasonable cause for this except the<lb/>
sanitary precautions we have taken, and in six months from<lb/>
now, as the Secretary of War gradually recognizes these things,<lb/>
I think he will do me justice in the premises and give me<lb/>
credit for good administration in about as difficult a position<lb/>
as I think a man could have.</p>
<p>I am deeply grateful for the backing Gen. O'Reilly<lb/>
has given me with Secretary Taft, but I have made many<lb/>
sacrifices in the last four months (you can probably imagine<lb/>
what they were) to stay here. Every inclination was to ask<lb/>
to be relieved, and it was always not entirely clear in which<lb/>
direction duty pointed, but as things have turned out I am<lb/>
glad I stayed. I look forward to much pleasanter service<lb/>
under the new order of things. I think now that I have data<lb/>
to show that we have accomplished all I every expected to accom-<lb/>
plish and all that probably can be accomplished in the way<lb/>
of sanitation on the Isthmus. Of course it would be more<lb/>
satisfactory, if things run smoothly, to demonstrate it for<lb/>
another year, but I feel pretty &ldquo;cockey&rdquo;. I certainly will<lb/>
not stand any such siege in the coming year as I went through<lb/>
during the last.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06206008"/>
<p>9:-</p>
<p>Now I think I have covered all the ground I started<lb/>
in to do. It is a legal holiday and still, the martyr to<lb/>
duty that I am, I got up this morning, rode through chaparelle<lb/>
12 miles to discuss with an engineer the non- advisability<lb/>
of locating a hotel in a swamp; got back for breakfast, came<lb/>
down to the office and have been writing this letter ever since.<lb/>
I feel better. I feel as though I had let off considerable<lb/>
steam, and so I come to the real gist of the letter with more<lb/>
pleasure, that is to urge you to come along down, come right<lb/>
to my house, and I will give you a good room and we will take<lb/>
you into our mess. There are several things I would like<lb/>
to talk to you about.</p>
<p>Please remember <add>me</add> most cordially to all in the office,<lb/>
Gen. O'Reilly and Mrs. Kean.</p>
<p>Mrs. Gorgas' health has been making rapid improvement.<lb/>
In her last letter she thought she might sail from New York<lb/>
about April 25th. Maybe you and she can come down in the same<lb/>
steamer.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely your friend,</salute>
<signed>W. C. Gorgas.<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer</signed>.
Letter dated Apr- 20 -<lb/>
C.A.L. Reed<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
