<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06216001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Howard A. Kelly, August 16, 1906</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06216001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1906-08-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kelly, Howard A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Gilman, [Daniel Coit?]</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1906-08-16">August 16, 1906</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06216001</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Howard A. Kelly, August 16, 1906</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean argues that Carroll deserves more recognition for his service. The last page includes Kelly's reply, dated September 10, 1906. Kelly writes that he will help to secure cooperation of Congressmen and write an article in support of Congressional action on behalf of the survivors and their families.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1906-08-16">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Howard A. Kelly, August 16, 1906</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06216001"/>
<p>WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
WASHINGTON.<lb/>
<date value="1906-08-16">August 16, 1906.</date>
My dear Dr. Kelly:</p>
<p>I was very glad to get your letter of July 25th, and note with special in-<lb/>
terest what you have to say about Dr. Carroll. I know that he feels that he has not<lb/>
gotten the reward which should have come to him for his work in Cuba, and in this I<lb/>
entirely agree with him, and I am very glad to know that you are taking an interest<lb/>
in the matter. There were difficulties in the way of his getting promotion in 1902<lb/>
when Gorgas got his and Reed would have gotten his but for his untimely death. These<lb/>
difficulties Carroll does not, I think, appreciate, but the Surgeon General stands<lb/>
ready to help him when a suitable opportunity presents itself. I believe that such<lb/>
opportunity has presented itself this morning and that you are responsible for it.</p>
<p>There was a review of your book in the Outlook for August 11th which, while<lb/>
it was a little mixed scientifically between malaria and yellow fever, was strongly<lb/>
written and entirely to the point as regards the rewards which should come to the men<lb/>
who did this work. It is called &ldquo;The Republic's Forgetfulness&rdquo;. The Secretary of<lb/>
the President has written to say that the President desired a report from the Surgeon<lb/>
General on the subject, and the Surgeon General has directed me to draw it up, so that<lb/>
I hope next winter we can do something for Carroll.</p>
<p>The main thing about the passage of these private bills is to have one man<lb/>
in each House who is sincerely interested. You must, in your large professional and<lb/>
personal contact with men, meet a number of Congressmen. If you can get some of them<lb/>
interested in this matter, you will immensely facilitate the passage of this bill.</p>
<p>I think that the Surgeon General will recommend that Carroll be made a major,<lb/>
and that Congress be asked to appropriate the money for a statue for Reed.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06216002"/>
-2-<lb/>
If Congress erects a statue, as they should, this will leave The Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
free to establish a scholarship or do something else in perpetuation of his memory.<lb/>
I think that your book is going to be a powerful stimulus to the completion of the<lb/>
Memorial Fund. I am exceedingly anxious to see it completed because I am in a po-<lb/>
sition to know that Mrs. Reed needs the interest on the fund in order to enable her<lb/>
to hold on to her little place, which was the strongest of Reed's local attachments,<lb/>
and every foot of which is associated with him.</p>
<p>Very sincerely yours,<lb/>
J. R. Kean-</p>
<p>Howard A. Kelly, M. D.,<lb/>
Indian Point, Parry Sound District<lb/>
via Brooks Falls,<lb/>
Ontario, Canada.<lb/>
<date value="1906-09-10">Sept. 10, 1906.</date>
Dear Major Kean,--</p>
<p>I trust matters are moving<lb/>
along in Carroll's interest. I will take<lb/>
active steps <unclear>to</unclear> secure the friendly co-<lb/>
operation of a representative and a member<lb/>
of the Senate, when you tell me the bill<lb/>
needs farthering, on my return from Aberdeen.<lb/>
I am going over to represent the Johns Hopkins<lb/>
University at the four hundredth anniversary<lb/>
celebration. I am glad the President is taking<lb/>
the matter up. I hear on all sides of renewed<lb/>
interest in the fund, and cannot think that<lb/>
it will be long before it is completed. A good<lb/>
many people have written to me, others to<lb/>
Pres. Gilman, and a number curiously enough<lb/>
to the McClures, to know to whom to send<lb/>
a subscription.</p>
<p>The Outlook review was a very kind one,<lb/>
was it not?</p>
<p>I am going to try to write a popular<lb/>
article on the subject for one of the Magazines,<lb/>
on my way over.</p>
<p>I <unclear>shall</unclear> be back by <unclear>Oct. 15th</unclear></p>
<p>H.A.K.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
