<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06225001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 2, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06225001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-03-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Thomas, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Magoon, Robert E.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Louise Young</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama City (Panama)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-03-02">March 2, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06225001</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 2, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas is convinced that mosquito eradication is the only method to keep yellow fever from developing into an epidemic.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1908-03-02">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 2, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06225001"/>
<opener>
Col. Gorgas letter<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
<hi>Copy</hi><lb/>
10<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1908-03-02">March, 2nd. 1908.</date>
</dateline>
Major Jefferson R. Kean,<lb/>
Adviser to the Sanitary Department,<lb/>
Havana, Cuba.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yours of February 20th just received. I generally read<lb/>
everything I can get hold of about you and your work in Cuba but<lb/>
I had overlooked you letter in the Journal. I have just gotten<lb/>
it out of our library and read your letter.</p>
<p>In your letter of transmittal you make a very clear statement<lb/>
of the difficulties under which you labor. The greatest of<lb/>
these, as far as Yellow Fever is concerned, seems to me the<lb/>
wide spread character of the infection in the country districts,<lb/>
and the large number of non-immunes with which you have to deal.</p>
<p>During my stay in Cuba I do not recollect that the fever<lb/>
was at all spread, and there seemed to be none in the country<lb/>
districts, or in the small towns or plantations. Toward the<lb/>
latter part of 1901 the suburbs of Havana, <del>Los Ba&ntilde;os-Las-Vega</del>s,<lb/>
Santiago de las Vegas San Antonio de los Ba&ntilde;os etc., became<lb/>
pretty sharply infected. This was probably due to the fact that<lb/>
the non-immune immigrants, who had been coming in since 1898 at<lb/>
the rate of twenty thousand per year, were numerous enough<lb/>
there to keep up the disease.</p>
<p>I have never been entirely prepared to accept the theory<lb/>
that the inhabitant of an infected locality gets his immunity<lb/>
because he had a light attack in childhood. It is a very<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06225002"/>
-2-<lb/>
reasonable and plausible theory but I have never understood how,<lb/>
if three or four thousand children were having Yellow Fever in<lb/>
Havana every year, we could have gotten rid of it as we did in<lb/>
1901.</p>
<p>My experience down here has lead me to believe that the<lb/>
great and all important factor in fighting Yellow Fever is to decrease<lb/>
the number of Stegomyia, and until you reduce the stegomyia below<lb/>
a certain point Yellow Fever is bound to spread if introduced; and<lb/>
that when you reduce them below a certain point, Yellow Fever will<lb/>
not spread no matter how much it is introduced.</p>
<p>Now in 1901 when we commenced stegomyia work, we did so with<lb/>
a well organized Department in which all that was necessary was<lb/>
to give the order and the work went rapidly ahead. By September<lb/>
we had gotten the stegomyia below the Yellow Fever point, and<lb/>
though we were getting Yellow Fever cases in all the time from the<lb/>
surrounding towns, it could not develop in Havana.</p>
<p>Now this may be the same with regard to children. When you<lb/>
get the stegomyia below the Yellow Fever point, even if you are<lb/>
having Yellow Fever among children at the rate of four or five<lb/>
thousand cases per year; children will cease to have it.</p>
<p>When I left Havana I was inclined to think that the all<lb/>
important point was isolation of the sick and the killing of the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes. When we came down here, owing to the difficulties<lb/>
in getting ourselves organized, getting supplies, want of support<lb/>
from my superiors and constant and direct interference from them,<lb/>
I was unable to get <unclear>effective</unclear> stegomyia work organized.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06225003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>Owing to the fact that I looked upon the destruction of the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes as the all important point, I concentrated<lb/>
everything upon getting this branch of the work in an efficient<lb/>
condition. From the beginning of 1905 the fumigation and isolation<lb/>
of the sick was efficiently and thoroughly done, much more generally,<lb/>
I think, that has ever been done anywhere else. The whole city<lb/>
of Panama every house in it was fumigated three or four times, but<lb/>
Yellow Fever did not begin to decline until the fall, and finally<lb/>
disappeared in December 1905.</p>
<p>We got to work in Panama at systematic stegomyia work about<lb/>
the first of March that year. Where you have a general infection<lb/>
with infected mosquitoes all about the city, no system of fumigation<lb/>
can kill them all. There must be a certain number everywhere that<lb/>
escape death from fumigation in parts of buildings that cannot be<lb/>
thoroughly fumigated, and these will always keep up the disease if<lb/>
you rely upon fumigation alone. You can get rid of the stegomyia<lb/>
with continuous and systematic work, but, it takes time.</p>
<p>I suppose that there is always the liability of a particular<lb/>
house for a time getting above the Yellow Fever mark with its<lb/>
stegomyia, and if a case happens to get into this house at this<lb/>
time you would have a local infection, just as you would in a ship,<lb/>
but such local infection would be easily controlled if your general<lb/>
stegomyia work were good.</p>
<p>I believe that we now have on the Isthmus every where the<lb/>
stegomyia below the Yellow Fever mark, and that we could drop our<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06225004"/>
-4-<lb/>
quarantines and let Yellow Fever in freely without any spread of<lb/>
the disease. Havana, too, I presume is in this condition.</p>
<p>In 1901 we admitted into Havana from infected points some<lb/>
twelve hundred non-immunes under observation, and picked up from<lb/>
these non-immunes some thirty or forty cases of Yellow Fever. The<lb/>
only explanation I can give as to why the disease was not kept up<lb/>
by this importation is the fact that the stegomyia were below the<lb/>
Yellow Fever point. There must have been many mild cases among<lb/>
so many non-immunes that we did not get hold of. This is the<lb/>
Gorgas theory of the spread of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>I am inclined to think now that if you and I took two cities<lb/>
of the same size, of same general conditions, and you went into<lb/>
one and put in vogue all our present methods, and I went into<lb/>
the other and did not do a bit of fumigation, isolating the sick,<lb/>
or have a quarantine, did nothing but stegomyia work, I would get<lb/>
rid of the Yellow Fever as soon as you would, or possibly a little<lb/>
sooner, as I would probably devote more attention to the stegomyia<lb/>
work that you would.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if you did no stegomyia work or did it<lb/>
so imperfectly that the stegomyia would remain above the Yellow<lb/>
Fever mark, you would never get rid of Yellow Fever if you<lb/>
worked at it a life-time, granting that these cities were in the<lb/>
Tropics as Panama is.</p>
<p>You speak of using canvas more and more in your fumigations.<lb/>
I presume you mean in fumigating huts, and buildings of that kind,<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06225005"/>
-5-<lb/>
and that you draw the canvas over the entire building. We use<lb/>
manilla paper, generally, for closing windows and doors; canvas<lb/>
might be cheaper for this purpose as you could use it so many<lb/>
times. Paper cannot in general be used more than once.</p>
<p>I look upon pyrethrum as one of the best insecticides in<lb/>
municipal fumigating. It is so much less hurtful to the contents<lb/>
of the building, than is sulphur, and I would rather use a less<lb/>
efficient material and have the co-operation of the people concerned<lb/>
than to use amore effective insecticide and get their opposition.</p>
<p>We went into the question of the efficiency of pyrethrum in<lb/>
our laboratory here quite extensively and found that when pyre-<lb/>
thrum was carefully selected it answered our purposes very well.<lb/>
I do not recollect Dr. Thomas' <del>proof</del><add>paper</add> here with regard to pyrethrum;<lb/>
he probably convinced himself but not us.</p>
<p>We use toward the latter part of our fumigations a carbolic-<lb/>
camphor mixture, which is a very fatal insecticide, more so that<lb/>
pyrethrum, but it is very inflammable. I think however that in<lb/>
future fumigations, I would depend upon the carbolic -camphor<lb/>
mixture for fumigating the better class of houses rather than<lb/>
pyrethrum.</p>
<p>We finally insisted upon getting only the Parke, Davis Company<lb/>
insect powder. The pyrethrum bought in the open market was<lb/>
found to be unreliable.</p>
<p>I understand what a very hard proposition you have had to<lb/>
tackle with the whole island full of non-immunes and foci of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06225006"/>
-6-<lb/>
Yellow Fever all over the country districts. But so much more the<lb/>
glory when you lay aside your shield and spear and take your<lb/>
&ldquo;otium cum dignatate&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Your great work in Cuba, it seems to me, will be the sanitary<lb/>
organization which you have built up. It is unique, and as far as<lb/>
I know, there is no such organization anywhere else, where the<lb/>
national and municipal sanitation are brought together, the<lb/>
maritime quarantines and public charities, all in one department,<lb/>
and the Head of the Department a Member of the Cabinet. I presume<lb/>
this is due to your eloquence with Magoon, for when he left here<lb/>
his ideas were entirely in the other direction.</p>
<p>The liberties with your name were taken by the Washington<lb/>
Office and not by ourselves. We know you better, they hear of<lb/>
you probably only through your relentless persecution of the poor<lb/>
Cubana and, therefore, think it ought to be rather Jackson than<lb/>
Jefferson.</p>
<p>Mrs. Gorgas joins me in kindest regards to both your-<lb/>
self and Mrs. Kean.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>(Sgd) W.C. GORGAS</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
