<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY t06242036 SYSTEM "t06242036.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="t06242020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Lecture: Sanitation Work in Cuba, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 23, 1912</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06242020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1912-05-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Glennan, A. H.</name>
<name type="person">Taft, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Estrada Palma, Tomas</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Cienfuegos (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>17 pp.</extent>
<date value="1912-05-23">May 23, 1912</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06242020</idno>
<title>Lecture: Sanitation Work in Cuba, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 23, 1912</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses the sanitation efforts used to prevent yellow fever in Cuba from 1906 to 1909. [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1912-05-23">
<head>Lecture: Sanitation Work in Cuba, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 23, 1912</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06242020"/>
<p>Keans lecture at Army Med. School<lb/>
May 23, 1912<lb/>
Sanitation in Cuba.</p>
<p>1</p>
<p>SECOND INTERVENTION IN CUBA OCT. 1, 1906 to Jan. 29, 1909:</p>
<p>As has been mentioned in speaking of the sanitary work of the 1st<lb/>
Intervention, it was performed by a number of independent sanitary workers<lb/>
acting under the different local military authorities but without the<lb/>
assistance and unity of effort which would have been afforded by a central<lb/>
sanitary organization. This work, although without uniformity of method<lb/>
or coherence of organization, was so well done that it was apparently<lb/>
not reali<unclear>[unclear]</unclear>ntil the end of the American Military Government of Inter-<lb/>
vention was in sight and the date of May 20, 1902, had been fixed for<lb/>
the establishment of the Cuban Republic that a sanitary department would be<lb/>
necessary for the Cuban Government in order to maintain good health con-<lb/>
ditions and carry out its obligations as regards sanitation which were<lb/>
imposed upon <add>it by</add> the United States in the Platt amendment to the Cuban con-<lb/>
stitution. Accordingly, General Wood, as well as I recall, early in<lb/>
May, organized a Commission which was instructed to draw up a sanitary<lb/>
law organizing a national department of health and describing its powers.<lb/>
This commission was composed of Col. Gorgas and myself, both of us being<lb/>
then Majors; Dr. A. H. Glennan of the Marine Hospital Service, and</p>
<p>The sanitary law prepared by this commission was published as Orders No.<lb/>
159, Hdqrs. Dept. of Cuba, Havana, May 17, 1902, three days before the<lb/>
withdrawal of the American Government and the establishment of the Cuban<lb/>
Republic. It provided for a superior sanitary board composed of five<lb/>
active members and six honorary members, which latter were the chief<lb/>
of the Marine Hospital Service of the Island, a member of the Academy of<lb/>
Sciences of Havana, a member of the faculty of the University of Havana,<lb/>
president of the tuberculosis league, a member of the board of education,<lb/>
and a legally qualified lawyer. The honorary members of the board were<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06242021"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
2<lb/>
not entitle to vote. The president and executive officer of the board<lb/>
was the chief sanitary officer of the Island. This board had general su-<lb/>
pervision of all health matters throughout the island and was charged with<lb/>
making sanitary investigations, the publication of useful information on<lb/>
sanitary subjects, the enforcement of sanitary laws including laws regulat-<lb/>
ing the practice of the medical profession, pharmacy, dentistry, midwifery,<lb/>
embalming and laws regulating prostitution, and for the control of offen-<lb/>
sive and dangerous trades. It had also supervision of all local boards of<lb/>
health and a general supervisory authority known in the Spanish law as<lb/>
&ldquo;alta inspeccion&rdquo; over all eleemosynary institutions, prisons, hospitals,<lb/>
and other public institutions. It was charged with the collection of vital<lb/>
statistics, the control of epidemic diseases, of interior quarantine regu-<lb/>
lations, the establishment and administration of biological, chemical and<lb/>
bacteriological laboratories, and the enforcement of vaccination.</p>
<p>I urged strongly the importance of making sanitation a separate depart-<lb/>
ment with representation in the cabinet, but Ceneral Wood was averse to an<lb/>
enlargement of the cabinet, and it was made a subordinate bureau under the<lb/>
Secretaryship of Gubernacion, in which my former department of Beneficencia<lb/>
or Charities was another bureau. Another point which I urged was the logi-<lb/>
cal appropriateness and administrative advantage of having marine quaran-<lb/>
tine placed under the Sanitary Department, but the Marine Hospital Service<lb/>
of the United States was opposed to this and its representative on the board<lb/>
Dr. Glennan, successfully opposed it, and it was left under the Treasury, as<lb/>
in the United States. <hi>Cuba was destined to pay dearly for this in 1905 when<lb/>
by lack of co-ordination between these two lines of sanitary defence yellow<lb/>
fever was re-introduced into Havana from New Orleans</hi>.</p>
<p>It took nearly two years for this organization to become effective and<lb/>
to prepare its sanitary code, which was a very elaborate one, based on Euro-<lb/>
pean models and quite unsuited to small towns and rural communities. The<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06242022"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
3<lb/>
small towns suffered much more from sanitary neglects than did Havana be-<lb/>
cause for the latter money was furnished by the national government, while<lb/>
local boards of health in the small towns had to depend upon the entirely<lb/>
inadequate appropriations of town councils and were submissive to political<lb/>
and personal influences of every kind. Thus the extensive powers given by<lb/>
the decree of General Wood to the national board existed without the neces-<lb/>
sary machinery by which these powers could be administered, operating as<lb/>
the board was compelled to do through the local boards of health, over<lb/>
whose personnel and finances the central authority had but nominal control.</p>
<p>The Cuban territory is divided into municipalities, each of which<lb/>
embraces a certain geographical area, both urban and rural. Each of these<lb/>
municipalities is governed by a town council or Ayuntamiento and for each<lb/>
of these municipalities was provided a local sanitary board of three mem-<lb/>
bers. These local boards were governed by general sanitary regulations<lb/>
adopted by the superior sanitary board and had general supervision of all<lb/>
health matters of the municipality. The funds needed for the sanitary<lb/>
services of the cities and of the other sanitary activities of the local<lb/>
boards were to be provided by appropriations by the municipalities, ex-<lb/>
cept in the case of Havana where the national government supported the<lb/>
local sanitary establishment which was immediately under the chief sani-<lb/>
tary officer. The Ayuntamientos, much like the majority of town councils<lb/>
in the United States, had other objects upon which to spend their money<lb/>
in which they took much greater interest than in sanitary matters and<lb/>
therefore the sanitary activities in the Cuban cities other than Havana<lb/>
practically ceased after General Wood's departure from the Island, except<lb/>
in the capital and except for the stimulus of occasional appropriations<lb/>
from the national government for sanitary work in the other larger towns<lb/>
when conditions became very bad or yellow fever made its appearance. The<lb/>
national board, however, accomplished much excellent work under the presi-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06242023"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
4<lb/>
dency of Estrada Palma, although after the manner of all boards it was a<lb/>
defective administrative agency.</p>
<p>A successful insurrection in August, 1906, compelled Estrada Palma<lb/>
to call on the United States to intervene in accordance with our treaty<lb/>
right and the Secretary of War, Mr. Taft, landed and assumed the reins of<lb/>
government Sept. 20, 1906. He cabled for me to report to him at once and<lb/>
placed me in <hi>general supervisory charge of the sanitary department</hi>. Being<lb/>
mindful of the importance of a right start I said &ldquo;Shall I report to you<lb/>
direct, Mr. Secretary&rdquo;, and as he hesitated I added &ldquo;in the former inter-<lb/>
<hi>vention <del>I</del><add>Gorgas</add> reported directly to General Wood&rdquo;</hi>. He said the precious &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;<lb/>
which established the independence of sanitation for the time being and I<lb/>
took my way to the <hi>familiar old Maestranza de Artilleria, where both Gorgas</hi><lb/>
and <hi>I had had our offices in the first intervention</hi>. There I found the<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer, my old and dear friend <hi>Dr. Carlos Finley</hi>, the ori-<lb/>
ginal champion of the mosquito theory<add>,</add> to whom I imparted my commission and<lb/>
handed the Secretary's brief note. <hi>After greeting me with that exquisite</hi><lb/>
courtesy which is one of the strongest characteristics of this fine old<lb/>
man he asked me what were my powers. I told him that I conceived them to<lb/>
be those <hi>of a cabinet secretary</hi>. Then he asked what would be my title. -<lb/>
There I was stumped and I asked him for a suggestion. - &ldquo;I am directed by<lb/>
the Secretary&rdquo;, said he, &ldquo;to follow your advice in all things so how would<lb/>
<hi>the title of Adviser do</hi>.&rdquo; This seemed fitting and not only did I keep it<lb/>
during the entire intervention but all the other Army officers and civilians<lb/>
who were placed at the head of the other departments of the governments were<lb/>
also given the title of Adviser instead of that of Secretary.</p>
<p>I found Gorgas' organization in the City of Havana largely intact,<lb/>
but it had evidently lost its discipline in the four years of immunity from<lb/>
yellow fever, and although yellow fever had for the last year been present,<lb/>
in the island, it had been unable to regain its discipline and effectiveness.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f06242024"/>
<p>- 5 -<lb/>
5</p>
<p>3 Proceeding Screening<lb/>
Killing infected mosquito.<lb/>
mosquito <unclear>prevention</unclear></p>
<p><del>There were 20 sanitary inspectors whose work was reinforced by a hord of un-<lb/>
instructed and ignorant laborers who wandered about the city with oil cans<lb/>
pouring petroleum into every rat hole and puddle.</del></p>
<p>The chief confidence of Drs. Finlay and <del>Gorgas</del><add>Guiteras</add> was placed in the divi-<lb/>
sion of disinfection where there was a large and well-trained force of men<lb/>
conducting fumigations. The operation of this brigade I made little change<lb/>
in, although in my opinion the importance of their work was entirely secon-<lb/>
dary to mosquito prevention. The division of sanitary inspection, La Prince's<lb/>
old organization, which did the house inspections for mosquito larvae, I found<lb/>
much disorganized and its shortcomings, which had quite escaped the notice<lb/>
of the sanitary authorities of Havana, were directly responsible for the<lb/>
infection being able to take root again. To it, therefore, I gave my close<lb/>
and unremitting attention. <add>There were 20 sanitary inspectors whose work was reinforced by a hord of un-<lb/>
instructed and ignorant laborers who wandered about the city with oil cans<lb/>
pouring petroleum into every rat hole and puddle.</add> The number of district inspectors was promptly<lb/>
increased to 42, one for every sanitary district into which I divided the<lb/>
city, while there were a number of auxillary inspectors who could be thrown<lb/>
into districts which required special attention. Each district inspector<lb/>
was informed that he would be held to strict accountability for the condi-<lb/>
tion of his district and this responsibility was emphasized by the summary<lb/>
dismissal of those who were found negligent. The inspectors were given<lb/>
credentials and a neat uniform which enabled the house-holders to distin-<lb/>
guish them from irresponsible persons and which also enabled the super-<lb/>
vising inspectors whom I placed over groups of districts to readily observe<lb/>
those who showed a disposition to sit in the cafes rather than search for<lb/>
stegomyia larvae.</p>
<p>By the next spring the mosquito work was well in hand in the city, the<lb/>
stegomyias were very scarce, and cases only appeared sporadically at<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06242025"/>
6<lb/>
<del>15.</del><lb/>
<del>-4</del><lb/>
sufficient intervals to furnish an excuse for maintaining quarantines on<lb/>
the part of the United States. The disease was continually reintroduced into<lb/>
Havana from the country districts, but I made no effort to prevent this be-<lb/>
cause the coming of patients to the great public hospitals of the city where<lb/>
they were kept in screened rooms often gave me the first intimation of the<lb/>
development of the new foci in the country and small towns. I was perfectly<lb/>
confident of my ability to prevent an epidemic in Havana, although it was full<lb/>
of non-immunes</p>
<p>Another peculiarity of this invasion or yellow fever, for it was<lb/>
never generally epidemic, was the small number of cases that occurred<lb/>
and the remarkable way in which they were spread over the period of<lb/>
three years and three months between the appearance of the disease in<lb/>
Havana in October, 1905, and the final occurrence of the last cases in<lb/>
the province of Oriente in the neighborhood of Santiago in the fall of<lb/>
1908. The entire number of cases during all this time was only 359.<lb/>
This number is made up of a number of scattered cases throughout the<lb/>
island, together with several small localized epidemics such as that in<lb/>
Havana in November and December, 1905, that in the towns in the south-<lb/>
east part of the Province of Havana in 1906, an outbreak in Cienfuegos<lb/>
in the summer of 1907, and one in the iron mines of Darquiri in 1909.<lb/>
Contrast this with the disease in Havana in 1900, when there were 1240<lb/>
cases and 305 deaths. The efforts of the sanitary department invar-<lb/>
iably brought each outbreak to a close with the exception of an occasional<lb/>
sporadic case as soon as a local organization could be effected and the<lb/>
number of mosquitoes reduced to a point which Gorgas called &ldquo;the yellow<lb/>
fever point.&rdquo; Now please observe that as soon as the mosquito reduc-<lb/>
tion reached this point in Havana in 1901 yellow fever disappeared not<lb/>
only from Havana but from all of Cuba, whereas no such good fortune at-<lb/>
tended the mosquito work in Havana in 1907.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06242026"/>
<p>7</p>
<p><unclear>&check; u 4&frac12;</unclear></p>
<p>The disease spread, however, during the year to every province in the<lb/>
island with the exception of the most western, but was promptly stamped out in<lb/>
the larger cities with the exception of Cienfuegos where a sharp epidemic oc-<lb/>
curred in the fall of 1907, and Santiago where the infection smouldered until<lb/>
the spring of 1908. Conquared in the centers of population, the disease<lb/>
adopted the tactics of the revolutionists and took to the woods and this ex-<lb/>
tension to the <del>woods</del><add>villages</add> and plantations broughtup new and troublesome problems<lb/>
which were not known to the first Intervention.</p>
<p>It was certain that the work against yellow fever in Cuba was equally<lb/>
thorough in detail and on a wider scale than that conducted in Havana and the<lb/>
other more important cities in 1901. Why was it not followed by the same<lb/>
prompt success? <add>in 1907</add> and why did not yellow fever at that time hang on in<lb/>
the rural districts? The disease having been so long endemic in Cuba<lb/>
the native Cuban population was then truely an immune one, and yellow<lb/>
fever rarely prevailed in Cuba, but lay in wait in the sea ports for the<lb/>
none- immune immigrants who were as a rule not long in finding either<lb/>
immunity or death. But since 1900 this process had been checked, and<lb/>
the non-immune population of Cuba had increased with great rapidity. <hi>The<lb/>
number of immigrants, chiefly Spania<add>r</add>ds, had averaged nearly 30,000</hi> a year<lb/>
and in the last two years amount<add>ed</add> to 88,000. The native white population<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06242027"/>
8<lb/>
<add>had also increased with great rapidity &amp; if we accept the theory of Guiteras that<lb/>
the white Cuban Child is born non-immune, this still greater source of supply of<lb/>
non-immunes must be added - amounting to 7800 annually for Habana and<lb/>
66,500 for the Island</add>.</p>
<p><unclear>G</unclear></p>
<p>Here I might allude to the well <hi>known theory of Guiteras as</hi> to<lb/>
the immunity of Cuban children which <hi>is now generally accepted</hi>, although<lb/>
when it was first announced it was much disputed by Cuban physicians.<lb/>
It is simply that immunity to yellow fever is acquired by Cuban children<lb/>
in the same way that immunity to other diseases is acquired by most people<lb/>
to the ordinary childrens diseases, viz: by an attack in infancy, this<lb/>
attack being usually mild and not recognized as yellow fever but being<lb/>
disguised under such diagnoses as dengue, malaria, or calentura.<lb/>
Even the severe attacks marked by jaundice, black vomit, and even death,<lb/>
were not formerly diagnosed as yellow fever by Cuban physicians so con-<lb/>
vinced were they that by some heaven bestowed gift the Cuban children<lb/>
were immune to it and so such cases were habitually diagnosed as feibre<lb/>
de borras. The only difficulty in the way of acceptance of this theory,<lb/>
and it always appeared to me a very real one, is the fact that this would<lb/>
have required an enormous number of cases every year to keep up the<lb/>
immunity of the Cuban people. In commenting upon an outbreak of 400<lb/>
cases of fever which occurred in October at Columbia Barracks and which<lb/>
the medical officer, Dr. <add>Saleeby?</add> Salene, who made a report of the epidemic, was<lb/>
inclined to consider yellow fever, I made the following remarks:-</p>
<p>Saleeby</p>
<p>&ldquo;The short mild continued fever of about a week's duration<lb/>
with a descending temperature curve from the first or second day, is<lb/>
an old acquintance. Whether this is an acclimatizing, i.e., a very<lb/>
mild sporadic form of yellow fever, is an interesting and important<lb/>
subject for investigation. Dr. H.R.Carter, Marine-Hospital Service,<lb/>
recently in conversation advanced the following facts, which are sug-<lb/>
gestive in this connection: All quarantine authorities agree that ten<lb/>
years' residence in Havana entitles a man to be considered immune; that<lb/>
is, that in that time he will certainly have had yellow fever or an<lb/>
immunizing fever. The Spanish immigration -nonmilitary - for years past<lb/>
has been on an average 15,000 a year. Of these, by a moderate estimate,<lb/>
5,000 make their home in Havana. Approximately 5,000 children are born<lb/>
in Havana each year. Supposing that half of these die before they<lb/>
reach the age of 10, we have 2,500 a year to acquire immunity in the same<lb/>
way that the Spaniards do. Thus we should have 7,500 cases a year of<lb/>
immunizing (yellow) fever. The average annual civilian death rate in<lb/>
Havana from yellow fever is 210, which, with a death rate of, say,<lb/>
30 per cent, would give 700 cases of clinically recognized yellow fever<lb/>
a year. Thus we would have left 6,800 persons a year who acquire<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06242028"/>
9<lb/>
<del>-2-</del><lb/>
immunity through fevers not to be recognized as yellow fever in the<lb/>
home of that disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the five years between the two outbreaks some 350,000 children<lb/>
had been born in Cuba and about 38,000 in Havana, and as this<lb/>
element would then constitute probably the largest non-immune element<lb/>
in the Island, it should have furnished most of the cases of yellow<lb/>
fever, but on the contrary I do not recall more than three cases in<lb/>
children during the second intervention. This is a phenomenon for<lb/>
which I have no explanation which it is at all satisfactory and when I<lb/>
was <hi>asked if I accepted Guiteras' theory I would say that I believed<lb/>
it on Monday, Wednesday and Friday, but rejected it on Tuesday, Thurs-<lb/>
day and Saturday</hi>. Sundays I <unclear>deliused</unclear> to think of it.</p>
<pb n="10" id="f06242029"/>
<p><del>16</del><lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear><lb/>
10</p>
<p><del>had also increased with great rapidity and if we accept the doctrine of<lb/>
Guiteras that the white Cuban child is born non-immune, this still greater<lb/>
source of supply of non-immunes must be added. The birth rate of Cuba being<lb/>
66,500, would <unclear>and</unclear> that many non-immune children to the population.</del></p>
<p>The number of non-immunes had already become sufficient to support a<lb/>
yellow fever epidemic in alsmot any town or large plantation in the island,<lb/>
and the increase of the facilities for communication by rail and by the con-<lb/>
struction of good public roads, together with the migratory habits of the<lb/>
Spanish laborers furnish a ready means for the distribution of the infection,<lb/>
which means existed to a far less degree in 1901. The sanitary forces had<lb/>
to pursue the enemy into the country and whereever a case of yellow fever was<lb/>
recognized, expert diagnostitions and brigades of men trained in the technique<lb/>
of fumigation and mosquito work were went from Havana to conduct operations<lb/>
against the enemy. These methods kept the infection from assuming great pre0<lb/>
portions but failed promptly to extinguish it <add>in 1907</add>. The reasons for this failure<lb/>
were two, the first was the lack of agencies for the discovering and reporting<lb/>
of cases outside of the large cities, the second, the lack of trained men to<lb/>
carry out carefully, conscientiously and thoroughly, the work of mosquito pre-<lb/>
vention. <del>No this</del><add>in the small times</add></p>
<p>Nothing is more difficult than the recognition of mild cases of yellow<lb/>
fever. Cases constantly occurred in Havana which puzzled the board of diagnosis,<lb/>
probably the most expert body in the knowledge of this disease in the world.<lb/>
Also it must be borne in mind that a large proportion of cases and, probably in<lb/>
Cuban children a very large majority, are mild, and so difficult or impossible<lb/>
of diagnosis with the help of all the resources of medical art. In the rural<lb/>
municipalities little attention was paid to mild attacks of fever and the<lb/>
physicians were not accustomed to employ the diagnostic aids of urinalisis and<lb/>
blood examination, and had neither the apparatus nor the technical training for<lb/>
so doing. Therefore, only the minority of grave or fatal cases were necognized<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06242030"/>
17&sol;<lb/>
<del>-6-</del><lb/>
11<lb/>
and reported, and the infection spread unchecked by preventive measures until<lb/>
a death gave the alarm. While the sanitary department could send trained<lb/>
parties to direct works of fumigation in recognized foci, the fundamental<lb/>
work of mosquito prevention required permanent garrisons of trained men in<lb/>
every town and village and even in the great sugar and tobaco plantations.</p>
<p>Such a plan of campaign can be conducted where the area is small<lb/>
and the pecuniary resources practically unlimited as in the strip ten miles<lb/>
wide and fifty miles long which constitutes the canal zone at Panama, but<lb/>
it was of course out of the question to conduct such intensive methods<lb/>
over the 44 000 square miles of Cuban territory, and was far beyond the<lb/>
resources of the Cuban Treasury. I <del>have</del> had, therefore, to limit my<lb/>
campaign of mosquito prevention to municipalities where yellow fever had<lb/>
appeared until a new and more prefect and centralized sanitary organization<lb/>
gave <del>me</del> the central department immediate control over all the sanitary agen-<lb/>
cies of the Island. <add>This reorganization will be described later.</add><lb/>
<add>c&rang; Here might be mentioned a controversy with the <unclear>Quarantine authorities</unclear> of U.S.</add></p>
<p>This was affected by the complete reorganization of the sanitary de-<lb/>
partment from top to bottom, which was affected by Governor Magoon's decree<lb/>
#894, signed August 26, 1907. The objects accomplished by this decree were:</p>
<p>1 - The abolition of the local and municipal boards of health and<lb/>
the transfer of all powers previously vested in them to national officials<lb/>
called local sanitary officers who are appointed by the President.</p>
<p>2 - The assumption by the state of the cost of all municipal works<lb/>
and service such as street cleaning, the removal of garbage, the suppression<lb/>
of nuisances, and the prevention of epidemics. To relieve in some measure<lb/>
the burden upon the national treasury it is required that the municipal<lb/>
government should refund to the state one-tenth of their total incomes for<lb/>
each year in part payment for these sanitary services.</p>
<p>3 - The supreme administrative authority in the sanitary department<lb/>
<add>a&rang; See Doc. &ldquo;Quarantine against yellow fever in Cuba&rdquo; p. 20 et seq.</add><lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06242031"/>
<del>18.<lb/>
-7-</del><lb/>
12<lb/>
was transferred from the national board of health where it formerly was vested<lb/>
to the chief sanitary officer who was made in fact the administrative authority<lb/>
of the sanitary department. The national board of health was retained in<lb/>
an advisory capacity.</p>
<p>By another decree the <add>Marine</add> quarantine service which constitutes the first<lb/>
line of national defense against epidemics was made an intergral part of the<lb/>
sanitary department, <del>a step which</del><add>as</add> I had strongly urged <del>in his law of</del> May,<lb/>
1902. &check;Finally the organization of the sanitary department was perfected<lb/>
and completed by joining to it the department of charities which has charge<lb/>
in Cuba of all the numerous public hospitals, the care of the insane, the<lb/>
responsibility for all dependent children and those who have been convicted<lb/>
of crime and <del>of all</del> in general of all elemosinary and charitable institu-<lb/>
tions and funds. This department called now &ldquo;The Direction of Beneficencia&rdquo;<lb/>
is joined with the Direction of Sanitation to make the Department of Sanita-<lb/>
tion and Charities, under a Secretary who is a Cabinet Officer.</p>
<p>Cases of Yellow Fever in Havana-<lb/>
See Chart-</p>
<pb n="13" id="f06242032"/>
<p><del>8&rang;</del><lb/>
13</p>
<p>The complete Department of Sanitation and Charities as shown by<lb/>
the diagram consists of the Direction of Sanitation<lb/>
Direction of Charities<lb/>
Board of Sanitation and Charities.</p>
<p>The Direccion of Sanitation is under a chief executive officer<lb/>
called the Director, which position is now filled by the well known<lb/>
yellow fever specialist, Dr. Juan Guiteras. It is divided into the<lb/>
following bureaus:-</p>
<p>(1) The Central Bureau, which has supervision over the sanitary<lb/>
services of all municipalities in the Republic, except Havana; of the<lb/>
various laboratories, bacteriological, chemical and bromological; of<lb/>
the hospitals for contagious diseases; of the sanitoria and dispensaries<lb/>
for tuberculosis; the vaccine stations, and the expert personnel of the<lb/>
Department.</p>
<p>(2) Bureau of Sanitary Services of Havana. This bureau con-<lb/>
tains complete the old sanitary organization of Gorgas with some addi-<lb/>
tions and its sphere of activity is limited as indicated by its name to<lb/>
the municipality of Havana, embracing a population of some 400,000 persons.</p>
<p>(3) General Affairs and Quarantine: This bureau has charge of<lb/>
regulations for the practice of the professions of medicine, veterinary<lb/>
medicine, pharmacy, dental surgery, obstetrics, embalming, undertakers,<lb/>
and the control of dangerous and noxious industries. One division of it<lb/>
also has charge of the marine quarantine service.</p>
<p>(4) Special Hygiene: This bureau has charge of matters connected<lb/>
with the control and regulation of prostitution and the prevention of<lb/>
venereal diseases in the cities of the Republic. This service of special<lb/>
hygiene as it is called is entirely self-supporting, receiving no appro-<lb/>
priation from the State, it is supported by fees which are required of<lb/>
prostitutes for the weekly physical examinations and by fines and taxes<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06242033"/>
<del>-2-</del><lb/>
14<lb/>
which are levied upon houses of prostitution or assignation. It<lb/>
supports lock-hospitals for the confinement and treatment of diseased<lb/>
public women and in Havana at least it supports free dispensaries where<lb/>
men may receive free treatment, day and night, for venereal diseases.</p>
<p>(5) Statistics and Correspondence. The duties of this bureau<lb/>
are suggested by its name. It is charged among other things with the<lb/>
collection and publication of the vital statistics of the Republic.</p>
<p>(6) Personnel, Property and Accounts. The functions of this<lb/>
bureau are indicated by its name, it being charged with the details of<lb/>
all the functions of the internal administration of the Department.</p>
<p>The Direccion of Charities is under a Director who is a superior<lb/>
chief of administration in the official hierarchy of Cuba and it is<lb/>
the Department of which I had charge during the last year of the 1st<lb/>
Intervention and upon which I am glad to believe that I left a certain<lb/>
impress in bringing it in line with the modern ideas of scientific<lb/>
charitable organization. It is divided into four bureaus:-</p>
<p>(1) Administration and Inspection: Charged with all matters<lb/>
relating to the administrative and legal affairs of charitable institu-<lb/>
tions. It has also charge of the correspondence of the Direccion.</p>
<p>(2) Hospitals and asylums. This bureau has charge of matters<lb/>
of a technical character pertaining to the hospitals, asylums, charitable<lb/>
institutions and schools for nurses.</p>
<p>(3) The Bureau of Minors is charged with the care and correction<lb/>
of destitute and delinquent children. It secures the adoption of<lb/>
orphans by private families and looks after their interests as long as<lb/>
they are minors.</p>
<p>(4) Personnel, Property and Accounts. Its functions are similar<lb/>
to those of the like bureau in the Direccion of Sanitation.</p>
<pb n="15" id="f06242034"/>
<p><del>-3-</del><lb/>
15</p>
<p>The National Board of Sanitation and Charities is organized as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>Director of Sanitation<lb/>
Director of Charities<lb/>
Chief of the Quarantine Service<lb/>
President of the Board of Infectious Diseases.<lb/>
Dean of the Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy of the University of Havana<lb/>
President of the League against Tuberculosis<lb/>
President of the Economic Society of Friends of the Country<lb/>
Local Chief of Sanitation of Havana<lb/>
President of the Special Hygiene Commission; and</p>
<p>Four additional members to be appointed freely by the President of<lb/>
the Republic, one of them to be a lawyer qualified to practice in the<lb/>
Republic, and another, a civil engineer.</p>
<p>The President of the Board shall be the Director of Sanitation,<lb/>
and the Director of Charities shall be Vice-President, and in the absence<lb/>
of both, the oldest member. The Chief Clerk of the Direccion of San-<lb/>
itation shall act as Secretary, in accordance with the provisions of<lb/>
article 298 of this law.</p>
<pb n="16" id="f06242035"/>
<p><del>9</del><lb/>
16</p>
<p>These changes and additions were all codified and published at the<lb/>
end of the second intervention as chapter 8 of title 3 of the organic<lb/>
law of the Executive Power, the organic act which states and defines the<lb/>
authority of all the different branches of the government. <unclear>[unclear]</unclear> Thus Cuba<lb/>
has obtained a goal in the matter of public health organization which<lb/>
we in the United States are still struggling for and which the American<lb/>
Public Health Medical Association, the Committee of One Hundred, and iin<lb/>
general all medical and socialogical associations are now <unclear>demanding</unclear> of<lb/>
Congress.<lb/>
<add><unclear>explain<lb/>
diagram</unclear></add></p>
<p>This legislation has already had its influence upon sanitary<lb/>
organization elsewhere. The essential feature of the substitution of<lb/>
sanitary officers for local sanitary boards has been adopted for the<lb/>
Sanitary Department of the Philippines and the entire law with but few<lb/>
changes has been recently enacted as the new sanitary law of Porto Rico.<lb/>
Within the last week I have been called upon to furnish a copy to the<lb/>
President, Board of Health of the State of Louisiana to be used as a model<lb/>
in the revision of their sanitary law.</p>
<p>J. R. Kean<lb/>
Lecture at Army Med. School May 23<lb/>
1912.</p>
<pb n="17" id="f06242036"/><lb/>
<p><figure entity="t06242036"></figure> Yellow Fever in Havana<lb/>
by months. See chart in Guiteras<lb/>
article in Boletin <unclear>form</unclear> 1. no 1. April 1909.<lb/>
<hi>Bound</hi> copy</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
