<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06246018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, December 7, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06246018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-12-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gorgas, William Crawford</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Petain, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Bradley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Andrew, A. P.</name>
<name type="person">Wrightson, Maj.</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Meaux (France)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-12-07">December 7, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06246018</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, December 7, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses logistical issues concerning supplies, assignments, and personnel in the Ambulance Corps.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-12-07">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, December 7, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06246018"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
FRANCE<lb/>
<date value="1917-12-07">December 7th, 1917.</date>
</dateline>
Major General W.C. Gorgas,<lb/>
Surgeon General,<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>There seems to be a fatality about our correspond-<lb/>
ence. Your letter of September 14th was not received until November<lb/>
5th, and yours of October 6th lingered by the wayside until November<lb/>
24th. Your last letter of November 2d did a little better, however,<lb/>
having arrived on December 4th.</p>
<p>In view of my experience with the volunteer sections,<lb/>
I can see that you are entirely right that I should not have bothered<lb/>
about trying to persuade them to come in and waste six weeks in ex-<lb/>
plaining and placating these spoiled children who thought that all<lb/>
should be officers, and should be put in command of the Allentown<lb/>
sections at once. If I had it to do over again I would announce<lb/>
that every man that wanted to enlist had to send his name in by a<lb/>
certain date, then I would have had a basis on which to estimate<lb/>
how many Allentown sections would be necessary to furnish the <hi>sixty-<lb/>
three</hi> which General Petain's Headquarters said was all they needed.<lb/>
These could have been sent over promptly and everything would have been<lb/>
settled. As it is, I have not satisfied the volunteers--no human<lb/>
being could do that. I have given myself infinite trouble for<lb/>
nothing, and the militarization of the service has dragged along.<lb/>
Birmingham has explained all these matters to you by now, so that I<lb/>
feel that I am in touch with the office.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06246019"/>
<p>(p.2--Major General W.C. Gorgas)</p>
<p>There is one thing, however, which is still a mystery,<lb/>
that is, what has delayed so long the ten additional sections and the<lb/>
300 unassigned men which General Pershing asked for in his cable of<lb/>
September 26th, and which were promised by the War Department in<lb/>
a cable on about October 3d. In your letter of October 6th, you<lb/>
say, &ldquo;In response to your last cable <hi>we have forwarded</hi> ten more<lb/>
sections and 300 unassigned men.&rdquo; These have, however, never<lb/>
arrived, but are now again promised in cable 468 of December 2d.<lb/>
I know that General Pershing sent a cable on the 31st of October<lb/>
asking that no more sections be sent without specific authority from<lb/>
him, but this should not have headed off these sections which had<lb/>
been promised to be sent immediately a month before.</p>
<p>The additional nine sections were a great help to me<lb/>
because it has enabled me to have a few additional officers. The<lb/>
provision made by the General Staff of only one lieutenant for each<lb/>
section allowed no additional officers to take place of those sick,<lb/>
on leave, under arrest, or in any way unavailable. As each section<lb/>
has to be mustered by an officer for pay, the commutation of ration<lb/>
vouchers have to be signed by an officer, and only an officer can<lb/>
act as Summary Court, the conditions were impossible until<lb/>
we got this leaway. All new appointments for vacancies will<lb/>
now be made by promotion from the sections, and will be selected by<lb/>
a board composed of field officers of the service on duty in<lb/>
France. I am also going to require all candidates to go through a<lb/>
Dec 7<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06246020"/>
(p.3.--Major General W.C. Gorgas)<lb/>
six weeks' course in the French school at Meaux, where they give<lb/>
admirable instruction in the principles of automobile structure,<lb/>
the <unclear>management</unclear> of convois, the rules of the road and the adminis-<lb/>
tration of military discipline. This course is also very valuable<lb/>
in enabling us to size up a man, and get the measure of his capacity<lb/>
and adaptability. We will gradually replace the medical officers,<lb/>
as Bradley wants them, except a few of the younger ones who like the<lb/>
service and show special qualifications for it.</p>
<p>I am trying now to establish a suitable Base Camp, so<lb/>
that when you send over additional sections <del>we that</del> we can exchange<lb/>
between those of the camp and those at the front so as to have some<lb/>
trained sections available for our army, if needed. The French<lb/>
authorities have agreed to this.</p>
<p>I am sending you a copy of the order showing the organi-<lb/>
zation of the Headquarters' Office. The only thing with which we<lb/>
are now having difficulty is the matter of spare parts. It seems<lb/>
that the supply of spare parts sent over with the ambulances has<lb/>
been inadequate, and as you know we are now suffering from a shortage.<lb/>
Major A. P. Andrew is in charge of this division of the office, and<lb/>
is handling the matter with some <unclear>pessimism</unclear> of spirt but with<lb/>
a good deal of energy. He will, I am sure, get it straightened out.</p>
<p>There has been a decided tendency at the Headquarters to<lb/>
criticize your office for sending over so many ambulances in excess<lb/>
Dec 7<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06246021"/>
(p.4--Major General W.C. Gorgas)<lb/>
of what were needed at the time. I have pointed out on all occassions<lb/>
with a good deal of emphasis that the excess of transportation was<lb/>
only due to the fact that the bringing over of the sections was<lb/>
<del>certainly</del><add>suddenly</add> checked by General Pershing in consequence of the difference<lb/>
of opinion of the Service de Sante and the Automobile Transport<lb/>
Service as to how many sections they needed. Meanwhile, some de-<lb/>
partments of the army were almost destitute of transportation, and<lb/>
I have had to come to the rescue by letting them have some of the<lb/>
vehicles, which for the time being we did not need. The number of<lb/>
cars transferred is as follows:</p>
<p>Quartermaster Department.....200<lb/>
Medical Department...........277<lb/>
Signal Corps..................70<lb/>
Engineer Corps...............100</p>
<p>Steps should be taken to replace these cars, which we will need by<lb/>
next June, the Medical Department being re-imbrused for their cost<lb/>
by transfers on the books of the Treasury. In this way we will get<lb/>
cars which have not been subject to deterioration from exposure<lb/>
to the weather, and we will have an opportunity to correct certain<lb/>
defects in the construction of these ambulances which have developed,<lb/>
as for instance, a slight enlargement of the bodies in all directions.</p>
<p>The Service de Sante is very anxious to have a program<lb/>
approved by which fifteen sections a month will be brought over here<lb/>
until the whole 120 have arrived, beginning next January. They have no<lb/>
Dec 7<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06246022"/>
(p. 5--Major General Gorgas)<lb/>
power to compel the Department of Munitions to assign these sections<lb/>
to duty at the front, and have, I think, no very clear idea as to<lb/>
what will be done with them, except that they propose to distribute<lb/>
the sections around to the hospitals of the interior, a work which I<lb/>
think belongs rather to the Red Cross than to the Ambulance Service.<lb/>
I am quite willing to have <add>my</add> command increased, but I can not recommend<lb/>
to General Pershing to have additional sections brought over in<lb/>
addition to the twenty-seven promised before the end of the year,<lb/>
without a clear and definite statement as to the need for them. This<lb/>
I can not give until the Motor Service agrees to assign them to duty<lb/>
at the front unless you are willing to have them stationed at the<lb/>
Base Camp and alternate with the sections at the front for the purpose<lb/>
of training.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the difficulties of taking care of the<lb/>
men properly over here are great. We have not yet been able to draw<lb/>
any clothing for our men, and it is difficult to get them properly<lb/>
housed. I feel very strongly that it is a mistake not to allow men<lb/>
to bring over their cots, and hope that you will be able to get this<lb/>
privilege for the sections coming over hereafter. Gold<lb/>
Medal Cota take up very small space and in the Ambulance Service they<lb/>
are absolutely necessary.</p>
<p>I appreciate very much the support which you have given<lb/>
me, and the prompt response which you have made to my requests. I hope<lb/>
Dec 7<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06246023"/>
(p. 6--Major General Gorgas)<lb/>
that Birmingham will be able to inform you fully as to the difficulties<lb/>
under which I have labored and the extraordinary degree to which we<lb/>
are out off from a <unclear>knowledge</unclear> of what is going on in Washington. I haven't<lb/>
received a War Department order since my arrival here, or any communi-<lb/>
cations from the office, <unclear>except</unclear> your very welcome and informing letters.</p>
<p>Please, after reading this letter, turn it over to Major<lb/>
Wrightson, and ask him to write to me occasionly.</p>
<p>With cordial greetings and best wishes for the New Year,<lb/>
I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J R KEAN<lb/>
Colonel, Medical Corps, USA</signed>.
JRK:p<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
 
