<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06245001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Jefferson Randolph Kean] to Henry P. Birmingham, August 29, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06245001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-08-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Birmingham, Henry P.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Bradley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Winter, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Blatchford, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Jones, Percy</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Martha</name>
<name type="person">[s.n.], Ada</name>
<name type="person">Goldthwait, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
<name type="place">Meaux (France)</name>
<name type="place">Tours (France)</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Bordeaux (France)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-08-29">August 29, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06245001</idno>
<title>Letter from [Jefferson Randolph Kean] to Henry P. Birmingham, August 29, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Kean] questions Birmingham about the organization of the Ambulance Corps in France.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-08-29">
<head>Letter from [Jefferson Randolph Kean] to Henry P. Birmingham, August 29, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06245001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>jrk-on</unclear><lb/>
XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX<lb/>
Office, U. S. A. Ambulance Service with French Army<lb/>
<dateline>
FRANCE - <date value="1917-08-29">29th August 1917</date>
</dateline>
Colonel Henry P. Birmingham, M.C., USA<lb/>
Office of the Surgeon General<lb/>
War Department, Washington<lb/>
<salute>My dear Birmingham:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I sent in a few days ago a letter to the Surgeon General giving an account of<lb/>
conditions in the ambulance service over here. I am sure that he has handed this<lb/>
to you to read. If he has not done so you can doubtless find it on file as it<lb/>
was really an official letter although personal in form. If you can't get it<lb/>
from the files ask him to let you read it.</p>
<p>I am daily embarrassed by the fact that we have over here more sections than the<lb/>
40 which were set aside for France; and everybody here, including the French,<lb/>
is opposed to breaking up any of these sections, which have a strong esprit de<lb/>
corps and have done excellent service. I hope it can be arranged that we can<lb/>
be credited with at least 5 more sections. I am sure that 5 of the sections<lb/>
recently organized at Allentown would not object to being sent over here with<lb/>
the understanding that they would be disbanded and the personnel used to fill<lb/>
up sections already at the front. They are so anxious to see active service<lb/>
that they would be willing to pay this price for it, I believe.</p>
<p>Percy Jones, who has joined me, is not sure whether they organized more than 118<lb/>
sections at Allentown. If not, 2 sections could be <unclear>creditalto</unclear> us and 3 sent over<lb/>
to be disbanded.</p>
<p>There are in connection with these sections a number of very good candidates for<lb/>
officers -- men who have not only had a number of months of active service at the<lb/>
front and who can speak French, but who have also taken the course at the French<lb/>
school of transportation at <unclear>Meaux</unclear> and have acquired in this way an accurate all-<lb/>
round knowledge of French transport administration. It is my idea as soon as<lb/>
the Chief Surgeon needs additional doctors to have the medical officers now with<lb/>
the sections transferred and replaced by those trained men. This is in accord-<lb/>
ance with what the Surgeon General told me was his desire, before I left, and<lb/>
what he has written me since I left.</p>
<p>The French military authorities have requested that the enlistment of the sections<lb/>
and their transfer to the United States Army Ambulance Service be made without<lb/>
interruption to their duties at the front; so I have sent out a recruiting party<lb/>
which will visit them at their 40-odd stations along the line and bring them<lb/>
into the service there. One trouble will be that they will be already in before<lb/>
we have any officers for them, as the officers of these sections will have to be<lb/>
commissioned from Washington. I hope that they will be able to accept their<lb/>
commissions by cable and that the delay will not be too long in getting them<lb/>
through. You will see the embarrassment of having the sections enlisted before<lb/>
the officers are commissioned and I hope will use your good offices in hastening<lb/>
through the list. I am going to recommend for commissions only those men who<lb/>
<pb n="2"  id="f06245002"/>
page 2 - Col. H. P. Birmingham - 29th August 1917<lb/>
---------<lb/>
have the approval of both the heads of their own services and of the French<lb/>
military authorities, who you know have a Lieutenant on duty with each section<lb/>
and who thus have quite accurate knowledge of the efficiency of the men who<lb/>
have been acting as officers of the sections under the volunteer system.</p>
<p>I have not yet been able to establish an office, but have been camping out in<lb/>
two little rooms which Bradley has been good enough to place at my disposal.<lb/>
It is a great pleasure to be with him and Ireland and Winter, and to see so many<lb/>
other officers of our corps and of the regular service. This will, however, be<lb/>
broken up at the end of the week, as General Pershing will take his headquarters<lb/>
into the field to join his troops. Winter, who is as you know Chief Surgeon of<lb/>
the line of communications, will probably go with General Blatchford, commanding<lb/>
the line of communications, to Tours or some other point southwest of Paris and<lb/>
nearer the coast. I will, therefore, in the near future probably lose all of my<lb/>
old friends. Percy Jones will, however, be a great comfort, and without his<lb/>
accurate and ready knowledge of the details of <unclear>company</unclear> administration I do not<lb/>
know how I would ever be able to organize these sections as self-contained units<lb/>
and got them supplied.</p>
<p>We are trying to get hold of some barracks, in some small town not too far from<lb/>
Paris, so as to be able to bring the sections up here and organize a base camp.</p>
<p>Bradley says that nobody ever writes to him from the office and he rarely gets an<lb/>
answer to his letters. I hope that you are not going to let me suffer from the<lb/>
same dearth <unclear>although.</unclear> I know well how full the days are for all of you at the<lb/>
office.</p>
<p>Please see to it that no appointments are made in Washington for any of the<lb/>
sections in <unclear>France</unclear> who are to serve with the French troops. The French authori-<lb/>
ities are most anxious that all vacancies shall be filled by men who have been<lb/>
trained by actual experience at the front. Ability to speak French is a very<lb/>
important qualification for the officers of this service.</p>
<p>Ireland and Bradley send their love. Bradley says that he has your letter in his<lb/>
basket of unfinished business and will write to you very soon. I hope that you<lb/>
found no difficulty in delivering the cable message which I sent from Bordeaux<lb/>
to Martha. I was sure that you could find her through Ada. I suppose that Gold-<lb/>
<unclear>thwait</unclear> has come back from England by this time and hope that you gave him my<lb/>
regards, which I left at the Surgeon General's Office for him.</p>
<p>With best wishes and regards to all my friends in the Office, I am, always,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your friend,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
