<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06246005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 6, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06246005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-10-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Bradley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Joffre, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">McFadden, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-10-06">October 6, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06246005</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 6, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas relays further information about the manning of ambulance sections in France. He mentions a possible misunderstanding between the French and American authorities.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-10-06">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 6, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06246005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL,<lb/>
WASHINGTON.<lb/>
<date value="1917-10-06">October 6,1917.</date>
</dateline>
wcg-hhw<lb/>
Rico Nov 24<lb/>
Colonel J.R. Kean,<lb/>
Medical Corps, U.S. Army,<lb/>
American Expeditionary Force,<lb/>
France.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yours of September the 6th was received some<lb/>
days ago. I appreciate the need that you and Bradley must<lb/>
feel about getting news from home. I feel the same way<lb/>
with regard to you and Bradley. I am having Bradley sent<lb/>
carbon copies of everything that goes on in the office that<lb/>
may give him information. If you and he are separated and<lb/>
you have no access to this matter I will also have you sent<lb/>
<unclear>a</unclear> carbon copies. I can see from your letter that you<lb/>
have misunderstood the status of the ambulance sections.<lb/>
The matter was considered when the war first broke out by a<lb/>
request from the French Embassy that we take over the trans-<lb/>
portation of the French wounded. After extended discussion<lb/>
with the military <unclear>attach&eacute;</unclear> at the Embassy it was agreed that<lb/>
we should form 160 sections for this purpose. When the<lb/>
French Mission came over, headed by General Joffre, he and<lb/>
the Secretary of War came to an agreement on the subject<lb/>
which was substantially this: That we should furnish the<lb/>
French Army 160 ambulance sections, as at present organized.<lb/>
Each section to be paid and cared for by the U.S. Army, just as<lb/>
any other troops serving in Europe. <del><hi>The idea of the</hi></del><add>The idea of the</add><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06246006"/>
2.<lb/>
Secretary of War was that these sections should go right<lb/>
into active service, thereby getting experience that<lb/>
would be useful to us, <add>and</add> that, as we needed them we would<lb/>
draw them off for use in our army, but replace each<lb/>
section that we took away by another one from the United<lb/>
States. We made the same agreement with the English<lb/>
Embassy with regard to American troops sent for service<lb/>
with the English Army, and this is what we are doing at<lb/>
present so far as the English service is concerned.</p>
<p>The whole thing was smashed up by General Pershing's<lb/>
cable saying that he wanted no more ambulance sections<lb/>
for France, that the French authorities had so stated to<lb/>
him. Upon the receipt of this cable we prepared to dis-<lb/>
tribute our sections at Allentown to the various cantonments<lb/>
for the purpose of expanding them into the Ambulance companies<lb/>
for the Divisions under training.</p>
<p>The French Embassy, however, begs me to wait until they<lb/>
can get some communication from their Government. They were<lb/>
cognizant of our promise to Gen. Joffre, and say that they<lb/>
know General Pershing has misunderstood what their Government<lb/>
wishes. Get the matter settled as soon as you can if<lb/>
the French wish any more ambulance sections. I would like to<lb/>
break up Allentown as soon as it is decided we have no more use<lb/>
for it.</p>
<p>So far we have complied with all the cablegrams that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06246007"/>
3.<lb/>
<del><hi>concern you</hi></del>. We have cabled that the Secretary authorizes<lb/>
9 more sections to be taken over in France.</p>
<p>In response to your last cable we have forwarded 10 more<lb/>
sections and 300 unassigned men. I judge, therefore, you<lb/>
have authority now to take over all the sections in France<lb/>
which you had in view at the time of writing your letter.</p>
<p>You know whom Mr. McFadden is - a son of Mr. McFadden<lb/>
who was so prominent before the war in scientific research in<lb/>
London in connection with Sir Ronald Ross.</p>
<p>You understand that we are limited as to officers by<lb/>
the organization prescribed by the War College. Within these<lb/>
limits I expect to carry out everything you recommend in the<lb/>
way of commissions. I will keep you informed of the men and<lb/>
numbers who have so far been commissioned. You understand<lb/>
that our general policy is to fill the ambulance sections as<lb/>
much as we consider desirable with men who are not M.D's. But<lb/>
until particularly needed, the M.D's., I think, you might as well<lb/>
use and give them training.</p>
<p>Birmingham has no doubt arrived by this time and he will<lb/>
give you all the news up to date.</p>
<p>Mrs. Gorgas joins me in kindest regards.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>W. C. Gorgas</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
