<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06246010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 2, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Gorgas, William Crawford</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06246010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-11-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Norton, Richard</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Joffre, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Bradley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Doyle, Capt.</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-11-02">November 2, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06246010</idno>
<title>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 2, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Gorgas describes to Kean further communication difficulties in constituting the Ambulance Corps in France.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-11-02">
<head>Letter from William Crawford Gorgas to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 2, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06246010"/>
<opener>
Reed Dec 4<lb/>
<dateline>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
OFFICE OF THE SURGEON GENERAL<lb/>
WASHINGTON<lb/>
<date value="1917-11-02">November 2,1917.</date>
</dateline>
wcg-hhw<lb/>
From Gen Gorgas<lb/>
Colonel J. R. Kean, U.S. Army,<lb/>
U.S. Army Ambulance Service,<lb/>
With the French Army,<lb/>
France.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yours of September 22d, enclosing letter of August<lb/>
24th from Richard Norton, is acknowledged. Before you re-<lb/>
ceive this letter you will have had letters from me which will<lb/>
explain the status of the Ambulance Sections. You evidently<lb/>
left the United States under an entire misapprehension as to what<lb/>
this status is. A good many questions in your letter of Sept.<lb/>
22d have already been answered in letters since written to you,<lb/>
but for fear some may have been mislaid I will answer your ques-<lb/>
tions in detail.</p>
<p>I do not see that it makes any difference to us how many<lb/>
men in the old sections enlist in our service. It is some<lb/>
advantage, of course, to have experienced men, but we can furnish<lb/>
you with just as many men as you wish of the very highest order<lb/>
of intelligence from Allentown. But I am so at sea here as to<lb/>
what you are driving at, and you are so at sea as to what we<lb/>
intend that I might evidently entirely misunderstand the whole<lb/>
situation. The taking over of these American organizations from<lb/>
the French is to be entirely voluntary on their part. If they<lb/>
want to stay in the service of the French and the French want to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06246011"/>
(Col. Kean, U.S.A.)<lb/>
2.<lb/>
keep them I would not urge them to come in; I don't see that<lb/>
we need them in the least. I don't see why you need bother<lb/>
at all about Mr. Norton; let him do exactly as he pleases.</p>
<p>So far everything you have asked for with regard to Sections<lb/>
in France has been granted. Your present authorization for<lb/>
taking over American Sections is 49. No cable has been<lb/>
received from General Pershing asking for twenty Sections from<lb/>
Allentown. A cable has been received asking for ten Sections<lb/>
and 300 loose men. This has been ordered by the Chief of Staff<lb/>
and the men are now awaiting transportation.</p>
<p>The French Legation is still begging us not to assign the<lb/>
Allentown Sections to the various camps. They assure me that<lb/>
General Pershing is in error as to the wishes of the French<lb/>
Government - that their wishes are still the same as those ex-<lb/>
pressed by General Joffre when he was here, namely, that we<lb/>
should furnish the French Government with 169 Sections to be as-<lb/>
signed to duty with the French Army. In this letter of yours<lb/>
you are still under the impression that these Sections were for<lb/>
use with our Army.</p>
<p>Your high officers who are Reserve Corps' men can be used<lb/>
anywhere; those not M.D.'s who have been commissioned in the<lb/>
Ambulance Section can only be used in that Section. I should<lb/>
think you and Bradley could manage this between you by assigning<lb/>
the M.D's. to other divisions. I want to conserve the M.D's. as<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06246012"/>
3.<lb/>
(Col. J.R. Kean, U.S. Army)<lb/>
much as possible and use non-M.D.'s wherever non-M.D.'s can be<lb/>
advantageously substituted. I should think it advantageous<lb/>
for you to commission the men who are with the Sections that you<lb/>
take over from the French service and it is my intention to leave<lb/>
the commissioning in all the Ambulance Sections under your juris-<lb/>
diction to yourself when they get over there. I think the<lb/>
commissioning should be as much as possible from the ranks of<lb/>
the Ambulance Section itself. This Section, I think, is com-<lb/>
posed of the very best material we have in the Army. It is the<lb/>
intention of the Department to replace by fresh Sections any Sec-<lb/>
tion that we may take away from the French Army as rapidly as such<lb/>
separation takes place, the idea being that it is advantageous to<lb/>
us to keep these trained Sections in France to be used by our Army<lb/>
in case of emergency. I imagine that when you once get in the<lb/>
swing and our Army supplied, it will not very often occur that we<lb/>
take the French Sections.</p>
<p>Captain Boyle's present status in the office is that of<lb/>
Captain in the Ambulance Section, to help out in anything that per-<lb/>
tains to this Section. He has been cabling direct to Andrew, because<lb/>
I thought in this way we could get an idea of what you all were driv-<lb/>
ing at, but I see that things cannot be hastened in this way and<lb/>
shall let the matter drop in order to try to get information through<lb/>
official channels. So far as you and I are concerned the official<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06246013"/>
4.<lb/>
cables have given me no information and have<lb/>
apparently caused you nothing but trouble.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>W. C. Gorgas.<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
