<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06246008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, October 24, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06246008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-10-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gorgas, William Crawford</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Doyle, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Sleeper, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Andrew, A. P.</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Persons, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Hallett, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Franklin, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Furbush, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Goodwin, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Noble, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
<name type="place">Meaux (France)</name>
<name type="place">Europe</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Salonique [s.l.]</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-10-24">October 24, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06246008</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, October 24, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean describes disagreements within the command of the Ambulance Corps on how to organize the ambulance service in France.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-10-24">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, October 24, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06246008"/>
<opener>
699<lb/>
file<lb/>
<dateline>
France - <date value="1917-10-24">24 October 1917</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Gorgas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I sent you a personal cable on October 7 as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Please disregard advice Doyle and Sleeper&rdquo;.</p>
<p>My reason for so doing was that apparently Captain Doyle constituted himself<lb/>
an &ldquo;officier de liaison&rdquo; between the Ambulance Service with the French Army<lb/>
and your office, and many of his ideas as expressed in letters and cables<lb/>
which he has been sending to Major Andrew are not at all in accordance with<lb/>
the interests of the service. His idea of making this a &ldquo;lame duck&rdquo; service<lb/>
and sending here the physically unfit which have been rejected for service<lb/>
with the National Army, and who could make use of their infirmities to get<lb/>
out of the service whenever they chose, is, I think, particularly objection-<lb/>
able. As long as we have such an enormous reserve of ablebodied men to draw<lb/>
from, I do not see why the Ambulance Service should be handicapped by accept-<lb/>
ing the physically unfit. Also, I know of no authorization from the War De-<lb/>
partment to waive absolute disabilities.</p>
<p>Although I requested Major Andrew early in September to cable to Mr.<lb/>
Sleeper that we did not want any more volunteers sent over for enlistment<lb/>
here, but preferred trained men from Allentown, Mr. Sleeper has continued to<lb/>
send men on nearly every boat. Many of these are physically unfit, and after<lb/>
having incurred the heavy expense of buying uniforms and paying their own<lb/>
transportation across the ocean, besides exposing themselves to the danger<lb/>
of ocean travel at the present time, have the disappointment of being rejected<lb/>
here. Those who are accepted are entirely untrained and therefore much less<lb/>
desirable than the Allentown men which you have promised to send me to fill<lb/>
up vacancies. Twenty (20) of these men arrived yesterday, and I understand<lb/>
more are expected in 3 or 4 days. Nearly half of the last group were physi-<lb/>
cally unfit. Colonel <unclear>Birmingham</unclear> tells me that about the 10th of September<lb/>
he told Captain Doyle not to send any more men over without physical examina-<lb/>
tion and enlistment, and that Captain Doyle promised that these instructions<lb/>
would be carried out.</p>
<p>On October 9 I got General Pershing to cable asking that the State De-<lb/>
partment be requested to refuse passports for all men coming here for enlist-<lb/>
ment in the Ambulance Service. I hope that you will see that this is done.</p>
<p>4. Another matter about which there has been cable correspondence be-<lb/>
tween Captain Doyle and Major Andrew is the question of taking over the two<lb/>
American Field Service sections at Salonique. I have told Major Andrew that<lb/>
of course if the War Department authorized their taking over I would adminis-<lb/>
ter them. I think, however, that in view of the fact that we have not a single<lb/>
commissioned officer with that army the matter of administration would occasion<lb/>
an amount of trouble and expense altogether out of proportion to the benefit<lb/>
conferred. The difficulties of communication and administration, which are<lb/>
certainly abundant enough here, would be much greater from Salonique. I have<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06246009"/>
2-- General Gorgas - 26 Oct. 1917<lb/>
therefore repeatedly recommended to Major Andrew that he turn over these<lb/>
units to the Red Cross, which has officials on the ground and has <unclear>the</unclear> money<lb/>
to administer the units. There does not seem to be any valid objection to<lb/>
this, but I do not think that he is going to do it.</p>
<p>5. I have asked the Chief Surgeon's Office to send a cable asking<lb/>
that the names of the officers above the grade of Captain in the Ambulance<lb/>
Service be sent to me by cable and the Captains and Lieutenants by mail.<lb/>
I am really a good deal at sea in the matter. I presume Colonel Persons is<lb/>
the Colonel, and he wrote Birmingham under date of September 20 that Major<lb/>
Hallett had been given one of the Lieutenant Colonelcies and he had recom-<lb/>
mended Major Franklin for the other. In your letter to me of August 10<lb/>
you <unclear>state/that</unclear> you had taken steps to fill these positions, and that I should<lb/>
take steps to fill the other places. I assume that these other places refers<lb/>
to any vacancies existing or that may occur in the 49 units authorized for<lb/>
France and the 30 which have been ordered here, from Allentown. I would be<lb/>
glad to have you give instructions to the Personnel Division looking to<lb/>
these positions being filled only on my recommendation. There is a good deal<lb/>
of jealousy between the three component parts of my command, and I am trying to<lb/>
get up a system of selection for promotions which will get the best men. One<lb/>
element of this will be graduation at the French transportation school at<lb/>
Meaux. I am emphasizing this matter because there have been a number of pro-<lb/>
motions made from the S. G. O. recently in the sections under my command.<lb/>
I have no complaint to make of the selections, but would much prefer to have<lb/>
the promise of your letter of August 10 carried out.</p>
<p>6. Colonel Persons mentions that Major Wrightson has been given the<lb/>
supervision of the Ambulance Service in the Office. I am glad to hear it<lb/>
because I will feel that I can get somebody who will answer letters. This<lb/>
is not intended as a reflection on you, as I know how overwhelmed with work<lb/>
you are and all I ask from you is that you will read my letters and then<lb/>
refer them to Major Wrightson or whoever will handle them.</p>
<p>7. Birmingham's visit has been a great pleasure to us all. He is with<lb/>
me now and leaves for the French front on Sunday. His promotion gave me the<lb/>
sincerest pleasure, and I believe it had the universal approval of every man<lb/>
in the corps. I believe that he will take back with him a great deal of very<lb/>
valuable information which will be of much assistance in enabling the Office<lb/>
to meet the needs of the service in Europe.</p>
<p>Can't you order my good friend Furbush to write me a letter and give<lb/>
me some of the news of the Office. There is a rumor that legislation was<lb/>
passed on October 5 which was of great importance to the Medical Corps, but<lb/>
none of us has the faintest idea as to what it was, as yet. In fact, it is<lb/>
hard to realize the isolation of our life from affairs in the United States.</p>
<p>With cordial good wishes to Furbush, Goodwin, Noble and my other friends<lb/>
in the Office, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
