<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06246014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, November 6, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06246014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-11-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Gorgas, William Crawford</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Doyle, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Joffre, Marshal</name>
<name type="person">Aujay, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Pershing, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Andrew, A. P.</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, [s.n]</name>
<name type="person">Wrightson, Maj.</name>
<name type="place">Allentown (Pa.?)</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Sandricourt (France)</name>
<name type="place">Italy</name>
<name type="place">Austria</name>
<name type="place">St. Nazaire (France)</name>
<name type="place">Fort de Vanves (France)</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Chemin des Dames (France)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-11-06">November 6, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06246014</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, November 6, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean provides a detailed description of Ambulance Corps problems; including supply, accommodation, and pay difficulties.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1917-11-06">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to William Crawford Gorgas, November 6, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06246014"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
France - <date value="1917-11-06">6 November 1917</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Gorgas:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of September 14 is just received, and it gives me great pleasure<lb/>
to feel that I am in letter communication with you, although I hope that future<lb/>
correspondence will not be subject to such enormous delays. Your letter took a<lb/>
month longer to come than Captain Doyle's, which was written October 13 and ar-<lb/>
rived today.</p>
<p>You understand by this time, I am sure, because it has been explained both<lb/>
in my letters and in cable, that the hitch about sending over all the Allentown<lb/>
sections is due to the fact that the ambulance service at the Front is under<lb/>
the Ministry of Armament and Munitions, which does not seem to desire us to take<lb/>
over the entire ambulance service of the French army as was proposed by Marshal<lb/>
Joffre. My liaison officer, Captain Aujay, told me this morning that the Service<lb/>
Automobile Militaire desired us to furnish them 63 sections. Two sections will<lb/>
also be needed for the military service of Paris, and about 10 to be held at the<lb/>
Base Camp for emergencies and to furnish details for the army parks and reserve<lb/>
parks and the depot of spare parts. This will make the total needs of the service<lb/>
here, as at present constituted, <hi>75 sections</hi>. We have now in service at the front<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p>
<table rows="6" cols="4">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>men</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>From the American Field Service</cell><cell>.................</cell><cell>25 sections</cell><cell>625</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>From the Red Cross service</cell><cell>......................</cell><cell>2 "</cell><cell>50</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>From the United States (Allentown)</cell><cell>..............</cell><cell>19 "</cell><cell>25</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>At the Base Camp, Sandricourt</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>(1 Red Cross &amp; 1 Allentown)</cell><cell>................</cell><cell><hi>2</hi> "</cell><cell><hi>700</hi></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>TOTAL</cell><cell>-------</cell><cell>48 sections</cell><cell>1400</cell></row></table></p>
<p>When the 10 sections whose arrival I am expecting daily and with impatience<lb/>
come, I will still be 17 sections short of this program, and I will ask General<lb/>
Pershing to cable for them as soon as satisfactory arrangements can be made for<lb/>
caring for them during the winter. I am by no means anxious to see men sent over<lb/>
here to sleep in the mud in this cold and harsh climate, as I believe they will be<lb/>
much better off in the United States until we can make arrangements to take care<lb/>
of them.</p>
<p>The Italian service may make very considerable additional demands on our<lb/>
service, as I have an intimation already that the French would like to send some<lb/>
of our sections to Italy. The question as to whether this should be done, in view<lb/>
of the fact that we are not at war with Austria, has been unofficially brought up,<lb/>
but I see no validity to that objection, because ambulance sections being a part<lb/>
of the sanitary service it is not an act of hostility or in any way contrary to<lb/>
the letter or spirit of the Hague treaty to send them to any belligerent. The<lb/>
question has not yet, however, been put up to General Pershing, and I do not<lb/>
know what view he will take of it.</p>
<p>There has been some talk in the Army about the great number of Ford ambu-<lb/>
lances lying crated on the pier at St. Nazaire, but to all critics I have replied<lb/>
that all of these Fords would have been in use if we had been allowed to bring<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06246015"/>
2<lb/>
over our sections as well as our cars. The fact is, however, that these cars<lb/>
have been the salvation of the Army, because the Quartermaster Department has<lb/>
been very short of transportation, and the Medical Department, which is de-<lb/>
pendent on them, equally short. Therefore I have turned over 200 cars to the<lb/>
Medical Department, 200 to the Quartermaster Department, and 70 to the Signal<lb/>
Corps, with the understanding that they would be replaced by them later. This<lb/>
replacement will, I think, have to be by a transfer of funds on the books of<lb/>
the Treasury and a fresh order of cars from Ford. I have been very much averse<lb/>
to having these cars assembled to stand out in the weather and deteriorate, es-<lb/>
pecially as in this way we spoil tires, of which article we are very short.<lb/>
The French automobile service have been promising me storage for two months<lb/>
but without any tangible results. So, I have turned to the <unclear>Service de Sante</unclear>,<lb/>
who have placed at my disposal, in the last day or two, a splendid great store-<lb/>
house just south of Paris, at the Fort de Vanves, where I can store out auto-<lb/>
biles crated, and have a depot of spare parts.</p>
<p>The spare part question is at present very urgent, as requisitions for<lb/>
spare parts come in every day.</p>
<p>I think that we will soon transfer our Base Camp to Ft. de Vanves, from<lb/>
Sandricourt, which is 40 kilometres north of Paris. This will make our admin-<lb/>
istration much more handy and efficient. I think the automobile service is a<lb/>
little jealous at my accepting anything at the hands of the Service de Sante,<lb/>
as there is a good deal of jealousy between them; but my reply to all remarks<lb/>
is that promises will not shelter either men or supplies, and so I had to turn<lb/>
to whoever would help me out.</p>
<p>It has been so far impossible to get any clothing, and my men are getting<lb/>
in a very bad way for lack of it; but I understand the same lack exists in the<lb/>
United States. I hope it will be relieved by a shipment before long.</p>
<p>You will be pleased to know that the Allentown sections at the front are<lb/>
doing well, and I have heard of one citation already, and many complimentary<lb/>
reports of the efficiency and gallantry of several of them during the recent<lb/>
battle at Chemin des Dames.</p>
<p>I have been very much handicapped by my inability to get a suitable office,<lb/>
but the Quartermaster's Office has at last rented me a stable which has very<lb/>
good rooms over it and will make a very satisfactory office. I expect to be<lb/>
able to get some quarters for my men in connection with it and start a mess,<lb/>
so that they can live comfortably and decently. The conditions of living for<lb/>
enlisted men in Paris are very hard, as all commutation was cut off on the<lb/>
1st of the month, and the two enlisted men's messes are said to be exceedingly<lb/>
poor, besides being so distant from my office that if the men had to eat there<lb/>
they would spend their entire time traveling back and forth and would have no<lb/>
time to give to the work of the office.</p>
<p>I am just transferring the offices from the old American Field Service<lb/>
office into my office and making a consolidation of the two. Major Andrew will<lb/>
have charge of motor transportation and will, I hope, be very useful at the head<lb/>
of that very important branch.</p>
<p>We have had much difficulty in getting to the sections their pay and their<lb/>
commutation of rations. The latter has given especial difficulty as the French<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06246016"/>
3<lb/>
are <unclear>acoustomed</unclear> to having commutation paid in advance and do business on a cash<lb/>
basis, whereas, you know, it is one of the peculiarities of our regulations<lb/>
that a man has to eat his meals before he can pay for them, and if he cannot get<lb/>
credit he will starve.</p>
<p>Birmingham has come back today from our Headquarters, having completed his<lb/>
inspection of the British and French, as well as the American, fronts. He is<lb/>
looking very well and is in fine spirits and will bring back a great deal of ex-<lb/>
ceedingly valuable information for the Office.</p>
<p>If I could only hear tomorrow that the 10 sections and 300 unassigned men<lb/>
from Allentown had arrived, I would be perfectly happy and would feel that the<lb/>
future is all smooth sailing and that my chief difficulties are behind me.</p>
<p>Please turn this letter over to Major Wrightson after you have read it.<lb/>
My next letter will be written to him direct.</p>
<p>With best wishes,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Kean</signed>
jrk-oh<lb/>
Major General W. C. Gorgas, USA<lb/>
Surgeon General<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
