<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06261001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Burton J. Hendrick, May 1, 1924</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06261001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1924-05-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hendrick, Burton J.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Ireland, Merrite W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Walker, Admiral</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, C. A. L.</name>
<name type="publication">World's Work</name>
<name type="publication">New York Times</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1924-05-01">May 1, 1924</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06261001</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Burton J. Hendrick, May 1, 1924</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean offers an explanation of how his rebuttal letter to Marie Gorgas' article came to be published in New York Times.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1924-05-01">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Burton J. Hendrick, May 1, 1924</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06261001"/>
<opener>
JHK-mrh<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1924-05-01">1 May 1924.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Burton J. Hendrick,<lb/>
Editor of The World's Work,<lb/>
Garden City, N. Y.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Hendrick:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was greatly pleased to get your second letter<lb/>
of April 16th., agreeing to publish in The World's Work the correct-<lb/>
ion with regard to the chapter of the life of Gorgas. I should have,<lb/>
perhaps, written to you again and thanked you for it, but I did not<lb/>
want to consume any of your valuable time with unnecessary corres-<lb/>
pondence.</p>
<p>Today I saw the May number of The World's Work and<lb/>
have not been able to find any correction in it. Yesterday I had a<lb/>
note from the Surgeon General to say that the correction had been<lb/>
published in the New York Times of last Sunday, April 27th. I feel<lb/>
that an explanation is due as to how this came about.</p>
<p>When your first letter of April 14th., was received<lb/>
on the 15th., I immediately forwarded it to General Ireland, to whom<lb/>
Mrs. Reed had also appealed for a correction, with a remark that it<lb/>
did not appear that you were inclined to make a correction in the<lb/>
World's Work and suggesting that he do what he thought best in the<lb/>
matter. General Ireland is a man of action and, assuming from your<lb/>
letter that you did not want to publish the correction, he sent it on<lb/>
April 17th. to the New York Times. Meanwhile, on that date, your second<lb/>
letter of April 16th., which was entirely satisfactory to me, arrived,<lb/>
and I forwarded it to General Ireland without the loss of an hour's<lb/>
time. I was out of town for three or four days at Easter and did not<lb/>
learn of General Ireland's action until the next week. I then looked<lb/>
up the file of the New York Times but did not find the article. I<lb/>
then wrote to him asking him to find out what the Times proposed to<lb/>
do about it as I wished to inform you immediately if they intended to<lb/>
publish it. He replied that they had had it over a week but he had<lb/>
heard nothing from them. From their delay I assumed that they did<lb/>
not intend to print it and as the May number of The World's Work was<lb/>
already in print, there was nothing to be gained by writing, until<lb/>
I found out what the Times would do.</p>
<p>As you did not publish it, I am glad to feel<lb/>
that you have no cause for complaint at the action which Mrs. Reed's<lb/>
friends saw fit to take in the matter. If you should see fit to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06261002"/>
-2-<lb/>
publish it or an abstract of it in the June issue, it would be an<lb/>
evidence of your desire to put the truth before the Public, which<lb/>
would be appreciated by Mrs. Reed's friends.</p>
<p>I find the chapter in the May issue most interesting.<lb/>
I am delighted to see the obstinate, self-sufficiency of the &ldquo;Old<lb/>
Man of the Sea&rdquo;, Admiral Walker, plainly set forth. I was busy in<lb/>
Washington at that time fighting Gorgas' battles against the Commiss-<lb/>
ioners and was in a dull rage against him until the President summar-<lb/>
ily dismissed him, as a result of the publication of the report of<lb/>
Dr. C. A. L. Reed of Cincinnati in the journal of the American Medical<lb/>
Association about his attitude toward sanitation.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean,<lb/>
Colonel, Med. Corps, USA</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
