<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06269033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Walter D. McCaw to Mark Sullivan, July 14, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>McCaw, Walter D.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06269033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-07-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Sullivan, Mark</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Sullivan, Mark</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Noble, R.E.</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, Henry P.</name>
<name type="person">Black, William M.</name>
<name type="person">Cruz, Oswaldo</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Canal Zone (Panama)</name>
<name type="place">Brownsville (Tex.)</name>
<name type="place">Barrancas (Fl.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Santiago (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</name>
<name type="place">Buenos Aires (Argentina)</name>
<name type="place">Texas</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-07-14">July 14, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06269033</idno>
<title>Letter from Walter D. McCaw to Mark Sullivan, July 14, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>McCaw offers comments on Sullivan's draft chapter about Gorgas and yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-07-14">
<head>Letter from Walter D. McCaw to Mark Sullivan, July 14, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06269033"/>
<opener>
M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Caw to<lb/>
Mark Sullivan<lb/>
7/16/'25<lb/>
Y. F.<lb/>
wdm ell<lb/>
<unclear>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Caw's</unclear> Comments on<lb/>
Mr Mark Sullivan's<lb/>
Chapter <unclear><hi>on</hi></unclear> Gorgas and<lb/>
Y. F.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1925-07-14">July 14, 1925.</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Mark Sullivan,<lb/>
91 Home Life Building,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Sullivan:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Referring to your letter of July 10th inclosing a copy of an article<lb/>
on General Gorgas, I must first state that I never had the honor of personal<lb/>
service with General Gorgas, either in Havana or on the Canal Zone. Perhaps<lb/>
you have <unclear>confounded</unclear> my name and that of General <unclear>R. E.</unclear> Noble, now retired.<lb/>
However, it was my duty to look into the history of the fight against yellow<lb/>
fever, when on duty in the Surgeon General's Office, and I venture therefore,<lb/>
having read your very interesting article, to make a few suggestions which I<lb/>
hope may be of use to you. These, however, will apply only to the Havana<lb/>
period, as I am not competent to speak from personal knowledge on any of the<lb/>
matters connected with General Gorgas's sanitary administration of the Panama<lb/>
Canal Zone. The following notes are simply intended to clear up what appear<del><unclear>s</unclear></del><lb/>
to me to be a few doubtful points in your narrative:</p>
<p><hi>Page 4:</hi> General Gorgas was present at an epidemic at Fort Brown and<lb/>
the city of Brownsville, Texas, in 1882, being himself infected. I do<lb/>
not think that he personally saw yellow fever cases from that time until<lb/>
1897 at Barrancas, where there was a moderate epidemic; nor again after<lb/>
that until he went to Cuba.</p>
<p><hi>Page 5:</hi> It was not Gorgas's job to clean up Havana, so far as the<lb/>
streets were concerned. This was done by Major William M. Black, U. S.<lb/>
Corps of Engineers, afterwards Chief of Engineers, and it was under<lb/>
General Ludlow, commanding in the city of Havana. The premises, such<lb/>
as backyards and patios, were cleaned up by the Sanitary Department,<lb/>
but the sanitary officer, Major Davis, was also under General Ludlow,<lb/>
reporting directly to him. Gorgas did not have charge, therefore, of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06269034"/>
Mr. Mark Sullivan - 2.<lb/>
any of the actual policing of Havana until about February, 1900. It is<lb/>
hardly fair, therefore, to credit him with cleaning up Havana of the<lb/>
accumulated filth of years.</p>
<p>(See General Kean's review of Mrs. Gorgas's book.)</p>
<p><hi>Page 6:</hi> The American Army of invasion, Shafter's army at Santiago,<lb/>
was indeed saturated with fever, but it was largely malarial in nature.<lb/>
There were some cases of yellow fever in the rear of the army - how many<lb/>
will never be known - but the large majority of fever-stricken soldiers<lb/>
that were returned to Montauk Point were purely malarial cases. I rather<lb/>
think you give the impression that the American and Spanish armies were<lb/>
fever-stricken with yellow fever</p>
<p><hi>Page 9:</hi> Note. Dr. Henry R. Carter, U. S. Public Health Service, knew<lb/>
nothing about incubation in the mosquito, which your statement would<lb/>
indicate. His careful study of the period of incubation of yellow fever<lb/>
in patients, briefly stated, shows that a non-immune going into an<lb/>
infected locality develops the disease in the usual period, less than<lb/>
ten days; whereas when an infected person goes to an uninfected locality<lb/>
twenty days <add>or</add> more must elapse before new cases develop. This indicates<lb/>
an incubation of the disease cause somewhere outside of the human body.<lb/>
Carter called this &ldquo;extrinsic incubation&rdquo;. It was not explained until<lb/>
the Reed experiments were made. Carter's observations were undoubtedly<lb/>
very suggestive and valuable to Reed.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06269035"/>
<p>Mr. Mark Sullivan - 3.</p>
<p><hi>Page 10:</hi> Carroll's inoculation was a methodical experiment by Lazear<lb/>
and it succeeded, as one of the mosquitoes used had been infected 12<lb/>
days before. Lazear's infection was accidental from a free mosquito<lb/>
in the yellow fever ward. He noticed the bite, however, and it no<lb/>
doubt caused his attack, from which he died.</p>
<p><hi>Page 12:</hi> Permanent receptacles of water, such as barrels and cisterns,<lb/>
were listed and regularly inspected. <unclear>A/s</unclear> to every small receptacle capable<lb/>
of holding water being catalogued and accounted for at each inspection,<lb/>
I rather think this to be impossible and that any account given to this<lb/>
effect is more or less fanciful.</p>
<p><hi>Page 17:</hi> I am inclined to believe that Oswaldo Cruz, using the Gorgas<lb/>
method, cleaned up yellow fever in Rio de Janeiro in 1909 and not Buenos<lb/>
Aires, prior to Gorgas's work in Panama.</p>
<p><hi>Page 20:</hi> Dr. C. A. L. Reed's visit to Panama was not fortuitous. He was<lb/>
sent there by Mr. Taft, when Secretary of War. (See Kean's review).</p>
<p><hi>Page 28:</hi> Preparations for war were made by the Surgeon General's Office<lb/>
in accordance with plans that had been long in existence. The Medical<lb/>
Reserve Corps of the Army was increased quite largely during the mobiliza-<lb/>
tion of troops on the Texas border in 1915-1916, during which years General<lb/>
Gorgas was absent for quite a long time in Peru engaged in yellow fever<lb/>
work, Colonel Birmingham being the Acting Surgeon General.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06269036"/>
<p>Mr. Mark Sullivan - 4.</p>
<p><hi>Page 29: (top)</hi> I may say that, whereas General Gorgas was of course the<lb/>
responsible head of the Medical Department of the United States Army and,<lb/>
in common with the rest of the War Department, did everything possible to<lb/>
furnish in a most liberal manner men, money, and supplies to the Army in<lb/>
France, the provision of hospitals, the management and establishment of<lb/>
the same were entirely in the hands of the Medical Department of the<lb/>
A.E.F., and the bureau chiefs in Washington assumed no authority in the<lb/>
matter. In fact it may be said that the A.E.F., under General Pershing<lb/>
and the G.H.Q. at Chaumont, was entirely autonomous and did its own<lb/>
fighting and administration.</p>
<p>I hope the above notes will be of some use to you. And now I may be<lb/>
pardoned for one other criticism, which interests me solely because the credit<lb/>
for the great conquest of yellow fever seems to a certain extent to be diverted--<lb/>
certainly in the public mind -- from the one who most truly deserves it.</p>
<p>You give a very clear though brief account of Walter Reed's experiments<lb/>
and then relate the brilliant result of Gorgas's putting this new knowledge into<lb/>
effect. It reminds me of a story, which you probably read as I did in your<lb/>
youth, to be found in the ordinary version of the &ldquo;Arabian Nights&rdquo;. In this<lb/>
story Habib, an Arabian prince, was called upon to rescue a captive princess<lb/>
from the hands of a legion of very powerful and malignant genii who were holding<lb/>
her in captivity. With a considerable amount of supernatural aid Habib was<lb/>
carried by a friendly roc to the bowels of Mt. Caucasus, where the treasure<lb/>
of King Solomon was hidden, guarded by benevolent genii. He was permitted to<lb/>
take therefrom the magic sword of Solomon engraved with the word &ldquo;POWER&rdquo;.<lb/>
Armed with this he was enabled to put to flight all of the evil spirits that<lb/>
attacked him in the form of horrible monsters of different kinds. By waving<lb/>
his sword and uttering the word of POWER, these monsters disappeared, disin-<lb/>
tegrated or fled before him, and he finally rescued the princess.</p>
<p>It seems to me that Reed, in this great fight against yellow fever,<lb/>
forged the sword of Solomon and engraved thereon the word of POWER. All honor<lb/>
to General Gorgas and everyone else who afterwards wielded this irresistible<lb/>
weapon in the fight against yellow Jack, but the conqueror of <unclear>Yellow</unclear> Jack is<lb/>
the forger of the sword and not the wielder thereof.</p>
<p>General J. R. Kean, retired, now Editor of &ldquo;The Military Surgeon&rdquo;,<lb/>
has this morning gone over your article with me, and these remarks and sug-<lb/>
gestions are made with his help. General Kean went to Cuba as Chief Surgeon<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06269037"/>
Mr. Mark Sullivan - 5.<lb/>
of the Seventh Army Corps, under Fitzhugh Lee, and was afterwards Chief of<lb/>
the Department of Beneficencia, under the American Governor of Cuba. He is<lb/>
intimately acquainted with all of the work against yellow fever that went on<lb/>
in Havana. I inclose you a copy of his editorial reviewing the recent<lb/>
biography of General Gorgas by his wife, and I also take the liberty of<lb/>
inclosing one of the few remaining copies of a little memoir of Walter Reed<lb/>
which I wrote in 1903 in the interests of the Walter Reed Memorial Association.<lb/>
You may find in them something to assist you.</p>
<p>I would suggest that, in case you would like to have the aid and<lb/>
testimony of one closely associated with General Gorgas during the Panama<lb/>
Canal period of his career, you communicate with General R. E. Noble, retired,<lb/>
who lives in Anniston, Alabama, but who is now in Washington for, I think, a<lb/>
few weeks, and whose address is c/o Mrs. M. R. Tyssowski, 2019 Columbia Road,<lb/>
N.W.</p>
<p>Your paper has interested me very much and I thank you for the<lb/>
opportunity of seeing it and commenting upon it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Faithfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Walter D. McCaw,<lb/>
Brigadier General, Med. Dept.,<lb/>
Assistant Surgeon General</signed>.
2 Incls.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
