<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06271010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Article: Vindicating Finlay's Glory, by Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, February 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06271010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-02-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Le-Roy y Cassa, Jorge</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William</name>
<name type="person">Vincent, George E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Argamonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>20 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-02-00">February 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06271010</idno>
<title>Article: Vindicating Finlay's Glory, by Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, February 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>LeRoy y Cassa defends Finlay against the claims of the Rockefeller Foundation and others. He refers to Marie Gorgas and Burton J. Hendrick's biography of William Crawford Gorgas.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1927-02-00">
<head>Article: Vindicating Finlay's Glory, by Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, February 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06271010"/>
<p>Translated from the Spanish, HRM</p>
<p>LeRoy y Cassa, Dr. Jorge</p>
<p>Reivindicacion de la gloria de Finlay, Sanidad y<lb/>
Beneficencia, Boletin Oficial, Havana, February and March,<lb/>
1927, v.32, p. 204-215.</p>
<p>The reputation of great men is in a position similar to that of<lb/>
precious articles exhibited in museums. In some people these articles arouse<lb/>
sentiments of admiration and appreciation for the craftsmen who made them and<lb/>
for their fortunate possessors; in others they arouse a desire to steal and to<lb/>
possess them, regardless of the method used to achieve this end.</p>
<p>It is, indeed, a pity that one should find it necessary to become a<lb/>
guardian of the glory of the benefactors of humanity in order to prevent<lb/>
usurpation of this glory by those who, having forgotten the commandment, &ldquo;Thou<lb/>
shalt not steal&rdquo; (Exodus, Chap. XX, Verse 15), in the Old Testament which Moses<lb/>
promulgated to the Hebrew people on descending from the summits of Sinai, stamp<lb/>
out historic truth and attribute to definite persons deeds that, were they alive,<lb/>
they would be the first indignantly to reject. Their honesty, their probity,<lb/>
their straightforward and patriotic judgment would not allow them to accept what<lb/>
others attribute to them, even though it cover them with the glorious splendors<lb/>
of discoveries foisted upon them by unscrupulous organizations who thus exemplify<lb/>
a well-known Spanish proverb to the effect that a foreigner is always fair prey<lb/>
to the mob.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06271011"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>The foregoing remarks were suggested to me by the firm in-<lb/>
sistence with which the Rockefeller Foundation has for years attributed<lb/>
to Reed and to the Commission appointed by the American Government,<lb/>
over which he presided (1900-1901), <hi>the discovery of the method of<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever</hi>. This opinion is also upheld in the book<lb/>
which has recently been published: <hi>William Crawford Gorgas--His Life<lb/>
and Works</hi>, by Marie D. Gorgas and Burton J. Hendrick; in an editorial,<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Fever Withdraws from the Americas&rdquo;, published by the <hi>Journal<lb/>
of the American Medical Association,</hi> Spanish edition, November 15, 1926,<lb/>
V. 16, p. 676, which reproduces almost <hi>ad pedem literae</hi> the section by<lb/>
Dr. George E. Vincent, President of the Rockefeller Foundation, in the<lb/>
<hi>&ldquo;Compte-Rendu de l'Oeuvre Accomplie en 1925&rdquo;</hi>, New York, 1926, p. 16-19.</p>
<p>The above article contains so many categorical and unjust<lb/>
statements that it is impossible to note them without making the neces-<lb/>
sary corrections, such as: &ldquo;Twenty-five years <unclear>ago,</unclear> the United States<lb/>
Commission, headed by Walter Reed, discovered in Havana the method of trans-<lb/>
mission (of yellow fever)&rdquo;; &ldquo;The yellow fever patient may infect the<lb/>
mosquito only on the first day of his disease&rdquo;; &ldquo;Now that the microbe<lb/>
that produces the fever is isolated, there are methods available for the<lb/>
diagnosis and possibly for immunity&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Were we not dealing with a publication of the importance and<lb/>
seriousness which characterizes the <hi>Journal of the American Medical<lb/>
Association</hi> and, above all, of the Spanish edition of this journal, which<lb/>
is read in all Central and South American countries and by other Spanish<lb/>
speaking people on the continent of Europe, we would have overlooked,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06271012"/>
-3-<lb/>
perhaps, these incorrect statements and this evident distortion of the<lb/>
historical truth. But since these remarks appeared in the nature of an<lb/>
editorial in such an important publication it is impossible to notice<lb/>
them without registering our protest, especially in view of the remarks<lb/>
made by Dr. Mario G. Lebredo at a solemn occasion (Feb. 6, 1926, on the<lb/>
unveiling of the bust of Finlay in the Academy of Medical Sciences):<lb/>
&ldquo;......only a few direct spokesmen of his fame are left; only a few of<lb/>
us who lived at the time of his campaign remain to impose his ideals,<lb/>
and the era is now beginning in which one has to search the literature<lb/>
to appreciate those moments when all scientific and applied speculation<lb/>
had to be derived from the principles of his doctrine. And, unfortunately,<lb/>
it is still necessary to make this point clear, for we still have to re-<lb/>
fer to his far-reaching <hi>fundamental</hi> and <hi>determining</hi> part in the magnifi-<lb/>
cent success in the eradication of yellow fever in order to correct<lb/>
the misinterpretation of the historical facts which tend to place his<lb/>
figure on a secondary plans.&rdquo; (Annals of the Academy of Medical, Physical<lb/>
and Natural Sciences of Havana, V. 62, p. 498; Bulletin of the Board of<lb/>
National Hygiene, Montevideo, 1926, p. 5-6 of the tribute to the memory<lb/>
of Dr. Carlos J. Finlay.)</p>
<p>Since I, fortunately, am one of the few survivors of that<lb/>
period in which Finlay worked with his faithful friend and constant<lb/>
collaborator, Dr. Claudio Delgado; since I witnessed the immortal work<lb/>
of the Commission of Medical Officers appointed by the Government of the<lb/>
United States, presided over by Reed, and which included Carroll, Lazear<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06271013"/>
-4-<lb/>
and our Agramonte, whom they also apparently would like to eliminate;<lb/>
since I collaborated with Finlay, Gorgas, Guiteras, Diaz Albertini, as<lb/>
Secretary of the Yellow Fever Commission precisely at the moment when<lb/>
Gorgas, by applying Finlay's doctrines which were demonstrated by the<lb/>
Commission, succeeded in completely eradicating yellow fever from our<lb/>
land; since it is not the first time that I have had to clarify this<lb/>
same subject, for in this Academy in the month of January and then in<lb/>
number 3 of February, 1924, I was compelled to use the columns of this<lb/>
very same <hi>Journal of the American Medical Association</hi> to refute similar<lb/>
beliefs, I now find it absolutely necessary to discuss once more this<lb/>
vexatious subject, for when the date to which Dr. Lebredo referred to<lb/>
comes, and it becomes necessary to search the literature for the appre-<lb/>
ciation of those moments, there shall be found together with the pub-<lb/>
lished errors the necessary corrections and the protest of those of us<lb/>
who have a right to do so, for we were his witnesses. It is our duty<lb/>
to do this as men of science who cannot allow the distortion of the<lb/>
truth of the historical facts.</p>
<p>We are to make use only of first-hand information, as given<lb/>
by those who actually took part in the work, and we shall limit ourselves<lb/>
in presenting their writings at the very moment in which a doctrine an-<lb/>
nounced twenty years earlier was being <hi>confirmed</hi> and not discovered. The<lb/>
Commission, by means of admirable and accurate experiments, demonstrated<lb/>
the doctrine and divulged it to the medical world in order that it may<lb/>
later be studied and confirmed in the various countries which were studying<lb/>
this important subject, since the black vomit was one of the greatest<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06271014"/>
-5-<lb/>
menaces and one of the greatest difficulties to the habitation of the<lb/>
tropics.</p>
<p>Let us now examine the facts.</p>
<p><hi>First statement</hi>: &ldquo;Twenty-five years ago the United States<lb/>
Commission headed by Walter Reed, discovered in Havana the method of<lb/>
transmission.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In Protocol No. 7, page 34, of the International Sanitary<lb/>
Conference held in Washington, D. C., and at the session of February 18,<lb/>
1881, Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, delegate of Cuba and Porto Rico, made the<lb/>
following remarks:</p>
<p>"My personal opinion is that three conditions are, in fact,<lb/>
necessary for the propagation of yellow fever:</p>
<p>"First - The presence of a previous case of yellow fever,<lb/>
within certain limits of time, counting from the moment we are considering.</p>
<p>"Second - The presence of a person apt to contract the disease.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Third - The presence of an agent entirely independent for<lb/>
its existence both of the disease and of the patient, but which is<lb/>
necessary in order that the disease shall be conveyed from the yellow<lb/>
fever patient to a healthy individual.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Finlay made these remarks in Washington, that is, in the<lb/>
United States, at an International Sanitary Conference; and they serve<lb/>
to answer the objection that Finlay wrote only in Cuba and for Cubans.<lb/>
As yet he does not state what is the intermediate agent between the sick<lb/>
and the non-immune; but a few months later, at the session of August 14,<lb/>
1881, (and not in 1880, as is erroneously stated in the Report of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06271015"/>
-6-<lb/>
General Wood) before the Royal Academy of Medical, Physical and Natural<lb/>
Sciences of Havana (Anales de la Real Academia De Ciencias Medicas,<lb/>
Fisicas y Naturales de la Habana, V. 18, pa. 147-169) he read a study<lb/>
entitled, &ldquo;The Mosquito Hypothetically Considered As Agent of Trans-<lb/>
mission of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, and his conclusions are as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Three conditions will, therefore, be necessary in order that<lb/>
yellow fever may be propagated: First, the existence of a yellow fever<lb/>
patient into whose capillaries the mosquito is able to drive its sting<lb/>
and to impregnate it with the virulent particles at an appropriate stage<lb/>
of the disease; second, that the life of the mosquito be spared after<lb/>
its bite upon the patient until it has a chance of biting the person in<lb/>
whom the disease is to be reproduced; third, the coincidence that some<lb/>
of the persons whom the same mosquito happens to bite thereafter shall<lb/>
be susceptible of contracting the disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In conclusion number 4 of this same study there is found a<lb/>
statement wherein with characteristic clearness Finlay foresees the<lb/>
successes that were to be demonstrated and even proved twenty years<lb/>
later by the American Commission and by the other Commissions which con-<lb/>
firmed the importance of the culcidae doctrine of yellow fever. He<lb/>
states as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Should it be finally proved that the mosquito inoculation<lb/>
not only reproduces the yellow fever, but that it constitutes the<lb/>
regular process through which the disease is propagated, the conditions<lb/>
of existence and of development for that dipterous insect would account<lb/>
for the anomalies hitherto observed in the propagation of yellow fever,<lb/>
and while we might, on the one hand, have the means of preventing the<lb/>
disease from spreading, non-immunes might at the same time be protected<lb/>
through a mild inoculation&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But there are still other statements of Finlay to be mentioned<lb/>
in order to show that long before the Commission was appointed which<lb/>
authentically proved his doctrines, he had already revealed in great<lb/>
details the transmission of yellow fever. The first statement was made<lb/>
in January, 1884, at the meeting of the Society of Clinical Studies of<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06271016"/>
-7-<lb/>
Havana held from January 31 to February 29. On this occasion he read<lb/>
another study on the &ldquo;experimental yellow fever compared with the natural<lb/>
in its benign forms,&rdquo; and &ldquo;experimental yellow fever inoculated by means<lb/>
of bites of mosquitoes&rdquo; which he published, revised and annotated in the<lb/>
ARCHIVOS DE LA SOCIEDAD DE ESTUDIOS CLINICOS DE LA HABANA (1903, V. 12,<lb/>
p. 281-332). In the latter study he states as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The fact that yellow fever can be inoculated by the bites<lb/>
of mosquitoes proves the necessity of protecting the patients infected<lb/>
with disease against such bites in order to prevent the propagation of<lb/>
the disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This conclusion, the fundamental principle on which the<lb/>
prophylaxis of yellow fever rests at the present time, is all the more<lb/>
interesting because it was formulated at the beginning of 1884, and<lb/>
represents the synthesis of the work read in the same Academy towards<lb/>
the end of 1898 (November 13) wherein he reveals the fundamental basis<lb/>
which Gorgas in 1901 used for the eradication of this terrible endemic<lb/>
from our country which had constantly been devastating our capital since<lb/>
1761. Finlay concludes that study by stating that:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In accordance with the theories on mosquitoes, in order to<lb/>
free the Island of Cuba from two of the most terrible scourges which have<lb/>
ravaged the land (yellow fever and malaria) it will be necessary, then, to<lb/>
declare a constant war against the mosquito and to surround each yellow<lb/>
fever or malaria patient with all the imaginable precautions to prevent<lb/>
that these insects become infected by the ill or by their infectious<lb/>
products.&rdquo; &ldquo;The mosquitoes considered as agents of transmission of yellow<lb/>
fever and malaria&rdquo;, published in English under title: &ldquo;Mosquitoes Con-<lb/>
sidered As Transmitters of Yellow Fever and Malaria&rdquo; in the NEW YORK<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06271017"/>
-8-<lb/>
MEDICAL RECORD, New York, 1899, (V. 45, p. 737-739, May 27).</p>
<p>Up to this point we have been considering Finlay. Let us now<lb/>
examine in chronological order the facts as recorded by the American Com-<lb/>
mission. Professor Sanarelli had announced his discovery that the<lb/>
specific cause of the vomit was the icteroides bacillus and for this<lb/>
purpose Dr. George Sternberg who at that time held the position of Sur-<lb/>
geon General of the United States and who had come as Secretary of the<lb/>
First Commission appointed by that country in 1879, presided over by<lb/>
Professor Chaille, in turn appointed a Commission presided over by Dr.<lb/>
Walter Reed, and composed of Drs. James Carroll, Aristides Agramonte and<lb/>
Jesse W. Lazear, created &ldquo;for the study of acute infectious diseases of<lb/>
the Island of Cuba&rdquo;. This is what they themselves state in the preliminary<lb/>
note published on October 27, 1900, in the PHILADELPHIA MEDICAL JOURNAL<lb/>
and translated by Dr. Guiteras for his REVISTA DE MEDICINA TROPICAL (Havana,<lb/>
October, 1900, V. 1, p. 49-64). This work was read before the American<lb/>
Public Health Association, at its 28th meeting, in Indianapolis, United<lb/>
States of America.</p>
<p>In this study Dr. Reed and his associates made the following<lb/>
statement:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Mosquito as host of the yellow fever parasite. Having<lb/>
failed to isolate B. icteroides, either from the blood during life, or<lb/>
from the organs of cadavers, two courses of procedure in our further in-<lb/>
vestigations appeared to be deserving of attention, viz., first, a careful<lb/>
study of the intestinal flora in yellow fever in comparison with the bac-<lb/>
teria that we might isolate from the intestinal canal of healthy individuals,<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06271018"/>
-9-<lb/>
in this vicinity, or of those sick with other diseases; and secondly, to<lb/>
give our attention to the theory of the propagation of yellow fever by<lb/>
means of the mosquito--a theory first advanced and ingeniously discussed<lb/>
by Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, of Havana, in 1881 (<hi>Anales de la Real Academia,</hi><lb/>
V. 18, 1881, pp. 147-169.) We were influenced to take up the second line<lb/>
of investigation by reason of the well-known facts connected with the<lb/>
epidemiology of this disease, and, of course, by the brilliant work of<lb/>
Ross and the Italian observers, in connection with the theory of the<lb/>
propagation of malaria by the mosquito.&rdquo;</p>
<p>And a little further on they add:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In view of the foregoing observations (referring to Carter's<lb/>
investigations) we concluded to test the theory of Finlay on human beings.<lb/>
According to this author's observations of numerous inoculations in 90<lb/>
individuals, the application of one or two contaminated mosquitoes is not<lb/>
dangerous, but followed in about 18%, by an attack of what he considers<lb/>
to be a very benign yellow fever at most.&rdquo; &ldquo;We here desire to express our<lb/>
sincere thanks to Dr. Finlay, who accorded us a most courteous interview<lb/>
and has gladly placed at our disposal his several publications relating to<lb/>
yellow fever, during the past 19 years; and also for ova of the species of<lb/>
mosquito with which he had made his several inoculations. An important ob-<lb/>
servation to be recorded here is that, according to Finlay's statement,<lb/>
30 days prior to our visit, these ova had been deposited by a female just<lb/>
at the edge of the water in a small basin, whose contents had been allowed<lb/>
to slightly evaporate, so that these ova were at the time of our visit<lb/>
entirely above contact with the water. Notwithstanding this long interval<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06271019"/>
-10-<lb/>
after deposition, they were promptly converted into the larval stage,<lb/>
after a short period, by raising the level of the water in the basin.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With the mosquitoes thus obtained we have been able to con-<lb/>
duct our experiments. Specimens of this mosquito forwarded to Mr. L. A.<lb/>
Howard, Entomologist, Department of Agriculture, Washington, D. C., were<lb/>
kindly identified as Culex Fasciatus, Fabr.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;In this preliminary note we have no space to refer, at length,<lb/>
to the various interesting and valuable contributions made by Finlay to<lb/>
the mosquito theory for the propagation of yellow fever......&rdquo;</p>
<p>The above remarks were written by the Commission presided over<lb/>
by Reed and made public in Indianapolis, United States, in nothing less<lb/>
than at a meeting of the American Public Health Association, the most<lb/>
notable authority in questions of public hygiene in that great country.</p>
<p>The conclusions arrived at by the members of the Commission,<lb/>
published in that <hi>Preliminary Note</hi> were: with reference to the first<lb/>
part of its study that:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Bacillus icteroides (Sanarelli) stands in no causative<lb/>
relation to yellow fever, but, when present, it should be considered as<lb/>
a secondary invader on this disease.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of the second part of our study of yellow fever we draw the<lb/>
following conclusion: the mosquito serves as the intermediate host for<lb/>
the parasite of yellow fever and it is very probable that the disease<lb/>
is only propagated by the bite of this insect.&rdquo;</p>
<p>At the Third Pan American Medical Congress held in Havana<lb/>
from February 4 to 8, 1901, Drs. Reed, Carroll and Agramonte, for poor<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06271020"/>
-11-<lb/>
Lazear had sacrificed his life in the holocaust of science and died as<lb/>
a result of yellow fever which had been inoculated by the mosquitoes in<lb/>
the Field of Experimentation,--the latter has since been named in his honor--<lb/>
read an <hi>Additional Note</hi> to the one presented in Indianapolis during the<lb/>
previous year in which they revealed all the work, observations and ex-<lb/>
periments which will make the names of said members of the commissions<lb/>
immortal, for science and humanity owes them the greatest debt of gratitude<lb/>
of our times.</p>
<p>Up to the present we have seen that Reed and his associates<lb/>
of the Commission recognize Finlay as the discoverer of the theory that<lb/>
yellow fever is transmitted by the mosquito. Let us now <del>see what</del><add>examine</add> Gorgas,<lb/>
the great organizer of the public health of Cuba, the good, just, modest,<lb/>
uncensurable man who collaborated with Finlay and who was fortunate enough to<lb/>
witness the eradication of yellow fever--by the application of the doctrines<lb/>
of this learned man--first from Cuba, then from Panama, and who later con-<lb/>
tinued his fight against the yellow monster into the heart of Africa,<lb/>
which he was unable to reach on account of his death in London on his way<lb/>
to investigate the existence of this disease in the African continent<lb/>
and, if present, to eradicate it.</p>
<p>Well, Gorgas in his Report as Commander, Surgeon of the Army<lb/>
of the United States, and Chief of the Public Health Department of Havana,<lb/>
for the year 1901, on July 9 of that year stated as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Towards the middle of February of the current year we based<lb/>
our campaign against yellow fever on the supposition that the mosquito is<lb/>
the method by which the disease is transmitted from one person to another.<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06271021"/>
- 12 -<lb/>
This theory which was originally presented by Dr. Carlos Finlay of Havana<lb/>
has finally been confirmed by the beautiful and complete experiments made<lb/>
by the Yellow Fever Commission presided over by Commander Walter Reed.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;When the results of these experiments became known, the Military<lb/>
Governor, General Leonard Wood, ordered that great efforts be made to dis-<lb/>
infect the areas in accordance with the indications of this discovery. The<lb/>
results of the work accomplished <hi>during the last four months</hi> have strength-<lb/>
ened the conclusions arrived at by the Commission.&rdquo; REPORT OF THE COMMANDER<lb/>
W. C. GORGAS, Havana, July 8, 1901 (p. 98).</p>
<p>On November 5, of the same year (1901) and in the same source of<lb/>
information (p. 210) Gorgas wrote as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I insist most emphatically on the records of yellow fever in our<lb/>
sanitary statistics, because of its considerable practical importance for<lb/>
the United States, and because it has definitely been assured that yellow<lb/>
fever is transmitted by the &ldquo;Stegomyia&rdquo; mosquito, a fact upheld by Dr.<lb/>
Carlos Finlay as against the ridiculous theory which has prevailed for so<lb/>
many years. Finlay's theory has recently been demonstrated by the com-<lb/>
mission of army officers, and will soon change our methods of quarantine<lb/>
in the United States.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The theory that the mosquito is the only method of spreading the<lb/>
disease is responsible for the success of our work in Havana this year.<lb/>
Since we have not considered it necessary to disinfect the clothing and<lb/>
other contaminable substances, we have concentrated our efforts in killing<lb/>
the mosquitoes which may have bitten the patient and in preventing other<lb/>
mosquitoes from doing likewise. Our results in accordance with this plan<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06271022"/>
- 13 -<lb/>
have been so positive that we soon saw not only the possibility of freeing<lb/>
Havana from yellow fever but also of destroying all the foci of infection<lb/>
imported from the exterior.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In the &ldquo;Vital Statistics Report of the Cities of Havana and<lb/>
Guanabacia, submitted to the Brigadier General Leonard Wood, U.S.A.,<lb/>
Military Governor, in January, 1902, Gorgas himself wrote:</p>
<p>&ldquo;In the summer of 1900 a commission of Army medical officers<lb/>
headed by Major Walter Reed, U.S. Army, had been sent to Cuba for the<lb/>
investigation and study of yellow fever. Due to the financial assistance<lb/>
given by the Military Governor to this Commission, they were enabled to<lb/>
experiment on the human subject. They based their work on the theory ad-<lb/>
vanced by Dr. Carlos Finlay, of Havana, in the year 1880, (it was in the<lb/>
year 1881) that the <hi>Stegomyia</hi> mosquito was the sole means of the trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever. Dr. Finlay had maintained this theory for some<lb/>
twenty years, and had done considerable experimental work in this direc-<lb/>
tion.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Commission through elaborate and careful experimentation,<lb/>
proved this theory to be correct, and in February, 1901, Doctor Reed read<lb/>
a paper before the International Sanitary Congress, in Havana, (it was the<lb/>
third Pan American Medical Congress) giving the results of their work.<lb/>
This idea was so new and so entirely contrary to all former theories on<lb/>
the subject, and, apparently, to all former experience, that the paper was<lb/>
received with scant belief. I myself had seen the experiments, and was<lb/>
convinced that the mosquito could convey yellow fever, but I could not<lb/>
accept the theory that it was the only way, or even the ordinary way, of<lb/>
conveying the disease.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="14" id="f06271023"/>
<p>- 14 -</p>
<p>Finally, Gorgas himself in his last REPORT written in the<lb/>
General Quarters of the Department of Cuba, Prefecture of the Department<lb/>
of Public Health, and dated Havana, July 12, 1902, addressed to the Briga-<lb/>
dier General Leonard Wood, Army of the United States, Washington, D.C.,<lb/>
states as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;General: I herewith forward the report of the sanitary department,<lb/>
bringing the account of the work up to May 20, of the present year.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;This being the final report of the sanitary department of the<lb/>
City of Havana, under the Military Government, it might be useful to review,<lb/>
in a general way, the work of the department since its inception in 1899.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;The great object of sanitation for Cuba, and particularly for<lb/>
Havana, as far as the United States was concerned, was the eradication of<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He discusses at great length the conditions in which they found<lb/>
the island and especially Havana; the dangers to which the country was sub-<lb/>
ject as a result of the infected neighborhood. He reproduces integrally<lb/>
the paragraphs which I have just transcribed from the Report issued in<lb/>
January, 1902, and he also describes the work carried out from February 4,<lb/>
1901, for combating yellow fever which caused him to change his opinion,<lb/>
and fully convinced he then says:</p>
<p>&ldquo;But there is no doubt that the most important sanitary lesson<lb/>
with regard to yellow fever is that the disease is only conveyed by the<lb/>
Stegomyia mosquito; that the disease can readily be eradicated, even when<lb/>
it has gotten a firm hold, and easily kept from establishing itself by<lb/>
taking measures looking for the mosquito as its cause.&rdquo; (p. 8).</p>
<pb n="15" id="f06271024"/>
<p>- 15 -</p>
<p>Up to this point we have been examining in a clear and precise<lb/>
manner the statements made by Reed and his associates of the Commission,<lb/>
and the remarks and statements made by Gorgas on various occasions. Let<lb/>
us now see the statements made in a solemn and formal manner by General<lb/>
Wood, who was not only the Military Governor of Cuba, but also a physician.<lb/>
This enabled him to personally appreciate not merely by reference, the<lb/>
truth of the facts which he himself describes in the REPORT OF THE BRIGADIER<lb/>
GENERAL LEONARD WOOD, U. S. A., MILITARY GOVERNOR OF CUBA for the period<lb/>
January 1 to May 20, 1902 (pages 172-174).</p>
<p>"Affairs were in this condition when a systematic investigation<lb/>
of yellow fever was undertaken by Drs. Reed, Carroll and Lazear (where does<lb/>
he leave Agramonte?). These officers took up the work in a very thorough<lb/>
and conscientious manner, starting at the point previously reached by<lb/>
Dr. Finlay.</p>
<p>&ldquo;They accepted Dr. Finlay's idea that yellow fever was transmitted<lb/>
by a mosquito. After several preliminary investigations, Dr. Lazear sub-<lb/>
mitted himself voluntarily as a subject for an experiment for the purpose<lb/>
of demonstrating that the yellow fever could be transmitted in this way.<lb/>
He was inoculated by an infected mosquito, took the fever and died.<lb/>
Dr. Carroll was also bitten by a mosquito and had a rather serious case<lb/>
of yellow fever, but, fortunately, recovered....&rdquo;</p>
<p>He then discusses the financial assistance given to the Commission<lb/>
for its experimental investigations and the conditions required by them, and<lb/>
continues as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The Stegomyia mosquito was found to be beyond question the means<lb/>
of transmitting yellow fever. This mosquito, in order to become infected,<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06271025"/>
- 16 -<lb/>
must bite a person sick with the yellow fever during the first five days<lb/>
of the disease. It then requires approximately ten days for the germ to<lb/>
so develop that the mosquito can transmit the disease, and all non-immunes<lb/>
who are bitten by a mosquito of the class mentioned, infected as described,<lb/>
invariably develop a pronounced cases of yellow fever in from three and a<lb/>
half to five days from the time they are bitten. It was further demon-<lb/>
strated that infection from cases so produced could be again transmitted<lb/>
by the above described type of mosquito to another person who would, in<lb/>
turn, have yellow fever. It was also proved that yellow fever could be<lb/>
transmitted by means of introduction of blood or blood serum, even after<lb/>
filtering through porcelain filters, which latter experiment indicates<lb/>
that the organism is exceedingly small, - so small, in fact, that it is<lb/>
probably beyond the power of any microscope at present in use. It was<lb/>
positively demonstrated that yellow fever could not be transmitted by<lb/>
clothing, contact, etc., and that, consequently, all the old methods of<lb/>
fumigation and disinfection were only useful in so far as they served to<lb/>
destroy mosquitoes, their young and their eggs.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;With the establishment of these facts, there was inaugurated an<lb/>
entirely new method of dealing with yellow fever, - a method very similar<lb/>
to that adopted in the treatment of malaria fever, with the only difference<lb/>
that it is carried out much more thoroughly (p. 174).&rdquo;</p>
<p>We have limited ourselves in quoting those authorities who took<lb/>
a direct and immediate part in the demonstration and confirmation of the<lb/>
doctrines which Finlay upheld as early as February, 1881, in Washington,<lb/>
because no one is better qualified to testify to the truth; that is, that<lb/>
Finlay before anybody else discovered the method of transmission of yellow<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f06271026"/>
- 17 -<lb/>
fever from the patient to the healthy, and that this method was the<lb/>
mosquito. Where is, then, the solemn affirmation made by the Rockefeller<lb/>
Foundation of the DISCOVERY of Reed, if he himself states the truth, which<lb/>
is contrary to that false statement? This fact simply and clearly con-<lb/>
stitutes an usurpation and what has been said above serves to confirm it<lb/>
in a categorical manner.</p>
<p><hi>Second affirmation</hi>: &ldquo;The yellow fever patient may infect the mosquito<lb/>
only during the first day of his sickness.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Let us see what Finlay says.</p>
<p>In the conclusions of the second part &ldquo;experimental yellow fever<lb/>
inoculated by means of bites from mosquito&rdquo; of the work &ldquo;experimental yellow<lb/>
fever compared with the natural in its benign forms&rdquo; dated 1884 (TRABAJOS<lb/>
SELECTOS DEL DR. CARLOS J. FINLAY, Havana, 1912, p. 103) he states as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>"1. Yellow fever is regularly inoculated on the third, fourth, fifth<lb/>
and sixth days of its usual development by means of the bite of the diurnal<lb/>
mosquito of Havana (Culex Mosquito-Robineau Desvoidy) and in a footnote of<lb/>
the page in the revised and annotated work by the author and published in<lb/>
the above source it states: &ldquo;In my recent investigations I have noted that<lb/>
the only condition for infecting the mosquitoes is that the disease should<lb/>
not develop beyond the fifth or sixth day. The French Commission of Brazil<lb/>
(1901-1903) has demonstrated that the fever is not communicated by injecting<lb/>
blood of the fourth nor of the eighth day.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;2. The above disease may be transmitted by the above mentioned method<lb/>
during the first days and after the sixth day of its evolution, regardless<lb/>
of the intensity of the symptoms present in this latter period.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="18" id="f06271027"/>
<p>- 18 -</p>
<p>In its turn, the Commission presided over by Reed and which was<lb/>
then composed by J. Carroll and A. Agramonte in its <hi>Additional Note</hi> called<lb/>
&ldquo;The etiology of yellow fever&rdquo; presented to the Third Pan American Medical<lb/>
Congress held in Havana in February, 1901, contains the following conclu-<lb/>
sion dealing with our present study:</p>
<p>"2. Yellow fever is transmitted to the nonimmune individual by means<lb/>
of the bite of the mosquito that has previously fed on the blood of those<lb/>
sick with this disease.</p>
<p>"3. It appears that an interval of twelve or more days, after contam-<lb/>
ination appears to be necessary before the mosquito is capable of conveying<lb/>
the infection.</p>
<p>"4. The bite of the mosquito at an earlier period than that mentioned<lb/>
in the preceding paragraph does not appear to confer any immunity against<lb/>
a subsequent attack of yellow fever.</p>
<p>&ldquo;5. Yellow fever can also be experimentally produced by the subcutan-<lb/>
eous injection of blood taken from the general circulation during the first<lb/>
and second days of this attack.&rdquo;</p>
<p>During the period that has elapsed since Finlay wrote his study<lb/>
in 1884 and that in which the Commission submitted its report in 1900-1901,<lb/>
the distinguished investigators who have studied this subject have not<lb/>
differed in anyway from what those authors had expressed; therefore it is<lb/>
to be supposed that a gross error has been made by the author of the edi-<lb/>
torial on which we are commenting when he states that &ldquo;the yellow fever<lb/>
patient may infect the mosquito only on the first day of his disease&rdquo;.</p>
<p>We now come to the third and last of the statements of the above<lb/>
mentioned writer: &ldquo;Now that the microbe of the fever has been isolated,<lb/>
there are methods available for the diagnosis and possibly for immunity.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="19" id="f06271028"/>
<p>- 19 -</p>
<p>A special article has just been published in No. 51 of volume 41<lb/>
of the PUBLIC HEALTH REPORTS issued weekly by the United States Public Health<lb/>
Service entitled: &ldquo;The Control of Communicable Diseases&rdquo; containing the<lb/>
report issued by the Committee on Standard Regulations to which the various<lb/>
sanitary services must be subjected. This report was prepared by the Ameri-<lb/>
can Public Health Association at its 55th meeting held in Buffalo, N.Y., on<lb/>
October 11, 1926, and approved by the Governing Council of the Association<lb/>
on October 14, 1926. The above report begins by defining the terms generally<lb/>
used to avoid possible errors or misinterpretations; each disease is briefly<lb/>
described in relation to its infectious agent; the source of infection; the<lb/>
mode of transmission; the period of incubation and of communicability; then<lb/>
control methods are given both for the individual and his environment and<lb/>
finally the general measures for the prevention of the diseases. Well, then,<lb/>
in that article, which is officially approved by the Public Health Service<lb/>
of the United States, the following statement occurs under yellow fever<lb/>
which I have translated:</p>
<p>1.- Infectious agent - Unknown</p>
<p>6.- Methods of control</p>
<p>3.- Immunization - None.</p>
<p>This does not need any comment, and with it I have answered the<lb/>
last statement which we refute.</p>
<p>Now, then, there is only one logical conclusion to be drawn from<lb/>
all that has been said above! The person is guilty either of gross ignor-<lb/>
ance or of a manifest determination to usurp the glory of the greatest man<lb/>
that America has produced in the medical field during the last half century.<lb/>
<pb n="20" id="f06271029"/>
- 20 -<lb/>
If the former is the case, it must be agreed that that ignorance is in-<lb/>
excusable by those who hold a high position in the scientific world. If<lb/>
the latter is the case, the entire weight of the blame by the man who<lb/>
loves truth and justice must fall on them.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
