<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06272035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to James E. Peabody, September 22, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06272035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-09-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Peabody, James E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Hendrick, Burton J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Meritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="place">Indianapolis (Ind.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-09-22">September 22, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06272035</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to James E. Peabody, September 22, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean responds to Peabody's questions about the work of the Yellow Fever Commission, offering his view on the contributions of various men and commenting on illustrations Peabody has selected for his article.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-09-22">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to James E. Peabody, September 22, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06272035"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Army Medical Museum,<lb/>
Seventh and B Streets S. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1928-09-22">22 September, 1928.</date>
</dateline>
Prof. James E. Peabody,<lb/>
The Morris High School,<lb/>
New York City.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Prof. Peabody:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter has just come with the galley of the illustrations<lb/>
of your article. That figure 14 is certainly no joke on me, because<lb/>
have not and never had the remotest connection with it. People who<lb/>
like practical jokes might think it a joke on Gorgas because it is<lb/>
certainly is a most unflattering picture of him, but it is he all<lb/>
right. I will lokk up a picture as soon as I go home and send it to<lb/>
you. I will try to find you one of those days when I was a Major.<lb/>
As you have three pictures of Kissinger and one of Jernegan, why don't<lb/>
you have a picture of Moran who was the real hero of that bunch, the<lb/>
man who volunteered at the same time with Kissinger, who always re-<lb/>
fused to accept any gratuity and has always shown a fine spirit of<lb/>
dignity and independence. I think we can probably scrape up a pic-<lb/>
ture of him if you want it. His present address is John J. Moran,<lb/>
Emprado 22, Habana, Cuba.</p>
<p>I do not think there are any points of dispute between Reed's<lb/>
friends and Gorgas'. Mr. Hendrick who collaborated with Mrs. Gorgas<lb/>
on their biography of him made some absurd claims of credit to Gorgas<lb/>
which belonged to Reed but I have direct information that this was<lb/>
done quite contrary to Mrs. Gorgas' wishes and belief. I understand<lb/>
that he cut out what she wrote and put in his own stuff because he<lb/>
thought it made a better story. Also I don't think there is any con-<lb/>
troversy between the friends of Finlay and Carter. I never heard of<lb/>
any. As to Agramonte and Noguchi, there is no longer any controversy.<lb/>
Agramonte was right all along, and Noguchi's friends and companions<lb/>
now all admit that he was in error.</p>
<p>You ask waht Agramonte did on the Commission. It was fully as im-<lb/>
portant as Carroll's or Lazear's. In the first investigations of the<lb/>
Board which cleared the field. Carroll had the bacteriological work,<lb/>
Agramonte the autopsy work and gross pathology, and Lazear the micro-<lb/>
scopical pathology. When the mosquito work was taken up, Lazear had<lb/>
charge of the mosquitoes as he had previous training with mosquito work<lb/>
when studying malaria in Italy. Agramonte conducted the autopsies<lb/>
and studied the pathological anatomy. Carroll continued to do the bac-<lb/>
teriological work. After Lazear's death, Agramonte took charge of the<lb/>
Mosquitoes and for a while when Carroll was ill and recuperating from<lb/>
his attack of yellow fever and Reed was absent in the United States,<lb/>
he had charge of everything. Agramonte and Lazear were classmates in<lb/>
Columbia University Medical School, and he is a fine man. I am sure<lb/>
that no Congressman will vote against the bill for the inclusion of<lb/>
his name. I explained the importance of recognizing his work fully to<lb/>
the Military Committee at their hearing last soring.</p>
<p>You ask why the Cubans do not honor Agramonte. I think they do but<lb/>
it is a little hobby of theirs to soft pedal the work of the Reed Board<lb/>
and give as much credit as possible to Finlay. <unclear>gramonte</unclear> received a<lb/>
great ovation at the medical meeting in New Orleans and was given a<lb/>
medal for his contributions to the victory of the Reed Board over yel-<lb/>
low fever.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06272036"/>
<p>I don't see any objection to your labelling figure 24 &ldquo;germs that<lb/>
Dr. Noguchi thought caused yellow fever&rdquo; but some of his friends may<lb/>
feel differently about this advertising of an error which he <unclear>told</unclear> for<lb/>
with his life. Why don't you ask Dr. F. F. Russell of the Rockefeller<lb/>
Foundation? He was devoted to Noguchi and was also one of <unclear>our</unclear> most<lb/>
distinguished army surgeons. I think it would be well to add to your<lb/>
label the statement that &ldquo;the true germ has never been discovered.&rdquo;</p>
<p>When you see Col. Wainwright I hope you will hearted him up. He<lb/>
seemed quite discouraged the last time General Ireland and I talked<lb/>
to him on the subject.</p>
<p>Yes, Reed's first announcement of his demonstration of the car-<lb/>
rying of yellow fever by the mosquito was made before the 28th. An-<lb/>
nual Meeting of the American Public Health Association at Indianap-<lb/>
olis, October 22-26, <unclear>1900</unclear>, where he read a paper entitled &ldquo;The<lb/>
Etiology of Yellow Fever<unclear>--</unclear> preliminary Notes&rdquo; His next paper in<lb/>
which <unclear>cation</unclear> was fully set forth, together with the<lb/>
<unclear>means</unclear> for preventing yellow fever by waging war on <unclear>th</unclear> mosquito, was<lb/>
read at the Pan-American Medical Congress, Habana, Cuba, February 4-7<lb/>
1901.</p>
<p>You are certainly wonderfully energetic in carrying on this work<lb/>
and getting hold of influential people. I am sure that you would <unclear>hav</unclear><lb/>
no difficulty in having a few minutes talk with the Secretary of War<lb/>
if he is in Washington when you are here.</p>
<p>I will <unclear>goak</unclear> to the Curator of the Museum and see if he will make<lb/>
a photograph of the model of Camp Lazear and make a photostat copy of<lb/>
the agreement between Major Reed (not General Wood) and the Spanish<lb/>
immigrant Antonio Benino (sweet <unclear>potatoes</unclear>).</p>
<p>With best wishes, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean,<lb/>
Colonel, U. S. Army, Ret.</signed>
-----<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
