<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06278004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with the Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06278004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1934-11-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Waring, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Matt</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Page, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Dodge, Col.</name>
<name type="person">Hanna, Lt.</name>
<name type="person">Brooks, E.C.</name>
<name type="person">Ferguson, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Guanajai (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Vedado (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Army Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1934-11-05">November 5, 1934</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06278004</idno>
<title>Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with the Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Baker's recollections of yellow fever in Havana from 1898 to 1900 include a description of deaths among the American military officers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1934-11-05">
<head>Recollections of Personal Experiences in Connection with the Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana 1898-1899-1900, by Chauncey B. Baker, November 5, 1934</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06278004"/>
<p>FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>With <unclear>Gen</unclear> Kean's<lb/>
<unclear>corrections</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Recollections of Personal Experiences<lb/>
In Connection With<lb/>
Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana<lb/>
1898 - 1899 - 1900</hi></p>
<p>Related By<lb/>
General Chauncey B. Baker</p>
<p>At Luncheon To<lb/>
The Board of Directors Of<lb/>
The American National Fire Insurance Company<lb/>
on<lb/>
November 5, 1934</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06278005"/>
<p>Par. 2 - Gen. Baker is in error as<lb/>
Major Gorgas never at any time had<lb/>
charge of street cleaning - only of<lb/>
patios &amp; backyards when made<lb/>
Sat Officers in 1900-</p>
<p>Baker turned our street cleaning to<lb/>
Major Barber of Vols who was<lb/>
succeeded by Major Black (after<lb/>
Chief Eng Corps) in 1900-</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06278006"/>
<p>Recollections of Personal Experiences<lb/>
In Connection With<lb/>
Yellow Fever Epidemics in Havana<lb/>
1898 - 1899 - 1900<lb/>
------------------<lb/>
(Dictated by Request)</p>
<p>Our Secretary, Mr. McLelland, has asked me to<lb/>
place on record the recital I gave at a recent meeting<lb/>
of our Board of Directors of episodes connected with<lb/>
Walter Reed and his investigations and discoveries with<lb/>
reference to yellow fever.</p>
<p>1 In November, 1898, after we had taken Santiago<lb/>
and peace had been made, a Peace Commission, of which<lb/>
General Wade was President for the United States and<lb/>
General Blanco for the Spanish Government, was formed<lb/>
for the purpose of arranging the details of transfer of<lb/>
the governmental authority from the Spanish Crown to the<lb/>
United States Government. During the sittings of this<lb/>
Commission, which commenced in August, an epidemic of<lb/>
yellow fever broke out in Havana. Colonel Williams, of<lb/>
the United States Army, and Colonel Waring, head of the<lb/>
Sanitary Department of New York City, had been ordered<lb/>
to Havana to make preliminary provisions of transfer,<lb/>
respectively, of everything pertaining to the Quarter-<lb/>
master's Department and to sanitation.</p>
<p>2 In November these two officers, together with<lb/>
a large number of their clerical force, died of yellow<lb/>
fever. I was ordered to Havana to take over the office<lb/>
of Colonel Williams and another officer was ordered<lb/>
there to take up the work of Colonel Waring. The second<lb/>
officer did not arrive, so when I reached Havana in<lb/>
November I found myself at the head of the Quartermaster's<lb/>
Department, under the orders of General Charles F. Humphrey,<lb/>
and in charge of the Sanitary Department, which had been<lb/>
undertaken by Colonel Waring. The latter activities I<lb/>
transferred to Major <unclear><hi>Gorgas</hi></unclear>, of the Medical Corps, who<lb/>
later was made Surgeon General of the Army, in the fol-<lb/>
lowing year, but I continued with the Quartermaster's<lb/>
Department until the final withdrawal of our troops on<lb/>
the twentieth of May, 1902.</p>
<p><unclear>no -<lb/>
Maj. Barbor<lb/>
Col Black</unclear></p>
<p>3 There was much sickness at this period and<lb/>
great anxiety on account of the prevalence of yellow<lb/>
fever. Colonel Williams and Colonel Waring had occupied<lb/>
an office jointly next door to the Passaje Hotel on the<lb/>
Prado. Practically all the clerks of both these offices<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06278007"/>
5-<lb/>
Mrs. Peterson was north at time her<lb/>
husband was taken ill &amp; hastened<lb/>
back arriving just the day of his death<lb/>
She shot herself not for fear of y. f-<lb/>
but because she did not wish to live<lb/>
without him-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06278008"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
met me on my arrival, with a resignation in one hand<lb/>
and a request for transportation back to the United<lb/>
States in the other. Of the few who remained, notably<lb/>
Sergeant Merzig and Mr. Curry, I proceeded to build a<lb/>
new organization for both services.</p>
<p>4 As the colder weather came on, the yellow<lb/>
fever conditions decreased in intensity and did not<lb/>
reappear again in epidemic form until two years later,<lb/>
in 1900. In that year, symptoms of the epidemic ap-<lb/>
peared in Havana and various outlying centers, notably<lb/>
Pinar del Rio, Guanajai, Vedado, Quemados and various<lb/>
military stations. At this time I had become the Chief<lb/>
Quartermaster of the Department of Cuba -- General<lb/>
Humphrey, my predecessor, having been ordered to duty<lb/>
in China. I occupied for my office the building then<lb/>
known as the Segundo Cabo, facing the Plaza on which<lb/>
was located the Governor General's Palace. In this<lb/>
same building were located the offices of Chief Pay-<lb/>
master and Chief Commissary. In a vacant room on the<lb/>
second floor of this building we organized a small<lb/>
mess, where we served our luncheons. There were eight<lb/>
people who were members of this mess, including my<lb/>
principal assistant, Major George Cartwright, Major<lb/>
Matt Peterson, Chief Commissary Officer, Mrs. Peterson,<lb/>
his wife, Captain Page, and aide-de-camp to the Command-<lb/>
ing General, Colonel Dodge, the Chief Paymaster,<lb/>
Lieutenant Hanna, an aide-de-camp to the Commanding<lb/>
General, Lieutenant E. C. Brooks, an aide-de-camp to<lb/>
the Commanding General, General Wood.</p>
<p>5 The earliest deaths from yellow fever during<lb/>
this epidemic occurred outside the limits of Havana,<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio and Marianao. The first of this group<lb/>
at mess to go down with yellow fever was Major<lb/>
George Cartwright, my principal assistant, who died<lb/>
of the disease. Sitting at his left was Major Peterson,<lb/>
who went down with the disease and died. Mrs. Peterson<lb/>
was ill at the time and when she was told by Major Gorgas<lb/>
that he feared she had contracted the disease, she pro-<lb/>
duced a pistol from her bag and shot herself. On the<lb/>
next day, as I followed this double funeral to the<lb/>
last resting place, a carriage ahead of me turned out<lb/>
and I paused long enough to speak with the occupant,<lb/>
Captain Page, who informed me that he was so ill he<lb/>
could not proceed. I told him I would go on to the<lb/>
funeral and as soon as I got back would get in touch<lb/>
with him. Page occupied quarters at the top story of<lb/>
Segundo Cabo. When I returned to my office I found<lb/>
him there, unable to climb the stairs to his quarters,<lb/>
and with help I assisted him to his room at the top of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06278009"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
the building. Within forty-eight hours he died of<lb/>
yellow fever. The next to be stricken with the<lb/>
disease was Colonel Dodge, Chief Paymaster of the<lb/>
Department. Fortunately, he recovered and later<lb/>
became Paymaster General of the Army. The next place<lb/>
at the table was vacant as Lieutenant Hanna had taken<lb/>
a leave of absence, returned to the United States, and<lb/>
later resigned his commission in the Army. That left<lb/>
Captain E. C. Brooks and me looking across the corner<lb/>
of the table at one another.</p>
<p><unclear>1 x</unclear></p>
<p>6 At the advice of the surgeons, we had been<lb/>
in the habit of serving a small quantity of red wine<lb/>
at luncheon. Someone of the group, at the early<lb/>
inception of the epidemic, had proposed the old English<lb/>
toast: &ldquo;To those who are gone already and here's to<lb/>
the next to go&rdquo;. This toast was drunk daily until Brooks<lb/>
and I were left looking across the corner of the table<lb/>
at one another. Then, when he poured out a glass of<lb/>
wine, and pushed the decanter to me, he lifted his<lb/>
glass and gave the toast. I remember saying; &ldquo;Brooks,<lb/>
I won't drink that toast to myself. You had yellow<lb/>
fever in Santiago and are immune and won't have it<lb/>
again. Besides that, you are a teetotaler and don't<lb/>
drink. So I'll drink my wine, but not the toast&rdquo;. He<lb/>
laughed and neither he nor I was stricken with the<lb/>
disease.</p>
<p>7 During this same period, one after the other<lb/>
I placed five men in charge of Major Cartwright's<lb/>
papers, which I was anxious should be closed up as<lb/>
promptly as possible, especially in view of the condi-<lb/>
tions that existed. In order to make sure that they<lb/>
would be promptly closed and worked upon continuously,<lb/>
I set aside a small room back of my own office and<lb/>
assigned a clerk to this special duty. The first that<lb/>
I placed in charge was Mr. Ferguson, a civilian clerk,<lb/>
supposed to be immune, having passed through more than<lb/>
one epidemic in New Orleans. Within twenty-four hours<lb/>
after he took charge of the papers he came to me and<lb/>
said he was too ill to go on. The next day he was<lb/>
dead of yellow fever. One after the other, five men<lb/>
working on these papers went down with yellow fever.<lb/>
The fifth man went down but fortunately recovered and<lb/>
finished the papers.</p>
<p>8 About this time Major Gorgas came to me and<lb/>
asked me to take his yellow fever ambulance (one that<lb/>
he had been using to haul yellow fever patients) into<lb/>
the shops and overhaul it. He assured me that there<lb/>
could not possibly be any contamination connected<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06278010"/>
Dr. Carlos <unclear>Finlay</unclear> was a British <unclear>subjects</unclear><lb/>
from in Cuba of English parents-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06278011"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
with the ambulance and it could not possibly communi-<lb/>
cate the disease. I explained to Gorgas that I would<lb/>
be very glad to take the ambulance in and put it<lb/>
through the shops, and had no misgivings in regard<lb/>
to the communication of the disease, but I feared for<lb/>
the morale of the men working on the ambulance if<lb/>
they knew it was an ambulance used to carry yellow<lb/>
fever patients. &ldquo;Well&rdquo;, he said, &ldquo;we'll try not to<lb/>
let them know that that is the case&rdquo;, and he suggested<lb/>
that he leave the ambulance out in the weather and I<lb/>
could pick it up and take it into my establishment<lb/>
and send him another ambulance to take the place of<lb/>
it temporarily. This I did. The result was that<lb/>
one after the other, the wheelwright, the blacksmith,<lb/>
the finisher, the painter, and the superintendent of<lb/>
shops all went down with yellow fever, and all died.</p>
<p>9 In the meantime, Major Reed, at the head<lb/>
of the Board that has made him his greatest fame,<lb/>
and all members of which became famous, came to<lb/>
Havana for the purpose of investigating the source<lb/>
and possible prevention of the disease. In my<lb/>
capacity of Chief Quartermaster I set up his office,<lb/>
furnished it for him, furnished him transportation,<lb/>
and built the small buildings in which he carried<lb/>
out his investigations and experiments. I was in<lb/>
constant contact with him. I had already known<lb/>
him when he came to the Seventh Army Corps to make<lb/>
the study of the typhoid epidemic, when he headed<lb/>
the Board known as the Reed-Vaughn-Shakespeare<lb/>
Board, and whose report is known to medical men<lb/>
throughout the world for its scientific determina-<lb/>
tion of the means by which that disease is carried.</p>
<p>10 Dr. Carlos Finley, an <del>American</del> physician<lb/>
who had lived and practiced in Havana for many<lb/>
years, had advanced the <unclear><hi>theory</hi></unclear> that yellow fever<lb/>
was carried by the mosquito, but he had never been<lb/>
able to prove it. Major Reed at once proceeded to<lb/>
investigate this theory, with the result that by<lb/>
the end of the year 1900 he had conclusively shown,<lb/>
together with the other members of his Board con-<lb/>
sisting of Majors Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte,<lb/>
that the mosquito was the guilty party in the dis-<lb/>
semination of this dread disease. The methods by<lb/>
which he arrived at this conclusion are well known<lb/>
to the medical profession and the details of the<lb/>
small buildings which he used in determining this,<lb/>
are also well known.</p>
<p>No Eng.<lb/>
in 1882</p>
<p>11 <del>Each</del> one was divided into <del>three</del><add>two</add> compartments.<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06278012"/>
Dr. Finlay had concluded that only<lb/>
the house mosquitos (Stegomyia now<lb/>
Called Aedes egypti) was the vector<lb/>
&amp; he gave Reed some eggs of this<lb/>
mosquito in a little dish<lb/>
Only one experiment was tried<lb/>
with any other mosquito<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06278013"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
The subject would enter the first compartment after<lb/>
having all mosquitoes carefully driven away, remove<lb/>
his clothing, enter the next compartment and clothe<lb/>
himself in sleeping garments, and from there he would<lb/>
enter his sleeping apartment where he remained during<lb/>
the period of the experiment. In order to test the<lb/>
possibility of the communication of this disease by<lb/>
direct contact or contamination, the garments and<lb/>
bedding in which patients had died of the disease<lb/>
were placed in the sleeping compartment of one of<lb/>
these buildings. In no case was yellow fever con-<lb/>
tracted by this means.</p>
<p>12 In order to satisfy the Board, infected<lb/>
mosquitoes were bottled up and after the subject<lb/>
had entered his sleeping compartment were permitted<lb/>
to bite him. In some instances yellow fever resulted,<lb/>
in others there was no result. By <hi>continued</hi> experiment<lb/>
it was found that only a certain breed of mosquito<lb/>
communicated the disease and eventually it was dis-<lb/>
covered that only the female of that breed was guilty.<lb/>
With further experimentation it was found that even<lb/>
she was not always capable of transmitting the disease.<lb/>
To make the transmission effective, it was necessary<lb/>
that the mosquito bite a patient suffering from the<lb/>
malady and at a particular stage of development, and<lb/>
in communicating it, it was necessary that the mosquito<lb/>
bite the victim at a certain time (about <del>five</del> days)<lb/>
after having bitten an infected person. The result<lb/>
of this was that after less than six months of<lb/>
experimentation, Walter Reed was able to publish<lb/>
his findings, to the effect that the disease is<lb/>
carried by nothing else but the mosquito, and one<lb/>
breed of mosquito, and only the female of that<lb/>
breed, at a certain stage after having bitten a<lb/>
yellow fever patient.</p>
<p>?</p>
<p>10-15</p>
<p>13 Both Dr. Lazear and Major Carroll submitted<lb/>
themselves to this test. Lazear, as everyone knows,<lb/>
was so unfortunate as to die in this experiment.<lb/>
Carroll recovered but was never an entirely well man<lb/>
afterward. Practically all members of the Hospital<lb/>
Corps on duty at that time at Camp Columbia in Marianao<lb/>
most heroically submitted themselves for this test.<lb/>
Fortunately, none of these men died. It was my<lb/>
pleasure, not long ago, to witness the placing of<lb/>
medals on the breasts of two of the survivors, after<lb/>
a period of something more than thirty years after<lb/>
the occurrence.</p>
<p>14 Major Reed became very much interested in<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06278014"/>
15 - Explained by fact that the y. f.<lb/>
<unclear>mosquitos</unclear> breeds &amp; lives about<lb/>
human habitations only<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06278015"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
my personal experience in connection with the disease<lb/>
and was rather curious as to why I had not been taken<lb/>
down with the disease, having been constantly living<lb/>
in the same conditions that so many others had lived<lb/>
and had been stricken---in the mess and in my office<lb/>
and in the corral. It could easily be understood that<lb/>
the mosquito was the guilty party, but it could not be<lb/>
understood why the mosquitoes would not bite me as<lb/>
well as all of those others. He asked me about my<lb/>
medical experience during the period when I had served<lb/>
in Havana. I told him that I had been taken down with<lb/>
what the attending surgeon called calentura, and was<lb/>
in bed for two days, but continued to perform my duties<lb/>
from my sick-bed. He consulted with the attending<lb/>
surgeon, Major Laine, and they arrived at the conclusion<lb/>
that the fever I had had, which had been called calentura,<lb/>
was in all probability a light case of yellow fever and<lb/>
had not been discovered, which rendered me immune to the<lb/>
bites of the mosquito.</p>
<p>15 One of the most interesting features of this<lb/>
final discovery is to be found in the comparison with<lb/>
what was actually known of the disease before these<lb/>
experiments were undertaken. For example, in cases<lb/>
of epidemic in the United States at various points,<lb/>
it was found that the disease was curbed by prospec-<lb/>
tive victims seeking certain localities, usually dry<lb/>
and free of mosquitoes. In the City of Jacksonville<lb/>
the entire population moved out into the sand-hills<lb/>
from the city and established themselves in tents<lb/>
and temporary quarters. The men would habitually go<lb/>
in to the city during the daytime to ordinary business,<lb/>
always returning before nightfall to the sand-hills.<lb/>
In that way the disease was finally obliterated<lb/>
without their knowledge of the reason why.</p>
<p>16 As a matter of fact, the yellow fever mos-<lb/>
quito, as a rule, does not go far away from her<lb/>
breeding place. She is not active except in a dark<lb/>
or gloomy corner or room, or after nightfall. Another<lb/>
incident that had been noted and commented on was<lb/>
that the disease might start on a street and continue<lb/>
until it reached a high wall and there it would be<lb/>
checked until something happened and it would seem to<lb/>
jump the wall and go on down the street. What hap-<lb/>
pened was that the winds carried the infected mos-<lb/>
quitoes over the wall where they continued their<lb/>
depradations. Another thing, it would go down one<lb/>
side of the street and leave the other side free<lb/>
of this dread disease, until all those conditions<lb/>
would change and it would jump across the street<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06278016"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
and go down the other side. This was puzzling, but<lb/>
after the detection of the culprit it was easily ex-<lb/>
plained. The winds would come right to carry the<lb/>
infected mosquitoes over the walls where they would<lb/>
proceed in their nefarious calling, or the winds<lb/>
would change and blow them across the street and there<lb/>
the mosquitoes would start a new center of infection.<lb/>
All of the phenomena that had been witnessed and com-<lb/>
mented upon in connection with yellow fever before<lb/>
Walter Reed's discovery, found a simple explanation<lb/>
as soon as he had determined that the mosquito was<lb/>
the culprit. The room in which our group held its<lb/>
luncheons was infested with mosquitoes which evi-<lb/>
dently buzzed about in the dark corners, the room<lb/>
being ill-lighted. The room in which the clerks<lb/>
worked on Major Cartwright's papers was a dark<lb/>
room infested with mosquitoes. All of the employees<lb/>
at the shops slept in the same quarters, which were<lb/>
found to be infested with mosquitoes. All of the<lb/>
members of the Reed Board are now dead but they<lb/>
have left behind them their places in the history<lb/>
of medical discovery that will remain so long as<lb/>
the medical profession exists.</p>
<p>17 I wish to add to this recital that it was<lb/>
of great interest to me to find that General Truby,<lb/>
now in command of the Army Medical Center, Washington,<lb/>
D.C., of which Walter Reed Hospital is a part, was a<lb/>
young officer of the Medical Corps during the entire<lb/>
period of the first occupation. Truby was the first<lb/>
medical officer to reach Havana. The Eighth and<lb/>
Tenth Infantry Regiments were on provost-martial<lb/>
duty in Havana until August, 1899, when they moved<lb/>
to Camp Columbia. Reed was a close personal friend<lb/>
of his and when Reed came to Cuba he and the other<lb/>
members of the Board, except Agramonte, accepted<lb/>
the invitation to live with the Medical Staff at<lb/>
the Hospital at the Camp. It was a great satisfac-<lb/>
tion, in a recent period of hospitalization, to talk<lb/>
with General Truby and crystallize my recollections<lb/>
of the incidents herein related.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
