<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06272005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from W.F. de Niedman to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 4, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>de Niedman, W.F.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06272005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-04-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Giddings, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Pilcher, Evelin</name>
<name type="person">Kneeder, William L.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Avendani, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Molina, Zacarias R.</name>
<name type="person">Alden, C. H.</name>
<name type="person">Girard, A. C.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Kansas</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
<name type="place">Antilles</name>
<name type="place">Camp Meade, Harrisburg (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Athens (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Savannah (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Colona (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Kansas City (Mo.)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Vera Cruz (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Manila (Philippines)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-04-04">April 4, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06272005</idno>
<title>Letter from W.F. de Niedman to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 4, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>De Niedman offers his recollections of yellow fever work in Cuba, including investigations of Sanarelli's bacillus and sanitary measures undertaken.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-04-04">
<head>Letter from W.F. de Niedman to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 4, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06272005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Los Altos, California<lb/>
<date value="1928-04-04">April 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1928.</date>
</dateline>
Colonel J. R. Kean<lb/>
U. S. Army.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Colonel:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Wonder, if upon the receipt of this you<lb/>
would say: Here he is again? You would be in the<lb/>
right to say this, for no busy man wishes to be<lb/>
interrupted upon any and every flimsy provocation<lb/>
or pretext.- I wish to thank you for the kind<lb/>
offer to assist me in processing another Badge<lb/>
of the Association of Military Surgeons of U. S. to replace<lb/>
one carelessly misplaced or lost. After reading<lb/>
your kind note, offering assistance to procure<lb/>
another Badge, my family decided to make<lb/>
another diligent search for the one lost, and so,<lb/>
I am living in the expectation and hope that their<lb/>
effort might be successful. But, in addition<lb/>
to expressing my many thanks for your ever kindness,<lb/>
these exist on other cause why I wanted to write to you:<lb/>
The other day, when picking up the March number<lb/>
of the Military Surgeon, the very first article that<lb/>
greeted my eyes, was one from your pen on<lb/>
&ldquo;The Dedication of the Birthplace of Walter Reed&rdquo;.-<lb/>
In reading this article many old memories of the<lb/>
days of 1898 came to life again, particularly of the<lb/>
period when I had the pleasure to serve under you<lb/>
in Pinar del Rio, Cuba:<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06272006"/>
2<lb/>
How well I am reminded of your constant<lb/>
kindness and consideration, as my Chief at<lb/>
Quemados, during the many vexations and trobles <unclear>and</unclear><lb/>
days there.- In one of my letters, quite a while<lb/>
ago, I casually asked you, if you did not desire<lb/>
to learn of other things that I was doing at<lb/>
Pinar del Rio, in addition to routine duties in<lb/>
connection with my hospital and command.<lb/>
Not hearing from you on this subject, I hesitated<lb/>
to speak, fearing that the subject matter would<lb/>
not be of interest to you. However, on reading<lb/>
your March article, so many incidents of my<lb/>
service in 1898 were <unclear>forcibly</unclear> brought to my mind,<lb/>
that I could not resist the temptation to let you know<lb/>
something about them.- On the page <del>at</del> 298 of your<lb/>
article reference is made to the study of Bacillus<lb/>
ichteroides by the Yellow Fever Board and of the<lb/>
experiments of Wasdin and Giddings of the Public<lb/>
Health Service of the U.S. with the Sanarelli serum<lb/>
as a preventitive agent against Yellow Fever <unclear>etc</unclear><lb/>
giving also the Reed Board findings,-<lb/>
A great deal of this, in a great measure, coincided,<lb/>
paralleled or interlocked, as it were, with some individual<lb/>
observations and efforts made by me and a corps of Cuban<lb/>
medical civilian practitioners while in Pinar del Rio.-<lb/>
I desire to preface this statement, about this particular<lb/>
experiment made in Cuba, by an other, and that is,<lb/>
that for two years or even longer, prior to the outbrake<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06272007"/>
3<lb/>
3<lb/>
<hi>2.</hi><lb/>
of the War with Spain I had the honor to hold<lb/>
the appointment of Chairman of Cuban League<lb/>
in the State of Kansas, collecting funds and medical<lb/>
supplies, forwarding these to Cuba via the Liegue<lb/>
Headquarters in New York. In this manner, I came<lb/>
naturally in possession of many important facts<lb/>
concerning conditions in Cuba. At that time I was<lb/>
also the ranking Surgeon of the Natl. Guard of the<lb/>
State of Kansas, and so thoroughly became I convinced<lb/>
that War with Spain was almost inevitable that<lb/>
I began to study Spanish and prepare myself by<lb/>
careful and systematic study both, of the Typhoid<lb/>
and the yellow fever. In this effort I was greatly assisted<lb/>
by General Geo. M. Sternberg the Surgeon General U. S. Army,<lb/>
who, not only aided <unclear>one with</unclear> books and periodicals <unclear>on</unclear><lb/>
these subjects, but enabled me to procure, through<lb/>
friends in Paris, France, a number of publications<lb/>
on the subject of Yellow Fever in the Antilles.<lb/>
In fall of 1898, while commanding the Corps Reserve Hospital<lb/>
and the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Division Hospital 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Army Corps at Camp <unclear>Meade</unclear><lb/>
near Harrisburg Pa. I met Major Walter Reed <unclear>us.a</unclear><lb/>
who was then on an inspection tour of Hospitals<lb/>
in connection with Typhoid fever investigation. He was<lb/>
accompanied by a Russian Military Medical Representative,<lb/>
Both of these officers expressed their agreeable surprise<lb/>
at the conditions they found in my hospital as<lb/>
compared with those recently inspected in the South.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06272008"/>
4<lb/>
4<lb/>
Shortly thereafter I was ordered to equip and<lb/>
organize the 3<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Division Hospital 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Army Corps<lb/>
with orders following to proceed to Cuba, via Athens Ga<lb/>
and Savannah Ga. While loading our Medical<lb/>
Supplies on the US. Transport Minnewaska at Savannah,<lb/>
Major Evelin Pilcher M. C. US. Army turned over to me<lb/>
in person a number of cases containing Sanarelli<lb/>
serum, and with these were explicit instructions<lb/>
from General Geo. M. Sternberg, Surgeon General of the Army,<lb/>
to give this serum a full and thorough test in any<lb/>
and all available cases of Yellow Fever, making<lb/>
full exhaustive records, submitting these records<lb/>
direct, to him, when proper time presented<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
upon arrival and while getting established at Pinar<lb/>
del Rio, Cuba- I found there, only one Cuban case<lb/>
of Yellow Fever, convalescing, in the so called<lb/>
&ldquo;Casa del Salud&rdquo;, the Spanish Pest House, and<lb/>
during my entire period of service at Pinar,<lb/>
we did not have a single case of Yellow Fever<lb/>
among our troops on duty there, but there were<lb/>
sporadic cases reported and treated in the provice<lb/>
among the native population. For this reason<lb/>
I had no opportunity to try out Senarelli serum<lb/>
among the members of our own command.<lb/>
Fortunately, with the assistance of Major Wm. L. Kneeder,<lb/>
M. C. US. Army (Coronado <unclear>Calif</unclear>) - we succeeded to organize<lb/>
a Medical Society of Cuban Civil. Practitioners in Pinar<lb/>
and the Provice proper, and these men, under<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06272009"/>
<hi>5</hi><lb/>
<hi>3.</hi><lb/>
leadership of Drs Ramos and <unclear>Avendani D.</unclear><lb/>
were liberally supplied with experimental material<lb/>
using it in every known case of yellow fever under<lb/>
my instructions and supervision, furnishing complete<lb/>
reports for verification and tabulation. In this<lb/>
manner was I enabled to follow up these cases,<lb/>
study them carefully and note the effect of<lb/>
Sanarelli serum as a curative and preventative agent<lb/>
on May 25- 1899, by G. <unclear>O.#</unclear> 23, Hdqrs. Military District No 1<lb/>
Pinar del Rio Cuba, I was appointed in addition<lb/>
to all other duties, as Health Officer of that District<lb/>
and this authority greatly strengthened my hands,<lb/>
more so, as it carried also the approval of the Civil<lb/>
Governor of the Province. Of course, this work<lb/>
added responsibility, worry and sleepless nights<lb/>
to my other duties- I was kept very busy.<lb/>
You may recollect also, that at an earlier period<lb/>
of my service in Pinar del Rio. I had the good<lb/>
fortune to break up successfully an incipient<lb/>
epidemic of Typhoid fever, - it was strenious work,<lb/>
I am almost sure to believe, that at that particular<lb/>
period you had no information, that I was also<lb/>
experimenting and testing out Sanarelli serum,<lb/>
but my friend Major Wm L. Kneedler know well<lb/>
that I was doing considerable microscopic and<lb/>
laboratory work, using <unclear>Widel's</unclear> agglutination test as well as<lb/>
and trying to demonstrate the Seidelin bodies in blood,<lb/>
smears taken from yellow fever patients, under all manner<lb/>
of difficulties by staining.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06272010"/>
<hi>6</hi><lb/>
6<lb/>
Major Kneedler knew also of many of my preventive<lb/>
measures adopted and carried out. One will<lb/>
I had never to admit a case of fever, at once, into<lb/>
our Field or Pavilion hospitals until, a thorough<lb/>
examination was made and determined excluding<lb/>
all chances admitting yellow fever.- Mosquito<lb/>
Bars were used by the entire command, even<lb/>
the Guard house was supplied with them, and a<lb/>
nightly inspection of all sleeping quarters was<lb/>
made in enforcing this regulation- You see,<lb/>
it was only the carrying out of your kind<lb/>
admonition to me that "Ethernal vigilance<lb/>
was the price of safety;- When Visiting Havana<lb/>
in 1899, I had the pleasure to meet Major Edward O.<lb/>
Shakespeare, but can not recollect if I have met Major<lb/>
Walter Reed or Major V. C. Vaughan at that time.<lb/>
Major Shakespeare informed me of the remarkable<lb/>
experiments carried out by the Yellow Fever Board,<lb/>
and we discussed some of my work undertaken<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio. He held, that no doubt, that<lb/>
my experiments were of great value in settling<lb/>
a vexing question at that time, but that my<lb/>
experiments were, in a measure, based on an<lb/>
entirely different principal and theory from<lb/>
those followed by Dr. Carlos Finlay or the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board at Havana. My stay at Havana was<lb/>
very short, and I did not learn at the time all I desired<lb/>
to know about the exact Modus Operandi of the Yellow Fever Board,<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06272011"/>
7<lb/>
7<lb/>
<hi>4</hi>.<lb/>
but Major Shakespeare was kind enough to<lb/>
keep me ported from time to time.-</p>
<p>Towards fall of 1899, I became fully convinced,<lb/>
both from personal observation as well as the records<lb/>
on hands, that Sanarelli serum was a failure<lb/>
as a prophylactic as well as a curative measure,<lb/>
and that Bacilus ichtheroides was not the agent<lb/>
or cause producing Yellow Fever. I was convinced,<lb/>
that the Mosquito carrier theory was correct, that<lb/>
the experiments of Major Reed and his Associates<lb/>
were in the right direction, and that my own work,<lb/>
while useful in a way, was based on a wrong<lb/>
supposition.- Half sick, tired, worn out from<lb/>
constant <unclear>petty</unclear> annoyances, I obtained through<lb/>
your kindness on Sept 12' 1899, one month<lb/>
leave of absence and returned to the States with<lb/>
the Depot Battalion of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> U. S. Infantry.<lb/>
On the date of my departure my report showed<lb/>
that there was not a single case of Yellow fever<lb/>
in the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Military District of Pinar del Rio, but<lb/>
that there were two cases of Small Pox at Colona<lb/>
among the natives. - Arriving at my home in<lb/>
Kansas, the Governor honored me by an appointment<lb/>
as a Delegate to the Convention of the Association<lb/>
of Military Surgeons of the U. S. at Kansas City Mo.<lb/>
While there on Sept 29-1899, during the morning session,<lb/>
I listened to the paper and discussion of Colonel<lb/>
Zacarias R. Molina of Mexico - on<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06272012"/>
<hi>8</hi><lb/>
"Observation upon Yellow Fever or Black Vomit<lb/>
in the City of Vera Cruz, Mexico, - He conveyed<lb/>
the idea, that at certain seasons when ships in<lb/>
the harbor of Vera Cruz, stirred up the mud<lb/>
at the bottom of the bay, invariably an epidemic<lb/>
of yellow fever followed. Also he held, that<lb/>
possibly the microscopic fungus Perosnapara<lb/>
lutea, was the causative agent, as its stained<lb/>
everything yellow, but admitted also, that so far<lb/>
as he knew, no substance was discovered, chemical<lb/>
or in laboratory or in the human body, which had<lb/>
the power to destroy or neutralize Yellow Fever.<lb/>
He stated also, that the elements producing the fever,<lb/>
whether Micro or Zoosporic were neither contagious<lb/>
or conveyable, and that the true cause was entirely<lb/>
unknown up to date. Imagine his surprise when<lb/>
he learned for the first time of the wonderful<lb/>
and conclusive experiments by Major Walter Reed<lb/>
and his Associates in Cuba,- On the same afternoon<lb/>
I had the pleasure to surrender to Colonel <unclear>C H. Alden</unclear>,<lb/>
the Assistant Surgeon General U. S. Army, in the<lb/>
presence of my old Chief of the 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Army Corp,<lb/>
Colonel A. C. Girard, all the records and finding<lb/>
I brought with me from Pinar del Rio, made there<lb/>
in connection with my tests and experiments<lb/>
with Sanarelli serum, and with it, my personal<lb/>
conclusions, that I held, that this serum was of<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06272013"/>
<hi>9</hi><lb/>
<hi>5</hi><lb/>
no practical utility as a curative or a<lb/>
prophylactic <add>agent</add> against yellow fever, and<lb/>
that in my opinion the Bacillus ichtheroides<lb/>
was not its causative agent.-</p>
<p>This terminated my Yellow Fever <add>work</add> in Cuba,<lb/>
for after expiration of my leave of absence,<lb/>
I was not permitted to return to Cuba, but<lb/>
was instead transferred for duty in the Philippine<lb/>
Islands, while in Manila, at a later date<lb/>
I learned through friends, that many of my so called<lb/>
precautionery measures in Pinar del Rio, were<lb/>
allowed to go into disuse, and that ultimately<lb/>
yellow Fever broke out among our command there<lb/>
with disastrous results. And now, allow me<lb/>
just a short word as to the Medical men, who so faithfully<lb/>
labored in the cause for the wellfare of humanity in Cuba <unclear>&amp; the P.</unclear><lb/>
A Reunion of the Spanish War Veterans is to take place this<lb/>
fall in Havana, Cuba. Do you think, <unclear>will</unclear> it possible for <del><unclear>our</unclear></del><lb/>
Great Country to recognice at this time the service rendered by the<lb/>
last survivor of the <unclear>Famous</unclear> Yellow Fever Board, the Dr. Aristides<lb/>
Agramonte? I feel, that at least a Distinguished Service Medal<lb/>
ought to be presented to him during the coming Reunion. Also,<lb/>
I have often <unclear>wondered</unclear>, why so few Medical Officers, Regulars or<lb/>
Volunteers have been recognized and honored for <unclear>their</unclear> valuable<lb/>
service rendered, both in Cuba and the Philippine Islands?-<lb/>
I wonder why? Must close,- this is getting too long.-</p>
<closer>
<salute>With <unclear>sincerest</unclear> regards yours</salute>
<signed>W. F. de Niedman</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
