<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06274016">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Notes of an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 21, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06274016</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Meritte W.</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-10-21">October 21, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06274016</idno>
<title>Notes of an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 21, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The interview centers on Kean's reluctance to give credit to the work done by Roger Ames during the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-10-21">
<head>Notes of an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 21, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06274016"/>
<opener>
From <unclear>Mrs</unclear> Ames<lb/>
<dateline>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1929-10-21">October 21, 1929.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>A call upon Colonel Kean in re the recognition<lb/>
of Doctor Roger Post Ames' services in stamping out Yellow Fever<lb/>
through experimentation in Cuba elicited the following facts and<lb/>
produced the following impressions:</p>
<p>Colonel Kean was most friendly. He said that the<lb/>
move for recognition of soliders was the result of a school teacher<lb/>
in New York who became interested because of a soldier - Kissinger;<lb/>
that he and the Surgeon General in conference with and by request<lb/>
of the committee (possibly Committee on Military Affairs) had de-<lb/>
cided to fix a rigid rule and that rule should say that only those<lb/>
who offered their bodies and those who did the scientific work<lb/>
should be recognized. That definitely Doctor Roger Post Ames did<lb/>
not fall into either <unclear>cales</unclear>. When asked whether the experiment could<lb/>
have been carried on if these others, the surgeons and nurses had<lb/>
not been willing to do the work, he said it could not have been done<lb/>
at all without them. He added hastily, &ldquo;had they not been willing<lb/>
to do their duty.&rdquo; He either forgot to answer or evaded answering<lb/>
the question when asked what other surgeons beside Doctor Ames were<lb/>
actually in charge of the camp. He said he had secured money to<lb/>
carry out the experiment but he <add>Major Kean</add> had not been in charge of the camp.<lb/>
Doctor Ames had been in charge but whether or not alone he did not<lb/>
answer.</p>
<p>He showed a book &ldquo;Senate Document&rdquo; No. 823 - <unclear>81st</unclear><lb/>
Congress Third Session, &ldquo;Yellow Fever&rdquo; - a Compilation of Various<lb/>
Publications, the title of which he wrote down. In this book there<lb/>
was a statement saying that Doctor Ames had been asked to diagnose<lb/>
the mysterious case for so long known as XY - and that Doctor Ames<lb/>
had pronounced the case undoubtedly Yellow Fever. This showed that<lb/>
Doctor Ames was not just an ordinary surgeon as to Yellow Fever.<lb/>
(Major Reed sent for Doctor Ames) He told of his surprise when<lb/>
his attention was called to the fact that Doctor Ames was not an<lb/>
immune and had actually had Yellow Fever in February, 1901. He<lb/>
was dubious about its being really Yellow Fever since it was at<lb/>
a time when few cases occurred and Doctor Ames was in the hospital<lb/>
such a short time. He admitted that it was in the record right<lb/>
enough and that Major Alex Stark certified to it as such. He<lb/>
said that he would not take the responsibility of saying who should<lb/>
or who should not be given recognition and that if the committee<lb/>
saw fit to include those who did the hospital service Doctor Ames<lb/>
would be the first to come in. He said over a hundred had sought<lb/>
recognition. He said that at the time the Committee asked for a<lb/>
ruling to guide them, the Surgeon General had called him in and<lb/>
that the division had been made without regard to who would or<lb/>
would not be included. Some thought he should be included but<lb/>
he did not.</p>
<p>The only places where Colonel Kean left impress-<lb/>
ions different to the facts stated above was when asked what other<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06274017"/>
doctors actually had charge of the camp beside Doctor Ames. He<lb/>
appeared to evade that question. He did not answer and because<lb/>
he appeared to evade, it was not pressed. He was uncomfortable<lb/>
about the fact that Doctor Ames was not an immune. He said<lb/>
that certainly they were under the impression that he was an im-<lb/>
mune and certainly he believed Doctor Ames thought he was an im-<lb/>
mune. He seemed to want to cast either some doubt on the <unclear>veracity</unclear><lb/>
of the person certifying; or on Doctor Ames; or in some way imply<lb/>
that something either mysterious or discreditable attached to it<lb/>
(see interview with General Ireland). The impression also was<lb/>
left that in this point <unclear>lies</unclear> the weakness of the refusal to give<lb/>
recognition to Doctor Ames' services. If this point is pushed,<lb/>
it will be found the source of their embarrassment. They are<lb/>
doing a good man a real injustice. Colonel Kean was plainly un-<lb/>
easy and restless when this fact of non-immunity on the part of<lb/>
Doctor Ames was brought up.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
