<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06279015">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 27, 1936</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06279015</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1936-04-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H. (X.Y.)</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, W. A.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sydney</name>
<name type="person">Black, Col. [William M.?]</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Meritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="publication">Sydney Howard, Yellow Jack</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1936-04-27">April 27, 1936</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06279015</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 27, 1936</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby provides his recollections of the yellow fever experiments, including Lazear's infection, Carroll's and Agramonte's claims, Dean's infection, Kean's leadership, and the memorial plaque for Lazear at Las Animas Hospital.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1936-04-27">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 27, 1936</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06279015"/>
<opener>
A true Copy<lb/>
<unclear>AET</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
3559 Jackson Street,<lb/>
San Francisco, California,<lb/>
<date value="1936-04-27"><hi>April 27, 1936</hi>.</date>
</dateline>
General J. R. Kean,<lb/>
2804 N Street, N.W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter came yesterday and I was delighted to hear from you.<lb/>
I have been thinking of you for some time and was about to drop you a line<lb/>
when your letter arrived.</p>
<p>Regarding the matter of Lazear's infection, I am glad to give the<lb/>
details, which, while meager, are I know to be absolutely correct. First<lb/>
of all let me tell you again that Agramonte knew little or nothing about<lb/>
Lazear's activities at that time. Carroll and Lazear were each working on<lb/>
their special jobs independently of each other or anyone else, except<lb/>
Reed's direction. Agramonte was in Havana all that time with no special<lb/>
work connected with the Board's activities. When Lazear died I was in<lb/>
command of the hospital at Camp Columbia (Stark was in the U.S.). I<lb/>
personally collected Lazear's effects, including the small pocket notebook<lb/>
containing the few entries regarding the dates, names, etc., of the persons<lb/>
who had allowed themselves to be bitten by his infected mosquitoes. The<lb/>
entries were very clear regarding Carroll and X.Y. and some others who did not<lb/>
develop yellow fever. There were also some entries so indefinite that they<lb/>
could not be understood by Reed. Some of these may have been about his own<lb/>
case, but that, as I remember, could not be definitely determined.</p>
<p>You know, Reed was in great haste, for good reasons, to publish<lb/>
his preliminary report. The notebook contained the only information avail-<lb/>
able, as Lazear did not confide in anyone, and died without giving us much<lb/>
information, about his own case or the others. He was, you know, quite sick<lb/>
for a day or two before anyone knew about it and when he was finally taken<lb/>
from his quarters to Ames' yellow fever ward, across the R.R. tracks, he was<lb/>
in no condition to question, and furthermore he would not talk.</p>
<p>Consequently Reed felt that Lazear was protecting his family because<lb/>
of the possibility that his life insurance might be forfeited if it were<lb/>
known that he deliberately infected himself. In writing up the first draft<lb/>
of his preliminary report Reed discussed this and other matters with me and<lb/>
also with you, I feel sure. Lazear had been making almost daily visits to<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital and as it was possible that he had been infected there,<lb/>
Reed finally decided to let it appear that he was accidentally infected while<lb/>
in the performance of his official duties as a member of the <unclear>Board;</unclear> a<lb/>
possibility of course. On the other hand all of us were convinced that Lazear<lb/>
had placed the mosquitoes on his arm just as he did on Carroll in accordance<lb/>
with the agreement of the non-immune members of the Board (all members except<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06279016"/>
Agramonte) that they would all test the mosquito theory on themselves. I<lb/>
am sure that Reed was convinced that such was the case. You and I know that<lb/>
Lazear would be most careful not to be bitten at Las Animas because <hi>at that<lb/>
time he knew</hi> the danger, and if he was to be bitten he would want to do it<lb/>
with his own mosquitoes, to prove the theory.</p>
<p>Of course he did it himself. But why not let the matter rest as it is<lb/>
and allow the tablet to be erected at Las Animas Hospital? We have all per-<lb/>
mitted Carroll, and then after his death Agramonte, to make false statements<lb/>
about the importance of their individual work as members of that Board in an<lb/>
effort to glorify themselves at Reed's expense. Reed, we know, was the guiding<lb/>
and directing head. If Reed had not returned to Cuba after Lazear died the<lb/>
entire thing would have been a mess! Certain failure! It was Reed who solved<lb/>
the problem with the aid of Lazear's notebook. Carroll was still incompetent<lb/>
to help him at the time the Preliminary Report was written and Agramonte, in<lb/>
Havana, was of no help and did not know anything about the Report until it was<lb/>
finished. I am positive about this. However, I have always agreed with you<lb/>
that as members of the Board, Carroll and Agramonte should come in for their<lb/>
share of the glory, and on that account it is best to let matters remain as<lb/>
they are. But it did hurt my sense of fair play to follow Carroll's claims<lb/>
after Reed died, and then again to find Agramonte going Carroll one better<lb/>
after the latter's death. What a pity Reeds died so untimely!</p>
<p>Recently I had a letter from Dr. W. A. Sawyer, who succeeded F. F.<lb/>
Russell at the Rockefeller Foundation, asking if X.Y. was a bona fide<lb/>
volunteer for Lazear's experiments. I am sure he was but I doubt if there is<lb/>
any record of that one way or another. I know that Lazear placed the mosquito<lb/>
on X.Y. while X.Y. was in his ward at the hospital (not in the Laboratory).<lb/>
Knowing Lazear I could not conceive of his doing anything to an enlisted man<lb/>
without his full consent. He picked Dean because he was an intelligent soldier<lb/>
and because he had been in the wards where he could not be exposed to yellow<lb/>
fever. If Dean had been tricked he would have complained to me, his immediate<lb/>
Commanding Officer, or to Reed after he recovered.</p>
<p>A few days ago I saw Sydney Howard's book, &ldquo;Yellowjack&rdquo;. So I bought<lb/>
it and brought it home. (Howard should have sent us copies I think). I was<lb/>
awfully disappointed in the play because of the many inaccuracies and the<lb/>
author's poor grasp of the kind of language intelligent medical officers and<lb/>
even men of the army use. In the main the author's story is based on facts<lb/>
but he makes an inference, for example that X.Y. was tricked into the experi-<lb/>
ment by Lazear, which is unwarranted. I wish that he had spent more time with<lb/>
us to get the picture accurate and that he had given us a chance to criticize<lb/>
the draft before it was published. Of course the playwright has his own ideas<lb/>
of what will have public appeal, but in this case the true picture could not,<lb/>
in my opinion, be improved upon.</p>
<p>Now let me digress a bit while I am on this subject for my heart is<lb/>
full of it. It was a great opportunity for a youngster like me to be associated<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06279017"/>
even in a small way with Walter Reed and his thrilling work in Cuba. I<lb/>
enjoyed it immensely at the time and still feel the thrill his experiments<lb/>
gave him and all of us who were there to witness the results from day to day.<lb/>
It is quite remarkable the way I was thrown in Major Reed's company. First<lb/>
he was a member of the Board in Washington which examined me for entrance to<lb/>
the Corps. Then we were together frequently when he did his work on Colonel<lb/>
Black's folly - electrozone in Havana, then at Camp Columbia and finally at<lb/>
the General Hospital when he died. I saw the operation and was detailed to be<lb/>
with him the first night after the operation. A most sad experience I can<lb/>
assure you. At Camp Columbia he had the two rooms next to mine and, of course,<lb/>
he was a member of our mess. He was particularly nice and seemed to take a<lb/>
fancy to me, possibly because I showed my admiration for his sterling qualities<lb/>
and my great respect for his high rank. (I was but a &ldquo;shavetail&rdquo; then).</p>
<p>On account of my close association with him at Camp Columbia, I know<lb/>
what a great source of help and comfort it was to him to have you there as the<lb/>
Department Surgeon. I know also that if he were living he would give you<lb/>
great credit for your wonderful cooperation and assistance which made his<lb/>
success possible. I honor you for the splendid way you have maintained the<lb/>
dignity of his work in the face of all that has or might have transpired, and<lb/>
for the grand and efficient way you have really carried on the unfinished ends<lb/>
which were left by Reed's death. You were doing this even while Carroll and<lb/>
Agramonte were still living. Evidence enough that you were the logical leader<lb/>
henceforth. Without you on the job much more &ldquo;bunk&rdquo; and much undeserved<lb/>
legislation would have resulted. General Ireland, too, deserves great praise<lb/>
for calling on you for the facts whenever these questions came up to him as<lb/>
Surgeon General.</p>
<p>If I were to write the story, I would show that the Board might well<lb/>
have been dissolved at the time of Lazear's death and then demonstrate that<lb/>
all the credit for the solution of Lazear's results and all the credit for<lb/>
the experiments which followed belonged to Reed. He planned them and carried<lb/>
them out almost alone. Then I would give you and Leonard Wood more credit<lb/>
than has been accorded for making Reed's work possible by administrative action<lb/>
and support. It was you who made the ideal facilities of the hospital at<lb/>
Camp Columbia available for his work. An enormous factor, I think, in bringing<lb/>
success to the project, not alone because of what was provided in personnel,<lb/>
shelter and equipment, but in the fact that those facilities helped Reed to<lb/>
promptly and efficiently care for all of the experimental cases without any<lb/>
mortality. (Lazear died before Reed began his final experiments and possibly<lb/>
because he did not get early treatment - his own fault).</p>
<p>If you do not concur in my suggestion to let Dr. Ramos go ahead and<lb/>
place a tablet in Las Animas Hospital, suppose you discuss it with a few old<lb/>
timers, especially General Ireland, and then do whatever you conclude to be<lb/>
best. I was a great admirer of Lazear's scientific ability and anything that<lb/>
can be done to further honor his memory will please me.</p>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06279018"/>
<p>It has been a pleasure to bring my recollections and views to you<del>r</del><lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>in this way</add> and I think you will find them in accord with your views. If not,<lb/>
let me hear from you and I will be glad to discuss them with you. I have<lb/>
loads of time you know.</p>
<p>Mrs. Truby joins me in best wishes for you and Mrs. Kean.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed><hi>A E T</hi></signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
