<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06271001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, August 27, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06271001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-08-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">LeRoy y Cassa, Jorge</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lopez del Valle, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Lebredo, Mario G.</name>
<name type="person">Duque, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Tamayo, Diego</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Uma, Rev. Padre</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-08-27">August 27, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06271001</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, August 27, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean expresses his disappointment in the competition between Cuba and America regarding the credit for the yellow fever work. According to Kean, it was Reed who demonstrated Finlay's theory and Gorgas who applied it.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1927-08-27">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Jorge LeRoy y Cassa, August 27, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06271001"/>
<opener>
Dr. P. <unclear>S.</unclear> Hench to read -<lb/>
Please return after reading- and<lb/>
taking copy if you wish<lb/>
<unclear>MK</unclear><lb/>
<hi>COPY</hi><lb/>
<hi>Reed and Finlay</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1927-08-25">25 August, 1927.</date>
</dateline>
Dr. Jorge Le-Roy y Cassa,<lb/>
Jefe de Demografia Sanitaria Nacional,<lb/>
c/o Secretaria de Sanidad y Beneficencia,<lb/>
Habana, Cuba.<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Le-Roy:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been much pleased to receive the Boletin Oficial, Nos.<lb/>
1, 2 and 3 bound together, containing the interesting and eloquent addresses<lb/>
of Dr. Lopez del Vallo, Dr. Lebredo and Dr. Duque with reference to the fine<lb/>
achievements of our departed friends, Dr. Finlay, Dr. Guiteras and Dr. Diego<lb/>
Tamayo. I have also read with great interest your article <unclear>Revindicacion</unclear><lb/>
de la Gloria de Finlay, and it is with reference to this that I wish to say<lb/>
a few words.</p>
<p>The conquest of yellow fever is a glorious episode in which Dr.<lb/>
Finlay, Major Reed and his coadjutors, Lazear, Agramonte, Carroll, General<lb/>
Gorgas and Dr. Guiteras all bore important and distinguished parts, as well<lb/>
as a number of other loyal and capable workers. Of these, I think we can<lb/>
agree, three names stand out more prominently - Finlay who originated the<lb/>
theory of the transmission of yellow fever by the mosquito; Reed who was<lb/>
the directing mind in the wonderful scientific demonstration in 1900-1901<lb/>
which caused its acceptance by the civilized world, and Gorgas who on a<lb/>
great scale successfully applied the theory enunciated by Finlay and demon-<lb/>
strated by Reed so as to make a conquest of this great plague. I loved and<lb/>
admired both Dr. Finlay and Dr. Reed and it is distressing to me to see a<lb/>
spirit of rivalry grow up between Cuba and the United States as to the<lb/>
division of the glory between them. I entirely agree with you that the<lb/>
word &ldquo;discovery&rdquo; is not the proper word to apply to Reed's work. I am<lb/>
accustomed to use the word &ldquo;demonstrated&rdquo; or &ldquo;proved&rdquo;. The line of this<lb/>
division was long ago pointed out by our good friend Guiteras, and when<lb/>
I mention the circumstances you will doubtless recall them. I recently<lb/>
read in my diary, written at the time, a brief account of the dinner gotten<lb/>
up by Dr. Guiteras and some other physicians of Havana (on Dec. 22nd 1900)<lb/>
to celebrate the demonstration by the Reed Commission of the truth of the<lb/>
theory of Finlay. This demonstration had been recently accepted by the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board of Havana of which both Drs. Finlay and Guiteras were mem-<lb/>
bers. At that dinner, sitting between Dr. Finlay and Dr. Reed, Dr. Guiteras<lb/>
spoke, with the eloquence and precision which was his gift, of the glory of<lb/>
these two men. He compared the discovery of the method of transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever to that which had been accomplished a year or two before with<lb/>
regard to malaria and said that the part of Finlay corresponded to that of<lb/>
Patrick Manson who clearly enunciated the theory, while the work of Reed<lb/>
corresponded to that of Ronald Rose who gave to this theory the scientific<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06271002"/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
2.<lb/>
demonstration which was necessary in order that the scientific world<lb/>
should accept it. This division of the glory seemed to all of us at the<lb/>
time to be appropriate and just and I can not see why there should ever<lb/>
be an departure from it. The theory was and is the theory of Finlay.<lb/>
The demonstration of it so as to cause its acceptance by the medical<lb/>
profession of the world belongs to Reed and his assistants. The epi-<lb/>
demiological arguments which Dr. Finlay brought forward to support his<lb/>
theory were very strong but his experiments all failed because of two<lb/>
factors which were necessary to the successful transmission of disease<lb/>
experimentally. These were, of course, first the twelve day period of<lb/>
incubation in the mosquito, and, second the fact that the yellow fever<lb/>
patient <unclear>ceases</unclear> to be infective for the mosquito after the third day.<lb/>
I discussed this failure with Dr. Finlay and went over his experiments<lb/>
with him. His notes were so full and clear that it could be demonstrated<lb/>
that each one of his experiments failed to fulfill either one condition<lb/>
or the other. Therefore, it could only be claimed that he had produced<lb/>
a case of yellow fever by allowing a very long period of incubation in<lb/>
one or two patients who, by the way, were not protected from infection by<lb/>
other mosquitoes.</p>
<p>Therefore, Dr. Finlay failed in twenty years to make a single<lb/>
prominent convert among the leaders of the medical profession, so far as<lb/>
I know, either in Cuba or abroad. It is my recollection that neither<lb/>
Dr. Guiteras or the other members of the Yellow Fever Board of Havana<lb/>
believed in the mosquito transmission of yellow fever until the experi-<lb/>
ments of Reed made it impossible of doubt. One of the last members of that<lb/>
board to be convinced was Gorgas. In the words of Goldberger &ldquo;Reed con-<lb/>
verted a discredited theory into an established doctrine.&rdquo; There are many<lb/>
other examples in medicine of such a division of credit between the orig-<lb/>
inal proponent of a theory and the man whose scientific demonstration,<lb/>
usually in a laboratory, causes the world to accept the theory. Dr. Oliver<lb/>
Wendell Holmes who besides being a poet and essayist was a professor of<lb/>
medicine at Harvard declared the infectious character of puerpual fever<lb/>
and its transmission to women by the hands of their attendants. This<lb/>
theory was, however, not accepted until some years afterwards the Austrian<lb/>
<unclear>Sommelweiss</unclear> demonstrated the truth of the theory so that it was generally<lb/>
accepted. In the same way Dr. A. F. A. King of Washington in 1882 read<lb/>
a paper before the Philosophical Society of Washington which he afterwards<lb/>
published in the Popular Science Monthly for September, 1883 in which he<lb/>
boldly and clearly announced the transmission of malaria by mosquitoes and<lb/>
gave many epidemiological arguments in support of this theory. In this<lb/>
paper, by the way, he refers to Dr. Finlay's work in Havana. His theory<lb/>
remained, however, barren of practical results until the demonstration<lb/>
by Ross and the Italian group converted it into an established doctrine.<lb/>
Since these facts are so, it appears to me as unjust and unscientific for<lb/>
Cubans to claim all the credit for Finlay as for Americans to fail to give<lb/>
Finlay his due share of the glory. To invoke the Seventh Commandment<lb/>
seems to me to be rather harsh language on either side; rather should be<lb/>
invoked that spirit of justice which should be an attribute of the scien-<lb/>
tific mind.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06271003"/>
<p>FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>It gives me great pleasure to read the Boletin Oficial de<lb/>
la Secretaria de Sanidad y Beneficencia, and I often hope that I may<lb/>
some day have the pleasure of another visit to Cuba to see again my<lb/>
good friends there of whom I shall always count you as one.</p>
<p>With cordial regards, I am</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>J. R. KEAN<lb/>
Colonel, U. S. Army, Retired<lb/>
Editor.<lb/>
The Military Surgeon</signed>
JRK/W<lb/>
Note May 14 1946- Several years ago Dr. Francisco Dominguez<lb/>
a distinguished doctor of Havana (now dead) sent me his<lb/>
book written in French written in the centennial year of Dr. Finlay,<lb/>
birth in which he claims that Finlays inoculation experiments<lb/>
with yellow fever were successful. He gives a very interesting<lb/>
account of the <unclear>dinner</unclear> to Doctor Finlay on Dec. 22 1900 by<lb/>
the doctors of Havana. He says that he got up the dinner<lb/>
at General Woods request and he presided <unclear>and</unclear> made the<lb/>
principal address which I have ascribed to Dr. Juan Guiteras.<lb/>
How the accounts of two reputable persons as to the same<lb/>
dinner can differ so widely I cannot imagine. My knowledge<lb/>
of Spanish was imperfect but my conversation with Dr. Finlay<lb/>
was in English and I knew the chief speaker Dr Guiteras<lb/>
very well.<lb/>
Dr. Dominguez <unclear>&amp;</unclear> Carlos E. Finlay &amp; others now<lb/>
claim for Dr. F several successful cases.<lb/>
The case of Rev. Padre Uma looks like one.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
