<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06275005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 25, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06275005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-07-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Goodale, Capt.</name>
<name type="person">Baldwin, T. A.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-07-25">July 25, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06275005</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 25, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby's recounts his memories of the yellow fever experiments, and his anger with Agramonte for making what he feels are unjustified claims.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1930-07-25">
<head>Memorandum from Albert E. Truby to Jefferson Randolph Kean, July 25, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06275005"/>
<opener>
<unclear>aet ell</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1930-07-25">July 25, 1930.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>MEMORANDUM for General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>When it became known that the Spanish immigrants were not satisfact-<lb/>
ory to Major Reed for his experiments on yellow fever, several members of the<lb/>
Hospital Corps detachment at Camp Columbia volunteered for this work. Those<lb/>
of us at Camp Columbia considered this one of the most heroic events in history<lb/>
since all of these men had been in Cuba and knew from experience at the<lb/>
hospital what it meant to contract yellow fever. They had been through the<lb/>
epidemic and had seen the high mortality caused by this disease among our<lb/>
officers at Quemados and Havana. Furthermore at this time the officers and<lb/>
men on duty at the hospital, including these volunteers, were all convinced<lb/>
that the mosquito was the agent that transmitted yellow fever to Lazear,<lb/>
Carroll and XY. There was no reward offered to these men at that time.<lb/>
They admired and respected Major Reed and volunteered because they felt that<lb/>
the positive proof needed to substantiate the mosquito theory could not be<lb/>
obtained in any other way. Later on Major Reed found that he could give them<lb/>
a gratuity from the funds which had been allotted to him for this work, and he<lb/>
decided to offer it to them. I am positive however that this money gratuity<lb/>
offered no inducement to any of these men.</p>
<p>I was in command of the detachment when Major Reed selected the<lb/>
site for Camp Lazear. Dr. Roger Post Ames and I went with Major Reed when<lb/>
he first inspected the site, and if I am not mistaken you were with us or<lb/>
went over to see the site before it was finally selected. As you know, it<lb/>
was not &ldquo;we&rdquo; (Agramonte, Reed and Carroll) who did these things. It was<lb/>
Major Reed alone, and it makes my blood boil to have the last surviving<lb/>
member of that board, and the one whom Reed <del>knew</del><add>used</add> so little, make such an<lb/>
effort to detract from Reed's work.</p>
<p>I certainly concur in your letter, but if I were writing it I would<lb/>
make it stronger and point out some statements he has made which are not in<lb/>
accordance with facts. Agramonte never saw <unclear>XY</unclear>, and he knew nothing about him<lb/>
until Reed published his preliminary report. He did not see Lazear during<lb/>
his illness and I doubt if he was present at the funeral. As Commanding<lb/>
Officer of the hospital the arrangements for that funeral fell to me and I<lb/>
have a very clear recollection of the occasion and my fight with Captain<lb/>
Goodale, Quartermaster, who did not want us to use the flag, as it would ruin<lb/>
it to be disinfected, and also my difficulties with Colonel Baldwin, the Com-<lb/>
manding Officer of Camp Columbia, over the band and the <unclear>chaplain</unclear> All these<lb/>
circumstances are still fresh in my memory. Of course I do not wish to start<lb/>
anything at this time, but as you know, there are a few of us left who know the<lb/>
details. Outside of the enlisted men who took part in the experiments the only<lb/>
living officers who knew what went on at that time are you and Dr. Pinto and<lb/>
myself.</p>
<closer>
<signed>Albert E. Truby<lb/>
Colonel, Medical Corps,<lb/>
Executive Officer</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
