<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06284121">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 9, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06284121</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-12-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, John M.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-12-09">December 9, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06284121</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 9, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench attempts to finish the Rheumatism Review, allowing little time for yellow fever research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-12-09">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 9, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06284121"/>
<opener>
y. f.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-12-09">December 9, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I feel so appreciative whenever you write to me, and yet I feel apologetic,<lb/>
knowing that you have to do it by long hand. Some of these days I am going to write you<lb/>
a long letter, and unfortunately, will be asking you quite a number of questions. It has<lb/>
pained me that I have had to drop the yellow fever investigations temporarily. I got<lb/>
into an unhappy jam, trying to finish the Rheumatism Review, as one of my supposed collab-<lb/>
orators fell down on the job at the last moment very miserably, but another two weeks<lb/>
will see the Review finished and sent to press.</p>
<p>I was asked to give my talk on yellow fever before our Clinical Society,<lb/>
which I did last Thursday, and the audience, though small, was most appreciative. I<lb/>
amplified my Washington and Jefferson talk with sixty slides, and although this lengthened<lb/>
it considerably, it seemed to add to it greatly.</p>
<p>You asked about the Lazear family. I planned to find out more about them.<lb/>
As a matter of fact, when I was a boy in Pittsburgh, one of my fairly good friends was<lb/>
John Lazear. At that time, I know nothing about Dr. Lazear and having left Pittsburgh,<lb/>
I lost sight of him. He lives a block from my mother's home, and has married into a<lb/>
very wealthy family, the Harkness family. I haven't see John for years, but mother tells<lb/>
me he often asks about me, and if I cannot raise funds elsewhere, I am planning to call<lb/>
on &ldquo;dear old Johnny&rdquo; to come across!</p>
<p>I am glad that Dr. Finlay sent you his book, and I am particularly happy<lb/>
to have your reaction to it. I have read over some of old Dr. Finlay's original papers<lb/>
and they are fascinating. He certainly had a wonderful intuition, and I quite agree<lb/>
that American physicians should have given him more credit than he got. I agree with<lb/>
you that it is unfortunate that Finlay began to make a few extra little claims after it<lb/>
was discovered that his theories were correct. I suspect that it was these claims that<lb/>
incited Carroll to his caustic criticism. This just set the argument going, so that<lb/>
everybody concerned got themselves out on a limb.</p>
<p>If I can, I plan to take a little more extensive vacation this Spring,<lb/>
going to California to visit Mrs. Lazear briefly, and also General Truby, then relaxing<lb/>
on a boat through the Panama Canal to Havana, spending a little while there settling up<lb/>
the matter of a deed to the old building and trying to find out from Dr. Ramos, Secretary<lb/>
of Defense, how our plans for its memorialization might fit in with theirs. I am sure<lb/>
that we can make some arrangements satisfactory to all.</p>
<p>I shall be most happy to have the excerpts from your diary, but hate to<lb/>
have you go to the trouble of coping them by hand. Nevertheless, I realize that you<lb/>
have trepedition in submitting it to the mail. May I say that I learned as much back-<lb/>
ground information from your diary as I did specific information. Your diary told me<lb/>
much of the mechanics of the medical setup, etc.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06284122"/>
<p>--2 --<lb/>
December 9, 1940</p>
<p>Several physicians and others have given me suggestions as to where<lb/>
to publish my remarks, and it looks now as if I would be able to make several<lb/>
choices. There will be no trouble whatever in getting it published. I think<lb/>
it would perhaps be best to publish it in two or three papers, but my first job<lb/>
is to get it in a paper to submit to Dr. Ramos.</p>
<p>May I extent to you and Mrs. Kean our most sincere best wishes<lb/>
for a happy Christmas season.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely and most appreciatively yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
