<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06280009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from Robin Lampson, December 14, 1937</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06280009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1937-10-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Hendricks, Burton J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Black, William M.</name>
<name type="person">Wrightson, Mrs. W. D.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Mary G.</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Mrs. Samuel T.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="publication">Marie D. Gorgas and Burton J. Hendrick, William Crawford Gorgas, His Life and Work (1925)</name>
<name type="publication">Military Surgeon (March 1925)</name>
<name type="publication">Robin Lampson, Death Loses a Pair of Wings</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1937-12-14">December 14, 1937</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06280009</idno> 
<title>Memorandum from Robin Lampson, December 14, 1937</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lampson solicits information about Gorgas for an upcoming book on the conquest of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>

<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1937-12-14">
<head>Memorandum from Robin Lampson, December 14, 1937</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06280009"/>
<p>TO THOSE INTERESTED IN THE LATE DR. WILLIAM CRAWFORD GORGAS:n</p>
<p>I am writing a book based on Dr. Gorgas's life, especially his<lb/>
conquest of yellow fever through mosquito abatement, to be<lb/>
called &ldquo;Death Loses a Pair of Wings.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Charles Scribner's Sons, New York, who published my first his-<lb/>
torical novel, &ldquo;Laughter Out of the Ground,&rdquo; have contracted to<lb/>
publish my Gorgas book as soon as the manuscript is ready. (I<lb/>
inclose--for your information, <hi>not</hi> as an advertisement--one of<lb/>
the publisher's announcements of the first book.)</p>
<p>I have already received much helpful information from Gorgas's<lb/>
daughter, Mrs. W. D. Wrightson, his sister, Miss Mary G. Gorgas,<lb/>
as well as from others associated with him in his great work,<lb/>
such as Dr. Joseph A. LePrince. Mrs. Jesse W. Lazear and Mrs.<lb/>
Samuel T. Darling are also cooperating.</p>
<p>Naturally, I am already familiar with the general outlines of<lb/>
Gorgas's life--the important incidents of historical record.<lb/>
But, except for a few items, I still lack the little more-or-<lb/>
less homely personal anecdotes such as make the characters of<lb/>
a novel come to life.</p>
<p>If you, or anyone else within your knowledge, can supply me<lb/>
with some of these little humanizing and vivifying items about<lb/>
Gorgas--what he did or said on such-and-such occasion--I, and<lb/>
my readers as well, I believe, will be permanently indebted to<lb/>
you. And of course, any contribution of material to the book<lb/>
will be gratefully acknowledged in the foreword.</p>
<p>I think General Gorgas's story is one of the proudest chapters<lb/>
in American and recent history. This truly great American de-<lb/>
serves to be more &ldquo;in the hearts of his countrymen&rdquo;--in their<lb/>
textbooks and on their tongues--than he now is. I sincerely<lb/>
hope you will cooperate to make my book, &ldquo;Death Loses a Pair<lb/>
of Wings,&rdquo; a fine and comprehensive memorial to that great man.</p>
<closer>
<signed>ROBIN LAMPSON</signed>.
2449 Dwight Way,<lb/>
Berkeley, California.<lb/>
1937-<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
