<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06284102">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 4, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06284102</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-11-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Washington (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-11-04">November 4, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06284102</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 4, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench mentions Carlos E. Finlay's comments about his father during his later years. He describes in detail the dedication ceremony for the Jesse Lazear Building and mentions Mabel Lazear's opinion of her husband's work. He offers his opinion of Moran and Kissinger.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-11-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 4, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06284102"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-11-04">November 4, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I appreciated your telegram so very much, and also the nice, full letter<lb/>
which just reached me a few days ago.</p>
<p>I was amused at your admonition to omit the words &ldquo;slightly touched&rdquo; in<lb/>
my description of Dr. Finlay -- amused because those words were quoted straight<lb/>
from the book of Dr. Finlay's son, which book has just appeared, published by<lb/>
the Oxford University Press in New York City. Nevertheless, I knew you had no<lb/>
knowledge of that and as I had not given the reference to that quotation, you<lb/>
were entirely right in suggesting that it be omitted, which I did. Should I<lb/>
ever use it, I will make it clear in the context of the paper that the quotation<lb/>
is from Dr. Finlay's own son.</p>
<p>We had a grand time in Washington. The memorial building is really very<lb/>
beautiful. The morning program was a fine one, and the audience gave Moran and<lb/>
Kissinger quite an ovation, both at the morning ceremony, and at the evening play,<lb/>
&ldquo;Yellow Jack&rdquo;. Mrs. Sidney Howard, widow of the author of the play, was also<lb/>
present. I was deeply appreciative of the honor which the college gave me, all<lb/>
the more so because it was the second honorary degree which I have received in<lb/>
six months. The audience at the banquet accepted my talk most sympathetically, and<lb/>
I heard many very pleasant remarks made about it. In particular, the relatives<lb/>
of Dr. Lazear who were present (there were three of them) were delighted, and were<lb/>
especially pleased to know that I had got in touch with Mrs. Lazear and that she<lb/>
was cooperating so nicely. They told me in confidence (and I am passing it on to<lb/>
you also in confidence) that Mrs. Lazear had had a curious reaction to her husband's<lb/>
work and death, that she had considered it foolish, and that he was by no means a<lb/>
hero to her, that for years she did not discuss it with her family or children,<lb/>
and more or less taught them that their father had done a foolish thing. You see,<lb/>
she was rather destitute for some time after his death. She has never apparently<lb/>
cooperated with anyone before to any extent. Dr. Hutchison, President of Washington<lb/>
and Jefferson, was a bit hurt at her lack of response to their dedication, but her<lb/>
letters to me in the last three weeks have been all that one could wish for, and I<lb/>
have a letter today from her, expressing her deepest gratitude. Perhaps I can find<lb/>
out more interesting information and will certainly pass it on to you.</p>
<p>I shall be delighted to have the excerpts from the diary, or the diary itself,<lb/>
whichever you permit me to have. I agree with you that no one should be permitted<lb/>
to quote your uncomplimentary reference to Colonel Wood. That is a personal item<lb/>
which any conscientious historian would leave strictly alone, and if you prefer, I<lb/>
will cross it off so vigorously in the photostatic copy that no one else can read it.</p>
<p>The more I see of Moran, the more I like him. He is a most substantial, care-<lb/>
ful and thoughtful individual. Poor old Kissinger died mentally about 1901. Because<lb/>
of his unfortunate illness, he was more or less forced &ldquo;to go into the hero business&rdquo;<lb/>
in order to live. He has found it rather pleasant, and his rather coy bows on being<lb/>
presented to the audience greatly amused my wife, who knew the inside story. But,<lb/>
of course, he is merely a simple minded farmer and one can't blame him too much.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06284103"/>
<p>General J. R. Kean</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>November 4, 1940</p>
<p>Dr. Sawyer's talk was splendid, and many people gave me much spiritual<lb/>
(so far no financial) support for my project to restore and present the building and<lb/>
memorial to the Cuban government.</p>
<p>I must make a hasty trip to New York and the East in a couple of days, speaking<lb/>
in three or four places, and on my return will write you in more detail about all<lb/>
of this. Meanwhile, I am sure the enclosed clippings, etc. will interest you.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
