<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06284055">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 12, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06284055</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Pittsburgh (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-12">September 12, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06284055</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 12, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench expresses great interest in reading Truby's paper. He requests the address of Emilie Lawrence Reed and Blossom Reed. He discusses the dinner honoring Moran at the University of Virginia, and he invites Kean to attend the dedication of the Lazear Memorial Building.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 12, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06284055"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-12">September 12, 1940</date>
</dateline>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N. Street N. W.<lb/>
Georgetown<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am so glad my memorandum and photographs arrived safely but my<lb/>
conscience hurts me at the amount of work I am asking you to do. My only defence is<lb/>
that it is in behalf of a cause that is so dear to your heart.</p>
<p>I should love to see General Truby's complete sketch. I agree with you<lb/>
that his contribution will be most important and has a participant his remarks will be of<lb/>
infinitely greater importance than any I could publish. Do you know where he plans to pub-<lb/>
lish it, as a book or in a medical journal? He only sent me a page of abstracts and I am<lb/>
delighted to have that for my Washington and Jefferson speech. I was interested to hear<lb/>
of your recent conversation with General Ireland and you state that since then you wrote to<lb/>
Mrs. Walter Reed. I did not know she was living and I am most anxious to get her address.<lb/>
You say her daughter answered. I would appreciate it greatly to have the addresses of both<lb/>
of these people. So far, I have been</p>
<p>May I again beg of you for once to cast off your long worn <unclear>cloak</unclear> of<lb/>
modesty and tell me in as intimate detail as you are willing, of the various ways you helped<lb/>
Dr. Reed and the commission. The amount of material I am getting is growing and the story<lb/>
becomes daily more fascinating. I am of the mind to make this a hobby, to keep on investi-<lb/>
gating the matter and publish my researches not only in the form of a medical article but<lb/>
perhaps even in the form of a book, at some distant future time, and it is only fair to you<lb/>
and to your family that, in the third person, your contribution can be spoken of with dignity<lb/>
and the full truth.</p>
<p>I am delighted to know that the medical faculty at the University of<lb/>
Virginia are giving Moran a dinner. I had a modest hand in this. In Havana, he spoke<lb/>
wistfully of his desire to see the University again. I made a note of this and after leaving<lb/>
Washington, I went to Charlottesville and spoke to a couple of individuals, telling them<lb/>
that Moran might be in the States on the twenty-sixth of October. I am delighted at the<lb/>
result of this conversation. Perhaps I told you that my brother is Professor of English<lb/>
Literature at the University of Virginia and has been there for about eighteen years.<lb/>
He married a local girl of the <unclear>Michie</unclear> family, long associated with the history of that<lb/>
part of Virginia. I wish indeed that I could attend this dinner, but as I will be seeing<lb/>
Moran in Washington, Pennsylvania a few days later, I think I will have to forego the<lb/>
pleasure.</p>
<p>I am most anxious to have your data from the diary. Although I have<lb/>
read much of the epidemic of yellow fever in Cuba, your simply written notes brought the<lb/>
tragedy more forcefully to my mind than anything I have read. I will appreciate it if<lb/>
you could amplify your diary, and dictate to the stenographer the general reaction of the<lb/>
army and the people of Havana to that particular epidemic. With citizens and soldiers dying<lb/>
right and left, was there much panic, quiet fear, or was it all accepted fatalistically?<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06284056"/>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
September 12, 1940<lb/>
You will note that I did not include the interesting story which you told me about<lb/>
interviewing your friend with yellow fever through the window, with you on the porch.<lb/>
It is such little anecdotes that bring a story to life, and if you are willing for<lb/>
me to insert that, I shall be delighted to use it.</p>
<p>I am sending you by separate post a photograph of the Lazear Memorial<lb/>
Building, to be dedicated at Washington and Jefferson College, Washington, Pennsylvania.<lb/>
I think it is a lovely building. Would you be able to attend this affair? I know that<lb/>
they expect to invite Moran and Kissinger, and confidentially, funds are being raised<lb/>
to pay their expenses. I fear that these funds would not cover the traveling expenses<lb/>
of others, even one as closely associated with the work as you were, but I am absolutely<lb/>
certain that the President would be highly honored to send you an invitation if you<lb/>
thought you could attend the affair. Washington is about thirty miles from Pittsburgh.<lb/>
It is a small college of about five hundred and not overly pretentious, but is rich in<lb/>
tradition and prominent alumni. It is the oldest college west of the <unclear>Allegheny</unclear> Mountains.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I just had a letter from Dr. C. R. Finlay of Havana, Dr.<lb/>
Carlos Finlay's son. I believe I told you that he was publishing a book, in English,<lb/>
on his father's work. He tells me that it is just off the press and I am sending for<lb/>
a copy at once, to the Oxford University Press, 114 Fifth Ave., New York City.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
