<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06283001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Memorandum from A.S. Dabney to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 15, 1938</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Dabney, A.S.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06283001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1938-04-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Murfreesboro (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Willets Point (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">New York City</name>
<name type="place">Fort Yuma (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lowell (Ariz.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Apache (Ariz.)</name>
<name type="place">Richmond (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Creedmoor (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Ontario (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McHenry (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Omaha (Nebr.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Sidney (Nebr.)</name>
<name type="place">Mt. Vernon (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Snelling (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">St. Paul (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fl.)</name>
<name type="place">Natural Bridge (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Principe (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Fort Thomas (Ky.)</name>
<name type="place">Minneapolis (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Tampa (Fl.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1938-04-15">April 15, 1938</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06283001</idno>
<title>Memorandum from A.S. Dabney to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 15, 1938</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Dabney provides Kean with a chronological listing of Reed's service in the U.S. Army Medical Corps.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1938-04-15">
<head>Memorandum from A.S. Dabney to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 15, 1938</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06283001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1938-04-15">April 15, 1938</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>MEMORANDUM FOR General Kean.<lb/>
Subject: Information re Service of Dr. Walter Reed.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>Dr. Walter Reed was appointed Asst. Surgeon, U. S. Army on June<lb/>
26, 1875. He accepted appointment on July 3, 1875. From July 3, 1875<lb/>
to July 23, 1875, he was at Murfreesboro, N. C., awaiting orders.</item>
<item>July 23, 1875, to April 14, 1876, on duty at Willets Point, N. Y.</item>
<item>April 15, 1876, to May 21, 1876, enroute to Dept. of California<lb/>
with recruits from New York City.</item>
<item>June 1, 1876, to August 5, 1876, on duty at Fort Yuma, California.</item>
<item>August 5, 1876, to August 10, 1877, on duty at Camp Lowell, Ariz.</item>
<item>August 10, 1877, to May 10, 1880, on duty at Camp Apache, Ariz.</item>
<item>May 10, 1880, to June 8, 1880, enroute to and awaiting orders at<lb/>
Richmond, Virginia.</item>
<item>June 26, 1880, promoted Asst. Surgeon with rank of Captain.</item>
<item>June 9, 1880, to September 3, 1880, on leave of absence and await-<lb/>
ing orders.</item>
<item>Sept. 6, 1880, to Sept. 18, 1880, on duty with Rifel Team at<lb/>
Creedmoor, L. I.</item>
<item>Sept. 23, 1880, to Feb. 23, 1881, on duty at Fort Ontario, N. Y.</item>
<item>Feb. 24, 1881, to May 2, 1881, on duty at Fort McHenry, Ma.</item>
<item>May 2, 1881, to Nov. 17, 1882, on duty at Washington Barracks, D. C.</item>
<item>March, 1882, examined for promotion at New York City and found<lb/>
qualified.</item>
<item>Nov. 17, 1882, to Dec. 4, 1882, enroute to and at Headquarters<lb/>
Dept. of the Platte for orders.</item>
<item>Dec. 4, 1882, to Jan. 1, 1883, Attending Surgeon at Headquarters<lb/>
Dept. of the Platte, Omaha, Nebr.</item>
<item>Jan. 2, 1883, to Oct, 4, 1883, on duty at Fort Omaha, Nebr.</item>
<item>Oct. 5, 1883, to Aug, 4, 1884, on duty at Fort Sidney, Nebr.</item>
<item>Aug, 8, 1884, to July 31, 1887, on duty at Fort Robinson, Nebr.</item>
<item>Aug. 5, 1887, to Oct. 6, 1890, on duty at Mt. Vernon Bks,, Ala.</item>
<item>Oct. 6, 1890, to Oct. 31, 1891, on duty as Attending Surgeon and<lb/>
Examiner of Recruits at Baltimore, Maryland.</item>
<item>Nov. 7, 1891, to Aug. 21, 1892, on duty at Fort Snelling, Minn.</item>
<item>Aug. 21, 1592 to Aug. 31, 1893, Attending Surgeon and Examiner<lb/>
of Recruits at St. Paul, Minn.</item>
<item>Sept. 6, 1893, Curator of the Army Medical Museum.</item>
<item>Sept., 1893, examined at Washington, D. C., for promotion and found<lb/>
qualified.</item>
<item>Sept. 11, 1893, to Oct. 21, 1893, member of Army Medical Board.</item>
<item>Promoted Surgeon with the rank of Major on Dec. 4, 1893.</item>
<item>July 22, 1896, to August 7, 1896, on detached service Key West,<lb/>
Florida.</item>
<item>Member Cholera Band Board.</item>
<item>Aug. 1, 1898, to Aug. 8, 1898, on detached duty making an inspec-<lb/>
tion of Camps and Field Hospitals.</item>
<item>Aug. 20, 1898, to Sept. 18, 189, member of typhoid fever board<lb/>
and inspecting certain <unclear>camps</unclear>.</item>
<item>Sept. 25, 1898, to Sept. 30, 1898, member of board investigating<lb/>
causes of typhoid fever.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f06283002"/>
<item>Oct. 1, 1898, to Oct. 10, 1898, on duty with typhoid fever board.</item>
<item>Oct. 18, 1898, to Oct. 25, 1898, on detached service inspecting<lb/>
buildings at Natural Bridge, Virginia.</item>
<item>Apr. 19, 1899, to May 9, 1899, on inspection duty at Puerto<lb/>
Principe, Cuba.</item>
<item>Sept. 28, 1899, to Sept. 30, 1899, on detached duty at Fort Thomas,<lb/>
Kentucky.</item>
<item>Oct. 31, 1899, to Nov. 3, 1899, delegate to American Public Health<lb/>
Association, Minneapolis, Minnesota.</item>
<item>March 7, 1900, to Apr. 3, 1900, on duty at Tampa, Fla. and Havana,<lb/>
Cuba on investigation as to use of electrozone as <unclear>a germicide</unclear> in Havana.</item>
</list>
<closer>
<signed>A. S. Dabney,<lb/>
Lieut. Colonel, Medical Corps,<lb/>
Executive Officer</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
