<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06284083">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 7, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06284083</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-10-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-10-07">October 7, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06284083</idno>
<title>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 7, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] informs Kean that he has found proof that a rental fee was paid by the U.S. military to use the Rojas family farm. He is thinking of purchasing Building No. 1 at Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-10-07">
<head>Letter from [Philip Showalter Hench] to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 7, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06284083"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-10-07">October 7, 1940</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In a day or two I will be returning, by registered express, your diary,<lb/>
with a half dozen questions. It has been of tremendous value to me but more of this<lb/>
tomorrow.</p>
<p>I am writing you hastily to tell you of the latest discovery. I sent my<lb/>
memorandum to the Rojas family and, you remember, asked them about the possibility of<lb/>
their having some sort of contract between Dr. Rojas and Reed or Agramonte. When I was<lb/>
there, Mrs. Rojas knew of none, but since receiving my detailed memorandum, the family<lb/>
has interested themselves and Miss Rojas has been hunting around the family records.<lb/>
Last week she found some old day books of her father and in one of them were notations<lb/>
written in her father's hand proving that the camp site was not ceded gratis, but that<lb/>
a rental of $20.00 American gold monthly had been paid from and including November 9, 1900<lb/>
to October 10, 1901, buildings nos. 1 and 2, to remain the property of the owner. Entries<lb/>
in Dr. Rojas' journal-cash book were made regularly, the first check having been received<lb/>
from &ldquo;Major Mr. Reed&rdquo; and subsequent checks from &ldquo;Major J. R. Kean, the latter evidently<lb/>
acting as disbursing quartermaster.&rdquo; Miss Rojas excitedly <unclear>phoned</unclear> Moran, who airmailed me<lb/>
at once this information. They are having it copied and translated for me and attested to,<lb/>
and I am arranging also to have more definite proof; that is, actual photographs of the<lb/>
entries.</p>
<p>In view of the stubbornness of the Cuban officials, including Dr. Angles,<lb/>
to recognize their mistake and the correctness of my information to them, this record of<lb/>
Dr. Rojas should act as final proof. Apparently you did not remember or at least did not<lb/>
tell me that you had been involved in this transaction and I should be most grateful if<lb/>
you could give me what information you remember. Doubtless, you kept records of these<lb/>
transactions. Where are these now filed, and could we get them from the quartermaster or<lb/>
War Department? The reason I am anxious to know is that I would like to plant the seeds of<lb/>
a campaign during my Washington and Jefferson talk. Indeed, I have not told you all. Moran<lb/>
revisited the site we investigated and has now decided that one of the <unclear>shacks</unclear> which we<lb/>
thought could not have been either building no. 1 or 2, is in truth building no. 1 with<lb/>
many renovations, mostly outside. Inside he found the tongued and grooved boards with weather<lb/>
boarding on the outside and a lean-to addition which distorted the appearance entirely.<lb/>
I am not yet willing to accept this, but nevertheless have written asking Pogolotti to<lb/>
quietly sound out the price for the house and lot. I will personally buy it at once if we<lb/>
can prove its historicity, to my satisfaction. I can assure you that I will buy it only<lb/>
to protect it and as a first step in a quiet campaign among medical friends and institutions<lb/>
proud of Reed, Lazear, etc. to raise enough money to restore it and memorialize it properly.<lb/>
More of this later, I enclose a copy of Dr. Angles' recent letter. It is not too clear,<lb/>
probably because of the translation but the ideals obvious, that i am entirely wrong, that the<lb/>
San Jose farm has nothing to do with Camp Lazear, that Camp Lazear was right by the railroad<lb/>
track near Camp Columbia and that the American followers of Reed robbed Finlay of all his<lb/>
glory.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
