<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06282020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 27, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06282020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-10-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-10-27">October 27, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06282020</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 27, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses his interest in the story of the conquest of yellow fever and asks for Kean's involvement.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-10-27">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 27, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06282020"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1939-10-27">October 27, 1939</date>
</dateline>
Gen. Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
U. S. Army, Retired<lb/>
2804 N. Street, N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have become interested in the fascinating story of the conquest<lb/>
of yellow fever by Dr. Walter Reed and his colleagues. A couple of years ago<lb/>
I <unclear>became</unclear> acquainted with Mr. John Kissinger who was one of the first to receive<lb/>
the experimental yellow fever. I had the privilege of visiting him in his home<lb/>
and he has visited here at the Mayo Clinic and has given a talk, at my request,<lb/>
before the members of our staff. I have had some interesting correspondence<lb/>
also with Mr. John Moran. It was my suggestion that both of these men publish<lb/>
brief personal stories of their experiences which I should be glad to help<lb/>
place in our best medical historical magazines. In discussing the story with<lb/>
each of them I found I came across certain controversial points which apparently<lb/>
have never been decided and which cannot be satisfactority decided by either<lb/>
Mr. Moran or Mr. Kissinger alone.</p>
<p>Mr. Moran has taken the liberty of suggesting that you might be<lb/>
willing to help in this work, and I am delighted at the suggestion. Mr. Moran<lb/>
has indicated that perhaps you might be willing to dictate answers to a list<lb/>
of questions that I might send to you, but I believe this would not be satis-<lb/>
factory to either one of us and perhaps the matter could be done more satis-<lb/>
factorily and less fatigueingly to you if I could visit you sometime in the<lb/>
not too distant future in Washington. I hope to visit Mr. Moran in Havana in<lb/>
March and perhaps after that I could visit you in Washington. If you should<lb/>
prefer, I should be glad to submit to you a list of questions concerning the<lb/>
controversial points, which list you could answer at your leisure and convenience.<lb/>
I have assured Mr. Moran that you are such an authority on the subject and that<lb/>
perhaps it might be best for all concerned if you yourself would write up the<lb/>
story with such help as I could give you. On the other hand, if you do not care<lb/>
to do so I should be glad to accept your collaboration as the editor of the two<lb/>
stories which I am helping Mr. Moran and Mr. Kissinger to prepare. It would be<lb/>
indeed a great privilege to have you as coeditor in this venture, and you could<lb/>
make such comments and notes as you think best.</p>
<p>I hasten to tell you that my purpose is purely unselfish and the venture<lb/>
is taken on purely from my interest in medical history. Medical historical<lb/>
magazines offer no fee for such articles and the best I could do is to get reprints<lb/>
for their own pleasure. However, it is possible that once the matter is down in<lb/>
black and white for the medical magazine that it could be written in a more<lb/>
popular style for some such journal as the &ldquo;Saturday Evening Post&rdquo;. Whatever fees<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06282021"/>
Gen. Jefferson Kean<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
October 27, 1939<lb/>
we might be able to get for the article I can assure you will be turned over<lb/>
entirely to Mr. Moran and Mr. Kissinger as it is their story written in<lb/>
their way that the public is interested in and not my comments.</p>
<p>I shall be grateful to hear from you at your convenience.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds:if<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
