<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06284057">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 17, 1940</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06284057</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1940-09-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Michie, Robert E. Lee</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Clemons, Harry</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar de Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Jacksonville (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Carlisle (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Lexington (Va.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>18 pp.</extent>
<date value="1940-09-17">September 17, 1940</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06284057</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 17, 1940</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean responds in detail to Hench's letter concerning the yellow fever experiments. He sends his diary from late 1900 and a copy of a speech at the dedication of Walter Reed's birthplace.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1940-09-17">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 17, 1940</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06284057"/>
<opener>
United States Commission<lb/>
for the Erection of a Permanent Memorial to the Memory of<lb/>
Thomas Jefferson<lb/>
1743 -- 1826<lb/>
COMMISSIONERS<lb/>
----<lb/>
UNITED STATES SENATE<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS UTAH<lb/>
CHARLES L. McNARY OREGON<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS FLORIDA<lb/>
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH VIRGINIA<lb/>
FRANCIS D. CULKIN NEW YORK<lb/>
FRITZ G. LANHAM TEXAS<lb/>
----<lb/>
THOMAS JEFFERSON MEMORIAL<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
STUART G. GIBBONEY<lb/>
DR. GEORGE J. RYAN<lb/>
DR. FISKE KIMBALL<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
STUART G. GIBBONEY<lb/>
VICE CHAIRMEN<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS<lb/>
CHARLES L. McNARY<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH<lb/>
PRESIDENTIAL COMMISSIONERS<lb/>
T. JEFFERSON COOLIDGE JOSEPH P. TUMULTY<lb/>
BRIG. GEN. JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN<lb/>
----<lb/>
EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE<lb/>
STUART G. GIBBONEY<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS<lb/>
CHARLES L. McNARY<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH<lb/>
FRANCIS D. CULKIN<lb/>
FRITZ G. LANHAM<lb/>
JOSEPH P. TUMULTY<lb/>
DR. FISKE KIMBALL<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1940-09-17">Sept.17/1940</date>
2804 N St. N. W.<lb/>
???<lb/>
WASHINGTON, D. C.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is going to be a long letter, and one<lb/>
too long postponed so I will write it on letter, in-<lb/>
stead of note, paper- I have been too much upset to<lb/>
write it sooner as I buried two weeks ago today<lb/>
my youngest brother - a splendid fellow whom I<lb/>
loved as a son- He was twenty years younger than<lb/>
I am- Your good letter of Sept. 12 is before <unclear>me</unclear><lb/>
for reply and I have numbered the paragraphs<lb/>
for convenience of reference - 5 <add>A G E</add> on p. 1 and <del>6 &amp; 7</del> <add><unclear>F. B</unclear></add><lb/>
&amp; <unclear>8</unclear> on p. 2 the latter being the P. S.</p>
<p>A The Cuban y. f. episode is as you say dear to me<lb/>
and you need not worry about me- I appreciate<lb/>
very keenly the value of your work and that you<lb/>
have got Gen. Truby and me to work together on<lb/>
it and supply materials for a revaluation of<lb/>
the contributions of the actors-</p>
<p>(There is too much headline to this paper I will look up some<lb/>
plain sheets- tho they may not match it)</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06284058"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>B. I hope you have received Truby's sketch by this time-<lb/>
He wanted me to read it before sending it to you<lb/>
so as to iron out any differences in our recollect-<lb/>
ion of details- His contributions are far more<lb/>
detailed than mine and far more valuable- His<lb/>
work at the hospital of which he was part of the time<lb/>
in <unclear>commenced</unclear> &amp; when not, was executive officer,<lb/>
brought him into intimate contact with the work<lb/>
of the commission, which I did not have- My<lb/>
office was busy with the troubles of the medical<lb/>
service all over western Cuba &amp; the 1001 sani-<lb/>
tary questions of the <unclear>posts</unclear> and camps; and the<lb/>
16 Cuban orphan asylums that old Clara<lb/>
Barton established inside of a month &amp; then<lb/>
went off &amp; left them on my hands without<lb/>
any records of rents or agreements or even a<lb/>
list of employe's and inmates, or any visible<lb/>
means of support - but that is another story-<lb/>
Therefore I did not know what part Agramonte<lb/>
took in the mosquito work of the Commission after<lb/>
Lazear's death and am quite willing to accept<lb/>
Truby's statement of it- But I do not think it of<lb/>
enough importance to challenge <unclear>A's</unclear> veracity<lb/>
about after forty years- Gen. Truby in a former<lb/>
letter found fault with me for publishing in Chap. 4<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06284059"/>
Par. 2.<lb/>
3<lb/>
p. 25 &amp; 26 (Senate Doc. No. 520. 61<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Congress 2. Session) of the<lb/>
Senate Doc. 822 <hi>Yellow Fever</hi>, which you have, Agra-<lb/>
monte's statement of his share of the work of the board.<lb/>
I put it in because A. had come to me and com-<lb/>
plained that I had done him great injustice in a<lb/>
former Senate doc. (No. 10 59<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Congress) page 21 of <hi>Yellow Fever</hi>-<lb/>
This I had written on Carroll's authority, having no<lb/>
suspicion of the hostility that C. had for A. So I<lb/>
thought it only fair to let A. make his own state-<lb/>
ment on the subject- In Truby's nice, gentle way<lb/>
he included Ireland in this statement of Agram-<lb/>
onte's share, but, as Gen. Ireland said, he had no-<lb/>
first hand knowledge of the matter and had<lb/>
nothing to do with the publication of the document-<lb/>
The Surgeon Gen. OReilly signed it, but as I recall, his<lb/>
apporval &amp; signature was all that he contributed-<lb/>
I had many contacts with Agramonte when I was<lb/>
in charge of the sanitary dept. of Cuba in the Second<lb/>
Intervention (1906 to 1909) and my opinion of Agra-<lb/>
monte is better than Truby's, as his opinion of<lb/>
Carroll is better than mine-</p>
<p>par. C. I have no cloak of modesty about what help I was<lb/>
able to give Reed- As all the medical personel<lb/>
of the Provinces of Havana &amp; Pinar del Rio was<lb/>
under my supervision I could give him support<lb/>
in having many little things done, but nothing<lb/>
to speak of- After he was established at Colum-<lb/>
bia barracks, Truby could do much more for him<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06284060"/>
4<lb/>
par C cont.) than I could- My only serious contribution<lb/>
to his success was in persuading him to ask<lb/>
Gen. Wood for money to establish Camp Lazear &amp;<lb/>
hire Spanish immigrants for the experiments-<lb/>
When I proposed this to Reed on our drive to<lb/>
Havana he made no reply, but seemed wrapped in<lb/>
deep thought, and until he made his request to Gen.<lb/>
Wood I did not know whether he would do it-<lb/>
It may be that he had it in mind to do it any<lb/>
way, but if so he did not tell any one<lb/>
I described this at length in an address <add>as Belroi</add> which I<lb/>
will send you with my diary, Vol. IV. I will also<lb/>
send, if I can put my hand on it, a copy of the Editorial<lb/>
Review of the Life of Gorgas which I wrote at the<lb/>
request of the Surgeon General (Ireland) and of Mrs<lb/>
Walter Reed- I put this in, as Gen Truby speaks<lb/>
of it in his letter to you of Sept. 10, of which he<lb/>
sent me a copy- Truby is right that Gorgas was<lb/>
the last man in the world who would try to filch<lb/>
any of Reed's laurels-</p>
<p>par. D I hope to be able to get down to Moran's dinner<lb/>
at the Univ. of Va. on Oct. 25 - but I am so weak on<lb/>
my legs and with such an unreliable old pump (<unclear>fibril-</unclear><lb/>
lation) that I can never be sure of my self- I do not<lb/>
think I can venture to get out to your celebration at<lb/>
Washington Pa. I had a nice letter from the President<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06284061"/>
5<lb/>
par. D cont.) of the Washington &amp; Jefferson College a few<lb/>
days ago- I hope to meet your brother and his<lb/>
wife at the Univ. Va- I had suspected that you<lb/>
had a hand in the Moran dinner-</p>
<p>Par. E- I will get off the diary by express or reg. mail<lb/>
today or tomorrow with the reprints- I have looked<lb/>
about for a photograph of myself during the<lb/>
days of the Episode but cannot find one-<lb/>
The nearest approach to it is a photo. of the<lb/>
portrait that the Cuban Nat. Board of Health had<lb/>
painted of me in 1909- Mrs Kean has this<lb/>
framed but says that I can take it out to<lb/>
send to you if you will return it with the<lb/>
diary- I am somewhat ashamed to send such<lb/>
a casual &amp; personal lot of joltings as my diary<lb/>
contains, with so little account of the great affairs<lb/>
which went on under my eyes and in which<lb/>
I was intensely interested- But it is a factual,<lb/>
not a discriptive, record and made in haste; and<lb/>
the busier I was the less I wrote- I see that during<lb/>
my terrible struggle to create &amp; run a hospital in<lb/>
the typhoid epidemic in Camp Cuba <unclear>Libes</unclear> at Jackson-<lb/>
ville, Fla. I did not make a note between Aug. 26 and<lb/>
Sept. 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1898- That period is still a nightmare to me<lb/>
but I won out and the inspection on Sept. 25 put me<lb/>
on the map with the Surgeon General (Sternberg) and was<lb/>
a turning point in my career (p. 82)<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06284062"/>
6-<lb/>
Par. E cont.) There was no panic in the army- The Chief<lb/>
Surgeon Col. later Surg. General OReilly thought<lb/>
that all the women, even the trained nurses, should<lb/>
be sent home, but the women or many of them chose<lb/>
to stay and take their chances with their husbands<lb/>
The nurses too were willing to stay, altho. I told<lb/>
those at Columbia Bks. that they would be sent to<lb/>
care for army personnel who were sick with<lb/>
y. f. even in Marianao- The soldiers knew that<lb/>
if the disease invaded the barracks they would<lb/>
be made safe by <add>quarantines and</add> ordering them into a camp <unclear>(tents)</unclear><lb/>
at a distance from the Barracks- They were forbid-<lb/>
den to leave the military reservation- Of course<lb/>
the Cuban civil population considered themselves<lb/>
immune and so had no fear of y. f.</p>
<p>Par F. I have no objection at this late date to your making<lb/>
reference to my last visit to Major <unclear>Edwards</unclear>-</p>
<p>Par G The photo of the Lazear Memorial has not arrived- Doubtless<lb/>
it will come later- I will be glad to see it- As stated above<lb/>
I do not feel able to go to the dedication, much as I would<lb/>
like to do so-</p>
<p>Par. H Dr. C. E. Finlay came to see me and told me about<lb/>
his book- I told him of the dinner to his father and Reed<lb/>
mentioned in my Belroi address- He seemed interested<lb/>
but made us comment- I know Dr Edward Angle's who<lb/>
was my neighbor on Gen. Lee St. in Quemados de Marianao-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06284063"/>
7.<lb/>
H contd) Has Angle's heterodox opinions on the location<lb/>
of Camp Lazear also? I do not recall that he had<lb/>
anything to do with the Episode-</p>
<p>Remarks on your Memorandum</p>
<p>Par 2. Truby says that Lazear was on duty in charge of<lb/>
the laboratory at Camp Columbia Hospital <unclear>where</unclear><lb/>
detailed on the Reed Y. F. Board- This agrees with<lb/>
my recollection-</p>
<p>Par. 6- The 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Army Corps went to Havana in Dec. 1898<lb/>
in many detachments and went into camps which<lb/>
they pitched west of the <unclear>Almendares</unclear> River which is<lb/>
west of Havana- Most of the units were camped<lb/>
as I recollect about Buena Vista Station on the <unclear>narrow gage</unclear><lb/>
R. R. between Havana &amp; Marianao- The last of the<lb/>
7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Army Corps Vol. regiments left Cuba on April 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>
1899- The 7 U. S. Can replaced them and camped<lb/>
where the Ciudad Militar now is and there were<lb/>
several batteries of light Artillery which were brought<lb/>
out from Havana to Camp Columbia in the spring<lb/>
Gen. Lee's <unclear>Hdqrs</unclear> moved from tents into the Toledo<lb/>
Casa on the Calzada Real on May 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1899-<lb/>
The wooden barracks were built in May &amp; June 1899<lb/>
but Gen. Lee on my advice would not allow the<lb/>
command to occupy them until satisfactory sanitary<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06284064"/>
8<lb/>
Par. 6 contd) arrangements <add>for disposal of <unclear>extra</unclear></add> were made by the Q. M. Dept-<lb/>
who had put in utterly bad arrangements, against the<lb/>
advice of the Medical Dept- They were occupied about<lb/>
July 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> 1899- The Hospital was built much earlier-<lb/>
These wooden buildings were still in use during the<lb/>
2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> Intervention and when I left there in Feb. 1909-<lb/>
The Cuban Gov. replaced them- I dont know when-</p>
<p>Par. 8. Godfrey was the Senior Medical officer at Pinar<lb/>
del Rio- I think he was a Captain in the regular<lb/>
Army &amp; he <hi>may</hi> have the Volunteer rank of major<lb/>
as I had until 1901- Cooke was an acting Asst<lb/>
Surgeon with the relative rank of 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Lieut- Major<lb/>
P. E. Lee Michie was a major &amp; the Adjt. Gen of the<lb/>
Dept- a fine, handsome, capable officer &amp; a relation<lb/>
of your sister-in-law doubtless, as he was from<lb/>
<unclear>Albemarle</unclear> Co. Va. He died in France in the World<lb/>
War at <unclear>Ronen</unclear> with rank of Brig. Gen- At Mar-<lb/>
ianao he was practically the chief of staff and<lb/>
drew up all the orders-</p>
<p>Par. 10 I do not know- I was absent from Cuba<lb/>
on sick leave from July 3 to Aug. 13- <del>1899</del> 1900-</p>
<p>Par 11. It was not the Chairman of the famous typhoid fever<lb/>
Board who died, but Dr Edw. O. Shakespeare of Phila<lb/>
the Recorder of the Board,<lb/>
a very important member- Major Walter Reed was the<lb/>
Chairman of the Board and Victor C. Vaughan of <unclear>Aun Arbor</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06284065"/>
9<lb/>
who was the third- I have just been reading <unclear>over</unclear><lb/>
the account of its work in Vaughan's delightful auto-<lb/>
biography &ldquo;A Doctor's Memories&rdquo;- Vaughan completed<lb/>
the Report after Reed's death-</p>
<p>Par. 19. Reed's purpose in visiting Gen. Wood on Oct. 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> as<lb/>
stated by him to me was to get Gen. Wood's per-<lb/>
mission to go to the U. S. to consult the Surgeon<lb/>
General- It was the latter whose approval for<lb/>
experiments on human beings he felt to be prima-<lb/>
rily necessary- If he had the intention of con-<lb/>
sulting Gen. Wood on this point he did not say<lb/>
so to me - even after my talk with him on the<lb/>
way to Havana on Oct. 12 - about asking Gen Wood's<lb/>
help- No officer under Gen. Wood's command<lb/>
could leave Cuba with<add>out</add> authority from him or from<lb/>
<del>Washin</del> the War Dept-</p>
<p>Par. 22. On Page 104 of the Senate <unclear>doc.</unclear> Yellow Fever you<lb/>
will find listed 10 Privates of the Hospital Corps- Kissinger<lb/>
and the cases VIII Jernigan to XVI <hi>Sonntag</hi>- Evidently these<lb/>
are the 9 referred to in the first par on page 71 of the <hi>Doc.</hi><lb/>
and one additional who came to the Camp later-<lb/>
Moran is not one of the H. C. privates as he was <unclear>there</unclear> an<lb/>
H. C. clerk- The immune one was I suppose Weather-<lb/>
<unclear><hi>walks</hi></unclear> who after the <hi>fomites</hi> test Dec. 21 to Jan 10 - was<lb/>
bitten by 12 mosquitos who had <unclear>fed</unclear> on case VII 22 days before-<lb/>
(see bottom of p. 102 Y. F.)<lb/>
Gen. Truby can tell you more about these men than<lb/>
I can- I do not recall that Reed told me about<lb/>
the circumstances of the volunteering of Moran and<lb/>
Kissenger- I would rely on Moran rather than Kissinger<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06284066"/>
10<lb/>
Par 22 contd) I find a notation that Weatherwalks<lb/>
refused to be bitten by two mosquitoes that had<lb/>
been infected from Kissinger 65 days before. This<lb/>
was on Feb 14, 1901 that he refused-</p>
<p>Truby can tell you how the H. C. volunteers were<lb/>
approached-</p>
<p>Par- 23 I do not know, ask Truby or Moran-</p>
<p>" 27 I do not know</p>
<p>" 29 I drove out there and saw it once I think<lb/>
I do not know what was done with the<lb/>
buildings.</p>
<p>Par. 49 I am entirely in accordance with your<lb/>
statements in this paragraph- I remember<lb/>
Dr. Juan Guiteras saying to me that Dr Finlay<lb/>
had excellent epidemiological arguments<lb/>
in favor of <del>t</del>his theory but I do not recollect<lb/>
that he claimed that he had made successful<lb/>
experimental proof of it- My account of the dinner<lb/>
given by the doctors of Havana Dec. 22<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>, 1900 to celebrate<lb/>
Reed's demonstration of Finlays theory shows that<lb/>
attitude of Guiteras at the time- It is in a letter<lb/>
I wrote to Mr Clemons of Sept. 22, 1939 and asked<lb/>
him to furnish you a photographic copy- I hope he<lb/>
did so- There is an account of it also in my Belroi address <unclear><hi>inclosed</hi></unclear></p>
<p>I have been awkward enough to cut my right fore-<lb/>
finger with a sharp knife and so Mrs. Kean has been<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06284067"/>
11<lb/>
good enough to be my <unclear>amannensis</unclear> and finish this<lb/>
Memorandum which I am most anxious to get off<lb/>
to you. I do not know the date of your address<lb/>
at Washington and Jefferson College, but imagine that<lb/>
you have not any too much time.</p>
<p>Par. 95 I am glad that you met Dr. Albertini, if he is<lb/>
the same one who was on the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Diagnosis Board with Dr. Carlos Finlay and<lb/>
General Gorgas, he is a very agreeable and capable<lb/>
man. By the way I notice that your stenographer<lb/>
spells the name of the flamboyant tree incorrectly<lb/>
in several places where it occurs. She spells the<lb/>
first syllable &ldquo;fram&rdquo; in each place, the name refers<lb/>
to the gorgeous red and yellow flowers that it bears<lb/>
in the spring.</p>
<p>Par. 100 It is certainly true that Carroll didn't take<lb/>
his experiment with the loaded mosquitoes<lb/>
seriously. This is the only possible excuse for<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06284068"/>
12<lb/>
his having <unclear>vitiated</unclear> the value of the experiment by going<lb/>
into Havana which was out of bounds, and of all<lb/>
places going to Agramonte's post mortem room. As re-<lb/>
gards the infection of Lazear, Reed told me the story of<lb/>
Lazear's having been bitten by a wild mosquito at Las Animas<lb/>
Hospital. If he had his doubts as to the truth of this<lb/>
story he did not express them to me. It was evidently<lb/>
the story he wanted generally accepted. I never heard<lb/>
any doubt of it expressed until within the last few<lb/>
years by general Truby. I never heard at what<lb/>
date the biting at Las Animas occurred and so the<lb/>
question of incubation period was not raised in my<lb/>
mind. The circumstances of the infection of X Y<lb/>
were not known to me. Agramonte's account of it<lb/>
I never heard from him or anyone else until he<lb/>
published it. I have never entirely accepted it, but<lb/>
I have no other facts to put against it. The story<lb/>
which Kissinger is said to have told that Lazear<lb/>
put a loaded mosquito on X Y in his sleep I do not<lb/>
believe a word of. Such an act would be totally<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06284069"/>
13<lb/>
inconsistent with Lazear's noble character.</p>
<p>Par.<lb/>
101-104 As to Mrs. Rodriguez-Leon's report of her father's<lb/>
(Dr. Agramonte's) report of the agreement between<lb/>
Lazear and himself I don't know what to think.<lb/>
It is all quite new to me, and I have my<lb/>
doubts. I shall be curious to learn what<lb/>
general Truby thinks of it.</p>
<p>Par. 109 <del>104</del> Quemados was the N. E. end of Mariano.<lb/>
It was simply a quarter of the town, as Georgetown<lb/>
is a district of Washington, Quemados means<lb/>
&ldquo;burned,&rdquo; and it was at some remote period a<lb/>
burned district</p>
<p>Par.<lb/>
111 &amp; 112 I cannot with any certainty locate the cases<lb/>
of yellow fever in Mariano which Reed in-<lb/>
dicates by the street numbers, <del>The bare be</del><lb/>
except 102 Real which is the only one given<lb/>
in the bare list of yellow fever cases which I<lb/>
find in my diary <add>pp 169-170</add>. At that number lived<lb/>
Private Ballentine, Company <unclear>D</unclear>, Eighth Infantry<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06284070"/>
14<lb/>
taken sick May 26, 1900. Private TEETER,<lb/>
Hosp. Corps, (my orderly), June 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>, and<lb/>
(Private?) HambuRGER, June 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.</p>
<p>No. 20 General Lee Street may have been where<lb/>
Captain Hepburn lived. He was taken sick June 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>
the day before I was. You will find a note of<lb/>
his case on page 172 of my diary. I was myself<lb/>
sick when I wrote that note. In the map<lb/>
that you sent me photo 5 portion of Cuban Army<lb/>
map 1937 you locate General Lee's Headquarters<lb/>
on Calsada Real at the head of General Lee<lb/>
Street. I think the handsome building which you<lb/>
visited with Moran and which was identified by<lb/>
Moran as the Headquarters is not located there<lb/>
but opposite the little park three blocks further<lb/>
down the Calsada, just beyond the black<lb/>
marked 86 on that map. I have sat too<lb/>
often on the portico and listened to the band<lb/>
play in this little park to be mistaken about<lb/>
that. Also every day for a <del>year</del> 5 or 6 months<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f06284071"/>
15<lb/>
I used to walk from my house No. 27 General Lee<lb/>
st. up the street to the Calsada and then along the<lb/>
Calsada to the Headquarters building. Dr. Angle's<lb/>
lived on the same block on General Lee St. with me.</p>
<p>Par. 114 Yellow Fever Ward. This was as you know<lb/>
across the railroad from Camp Columbia and as I<lb/>
recollect it further north towards La Plaza than<lb/>
you have it located in red pencil on the Cuban Army<lb/>
Map. It was composed as I recollect it partly of<lb/>
framed tents and partly of <unclear>huts</unclear> of the same size<lb/>
as <del>of</del> a hospital tent. My recollection is that <unclear>Hepburn</unclear><lb/>
and I occupied a hut, being in the same room.<lb/>
General Truby's recollection about this would however<lb/>
settle the matter. The Camp Model of Columbia<lb/>
Barracks, Quemados 1900-1901 by Y. PeREz now<lb/>
at Carlisle I recollect having examined where<lb/>
it was at the Army Medical Museum. My im-<lb/>
pression is that it gives a quite accurate idea<lb/>
of the buildings but is not entirely accurate<lb/>
as to relative distances and locations as he<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06284072"/>
16<lb/>
had to get all of his buildings on a relatively small<lb/>
area. PeRez is certainly correct about the bridge<lb/>
over the railroad.</p>
<p>Par 118 &amp; 119 These are covered by the above.</p>
<p>Par 122 I do not know that Dr. R. P. CooKE has<lb/>
ever written anything about his experiences. I never<lb/>
heard that he refused to submit to the bites of mos-<lb/>
quitos. He is now living in <unclear>Lexington</unclear>, Va. His name is<lb/>
on the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor, published in the<lb/>
back of each Army Register. Have you a copy<lb/>
of this Roll? If not you can doubtless get one<lb/>
by application to the Adjutant General, U. S. Army.</p>
<p>Par 123 As stated above Major <unclear>Michie</unclear> died at<lb/>
Ronen, about June 1918, being then a Brigadier<lb/>
General, National Army. (An able and lovable man)</p>
<p>Par 125 &amp; 126 At the time of Reed's death he was<lb/>
librarian of the great Army Medical Library<lb/>
then known as &ldquo;Library of the Surgeon General's office&rdquo;<lb/>
He probably therefore had two desks one for the<lb/>
Library and another <del>as</del> in connection with his<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f06284073"/>
17<lb/>
his work as an instructor in the Army Medical School.<lb/>
I imagine both were examined for papers connected with<lb/>
the Yellow Fever work. There was however I think no<lb/>
formal investigation. It was probably assumed that they<lb/>
would turn up in the course of time, and certainly the<lb/>
matter did not appear to have then the importance which<lb/>
it has now.</p>
<p>Dr. Roger Post Ames died a number of years ago<lb/>
while living somewhere in Central America in the Em-<lb/>
ployment of the Public Health Service. He has a wife who is<lb/>
very much alive and who has for some years been<lb/>
making efforts through Senator Shepherd of Texas<lb/>
to have Ames' name placed on the Yellow Fever Roll<lb/>
of Honor. The Surgeon General has put on record his<lb/>
opinion that Ames did not contribute anything to<lb/>
the conclusions of the Reed Yellow Fever Commission<lb/>
and his name should <hi>not</hi> be on that Roll-<lb/>
Although like many others he did good service in<lb/>
the care of the yellow fever sick. In this opinion<lb/>
I entirely concuR, although he took good care of<lb/>
me in my illness.</p>
<p>I hope that this long memorandum may arrive<lb/>
in time to assist you in the preparation of your<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f06284074"/>
18<lb/>
address. You can send it to General Truby<lb/>
if you wish to have his opinion on it or any<lb/>
part of it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours</salute>
<seg>
P. S. I think it would be tactful and just for as<lb/>
in all our writing to allude to the mosquito theory<lb/>
as <hi>the Findlay theory</hi> (just as the Cubans do) which<lb/>
was <hi>proved</hi> by the Reed commission- So we<lb/>
should applaud the marking by them, with a<lb/>
monument, of the place where Lazear died, but<lb/>
should get the <hi>inscription</hi> changed to show<lb/>
that fact- Then the site of Camp Lazear,<lb/>
which you have correctly located, should be<lb/>
fittingly marked to show that it is the site of<lb/>
Camp Lazear where the Reed Commission<lb/>
demonstrated the truth of the Finlay theory of<lb/>
the transmission of yellow fever by the mosquito<lb/>
<hi>Aedes Egypti</hi>- Sept. 20 I will now pack up this<lb/>
M S S &amp; the diary and send them by Express.<lb/>
Please return the letter as soon as you <hi>conveniently</hi><lb/>
can- Mrs Kean is much disturbed at my letting<lb/>
it go out of the house-<lb/>
J. R. K.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
