<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06305001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Testimony of John R. Bullard, recorded by Philip Showalter Hench, April 16, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06305001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-04-16</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Louise Young</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-04-16">April 16, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06305001</idno>
<title>Testimony of John R. Bullard, recorded by Philip Showalter Hench, April 16, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Bullard reports about his experiences in Cuba during the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-04-16">
<head>Testimony of John R. Bullard, recorded by Philip Showalter Hench, April 16, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06305001"/>
<p>EXPERIENCES OF MR. JOHN R. BULLARD IN HAVANA, 1901</p>
<p>IN CONNECTION WITH THE U.S. ARMY YELLOW FEVER BOARD AND EXPERIMENTAL YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>(As told by Mr. Bullard to Dr. P. S. Hench in St. Augustine, April 16, 1941.<lb/>
To be corrected and amplified by Mr. Bullard, July, 1941.)</p>
<p><hi>Foreword:</hi> &ldquo;Mr. John R. Bullard, native of Massachusetts, a graduate<lb/>
of Harvard University where he was a distinguished athlete, and engaged in farming<lb/>
in Cuba, volunteered and was infected with yellow fever by the injection of blood.<lb/>
He became sick October 23, 1901 "(From Senate Doc. 822, p. 28). For the official<lb/>
record of Mr. Bullard's case see article &ldquo;The Etiology of Yellow Fever--A Supple-<lb/>
mental Note&rdquo; by Reed and Carroll originally published in American Medicine, <hi>3</hi>:<lb/>
301-305; Feb. 22, 1902; also published in Senate Doc. 822, Chapt. 7, p. 156 (case<lb/>
IX--J.R.B.) and pp. 158-159 (Case X--erroneously labelled case of J.M.B. instead<lb/>
of J.R.B.). On October 15, 1901, Bullard was given a subcutaneous injection of<lb/>
infected serum filtrate. A transient febrile reaction occurred on October 19<lb/>
but no yellow fever developed. On October 22, 1901, he was given a subcutaneous<lb/>
injection of infected blood and on October 23 developed experimental yellow fever.</p>
<p>Mr. Bullard never met Walter Reed; the latter had left Cuba <del>in</del><add>on</add> February 9,<lb/>
<del>or March</del>, 1901. Carroll returned to Havana October, 1901 to do some supplementary<lb/>
experiments. Since Carroll was still acting as a member of the U. S. Army Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board the work done by Carroll (including the experiments on Bullard) was<lb/>
reported with Reed as coming from the board. (Comment of P.S.H.--Why wasn't<lb/>
Agramonte's name listed as co-author?) Hence Bullard's case was officially among<lb/>
those studied by the board and he was therefore eligible for the honors (medal<lb/>
and annuity) later voted by Congress. However, since his case belongs to Carroll's<lb/>
late series (October, 1901) Bullard's name (and that of the others of Carroll's<lb/>
October, 1901 series) is often not listed by writers who only consider the cases<lb/>
of the fall of 1900 and the spring of 1901. P.S.H.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06305002"/>
<p>Hench--2--ds</p>
<p><hi>Mr. Bullard's own story</hi>(to be corrected and amplified by him).</p>
<p>I was born at Dedham, Massachusetts, July 5, 1872. In 1894 when I<lb/>
went to Harvard my family lived in Boston. I was a member of the Harvard crews<lb/>
of 1894, 1895 and 1896, being captain in 1895 and 1896. (The only other Harvard<lb/>
crewman who ever became captain for two years was my younger brother,<lb/>
who was captain in and .) I graduated from Harvard academic (?) course<lb/>
in 1896 and that fall entered Harvard Law School but did not enjoy my studies<lb/>
and left law school after two months. I met a man in Boston who offered me a<lb/>
job in Mexico on a coffee plantation. I worked there from to</p>
<p>But after 6 months in Mexico I tired of the life and work and<lb/>
took a steamer for Boston via Havana. Enroute to Havana I became very ill and<lb/>
when my boat entered the harbor of Havana the physician of the port who was none<lb/>
other than &ldquo;dear old Dr. Carlos Finlay&rdquo; (this was in 1897) wanted me to disembark<lb/>
and enter a hospital in Havana. But I was so anxious to get home that I refused<lb/>
and stayed aboard only after assuming full responsibility in case I should die<lb/>
enroute to Boston. Thereafter I was sick most of the time for three years of what<lb/>
was found in 1899 to be amebic dysentery. During these three years (1897-1899)<lb/>
I lived part time in Boston, part time in Bermuda where I ran a farm of potatoes<lb/>
and lilies. I was cured in the spring of 1899. About that time my father, a<lb/>
Boston lawyer, died.</p>
<p>In the fall of 1901 I felt I couldn't stand Boston anymore as I was<lb/>
fed up with my life there and distracted by personal grief, so I decided to go<lb/>
to Cuba, buy a farm and settle down permanently there. I landed in Cuba September<lb/>
8, 1901, a few days after the assassination of President McKinley. On arriving in<lb/>
Havana I went to visit Major Jefferson R. Kean who with Mrs. Kean was living with<lb/>
their two children in the &ldquo;officers row&rdquo; of houses at Columbia Barracks, Quemados,<lb/>
Cuba. I had known the Major and his wife (the first Mrs. Kean) who had been Louise<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06305003"/>
Hench--3--ds<lb/>
Young, the daughter of my mother's first cousin. Major Kean had met Miss Young<lb/>
at St. Augustine. Major and Mrs. Kean invited me to live at their home until I<lb/>
should start out to hunt for a farm to purchase. After a very few days I set out<lb/>
and while hunting for a farm in Artemisa in the province of Pinar del Rio, I de-<lb/>
veloped malaria about September 18, 1901. I returned to the home of Major Kean<lb/>
while I was ill of malaria. Dr. (Major) Kean had Dr. Carroll see me and it was de-<lb/>
cided that I had probably gotten my malaria by exposure while on a house party in<lb/>
Cape Cod just prior to leaving for Havana. (Comment--Isn't that a long incubation<lb/>
period?)</p>
<p>While convalescing from my malaria at Major Kean's home I frequently was<lb/>
present when Kean and Carroll, the latter a constant visitor at the Kean house,<lb/>
discussed Carroll's yellow fever experiments. In the evenings Carroll often stopped<lb/>
in to discuss his cases of experimental yellow fever. Having become somewhat fam-<lb/>
iliar with Dr. Carroll's work I decided to get an immunizing dose of yellow fever<lb/>
from Dr. Carroll so that I could stay in Cuba without further interruption of my<lb/>
career. I had already changed occupations and habitations several times and was<lb/>
determined to make a real go of it this time in Cuba. Volunteering to Dr. Carroll<lb/>
for experimental yellow fever was, I can assure you, a cold blooded business proposi-<lb/>
tion. There were no heroics in it as far as I was concerned. Although the recent<lb/>
experiments of Reed, Carroll and their associates had strongly incriminated the<lb/>
mosquito as the cause of yellow fever nobody yet know at that time (October, 1901)<lb/>
that yellow fever would really be eradicated from Cuba; I suspected that I would<lb/>
probably get it spontaneously anyhow, so I decided I'd rather have it under favorable<lb/>
circumstances via Carroll's &ldquo;immunizing dose&rdquo;.</p>
<p>But I had a hard time persuading Dr. Carroll to use me. After he turned<lb/>
me down several times (Mr. Bullard, please amplify) one evening Dr. Carroll turned<lb/>
to Major Kean and said, &ldquo;What do you suppose this young bum wants? He wants us to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06305004"/>
Hench--4--ds<lb/>
experiment on him so he'll have an immunizing dose of yellow fever.&rdquo; Thereupon<lb/>
Major Kean &ldquo;gave me hell&rdquo; telling me he thought I was foolish (Mr. Bullard, why?<lb/>
please amplify). But Dr. Carroll finally agreed to take me on. So on October 15,<lb/>
1901 I went to the &ldquo;General Wood Laboratory&rdquo; on Calzada de la Re<del>m</del><add>in</add> a in Havana.<lb/>
This was a government laboratory where Carroll was raising his mosquitoes at that<lb/>
time. There I met two army privates, Paul Hamann and Albert W. Covington who had<lb/>
also volunteered for Dr. Carroll's experiments. We three men sat in a row while<lb/>
Dr. Carroll injected us with infected serum under our shoulder blades.</p>
<p>(Mr. Bullard, please note a discrepancy here between your story and the<lb/>
official record. You infer that all three of you received your injections at the<lb/>
same time, i.e. almost simultaneously the same hour. But the record (Senate Doc.<lb/>
822, p. 156,) says Hamann was injected 11 A.M. October 15, Covington at 11:05 A.M.<lb/>
October 15 and yourself at 2:30 <hi>P.M.</hi> that day. Perhaps the three of you sat to-<lb/>
gether in an outer office; they were injected in the morning but for some reason<lb/>
your injection was postponed till after lunch. How about this?)</p>
<p>After receiving their injections Hamann and Covington returned to their<lb/>
stations (I suppose you mean at Camp Columbia). After receiving my injection I<lb/>
went at once (how? By yourself, by train or in an ambulance?) out to one of the<lb/>
yellow fever wards at Columbia Barracks. I was quarantined in one of the little<lb/>
buildings which made up these wards. My recollection is that in October, 1901<lb/>
these yellow fever wards consisted of about six small shacks; some held only two<lb/>
beds, others held several beds. Each shack had a complicated double entrance,<lb/>
double doors protected by permanent mosquito netting. These shacks were beside<lb/>
the La Playa Railroad track. When I was there I do not believe there were any tents<lb/>
used for yellow fever cases. I remained in one of these little buildings (two beds<lb/>
or more?) night and day. Dr. Carroll came to see me twice a day, and Major Kean<lb/>
often called. About the third day of my quarantine (i.e. about October 18) [the<lb/>
records say it was October 19] I heard an ambulance pull up outside. I went out<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06305005"/>
Hench--5--ds<lb/>
to see if I could help the orderly and there I found that the occupants of the<lb/>
ambulance were none other than my two fellow volunteers, Hamann and Covington,<lb/>
who had come down with yellow fever! This gave me quite &ldquo;a kick&rdquo;. I admit I felt<lb/>
rather excited, and promptly developed a rapid pulse and a mild fever. But these<lb/>
soon passed off. Obviously I didn't have yellow fever although I don't know yet<lb/>
why they got it and I did not.</p>
<p>The next few days I remained under quarantine and kept myself occupied<lb/>
by helping the orderlies at the yellow fever shacks. Major Kean decided I must be<lb/>
a natural immune and advised me to return to his house but I said, &ldquo;Hell, no!<lb/>
I'm only half way through this.&rdquo; So I persuaded Dr. Carroll to give me an in-<lb/>
jection of blood from Hamann. (Covington's blood test was such that Dr. Carroll<lb/>
wouldn't give me any of Covington's blood.) I had this injection on October 22.<lb/>
Next day I came down with yellow fever. I had a &ldquo;mild case&rdquo; and wasn't officially<lb/>
very sick but it was bad enough. I had headaches, pains and tenderness in my<lb/>
abdomen, mild jaundice and albuminuria. I was cared for in the same &ldquo;yellow fever<lb/>
ward&rdquo;, one of the several small wooden buildings I have mentioned as being beside<lb/>
the La Playa railroad track. I recall the little old bridge across this track<lb/>
for I crossed it (when, Mr. Bullard?).</p>
<p>On the third day of my illness the Havana Yellow Fever Board came out<lb/>
to see me. It included Drs. Agramonte and Finlay. I remember Dr. Finlay best<lb/>
because of the following incident. When Dr. Finlay came into the room and saw me<lb/>
he promptly said, &ldquo;I have seen you before&rdquo; and then Finlay recalled that <del>he</del> I<lb/>
(Bullard) was the young fellow whom he had seen four years before sick on a boat<lb/>
in Havana harbor!</p>
<p>After the acute phase of my illness I returned to Major Kean's house<lb/>
to recuperate for a few days and then returned to Artemesa in my search for a<lb/>
farm. There I bought a farm and raised tobacco for three and a half years. Then<lb/>
in 1905 I went into the real estate business with offices in Havana till 1909<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06305006"/>
Hench--6--ds<lb/>
when with a partner I bought a sugar plantation &ldquo;Central Armonia Bolondron&rdquo; in<lb/>
Matanzas Province. In 1911 I entered the employ of the Cuba Company, a large<lb/>
sugar company of which I became Vice President in 1924. I left Cuba in 1928 because<lb/>
of ill health and have not returned since. I have retired from business and have<lb/>
lived in St. Augustine since</p>
<p>(In 1929-1930 Mr. Bullard was a patient for several months at the Mayo<lb/>
Clinic. He stayed at the Kahler, met Mr. Kahler, my wife's father, and was enter-<lb/>
tained a couple of times in Mr. Kahler's home. Mr. Bullard recalls meeting me in<lb/>
Rochester and recognized me at once when I visited him in St. Augustine on<lb/>
April 16, 1941. - P.S.H.)</p>
<p><hi>Addenda.</hi> Mr. Bullard never saw Camp Lazear nor Military Hospital No. 1.<lb/>
He only visited Las Animas Hospital once (for what reason?). He knew nothing as to<lb/>
whether Moran or Kissinger volunteered first. He had never met Miss Maas. He<lb/>
did not know exactly where Lazear died but <hi>he distinctly remembered that the first<lb/>
Mrs. Kean told him that she and others were convinced that Lazear had been bitten<lb/>
on purpose.</hi> Bullard's case belongs to Carroll's late series (October, 1901) and<lb/>
was not listed in Guiteras' series. Bullard did not know personally any of those<lb/>
who participated in the earlier experiments of Lazear, Reed, Carroll or Agramonte.<lb/>
He stated that the brief data about him in the article &ldquo;Honor the Memory of Heroes...&rdquo;<lb/>
etc. (page 6) was correct. He had a few clippings re three or four volunteers who<lb/>
had died and very kindly gave them to me. He had no other data except the early<lb/>
photographs of himself taken in 1895 (?) and in 1901, copies of which he kindly<lb/>
gave me.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
