<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06307117">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 23, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06307117</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-12-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Roper, Laura Wood</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Dominquez, Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Havana, Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-12-23">December 23, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06307117</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 23, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench has received microfilm of the notebook found at the New York Academy of Medicine and has recognized Lazear's and Reed's handwriting. The contents include case reports of sick soldiers, electrozone experiment notes, observations of non-experimental and experimental yellow fever cases, and notes about mosquitoes. The notebook shows that Lazear was working with mosquitoes even before the Yellow Fever Board was created.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-12-23">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 23, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06307117"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1941-12-23">December 23, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Truby and General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I had hoped to write you many days ago to send you further data on the<lb/>
yellow fever note book found by Miss Wood in the New York Academy of Medicine. But<lb/>
Dr. Malloch, the librarian, didn't pay too much attention to my original letter and<lb/>
wasn't very prompt even after I wrote him airmail and a telegram. And here it is<lb/>
Christmas time, so let me first send you both my most sincere and heartfelt greetings<lb/>
and my earnest wish for your continued health and happiness. I count it a very real<lb/>
privilege to know you.</p>
<p>I wrote Malloch asking him to lend the notebook to our library as an<lb/>
inter-library loan, telling him I'd do all I could to study the book in detail and<lb/>
identify not only the handwritings therein but also try to explain its contents. I<lb/>
wanted to photostate it here and send you and others full copies for your leisurely<lb/>
perusal. But Malloch refused to send it and I can't say that I blame him. Then I<lb/>
asked how much a photostat would cost. He replied, &ldquo;$24.00&rdquo;. At the moment that<lb/>
seems like a lot so I ordered a complete microfilm instead. They finally sent <lb/>
one about 10 days ago but when I eagerly tried to examine it in our library's viewer<lb/>
I found every other page had been photographed out of focus! Very sloppy work--one<lb/>
couldn't even read it. We tried two viewers and our photographic department tried to<lb/>
blow up the bad pages to see if they would be clear enough to read but they weren't.</p>
<p>More correspondence with Malloch and finally I have a clear microfilm of<lb/>
the complete notebook. It is very inconvenient to study and I am going to try to make<lb/>
photoprints from it--these would be cheaper than the price of photostats. Be assured<lb/>
that when I get a readable copy I will send it to each of you for your study and comments.</p>
<p>While all this correspondence with Malloch was going on I made a copy of<lb/>
4 pages which Miss Wood had had photostated and which she kindly sent me (I am sending<lb/>
her a carbon of this letter; I'm sure you won't mind). I recognized Lazear's hand-<lb/>
writing at once as I have copies of it sent me by Mrs. Lazear. In her letters which<lb/>
she sent me are certain individual words identical in writing style to those in the<lb/>
photostats of Miss Wood. Especially distinctive is his way of writing the letter &ldquo;r&rdquo;.<lb/>
But for the sake of complete authenticity I airmailed these four pages to Mrs. Lazear<lb/>
and asked if she could identify her husband's handwriting absolutely and, if so, would<lb/>
she certify to that in her own handwriting on each page. She was much interested as<lb/>
you can imagine and wrote me &ldquo;There is not the slightest doubt in my mind but that the<lb/>
writing......is that of my husband.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having gotten nowhere with Malloch I sent him (to keep) one of these en-<lb/>
dorsed pages, thinking he'd appreciate it enough to reconsider and perhaps lend me the<lb/>
book. But (as I was afraid it might) this made the book all the more valuable and he<lb/>
still refused.m When I examined the out-of-focus microfilm I recognized Reed's hand-<lb/>
writing continuing the notes where Lazear's left off but thought that some later pages<lb/>
were written by still another person. Viewing the clear microfilm I now see that<lb/>
(with the exception of 2 or 3 inserts) the writing is entirely that of Lazear, then<lb/>
of Reed and in the back of the book, that of Lazear again. A few pages were written<lb/>
hastily by Reed and his handwriting looked different but it is undoubtedly that of Reed.</p>
<p>I won't attempt to give you a complete account of the contents but <del>t</del> here<lb/>
is a brief synopsis:</p>
<p>Pages 7 - 34: Brief handwritten case reports by Lazear concerning various<lb/>
sick soldiers; about 10 or 12 case reports in all--cases of &ldquo;diarrhea&rdquo;, typhoid, chanore,<lb/>
gonorrheal arthritis, tonsillitis, amebic abscess (necropsy) etc; dates Mar. 2 to May<lb/>
12, 1900.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06307118"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Pp. 12-23: Interrupting the above case reports are some notes on<lb/>
various experiments with electrozone started by Lazear Mar. 14, 1900.</p>
<p>Pp. 37-143 are also in Lazear's handwriting (many single pages not written<lb/>
on). The notes refer to Lazear's early observations in yellow fever cases, the first<lb/>
one being that of King May 23, 1900 (see photostat enclosed). Then the cases of Sher-<lb/>
wood, Hamburger, Jacob Caesar (autopsy), Lutig who had a &ldquo;restaurant near the railroad<lb/>
by the yellow fever wards&rdquo; and who died at Marianao hospital June 17, 1900; notes<lb/>
on blood cultures and counts from these cases; a note that he caught "eight well filled<lb/>
brown culices from Colby's mosquito net July 8 and dissected them July 10--&ldquo;but nothing<lb/>
abnormal found&rdquo;. (Lazear was hunting for changes in them analogous to those in malarial<lb/>
mosquitoes); notes re &ldquo;mosquitoes sent to Mr. Howard&rdquo; which were caught at the Barracks,<lb/>
at Quemados, at Marianao, at Pinar del Rio, at Havana, etc. (Apparently Lazear was<lb/>
well embarked on his mosquito-yellow fever studies as early as May 23, 1900). There are<lb/>
notes regarding several patients with yellow fever (spontaneous) at Las Animas Hospital<lb/>
in August, patients who were bitten by Lazear's mosquitoes, also blood counts on the<lb/>
patients. Their names are given but unfortunately in this notebook Lazear doesn't have<lb/>
the names of the unidentified seven early volunteers who were inoculated with Pinto and<lb/>
Lazear between August 11 and 25. It was a great disappointment to me not to find these<lb/>
names.</p>
<p>Lazear's last note was written September 13 (was this the last day he was<lb/>
able to work?) and concerns notes on &ldquo;guinea pig No. 1 - red&rdquo; bitten by a mosquito. No<lb/>
results were noted.</p>
<p>On page 42 there is pasted an insert written in somebody' else's handwriting<lb/>
as follows:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Folk, A. M. Feb. 3rd. A. O - casts; 1 coarse gr. and few fragments.</item>
<item>Sonntag, Feb. 3. A.M. A. O</item>
<item>West, 7 A.M. Feb. 3. A. O</item>
</list></p>
<p>The dates obviously refer to Feb. 3, 1901, not 1900 and the notes I<lb/>
suspect refer to urine analyses. Does the A. O simply mean albumen negative?</p>
<p>Pages 105-143 (many pages not written on) are in Reed's handwriting. I<lb/>
am absolutely sure of this, and briefly describe 14 or 15 of the cases of experimental<lb/>
yellow fever from the case of Kissinger to that of West (Jan. 31 - Feb. 2). Some of the<lb/>
errors in spelling of names and dates and hours of inoculation (contradictions I noted<lb/>
in the Senate Document) can be traced to these notes of Reed, for in several places<lb/>
he was uncertain of the spelling of <hi>Kissenger</hi>, <hi>Olsen</hi>, Hanberry and Handbury, Sonntagg,<lb/>
<hi>Weatherwalk</hi>, etc.; also a couple of times he corrected himself writing over some date<lb/>
and hour of inoculation. On page 129 is the case of Springer bitten by a 16 day<lb/>
<hi>pungens</hi> with negative results and on p. 141 notes on the <hi>urine of Dr. Ames from Jan. 27<lb/>
to Feb.</hi> 1. (Was Ames sick then?)</p>
<p>Ames Y.F.</p>
<p>Pages 170 to 197 are again in Lazear's handwriting and are his notes on<lb/>
45 cases of malaria, mostly tertian, dated Feb. 19 to Aug. 17, 1900.</p>
<p>On page 199 are three inserts pasted on the page. One is in Reed's hand-<lb/>
writing (I believe) as follows:<lb/>
S O #122 Par. 34 A.G.O. Wash. May 24, 1900<lb/>
Dr. Reed<lb/>
Oct. 1-13 Camp Columbia<lb/>
Oct. 14-20 enroute to U. S.<lb/>
Feb. 9, 1901 left Havana<lb/>
Date Agramonte was relieved from the board.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06307119"/>
<p>- 3 -</p>
<p>(Below this is written a letter which looks like a double M, like<lb/>
this <del>MM</del><add>Mm</add>; then &ldquo;M and P Rolls&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Obviously these are Reed's notes to himself re the Sternberg order and<lb/>
Reed's whereabouts on certain dates. Does it infer that Agramonte was discharged<lb/>
from the board Feb. 9, 1901? What does &ldquo;M. and P. Rolls&rdquo; mean?</p>
<p>On page 198 is an insert--somebody's pulse and temperature record Jan.<lb/>
21-24; and on page 200 a record of the pulse and temperature of <hi>Weatherwalks</hi> Jan. 31-<lb/>
Feb. 3. I have not identified the handwriting.</p>
<p>In summary - this is a very historical notebook and I'll bet the Army<lb/>
Museum would like to know how Malloch got it. Its importance lies in the fact that<lb/>
it shows how early Lazear began his mosquito work, weeks before the Board got together<lb/>
in Havana and <hi>even before May 24</hi> when Sternberg's order created the board. But it<lb/>
doesn't give us the answers to many questions that Lazear's other and still-lost<lb/>
notebook might answer.</p>
<p>Gen. Truby, I was glad to get the photos of the model; they aren't too<lb/>
good as photographs but are much more accurate in showing the layout of the hospital.<lb/>
Too bad the one wasn't taken closer! Have you received this week a 31 page article<lb/>
by Dominguez re &ldquo;The action of the physicians of the American army in <hi>proving</hi> the<lb/>
<hi>doctrine</hi> of Finlay (comprobacion de las doctrinas). The choice of words is interesting.<lb/>
He shows a photograph of the banquet (menu card) to Dr. Finlay at Delmonicos Dec. 22,<lb/>
1900. In Havana there was much debate as to where this banquet was held.</p>
<p>In our library in the clinic I have set up an exhibit, many photographs,<lb/>
the 2 oil sketches of the Cuban version which Cornwell so kindly sent me, also the<lb/>
contract which General Kean so graciously gave me. I'll try to photograph the setup<lb/>
for you. The library had certain labels and notes printed--see the enclosed. Also<lb/>
to go with it the Proceedings printed the <hi>full version</hi> of my Cleveland talk (see<lb/>
enclosed). I'll send you each reprints if you wish more.</p>
<p>By separate post I am sending to Gen. Truby the two maps which at long<lb/>
last I finally got from Washington.</p>
<p>I have more to write--about a plan of Mr. Peabody to raise money to<lb/>
memorialize Camp Lazear in <hi>honor of two of his college classmates</hi> at Dartmouth. An<lb/>
embarrassing plan because Camp Lazear <hi>cannot</hi> be dedicated to any outsider no matter<lb/>
who puts up the money. Nobody can <hi>dedicate</hi> Camp Lazear; it is already and forever<lb/>
dedicated, by virtue of its own history, to Finlay, Lazear, Reed, et al. So I'll<lb/>
have to turn down, diplomatically, some real financial help, I fear. But all for<lb/>
now or this won't reach you Christmas.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Every good wish.</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
My kindest regards to<lb/>
Mrs. Kean. I expect<lb/>
to stop in Washington<lb/>
Jan 13-14.<lb/>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
