<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06306111">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 1, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06306111</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-10-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Roper, Laura Wood</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Richmond (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-10-01">October 1, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06306111</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 1, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench enjoys the second draft of Truby's manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-10-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 1, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06306111"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-10-01">October 1, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am busy trying to finish our Rheumatism Review, which occupies almost<lb/>
every spare moment. Therefore, I am late in answering your last letter (I am also<lb/>
again tardy in answering General Truby!). Let me first answer your letter of Sep-<lb/>
tember 19.</p>
<p>Thank you very much for getting me straight on the whereabouts of Dr.<lb/>
Henry Rose Carter. I am much disturbed about your request for me to return the<lb/>
original print of your portrait still hanging in Havana. You say that Mrs. Kean<lb/>
does not believe I returned it in the little steel box with the diary. I hate<lb/>
very much to disagree with her but I remember your telling me when you sent it to<lb/>
me that she had rather regreted your removing it from the safe in your home, and I<lb/>
was particularly careful of it. I am as positive as one can be that I returned it<lb/>
in the little box in a regular, small sized buff colored envelope. I distinctly<lb/>
remember checking that over a couple of times before mailing it. In the envelope<lb/>
were not only the original but also a copy of the original which I had had made here.<lb/>
I have made it a policy when copying photographs loaned to me not only to return the<lb/>
original but to return a copy as an expression of my appreciation and so that the<lb/>
lender might hereafter not have to send out an original for further requests. It<lb/>
disturbs me greatly that you cannot lay your hands on this. I hate to ask you to<lb/>
look through your desk again but I am practically positive that you will find it.<lb/>
Perhaps it was stuck in the diary itself. However, even if you can't find it, the<lb/>
loss may not be too great as I have the film which is practically as good as your<lb/>
<add>C 81740</add> own. It is listed in our Mayo Clinic photographic file as c<add>8</add>1740, so that you and<lb/>
your relatives can always find it here and have copies made. I am sending not a<lb/>
very good copy of this print but just to refresh your memory. If you really cannot<lb/>
find your original I shall be very glad to have a nice enlargement of this photograph<lb/>
made on special paper and send it to you with my sincerest regrets and best wishes.<lb/>
To fortify myself I reviewed my correspondence as of the time I sent you the box<lb/>
with the diary and photographs. At that time, my correspondence says that I also<lb/>
returned two reprints you loaned me and four photostatic copies of pages from your<lb/>
diary. These were all sent together and later you returned to me the photostatic<lb/>
copies of the diary with some corrections in your own handwriting. These were re-<lb/>
ceived at your home while you were in Richmond. They were sent about October 21, 1940.<lb/>
You were unable to acknowledge their receipt until your letter of November 27 as you<lb/>
had been away and on your return were ill for a few days.</p>
<p>I am so pleased with the little snapshot I took of you and General<lb/>
Ireland that I am sending you by separate post one for you to keep, one for General<lb/>
Ireland to keep and one which I shall be very proud to have returned to me with the<lb/>
signatures of yourself and General Ireland. In order to save you bother after your<lb/>
autograph it, I am enclosing two labels, one which you can use to send it to General<lb/>
Ireland and one which he in turn can use to return the photograph to me. I will be<lb/>
very proud to have this.</p>
<p>Just yesterday I received the second draft of General Truby's autobio-<lb/>
graphy. What a tremendous improvement it is on the first one. I had a rather bad<lb/>
cold with a sinusitis and was feeling rather weary. I picked it up at 10 P.M. to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06306112"/>
General J. R. Kean &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; October 1, 1941<lb/>
read a few pages. It was so fascinating that I read it all, finishing it at a<lb/>
quarter of 3 A.M., amid the scoldings of my wife! I have made a few suggestions<lb/>
for corrections and I think have been able to give him a couple of dates that he<lb/>
wanted: the approximate date of the visit of Durham and Myers as given in one of<lb/>
Reed's letters to his wife. I sincerely hope that his manuscript can be published<lb/>
by the Surgeon General's office. I don't know that they publish such things but<lb/>
it simply must not be lost. It should be printed even if it has to be privately<lb/>
printed and I for one will be glad to make a contribution to see that it is published.</p>
<p>Now for your letter of September 26. I will send to General Truby rather<lb/>
than to you the items which you sent to me. I am having them copied and they should<lb/>
go to General Truby this week. I was able to get a copy of the Military Surgeon<lb/>
which has General Winter's article in it.</p>
<p>I have had a couple of very appreciative letters from Miss Wood and so<lb/>
far as correspondence is concerned she seems to be a very nice woman.</p>
<p>I am also sending you by separate post, a copy of Hygeia, with my yellow<lb/>
fever article in it. Shortly I will have a voluminous number of reprints and will<lb/>
be glad to send you any number you wish, even as many as twenty or twenty-five.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
