<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06306037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 22, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06306037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-22">August 22, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06306037</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 22, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench argues that Ames would be a good choice to include in the yellow fever painting.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-22">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 22, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06306037"/>
<opener>
Mr. Kellogg Please return to<lb/>
J. R. Kean when you have no<lb/>
further use for this &amp; Gen<lb/>
Trubys letter<lb/>
JRK<lb/>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-22">August 22, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am glad to have your suggestions that if the Wyeth people are willing,<lb/>
the name of either Folk or Hanberry should be given to the soldier behind Moran<lb/>
in the group on the right. I am glad you corrected me. I meant of course the<lb/>
Spanish immigrants, not the Cuban volunteers and I gather that you do not think<lb/>
the one Spanish immigrant in the picture should be named but should be nameless<lb/>
and represent the group. I note your comments against specifically naming Carter<lb/>
or Ames in the group, but this still leaves unfinished the matter of naming the<lb/>
second man on the upper right (the one sitting on the porch rail). Kellogg tells<lb/>
me that Dr. Cooke is the other of these two men, that is, the officer with the<lb/>
white uniform. The other unnamed person will have to be an officer as he has an<lb/>
officer's insignia on and Cornwell definitely separated the privates from the<lb/>
officers. Must we leave this man unnamed? Since this picture will, as time<lb/>
passes, assume more and more historical significance, it seems a shame to have<lb/>
an anonymous figure therein. I agree that the inclusion of Carter would be a<lb/>
considerable stretch of the imagination. It was my thought that Dr. Ames might<lb/>
be included as a recognition of his obviously excellent care of those who came<lb/>
down with experimental yellow fever and also because he was officially in imme-<lb/>
diate charge of Camp Lazear or at least Reed says so on the top of page 71, Senate<lb/>
Document. (However, Moran disputes this, saying he never saw Ames at Camp Lazear<lb/>
while he was there.) He, I should believe, belongs in the group as much as Gen-<lb/>
eral Truby who was inserted as a matter of convenience and courtesy because he<lb/>
was at least temporary commanding officer in the hospital, because he found<lb/>
Lazear's important notebook and because he has been so helpful all along.</p>
<p>If you do not agree that Ames' name should be attached to the figure be-<lb/>
side Dr. Cooke, can you suggest some other officer? Unfortunately, according to<lb/>
the telephone conversation which I had with Kellogg a few days ago, he must have<lb/>
this information on Monday. Would it be possible for you to write to him directly,<lb/>
sending me a carbon copy of your letter by writing in pencil and using the enclosed<lb/>
carbon paper? You remember Mr. Kellogg's address is 257 Cornelison Avenue, Jersey<lb/>
City, N. J. I enclose an airmail special delivery for your reply to me. Do you<lb/>
think Dr. Pinto, having received a negative inoculation, deserves to be in more<lb/>
than Dr. Ames?</p>
<p>I realize that I have scandalously neglected General Truby. I have been<lb/>
so very busy that my yellow fever researches have been neglected. I intend to<lb/>
write him very shortly, telling him many things that I have not been able to tell<lb/>
him yet. Rather than being disturbed by his frank comments on the Hemmeter photo-<lb/>
stats, I was completely delighted. He seems to be a wonderful gentleman and I hope<lb/>
to visit him on my vacation in California next February. In fact, I am choosing<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06306038"/>
General Kean&nbsp;&nbsp;- 2-&nbsp;&nbsp;August 22, 1941<lb/>
<lb/>
a California vacation specifically to meet him and Mrs. Lazear.</p>
<p>Thank you so much for your comments on the Bullard article. I still<lb/>
have more information to send you which I will do when I have more time. Please<lb/>
keep the list of the data I found in the National Archives.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip S Hench</signed>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. Since dictating this this morning, I have just received the<lb/>
enclosed letter from General Truby. He favors naming Ames. Note that the figure<lb/>
we are naming has an officer's coat, apparently with a lieutenant's insignia. I<lb/>
believe Ames was a contract surgeon with a rank of acting assistant surgeon.<lb/>
Would the uniform portrayed be contradictory to Ames' position? The uniform of<lb/>
the figure we are naming does not seem to differ materially from that of Lazear<lb/>
who was also a contract surgeon. It is of course too late to redo the face after<lb/>
a photograph of Ames but I don't suppose his family would worry too much over<lb/>
that if he had the honor of being named.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
