<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06306067">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 3, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06306067</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-09-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Hendrick, Burton Jesse</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-09-03">September 3, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06306067</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 3, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses his health problems. Hendrick, in his Gorgas biography, made misstatements and did not correct them - it was Howard who advocated the use of kerosene to combat mosquitoes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-09-03">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 3, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06306067"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Washington D. C.<lb/>
2804 N St. n.w <date value="1941-09-03">Sept. 3, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<hi>6</hi> Inclosures<lb/>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have a lot that I would like to say<lb/>
this morning if I had your good stenog-<lb/>
but I am rather rocky from a two days spell<lb/>
with the Old pump- It has now stopped its inter-<lb/>
mitting and various irregularities and is going<lb/>
steadily, but these spells leave me weak for a day<lb/>
or too- I looked up Carter yesterday and am<lb/>
sending you his own statement and his daugh-<lb/>
ter's- If I said he was in Cuba from July 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> to<lb/>
Sept. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> <add>it was in 1899</add> I was certainly mistaken <add>if I wrote 1900</add> as you see,<lb/>
from their letters- He left Havana July 23, 1900<lb/>
<hi>on account of illness</hi>, so he could not have had<lb/>
anything to do with the mosquito work. In looking<lb/>
for these letters I came across my correspondence<lb/>
with Mr. Burton J. Hendrick at that time Editor of <hi>The<lb/>
World's Work</hi> and engaged in writing his Life of Gorgas<lb/>
with Mrs. Gorgas as co-author- It was the mis statements.<lb/>
in an advance chapter of this biography <add>published in World's Work April, 1924</add> that caused me<lb/>
to write, at the request of Mrs. Reed and of the Surgeon<lb/>
General (Gen. Ireland) a letter to him correcting these errors<lb/>
which I asked him to publish in his magazine <hi>World's<lb/>
Work</hi>- He made a very unsatisfactory reply, which I<lb/>
sent to Gen. Ireland with a copy of my letter- Gen. Ireland<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06306068"/>
Ac<lb/>
K<lb/>
2<lb/>
sent the latter to the N. Y. Times &amp; they printed it with the<lb/>
reviews in the Sunday edition- Hendrick afterwards wrote<lb/>
saying he would publish it, but retracted this offer when<lb/>
I wrote him of Gen. Ireland's <add>action-</add>- This was in the spring of 1924<lb/>
and the book did not appear until 6 or 8 months later,<lb/>
but to our amazement there had been <hi>no correction</hi><lb/>
of these mis-statements- It was this letter published<lb/>
in the N. Y. Times that Dr. L. O. Howard, the eminent<lb/>
Chief of the Bureau of Entomology and a great friend<lb/>
of Walter Reed, refers to in his letter which I inclose-<lb/>
The Dr. Backeland to whom he refers is the famous chemist<lb/>
see who's who<lb/>
the inventor of Bakelite the first plastic I think- It<lb/>
was Dr. Howard that taught us to use kerosene to fight<lb/>
mosquitoes- I dont think that Gorgas knew anything<lb/>
about fighting mosquitoes <del>at</del> until this G. O. no. 6<lb/>
from Gen. Wood's Hdqrs was issued Dec. 21, 1900-<lb/>
Now dont ask me for a copy for I dont know where<lb/>
I would put my hand on one, altho. I wrote it-<lb/>
Please return this letter after taking a copy of it-<lb/>
I happened to be the Chief Surgeon at that time in place<lb/>
of Col. Havard as he went on leave to the U. S. Nov. 19<lb/>
1900 and returned Jan. 8, 1901- Why I was assigned<lb/>
to take his place instead of Gorgas I do not now<lb/>
remember if I ever knew, for Gorgas was my senior-<lb/>
Well I have not yet begun to tell you what I started<lb/>
out to write about, which is Gen. Truby's story of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06306069"/>
3<lb/>
<del>the</del> Episode of Walter Reed and Yellow Fever-<lb/>
I am delighted with it and you will be also when<lb/>
you read it- It is written in such a simple, direct<lb/>
style which I think is charming and has so many<lb/>
interesting details- I wrote him that the only thing<lb/>
I was not satisfied with was what he had to<lb/>
say about his own work- You will have to make<lb/>
up for his modesty where you write your history.<lb/>
Did he send you the other carbon copy? I hope<lb/>
so- You will find many dates and details<lb/>
that will delight you- When I began it I could<lb/>
not put it down until I finished it- I am<lb/>
going over it again carefully and will make notes<lb/>
He has many dates which my diaries do not<lb/>
contain and of course I have some that he lacks<lb/>
I am going to put in with the inclosures to this letter<lb/>
a part of a letter which came from Truby yesterday<lb/>
which I think you should read but do not quote from<lb/>
it in writing to him- The comments about the painting<lb/>
are of interest- I do not send the first two pages<lb/>
as they are about his daughter, who is expecting a<lb/>
baby in Phila, and is the apple of his eye. The baby<lb/>
arrived on the 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>- How the generations crowd along- The great<lb/>
grandfather of this baby was Col. La Garde of the Medical Corps<lb/>
of the Army &amp; a warm friend of Gen. Ireland and me-<lb/>
Please return all the inclosures after reading &amp; noting-</p>
<p>Especially Dr. Howard's letter-</p>
<p>World Work of ? 1924</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
