<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06303005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Questionnaire for an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, May 8, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06303005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriquez</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lyster, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-08">May 8, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06303005</idno>
<title>Questionnaire for an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, May 8, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench's questionnaire deals with myriad topics, including: Moran and Kissinger, locations of hospitals and living quarters, the X.Y. case, Kean's case of yellow fever, and the discovery that someone had removed all the papers from Reed's desk after his death.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1941-05-08">
<head>Questionnaire for an interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, May 8, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06303005"/>
<p>QUESTIONING OF GENERAL KEAN BY DR. HENCH<lb/>
WASHINGTON, May 8, 1941.</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<item><hi>QUESTION #2</hi> - I do not know. I am not impressed by Miss Agramonte's<lb/>
suggestion that Carroll would have been the one, for my impression is<lb/>
that he was not always with Reed. I do not recall that he was ever<lb/>
with Reed when Reed came to see me.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #3</hi> - I think it is a very evident attempt to give Carroll a<lb/>
much more important role in the work of that Commission than he really had.<lb/>
<p><hi>DR. HENCH:</hi> What do you think of Dr. Carroll's statements regarding<lb/>
the purchase of the watch for Kissinger?</p>
<p><hi>GENERAL KEAN:</hi> I have no doubt that he bought the watch. If Carroll brought<lb/>
a note, or if Reed asked me by 'phone to let Carroll have a check for<lb/>
150 or $<del>250</del>.00 I would have given it without hesitation. I am quite sure the<lb/>
money was gotten by cashing my check.</p>
<p><hi>REMINISCENCES:</hi> Lazear was interested in mosquitoes before the Commission<lb/>
came to Cuba, and about June 1st, 1900 when we were inspecting a house<lb/>
where there cases of yellow fever he explained to me the difference be-<lb/>
tween the male and female mosquitoes as they perched on the walls. I do<lb/>
not know whether or not at that time Lazear suspected the mosquito as<lb/>
the cause of yellow fever.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #8</hi> - Lyster was Mrs. Gorgas' nephew; he was old enough to have<lb/>
-1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06303006"/>
-2-<lb/>
been in Panama in 1900. He was a sergeant during the Spanish War in the<lb/>
Medical Department. He came before the Board and was given a commission<lb/>
in the Medical Corps. He became a Brig. General in the Medical Department<lb/>
about the same time I did in the World War. He was Gorgas' executive<lb/>
officer. I doubt if he was there when Lazear was bitten. It is pos-<lb/>
sible, but not probable.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #9</hi> - Major Peterson's wife was at the hospital when her husband<lb/>
died. She had the revolver in her bag, and the suicide happened in the<lb/>
nurses' quarters. This was a very pathetic case. They were a handsome,<lb/>
good looking couple, both in their thirties.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #11</hi> - I think that Lazear put the mosquito on Carroll, because<lb/>
Carroll made the complaint (given in Hemmeter's book) and I remember hear-<lb/>
ing Carroll say it, that Lazear had put a mosquito on him that had bitten<lb/>
four serious cases of yellow fever, and that he had used one on himself that<lb/>
had bitten only one case.</item>
<item>amplify</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #12</hi> - About where General Truby has his mark on your 1907 map.<lb/>
It was between the old road to La Playa and the railroad track. That is<lb/>
my recollection. I do not remember crossing the railroad track before<lb/>
coming to the cemetery.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #15</hi> - Having told you the stories about the volunteering of Moran<lb/>
and Kissinger, what is your recollection of the matter, or your impression<lb/>
of what I have told you?<lb/>
<p>-2-</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06303007"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>GENERAL KEAN</hi> - I have always accepted the story that they went together. I<lb/>
have no personal recollection of who volunteered for Reed. This was a<lb/>
matter aside from my activities. I was told about their volunteering -<lb/>
by whom, I do not remember. My plan was to get Spaniards for these ex-<lb/>
periments, but there were certain <hi>difficulties in the way, and</hi> I could<lb/>
see it was more convenient to handle the soldiers if they volunteered.<lb/>
Moran had been discharged from the service., at his own request.</p>
<p><hi>DR. HENCH</hi> - In the light of this story, what is your impression?</p>
<p><hi>GENERAL KEAN</hi> I would take Moran's story. I think he is a more reliable<lb/>
man than Kissinger. I know Kissinger personally very slightly.</p>
<p>what</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #16 -</hi> It is not my recollection. My recollection is that it was<lb/>
paid for in lieu of the money that would have been given him from the <add>Cuban</add> funds<lb/>
given by General Wood for these experiments. Moran had refused any re-<lb/>
wards; I could not give him a promotion <add>he was a civilian then?</add>, and it did not occur to me that he<lb/>
would accept a watch. It did not occur to me that he would feel slighted<lb/>
in view of the fact that he had refused any reward. My recollection is<lb/>
that it was my idea to give Kissinger the promotion and the watch. I do<lb/>
not remember whether I consulted Dr. Reed or not; probably I did. The<lb/>
promotion of Kissinger had to be made by the <hi>Division Surgeon</hi>, <add>Chief Surg of the Division of Cuba</add> Colonel<lb/>
Havard, and so I recommended Kissinger to Colonel Havard, and he made the<lb/>
presentation at the ceremony. I do not remember the details of the cere-<lb/>
mony, except that the Hospital Corps detachment was turned out as for an<lb/>
inspection and the Chief Surgeon <add>Havard</add> stated the reason for the ceremony, and<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06303008"/>
-4-<lb/>
made some appropriate remarks as to the importance of these experiments<lb/>
and in praise of those men who volunteered for them, and Kissinger was<lb/>
ordered to advance and stand in front of the Colonel who then gave him<lb/>
the watch and chain in a case., and his warrant of appointment as a<lb/>
Corporal (Acting Hospital Steward)<lb/>
<p>What<lb/>
division?</p>
<p>who? Havard?</p>
<p>When<lb/>
about what time?</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #19</hi> General Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters were the Casa Duranon;<lb/>
we also called it the Toledo House, but why I do not remember. I lived<lb/>
on the second floor on the right side of the house, looking at the house.<lb/>
Major Cartwright lived on the same floor. General Lee lived in the second<lb/>
floor front.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #20</hi> - Can you identify my photographs as being the old buildings<lb/>
of military hospital No. 1?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: No.</p></item>
<item>QUESTION #26 - I do not know whether Lazear died in a hospital tent or in one<lb/>
of the little buildings in the yellow fever hospital across the La Playa R.R.<lb/>
tracks.<lb/>
<p><hi>QUESTION</hi> When you were there were there tents or buildings?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> It is my recollection that I had yellow fever in one of the<lb/>
little one room houses.</p></item>
<item>QUESTION #27 - The Corps had three divisions, but only two divisions of the<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06303009"/>
-5-<lb/>
VII Army Corps went to Cuba. Each division had its own hospital for the<lb/>
sick of its own division. The second division hospital was where the post<lb/>
hospital was later. The first division hospital was at the opposite end<lb/>
of the camp, that is near Buena Vista. The first division did not stay<lb/>
very long. The regiments were sent home and mustered out. The whole<lb/>
Corps returned to the United States to be mustered out by May of 1899.<lb/>
The garrison at Columbia Barracks was replaced by regiments of the re-<lb/>
gular army from the United States.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #28</hi> I imagine men from the Quartermaster Department probably<lb/>
helped in the construction of Camp Lazear, and probably went out and bought<lb/>
<hi>coal oil stoves.</hi> It was probably not an army stove, because the only<lb/>
stoves the army would have would be the army cooking stoves, and the Cu-<lb/>
bans did not even have cooking stoves. The Cubans did not have heating<lb/>
stoves either in their private buildings.<lb/>
<p>Kean doesn't really know what<lb/>
kind of stove</p>
<p><unclear>K re and from</unclear> Moran's idea of the stove</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #29</hi> The first five lived at #20 General Lee Street; Number 6,<lb/>
O'Cain, a teamster, lived at the post. Numbers 7 and 8 lived at 102 Real;<lb/>
Number 9, Reilly, lived at 89 Real; numbers 10 and 11, the Caesars, lived<lb/>
at 89 Real. The Caesars were Jews and had a little tailor shop. Number<lb/>
12, Hamburger, lived at 102 Real. Numbers 13, 14, and 15, I do not know<lb/>
where they lived.<lb/>
<p>I recognize your photographs of General Lee Street as the old house<lb/>
where I lived. I stood on the porch in front of the room where Major Ed-<lb/>
munds was sick of yellow fever, the room on the left side (facing the house).</p>
<p>It is quite possible that I gave a wrong number for 89 Real.</p></item>
<item>-5-</item>
<pb n="6" id="f06303010"/>
<item>- 6 -</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #32</hi> Where can I find the contract between Dr. Rojas and Walter<lb/>
Reed or the army?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi> I think the contract for the rent of the land where Camp Lazear<lb/>
was located was an informal one between Major Reed and Dr. Rojas; what be-<lb/>
came of it when the arrangement terminated, I do not know; I do not be-<lb/>
lieve it was preserved. If a contract had been made, it was probably<lb/>
an informal one like that between Reed and the Spanish volunteers; these<lb/>
contracts were not filed in any government office, as I was the officer<lb/>
to whom was entrusted the funds given by the General Wood for the expenses of<lb/>
the experiments at Camp Lazear. These funds were Cuban funds, not U.S.<lb/>
Army funds. They were from the Cuban Treasury under the control of General<lb/>
Wood, the Governor General. There were several of these contracts with<lb/>
volunteers. I do not know what happened to them; the originals may be<lb/>
in the Army Medical Museum since they have photographs of some of them.<lb/>
I had two framed, one (Antonio Benigno) for myself, and the other is in<lb/>
the Army Medical Museum. My framed copy of the contract hung on the<lb/>
wall of the office of the Association of Military Surgeons in the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum while I was the Secretary. After I gave up the Secretary-<lb/>
ship October 1934, the framed contract disappeared, and has only recently<lb/>
been found in a store room of the Army Medical Museum with something else<lb/>
pasted over it.</p>
<p>Then<lb/>
saying<lb/>
printed<lb/>
note at the<lb/>
contract<lb/>
is OK.<lb/>
May<lb/>
1941<lb/>
when - doesn't know<lb/>
'he left it in the office</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #34</hi> - What do you think Agramonte meant when he said in his ban-<lb/>
quet speech, 1902, that Lazear produced the first case unknown to the other<lb/>
members of the Board, and when he stated in the letter to Finlay, page 22<lb/>
- 6 -<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06303011"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
of Finlay's book, that Lazear produced the first two cases of yellow fever<lb/>
unknown to the members of the Board ? What do you think Agramonte meant<lb/>
by that?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi> I haven't the faintest idea. The first two cases as far as<lb/>
the records show were Carroll and X.Y. (Dean)</p>
<p><hi>(CONFIDENTIAL)</hi> I remember very well Reed reading me the report about X.Y.<lb/>
for his paper, and he was exceptionally anxious to make it clear this man<lb/>
had not been exposed to yellow fever, and was also anxious not to show that<lb/>
a soldier had been infected on the reservation. If the Commanding Officer<lb/>
of the post found they were infecting soldiers inside the limits of the<lb/>
garrison, Reed probably would have been <hi>arrested</hi>. I told him if he made<lb/>
it clear that the man had not been outside, it would show he was infected<lb/>
inside; so he just had to take the chances.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION:</hi> Do you now believe Finlay did produce experimental yellow<lb/>
fever in Father Urra?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> It can be considered yellow fever only by disregarding the<lb/>
laws established by the Reed Board as to the incubation period in a mosquito<lb/>
and in the human being.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION:</hi> Do you think he produced any case of experimental yellow<lb/>
fever?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi> Dr. Finlay Sr. loaned me his notes, and I did not think any<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06303012"/>
- 8 -<lb/>
case according to these rules could be yellow fever, and told him so.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#7</add>:</hi> (CONFIDENTIAL) Why is General Truby so certain that Agramonte<lb/>
played a very minor role, and what is behind General Truby's feeling that<lb/>
Agramonte published statements that could not be proven true.<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Truby is very upright in his gentle way, and if he thinks<lb/>
that Agramonte had made misstatements to increase his importance, he would<lb/>
resent it.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#10</add>:</hi> Will you describe your visit to Major Edmunds?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Officers of General Lee's staff who messed together at the<lb/>
headquarters building became uneasy that I should visit yellow fever cases<lb/>
and then go back and mix with them, and so they got General Lee to direct<lb/>
me not to visit any more yellow fever cases. Major Edmunds of the Infantry<lb/>
became sick and was reported to have yellow fever. He lived in the house<lb/>
at 27 General Lee Street, which I had formerly occupied. I became very un-<lb/>
easy about his case, and being awake one monring very early I dressed and<lb/>
went down to his house (between 5 and 6 A.M.) and sat on the portico out-<lb/>
side the window of his bed room, which had no glass in it, simply iron<lb/>
bars reaching down to the floor. Through this window I spoke to Edmunds,<lb/>
and had some conversation with his nurse, and saw that he was very ill.<lb/>
I was also conscious of being bitten by mosquitoes whilst I was sitting<lb/>
there. Five days after that, in the early morning, I woke up with a<lb/>
headache, backache and a fever, and realized that I probably had yellow<lb/>
fever, which I must have contracted on the visit to Edmunds' house. In<lb/>
- 8 -<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06303013"/>
- 9 -<lb/>
going there I obeyed the letter, but not the spirit of the order because I<lb/>
did not go in the house.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#11</add>:</hi> When you had yellow fever were you taken care of in one of<lb/>
the tents or huts?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I am not quite sure, but I think it was in one of the army<lb/>
huts; however, I think there were some tents there also.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#12</add>:</hi> After General Lee left Cuba where did you live at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> At first in the officers' row, that is the row of line of-<lb/>
ficers' houses at the main part of Columbia Barracks - not at the post hos-<lb/>
pital officers' quarters. For a short time after I lived in one of the<lb/>
other buildings. I moved over to the hospital when I became post surgeon<lb/>
for a while before I joined General Wood's staff.</p></item>
<item><hi>DR. HENCH <add>#13</add>:</hi> You said that Reed was very indignant about Carroll's lack<lb/>
of self quarantine; when was he indignant, and how did he express his<lb/>
indignation?<lb/>
<p><hi>GENERAL KEAN:</hi> When Reed came back from the United States, Carroll was<lb/>
still sick and Lazear had died. I happened to be on an inspection trip at<lb/>
Matanzas, and when the transport came in there I went aboard and saw Reed<lb/>
who was returning to Cuba. <add>Did Reed know Lazear had died?</add> Of course the only value to Carroll's case was<lb/>
- 9 -<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06303014"/>
- 10 -<lb/>
if he had been shut up in quarantine, but he did not believe in the mos-<lb/>
quito, and he thought he had malaria. It made Reed very indignant that<lb/>
Carroll went into Havana during the period of incubation and partly de-<lb/>
stroyed the value of his case as evidence. Reed's indigantion was ex-<lb/>
pressed privately to me, and also in describing Carroll's case, and X.<lb/>
Y.'s case to General Wood when we saw General Wood together before Reed<lb/>
went to the United States October 12.</p>
<p>Did he discussed it <unclear>c</unclear> Carroll?</p>
<p>What did he say</p>
<p>amplify</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #18</hi> Godfrey was not dismissed from the service. He would have<lb/>
come up for promotion, but knew perfectly well he would never get past the<lb/>
Board, but what the circumstances of his suicide were I do not know. He<lb/>
had gone back to the United States.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#19</add>:</hi> Do you have any idea why Agramonte wrote he was present when<lb/>
Dean was inoculated?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not know. In view of the inferences in his speech and<lb/>
letter to Dr. Finlay, it would appear that he was not present. But the<lb/>
memory of per ectly honest people often gets confused after the lapse of<lb/>
years, and they mix up what they actually saw with details that they<lb/>
learned of by being told of them.</p></item>
<item>QUESTION <add>#22</add> - pertaining to Diary notes Nov. 25, 1900 - &ldquo;Reed thought Menocal<lb/>
was at the bottom of it&rdquo;. What does this mean ? Who is Menocal?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi> He was in command of the Quarantine Camp for Spanish im-<lb/>
migrants; a Cuban physician in the Quarantine Service. The immigrants who<lb/>
came into Havana usually got yellow fever, so General Wood established a<lb/>
- 10 -<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06303015"/>
- 11 -<lb/>
camp for non-immune immigrants across the Harbor, and did not allow them to<lb/>
go into the city. They were shipped direct from this camp to the sugar<lb/>
&ldquo;Centrals&rdquo; in the country.</p>
<p>amplify</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#24</add>:</hi> Would you mind giving me a little more of the story of how,<lb/>
after the funeral, you decided to have Reed's office desk locked, and you<lb/>
found that his office had been entered and the things removed?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: Two or three days after the death of Reed I spoke to the<lb/>
Surgeon General and I said I thought we should get Reed's papers together.<lb/>
Reed had two offices. He had been put in charge of the great Medical Li-<lb/>
brary, and he had <add>also</add> a little desk at the other end of the building on the<lb/>
Museum side where he kept his paper work about the Army Medical School and<lb/>
the yellow fever work, his laboratory notes, etc. I <hi>telephoned down</hi> <add>for the S G O (old War, may &amp; State Bldg)</add> to<lb/>
the Chief Clerk <add>at the library</add> and told him to go in there and get together all the papers<lb/>
in Reed's desk and put them in an envelope and hold them for further in-<lb/>
structions. He came back and reported that there was nothing at all in<lb/>
the desk. I reported this to the Surgeon General, and we talked it over<lb/>
and concluded that Carroll, being Reed's assistant, had probably taken them<lb/>
away. No inquiry was made; in a way it was the natural thing for him to<lb/>
think that he should take charge. I intended to ask Carroll about it, but<lb/>
we never heard anything more about it. Lazear's notebook should have been<lb/>
with the Reed material. I recently asked Mrs. Reed if she had ever heard<lb/>
anything of the papers, but she said he never brought anything to the house.<lb/>
No one has ever made any further inquiry about it.</p>
<p>Where<lb/>
was Kean</p>
<p>Kean was Exec officer<lb/>
to the S G</p>
<p><unclear>same</unclear> make by phone</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#26</add>:</hi> Did you ever visit Camp Lazear during the second intervention?<lb/>
<p>- 11 -<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06303016"/>
- 12 -</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Not that I recall.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION:</hi> Do you know personally whether these buildings were still<lb/>
there?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> No, I have no recollection of them.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#34</add>:</hi> Reed says Ames was in charge of Camp Lazear; was Dr. Ames<lb/>
actually in charge of Camp Lazear?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think he was actually in charge of Camp Lazear - that is<lb/>
in an administrative capacity. Ames was not a participant in the experi-<lb/>
mental work, but came in to look at any men that were sick. Dr. Ames saw<lb/>
Moran when he became sick and probably arranged for him to be transferred,<lb/>
but his primary job was to administer the camp. He also attended the men<lb/>
at the yellow fever detached section of the hospital.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION <add>#35</add>:</hi> Where would you find the various cables that went back and<lb/>
forth between Reed in Washington and Lazear in Cuba?<lb/>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I suppose in the files in the War Department, in the Adju-<lb/>
tant General's Office.</p></item>
<item>Convert # 36</item>
<item><hi>GENERAL KEAN:</hi> The Pan American Medical Congress met in Havana February<lb/>
4 - 9, 1901. I had been delegated to be a member of that Congress, but<lb/>
before the Congress met I had received an order to report in Washington for<lb/>
examination for promotion to Major in the regular Medical Corps. So I<lb/>
went to Gorgas and said: &ldquo;Now Reed has proven that yellow fever is spread<lb/>
by mosquitoes, and we medical officers should stand by him at the meeting<lb/>
- 12 -<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06303017"/>
- 13 -<lb/>
of this Congress and see that he has proper support&rdquo;, and his reply was,<lb/>
&ldquo;Kean, I know that Reed has shown that mosquitoes who have bitten yellow<lb/>
fever patients can infect others, but I am not certain that it is the<lb/>
only way that yellow fever can be spread, or <hi>even the usual way.&rdquo;</hi> I<lb/>
think he got orders sometime in February from General Wood to try out the<lb/>
mosquito theory, but active work with the mosquito inspection of premises<lb/>
and their kerosene squads did not begin until after the first of March.<lb/>
The municipal law placing a fine on the occupant when mosquito larvae<lb/>
were found on the premises was not issued until May.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The phrase of Gorgas quoted above was also used by him in his final<lb/>
report to General Wood. (See Yellow Fever Senate Doc. No. 822, 1911 -<lb/>
page 236, line 7).</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. R. Kean<lb/>
Read and approved by General Kean</signed>.
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
