<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06302034">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 18, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06302034</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E. </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Donnally, H. H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-18">March 18, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06302034</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 18, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench wonders if Agramonte was with Lazear at his death because Carroll claimed that Agramonte had left three days earlier.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-18">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby and Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 18, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06302034"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-03-18">March 18, 1941</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N Street, N. W.<lb/>
Georgetown, Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Generals Truby and Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am leaving Friday for Florida and Havana. I certainly appreciate all<lb/>
you have done to help me. I am sending you either by separate post or by express<lb/>
depending on the relative expense, a note book containing photostatic articles by<lb/>
Hemmeter and Donnally regarding Maj. Carroll. I have marked these articles with<lb/>
my notes and would appreciate it if you would read them at your leisure and with<lb/>
ink or pencil write your own comments either on the margin or on the back of the<lb/>
pages. I will consider them confidential. I am very anxious to have your reaction<lb/>
to them and I do not believe you have seen them. Note especially the letter to<lb/>
<del>Maj</del><add>Mrs</add>. Carroll in which he states that Dr. and Mrs. Agramonte left Havana two or<lb/>
three days before Lazear's death and in view of what Dr. Argramonte wrote this<lb/>
idea seems impossible and yet there it is. I have a letter which Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
wrote to Mrs. Lazear sometime after Dr. Lazear's death in which <del>s</del>he mourned the<lb/>
latter's death and made some remark to the effect that he would never forget the<lb/>
day Dr. Lazear died. I asked Mrs. Lazear about this and she felt that Maj. Carroll<lb/>
surely must have been in error. She had been lead to believe that Dr. Agramonte<lb/>
was with Dr. Lazear when he died and felt sure that since Reed was also away and<lb/>
Major Carroll was still here, Dr. Argramonte most assuredly could not have left.</p>
<p>I will send this notation first to General Truby and ask you (Gen. Truby)<lb/>
to send it to General Kean. I am doing this because General Keen has just written<lb/>
that he has been none too well recently. There is no particular hurry about returning<lb/>
it until I return to Rochester, about April 26th.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Philip S. Hench</signed>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
PSH:FP<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I have long since received my little tin box but you did not return the key.<lb/>
As I had an extra key it made no particular difference but I wonder if you happen to<lb/>
have the key and would return it to me, if not it will be an easy matter to have an<lb/>
extra key made. I will return to Rochester about the 26th of April for only a week<lb/>
when I go to Atlantic City for the medical meetings May 5th to 7th. I hope to return<lb/>
through Washington, D. C. and perhaps spend the 8th or 9th of May in Washington. You<lb/>
have often expressed yourwillingness to discuss matters at length if only we could<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06302035"/>
General Kean<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
March 18, 1941<lb/>
do it face to face and without the need for long hand writing on your part. Would<lb/>
you be willing to try and arrange to have a professional stenographer spend the<lb/>
afternoon or as much time as will be required while you and I visit with each other.<lb/>
I could ask you many questions and you could give me much information which she<lb/>
could transcribe and give you a copy for correction and approval before letting me<lb/>
have it finally. I shall be delighted to pay her expenses. If you know of a<lb/>
stenographer whom you would prefer, it would be splendid, otherwise, I think I<lb/>
could get help from one of my medical friends whose secretary might be available<lb/>
and willing to earn a little extra money.<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
My addresses<lb/>
Hotel Villa Atlantique - Palm Beach Fla Mar 23 - April 16<lb/>
except for 1 week in Havana - Hotel Nacional Mar 28 - Apr 3.<lb/>
Hotel Statler, Boston Mass Apr 20-25.<lb/>
Home thereafter till May 3 &rarr; to Atlantic City &amp; return<lb/>
via Washington.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
