<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06302140">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 11, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06302140</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-06-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Elizabeth L.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Peabody, James E.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, Ida E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-06-11">June 11, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06302140</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 11, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench discusses the Kissinger interview, which was published in a Cleveland newspaper. He offers his opinion on the role played by Kissinger during the yellow fever experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-06-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 11, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06302140"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-06-11">June 11, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I enjoyed so much receiving your last letter. First of all, I am delighted<lb/>
to hear that you are again feeling fit after your unhappy experience in the hospital.</p>
<p>Thank you so much for your kind words about my Cleveland talk. The audience<lb/>
seemed to appreciate fully the significance of the story. It was a great pleasure<lb/>
for me to meet Mrs. Reed, Colonel Siler and again General Ireland and his wife. The<lb/>
Wyeth folks sent me several clippings from newspapers, including the one from the<lb/>
Plain Dealer of June 3. That interview certainly was a mess but I do not believe<lb/>
we can blame Kissinger. I happened to be standing at the door of the room where<lb/>
the reporter was interviewing Kissinger. The interview was very brief, but some-<lb/>
body gave the reporter a copy of my talk. You will note that much of the supposed<lb/>
interview with Kissinger consists of fragments of sentences from my talk. The<lb/>
man would use a half sentence or a whole sentence, filling out the rest himself,<lb/>
and he certainly got it all bawled up. Since Kissinger had not seen my talk pre-<lb/>
viously, we must conclude that the reporter made up the story with the grossest<lb/>
carelessness. That small erroneous part which may (or may not) have derived from<lb/>
Kissinger, unfortunately we will have to forgive.</p>
<p>While chatting with me he told me that not long ago he had some sort of<lb/>
an affair which affected his face but which cleared up. The thought passed through<lb/>
my head that he might have had a slight stroke. Mr. Kissinger was called upon to<lb/>
make just the briefest acknowledgement of an introduction. His speech was only<lb/>
about three or four sentences long but he was even more ill at case than usual.<lb/>
As he said, he was &ldquo;all choked up&rdquo; and had to stop a moment to regain his composure.<lb/>
That was Monday afternoon. He went home the next day, I think, arriving Tuesday<lb/>
evening, very happy about the whole affair. Wednesday morning at nine o'clock he<lb/>
had a very severe stoke and two days later when Mrs. Kissinger wrote me he was still<lb/>
unconscious and not expected to live. I have been trying to keep in touch with them<lb/>
but have heard nothing yet. So, if the poor fellow gave any erroneous statements to<lb/>
the report, we will have to excuse it on the basis of his confusion.</p>
<p>I am aware that several of those closely connected with the yellow fever<lb/>
affair (not including yourself) have on occasion spoken a little slightingly to me<lb/>
of Kissinger, accusing him of having &ldquo;gone into the hero business&rdquo; a little too ex-<lb/>
tensively, but I have seen the fellow in his own home and also here in Rochester<lb/>
and elsewhere, and I am absolutely sure that he deserves to be forgiven if one<lb/>
analyzes his personality and career. I entirely agree with you that his myclitis<lb/>
had nothing whatever to do with his yellow fever but who can blame him, when he was<lb/>
down and out, with his wife taking in washings, etc., for jumping at the chance to<lb/>
get help from Dr. Peabody and others on the strength of his previous heroism. If<lb/>
that made a hero out of him it has meant bread and butter, and taking his wife from<lb/>
the wash tub. Certainly I must look on his actions with considerable charity. His<lb/>
actions are explained further by an analysis of his simple character. He is nothing<lb/>
but a rather ignorant farmer who more or less mentally died after his Cuban exper-<lb/>
iences. Life has meant nothing since then except in retrospect. Living on a little,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06302141"/>
General J. R. Kean<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
June 11, 1941<lb/>
rather isolated farm, the only excitement that has come to his life has been the<lb/>
occasional invitation to go out and speak on the yellow fever story. Not having<lb/>
had enough education to write the story up, he has relied on his memory which has<lb/>
become rather poor. He has little sense of the relative values as I saw in his<lb/>
home, when he showed me with a simple, childish delight the citation making him an<lb/>
honorary member of some senior high school class. This citation pleased him<lb/>
practically as much as the Congressional Medal of Honor, and his honorary membership<lb/>
in both Kiwanis and Rotary were as impressive to him as a congressional citation.<lb/>
I would say that in the last analysis he was a simple but brave soldier and a<lb/>
Christian gentleman who deserves understanding rather than condemnation.</p>
<p>Naturally, he would like to connect his myclitis with his yellow fever.<lb/>
That would make it easier to bear and one's friends are always inclined to do such<lb/>
things. For example, on several recent occasions when some senator or congressman<lb/>
died, his friends in Washington promptly have stated that &ldquo;he died on the battlefield<lb/>
fighting for the rights of the people, etc.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I for one will entirely agree that you are completely exonerated from any<lb/>
responsibility for getting yourself in the Wyeth painting. Your friends are entirely<lb/>
responsible and are very happily responsible. It was felt, and justly so, that you<lb/>
and General Wood had done so much for the Board that you deserved inclusion and I am<lb/>
delighted that you are in it.</p>
<p>I am overwhelmed with your offer to give me the Walter Reed contract. I<lb/>
cannot tell you how greatly I would appreciate this, But before making your final<lb/>
decision I wonder if you honestly think I should be the custodian of it. How about<lb/>
your own son's interest in it? Should you still insist on giving it to me, I can<lb/>
only tell you how very grateful I am for it and I shall promise that it will be safe-<lb/>
guarded as it should be and made an integral part of the collection of Reediana which<lb/>
I am assembling. I may have told you of the great kindness of Dr. Kelly who handed<lb/>
over to me all his collection of Reed material, including many letters of Carroll,<lb/>
Agramonte and a couple of Reed. All of this material will be carefully preserved and<lb/>
presented permanently to the Mayo Clinic on the condition that it be accessible to<lb/>
all those interested in it, and it is my hope to have much of the material actually<lb/>
copied in photostatic form and deposited in the four or five institutions who have<lb/>
so far expressed an interest in my collection. For sentimental reasons I should be<lb/>
very glad, should you decide to send it to me, to have the contract in its original<lb/>
frame. The story you told me about its disappearance, etc. is certainly an interesting<lb/>
one and I would just as soon have it in that form. May I suggest that I believe if you<lb/>
should phone to the American Railway Express Company, they would call for the picture,<lb/>
pack it appropriately and ship it to me, without any bother to you. I should be only<lb/>
too delighted to defray the expenses entailed.</p>
<p>May I say that Mrs. Franck's work and charge were entirely satisfactory.<lb/>
I know she worked very hard on it and the information is worth much more than her bill.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
