<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06309001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Text of speech to be given upon the receipt of the Gorgas Medal, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 15, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06309001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-12-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Stitt, Edward R.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Osler, William</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Key West Barracks (Key West, Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-12-15">December 15, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06309001</idno>
<title>Text of speech to be given upon the receipt of the Gorgas Medal, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 15, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses the &ldquo;warfare&rdquo; against the mosquito.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1942-12-15">
<head>Text of speech to be given upon the receipt of the Gorgas Medal, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, December 15, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06309001"/>
<opener>
For Col. Philip S. Hench-<lb/>
What was in my mind to say, but was left unsaid- J. R. Kean-<lb/>
<dateline>
THE GORGAS MEDAL. <date value="1942-12-15">December 15, 1942</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>It is certainly a singular good fortune for me to be here today to<lb/>
receive, before this distinguished company, a beautiful medal bearing<lb/>
the name of an old and valued friend. An additional honor is that of<lb/>
being bracketed with two such notable scientists as are Admiral Stitt<lb/>
and General Russell. The engrossed citation which has been handed me by<lb/>
Mr. Law pleased me no less, albeit I am somewhat embarrassed at the gen-<lb/>
orosity of the ascriptions. Far be it from me to be critical of them<lb/>
however, signed as they are by the President and the Secretary of the<lb/>
Association of Military Surgeons of the United States of America.</p>
<p>The statement at the beginning of the citation that I was the first<lb/>
to initiate warfare against the mosquito is one on which I desire to<lb/>
say a few words. I asked my friend Colonel Hume why it was this, which<lb/>
seemed most to interest the members of the press, though I considered<lb/>
it of less importance than some of the other things mentioned. He said<lb/>
that it seemed to have for the public more news value than matters of<lb/>
organization or planning.</p>
<p>The method of attack on the mosquito was not invented, as has been<lb/>
thought, for the Yellow Fever Campaign of 1901 in Cuba. It had been de-<lb/>
vised and described years before by Dr. L. O. Howard who was for many<lb/>
years the Chief of the Bureau of Entomology, Dept. of Agriculture. He<lb/>
was an esteemed friend of Walter Reed and he and his assistant Dr.<lb/>
Carroll went to Dr. Howard's laboratory to get points on mosquitoes be-<lb/>
fore the Yellow Fever Board went to Cuba. Dr. Howard is still living,<lb/>
though well along in the eighth decade and is a member of the Walter Reed<lb/>
Memorial Association. It was from one of his publications that I had<lb/>
learned some years before the Spanish War the use of kerosene sprayed<lb/>
on the surface of deposits of water to kill the larvae of mosquitoes..<lb/>
When I was stationed at Key West Barracks in 1895 I recall recommending<lb/>
to the Mayor to use this method upon some pools just off the Military<lb/>
Reservation and within the city limits which were breeding clouds of<lb/>
mosquitoes. But the average Key Wester of those days was more philo-<lb/>
sophical than progressive. He was inclined to accept flies, fleas and<lb/>
mosquitoes as the expected and unavoidable accompaniments of mundane<lb/>
existence, upon which it was useless to expend precious dollars and un-<lb/>
welcome efforts. It was at this time that I first met our friend Admiral<lb/>
Stitt, and also Walter Reed who came down on a scientific errand and<lb/>
was my guest for a week.</p>
<p>May I now skip five years over the period of the Spanish War, one<lb/>
of the consequences of which to me was to land me in Cuba with the Army<lb/>
of Occupation. A year later we had a Yellow Fever epidemic. Major<lb/>
Walter Reed was at Columbia Barracks with his famous Yellow Fever Board.<lb/>
Soon Lazear had produced a couple of verified cases with his infected<lb/>
mosquitoes, and their agency in transmitting malaria also had been re-<lb/>
cently demonstrated by a British Army doctor named Ross. So it was no<lb/>
-1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06309002"/>
The Gorgas Medal p. 2-<lb/>
great stroke of genius in me to think of Dr. Howard and kerosene and to<lb/>
recommend to my good Chief General Fitzhugh Lee in October, and to<lb/>
General Wood in December, the warfare against this enemy of man. Gen-<lb/>
eral Lee I think did not believe a word of the theory, but he disliked<lb/>
mosquitoes and liked me, so he promptly signed my circular of instruc-<lb/>
tions to all commanding officers.</p>
<p>But the case was different with the men who had much experience<lb/>
with this extraordinary disease and had seen one theory after another<lb/>
disproved almost as soon as it was published. Dr. Osler in an address<lb/>
to a graduating class of medical students quoted with approval the state-<lb/>
ment of some old Greek philosopher that a judicious skepticism is an<lb/>
important attribute of the scientific mind. Major Gorgas whose name<lb/>
this medal appropriately bears, had long been looked up to by us all as<lb/>
the Yellow Fever expert of the Army Medical Corps. He had been kept<lb/>
stationed at Southern Military posts for years so as to be conveniently<lb/>
on call. He and Reed were good friends and held each others opinions<lb/>
in high respect. But he viewed Reed's experiments with Osler's scienti-<lb/>
fic skepticism. I am not telling any tales out of school, for he has<lb/>
left on record in an official report, written more than a year later,<lb/>
after we had all left Cuba, his disbelief in the mosquito theory when<lb/>
it was announced by Walter Reed at the Pan American Medical Congress<lb/>
held in Havana, Cuba, Feb. 4, 1901. He said in this report &ldquo;I myself<lb/>
had seen the work, and was convinced that the mosquito could convey<lb/>
yellow fever, but I was hardly prepared to believe that it was the only<lb/>
way or even the ordinary way of conveying the disease.&rdquo; * But General<lb/>
Wood wanted it done and would find the money to do it and Gorgas was<lb/>
quite willing to carry out loyalty and efficiently the wishes of his<lb/>
Commanding General. Conviction came to him from the success of his own<lb/>
work.</p>
<p>Looking back on the episode in its entirety, as we can do after a<lb/>
lapse of more than 40 years, we can see that Gorgas lost nothing in<lb/>
fame or in opportunity by his scientific skepticism. I, however have<lb/>
gained something by the promptness of my conversion, of which the re-<lb/>
searches of Dr. Philip S. Hench of the Mayo Clinic has dug up the doc-<lb/>
umentary evidence, out of the limbo of forgotten records. I have ob-<lb/>
tained a place, which I hardly deserve, in Cornwell's now famous paint-<lb/>
ing of the Conquerors of Yellow Fever and mention in this much valued<lb/>
citation. I wish to thank Mr. Law and Mr. Kellogg for the medal and<lb/>
for the very acceptable Christmas gift which comes with it.</p>
<p>* Final Report as Chief Sanitary Officer of Habana dated July 12, 1902</p>
<p>-2-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
