<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06302098">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 2, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06302098</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-05-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Crain, Darrell C.</name>
<name type="person">Yater, Wallace</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-05-02">May 2, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06302098</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 2, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is anxious to discuss his questions with Kean.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-05-02">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 2, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06302098"/>
<opener>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-05-02">May 2, 1941</date>
</dateline><lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
General J. R. Kean<lb/>
2804 &ldquo;N&rdquo; St. N.W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I leave today for the meetings in Atlantic City, address Chalfonte-<lb/>
Haddon Hall from Sunday to Wednesday night. I had hoped to see Dr. Howard Kelly enroute<lb/>
and to save next Thursday and Friday for Washington, but Dr. Kelly will be away this<lb/>
week-end. According to my present plan, I will leave Atlantic City Wednesday about<lb/>
supper time for Baltimore, spend all Thursday morning with Dr. Howard Kelly, see his<lb/>
yellow fever material, and come to Washington probably after lunch Thursday. I have<lb/>
many questions to ask you and have them all written down so that we can cover matters<lb/>
as rapidly as possible. Would it be possible for you to see me Thursday afternoon?<lb/>
Would you prefer to continue our discussion Thursday evening and get it over with, or<lb/>
would you prefer to rest in the evening and have me return the next morning if necessary?<lb/>
I hope to spend at least part of Friday, as much of the day as possible, part of it in<lb/>
the Congressional Library and perhaps a visit to the office of the Chief of the Signal<lb/>
Corps to see if I can find some old photographs and also visit the General Staff Map<lb/>
Collection of the War Department. General Truby suggested that I might find in the<lb/>
latter the 1899 map and the 1900 map of Camp Columbia as well as the lost key to the<lb/>
1902 map. I tried to get these through Chief Clerk Freer, I think in the Adjutant<lb/>
General's department, but they were not to be found. I would appreciate it if you<lb/>
would be able to tell me how to contact these two departments, the Signal Corps, and<lb/>
the Map Collection, sometime next Friday.</p>
<p>Last night I reviewed our entire correspondence so that this time we<lb/>
could finish a lot of unfinished business while we have a secretary to help us. Will<lb/>
you please contact the girl in the office of the Military Surgeon, to see if she could<lb/>
be available either for Thursday afternoon (and evening?) or for Friday morning. If<lb/>
she is not available Thursday afternoon, perhaps I can go to the Signal Corps and Map<lb/>
Collection then, and we might get her Friday morning or afternoon at your home. Lest<lb/>
she might not be available, I am writing a brief note to my friends, Dr. Darrell Crain<lb/>
and Dr. Wallace Yater, to see if they know of someone who might be available, but I<lb/>
will make no definite arrangements with their secretaries until I hear from you.</p>
<p>Five things that I am particularly anxious to discuss are; (1) the<lb/>
additional letters from Reed which you have; (2) the &ldquo;little bundle of retained papers&rdquo;<lb/>
which you said you had in your personal file of correspondence and which you thought<lb/>
we might be able to find; (3) the data which you just received from the files of the<lb/>
Military Surgeon; (4) Dr. Goldberger's reference which you mentioned--I have not been<lb/>
able to find it; (5) the copies of the contracts which you said Colonel Siler was making<lb/>
for me. I shall also get the key to my tin box.<lb/>
</p>
<p>I should most appreciate help in getting the address of Mrs. Ames<add>?</add> and the<lb/>
address of Dr. Carroll's survivors. I wrote the Pension Bureau and they have the address<lb/>
of the Carroll family but would not give it to me. They presumably forwarded my letter<lb/>
but I never received a reply. I am so anxious to find this out as I hope to visit them<lb/>
sometime with the vague idea that we might find some of Reed's records and Lazear's<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06302099"/>
General J. R. Kean&nbsp;&nbsp;- 2 -&nbsp;&nbsp;May 2, 1941<lb/>
<lb/>
notebook which the relatives may have, in complete ignorance of the fact that<lb/>
perhaps they shouldn't have had them.</p>
<p>You mention that you were going to discuss my plans for memorializing<lb/>
Camp Lazear with General Ireland. I wondered whether you had had a chance to do<lb/>
so. General Truby suggested that when I was in Washington I should try to find the<lb/>
&ldquo;Medical History of the Post&rdquo; which he says should be somewhere and contains invaluable<lb/>
information. He also says that the Q.M.G.O., which I suppose is the Quartermaster<lb/>
General's Office, should have the plans of Buildings 1 and 2, and he thought it<lb/>
important for me to find it in order to cancel out the error in the locations of<lb/>
the stove pipe as apparently erroneously given in Agramonte's drawing. I realize<lb/>
that in the present state of a national emergency, as you have said, most of these<lb/>
departments are working overtime. I certainly don't want to be a burden to any<lb/>
of them, but I gather from my experience to date that most of these departments<lb/>
have pretty efficient chief clerks who, with the help of their efficient indices<lb/>
can find an amazing amount of material without much trouble. At least I might<lb/>
contact some of these men and at their leisure (if any) in the coming weeks or<lb/>
months, they might be able to find what I want without much trouble. Any help or<lb/>
advice that you give me will be most gratefully received and if you wish to address<lb/>
me I shall be at the Chalfonte-Haddon Hall. I have written for reservations at<lb/>
the Mayflower Hotel while I am in Washington.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>PS Hench</signed>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
