<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06301055">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 7, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06301055</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-01-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Ignacio</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Echeverria, R. F.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose Farm (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital # 1, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>16 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-01-07">January 7, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06301055</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 7, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains Moran's and Kissinger's differing memories of the yellow fever experiments. He informs Truby that he wants to write an account that will glorify all concerned with the Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-01-07">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 7, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06301055"/>
<opener>
1<lb/>
This is the original-<lb/>
Have kept the carbon<lb/>
<hi>A E T</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<date value="1941-01-07">January 7, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am so sorry that you did not get the data I sent you just after<lb/>
my W. and J. talk and hope that the program and clipping sent a few days ago reached<lb/>
you. You have been most kind and patient and it has been a rare privilege for me to<lb/>
&ldquo;meet you&rdquo; in such a friendly fashion if only via correspondence, and a rarer privi-<lb/>
lege to be allowed to read and even to use part of your unfinished manuscript. You<lb/>
and Gen. Kean have been most kind indeed.</p>
<p>Before making some comments on your valued manuscript may I make clear<lb/>
my intentions regarding the publication of my yellow fever data. I got into this<lb/>
thing at the request of President Hutchison who asked me to get in touch with some<lb/>
of the soldier-survivors of the experiments and advise him as to whether they were<lb/>
available and able to be invited to W. and J. as representatives of the whole group<lb/>
of researchers and volunteers to receive some sort of honor. I had no idea when I<lb/>
started it that there were any &ldquo;untold stories&rdquo; re the affair. When I met Kissinger<lb/>
at his home I found he had never published his story. I then got in touch with<lb/>
Moran and found he'd never published his either. This was of course months, indeed<lb/>
two years, before I had the opportunity of corresponding with you or General Kean.<lb/>
Kissinger disclaimed any ability to write up his story, said he hadn't had enough<lb/>
education to be able to do it. I was so determined to get his version that I<lb/>
corresponded at length with him and finally got him invited to Rochester to give us<lb/>
his story extemporaneously before the staff. I had his remarks transcribed and<lb/>
corrected by him. But there were many obvious errors in his story, due to faulty<lb/>
memory, no doubt.</p>
<p>I then got Moran to write out for me his story. It conflicted with<lb/>
Kissingers in some details and no amount of correspondence could straighten it out.<lb/>
For example Kissinger claims that he was <hi>one of first nine</hi> (unidentified) volunteers<lb/>
listed in Table III (Sen. Doc. p. 62) who were first (unsuccessfully) bitten. He<lb/>
claims he went alone to see Reed and volunteered a day or so before Moran did and<lb/>
more or less instigated Moran's volunteering. Moran insists (and his memory is<lb/>
<hi>much</hi> better than Kissinger's) that he (Moran) put the idea into Kissinger's head,<lb/>
that they talked it over all night and went <hi>together</hi> the next day to volunteer<lb/>
<hi>together.</hi> Knowing both men as well as I now do I do <hi>not</hi> believe that these differ-<lb/>
ences of opinion are based on any intentional desire for self-exploitation. Kissinger<lb/>
as you know became seriously ill (transverse myelitis with palay) a few years after<lb/>
1900, became destitute and was supported by his wife. In this grave moment Dr.<lb/>
Peabody of New York &ldquo;discovered&rdquo; him, and hero-ized him. Had Kissinger been solvent<lb/>
and leading an active mental and physical life he might (or might not) have rejected<lb/>
these attempts to publicize him. But in desperate financial straits Kissinger<lb/>
simply couldn't afford to refuse any help and so he accepted the not unpleasant<lb/>
role thrust so belatedly on him. After he recovered (I had him examined at the Clinic<lb/>
by our neurologists and we found no residues) he was called upon to make speeches<lb/>
here and there, all without notes. He never wrote up his story and hence had no<lb/>
original carefully authenticated version to stick to. You can well understand how<lb/>
in each re-telling some little change here and there might slip in until version 50<lb/>
might differ notably from version one.</p>
<p>No. 7 of table III might have been Kissinger<lb/>
Pinto might<lb/>
know</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06301056"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>Kissinger really &ldquo;died&rdquo; physically and mentally when he took sick.<lb/>
Thereafter he has lived only one role--that of a yellow fever martyr and hero.<lb/>
In contrast Moran, a man of much greater original ability and education, went on<lb/>
to live a normal progressive life culminating in his becoming president of an oil<lb/>
company in Cuba which was taken over by the Sun Oil Co. with Moran continued as<lb/>
general manager. He has a very nice job, is a well known and highly respected<lb/>
citizen of Cuba, a member of social and business clubs, etc. Although his role<lb/>
as a yellow fever volunteer is well known in Havana I imagine only a percentage<lb/>
of his friends and acquaintances know the story. In other words he isn't living<lb/>
on his &ldquo;hero-role&rdquo; and as far as I could see he is a most modest sort of fellow.</p>
<p>I do <hi>not</hi> think one can blame Kissinger - one must understand the differ-<lb/>
ences in background and foreground. Kissinger is, I am absolutely sure, <hi>completely<lb/>
honest</hi> within the limits of a faulty memory and a lack of education. He is a very<lb/>
nice simple person, very religious, a strong personal prohibitionist and church<lb/>
goer, a respected and very respectable citizen of a small Indiana town, an honorary<lb/>
member of both Rotary and Kiwanis, a simple farmer enjoying in a simple boyish way<lb/>
the simple hero-worship of his village.</p>
<p>Kissinger &amp; Moran are<lb/>
both honest but Moran is<lb/>
definitely <hi>wrong</hi> - A E T</p>
<p>When I first met each of these men I found under the surface a definite<lb/>
vein of antagonism for each other. They might now deny it but it was unmistakably<lb/>
there, although they tried to cloak it. It was borne of the fact that the <hi>friends</hi><lb/>
of each one would clip out any clippings that appeared in the newspaper about the<lb/>
other and send it to the other. One reporter would call Moran the participant<lb/>
in Reed's &ldquo;most crucial experiment&rdquo; and some friend of Kissinger would see it, re-<lb/>
sent it and send it to Kissinger. Kissinger would give a talk somewhere and a<lb/>
reporter would call him &ldquo;the sole survivor of the whole series of experiments,<lb/>
others surviving having only participated in the later experiments&rdquo;----etc. Sure<lb/>
enough one of Moran's friends would see that, clip it and send it to Moran. Each<lb/>
therefore was rather sure that the other was deliberately trying to grab the<lb/>
spot-light.</p>
<p>Well I saw that wasn't true. It was simply that reporters when they<lb/>
interview one hero make the most of the material at hand. Why should they worry<lb/>
about &ldquo;some other guy&rdquo; miles away? Their job was to make their story as big as<lb/>
possible. The inflation and misrepresentation came, not from either Kissinger or<lb/>
Moran but from the reporters. I therefore took on as my first job this task of<lb/>
re-uniting these two very worthy men as friends. I gave each the address of the<lb/>
other. I wrote to each a nice sentence that the other had included in a letter to<lb/>
me, and finally I told each in substance what I have just written above, that the<lb/>
world considered them both heroes, equally worthy of honor and distinction regard-<lb/>
less of who volunteered first, or who got bitten first, or who happened to develop<lb/>
yellow fever first. These latter events were beyond their control; each had given<lb/>
his all--each had offered his life and what happened thereafter should not be<lb/>
allowed to upset their equality of sacrifice.</p>
<p>Moran, being the smarter man, got the hint first and acted on it splendidly.<lb/>
The Cuban authorities had neglected him but when I appeared and spent so much time<lb/>
with him interviewing Albertini, Finlay, Jr., and Secretary Ramos, apparently the<lb/>
Cubans decided that if an American was so interested in Moran perhaps they should<lb/>
be interested too. (At least I like to think so.) So toward the end of our very<lb/>
strenuous series of conferences, arguments and interviews, Albertini, head of the<lb/>
Finlay Institute, as he walked out with Moran and me one day asked Moran to step<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06301057"/>
3.<lb/>
aside and there and then told him he had decided to nominate him for the Finlay<lb/>
Medal. He asked Moran who else should be nominated. Moran was at first inclined<lb/>
to decline the honor but I insisted that it was eminently deserved and that he must<lb/>
accept. Then Moran said he thought Kissinger should share the honor. I was de-<lb/>
lighted to agree and was happy to give Moran Kissinger's address so that Albertini<lb/>
could get in touch with him. So I believe any animosity that might have existed<lb/>
between them is buried. When Kissinger and Moran met in Washington, D. C. last<lb/>
summer for the receipt of the Finlay Medal they tried to correct each other's ver-<lb/>
sions for me but simply couldn't agree on a few details. At W. and J. in October<lb/>
I got them alone in my room (in a most amiable conversation) and we tried to iron<lb/>
out some differences but it is impossible. It is simply that each &ldquo;remembers&rdquo;<lb/>
certain parts his own way and that is that. Neither has proof so it is a matter<lb/>
of opinion. I suspect strongly that Moran is the more nearly correct but he too<lb/>
probably is in error in parts.</p>
<p>It was my purpose to publish their stories side by side <hi>under their<lb/>
own names</hi>, with a foreword by myself, in some American journal of medical history.<lb/>
Thus we could have them for permanent record. Their stories are short but afford<lb/>
an interesting sidelight on the official records. I hope to finish my editing of<lb/>
their stories this year and submit them for publication.</p>
<p>My trip to Havana was merely to meet Moran, iron out some of these differ-<lb/>
ences and visit &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;. You know what came out of that visit. Moran and<lb/>
Kissinger both insisted that I write up, not their stories, but the &ldquo;true version&rdquo;<lb/>
of the whole affair because so many false versions have appeared and especially<lb/>
because the Cubans have rather successfully launched a campaign to enhance Finlay.<lb/>
In so doing they have deliberately minimized (to the point of almost completely ig-<lb/>
noring it) the role of the U. S. Army board. Again in my role of a dispassionate<lb/>
disinterested outsider I can see some justification in the Cuban attitude. Fin-<lb/>
lay's contribution was ignored too much by the Americans especially by Carroll<lb/>
who, I believe, went too far in criticizing Finlay. Then when Agramonte tried to<lb/>
act as peace-maker and defended Finlay (A.M.A., June 13, 1903, p. 1660, letter)<lb/>
ill-will flared up between Carroll and Agramonte, or at least between the defenders<lb/>
of each.</p>
<p>I have uncovered so much of interest that was never published (aside from<lb/>
your most valuable true version of Lazear's death) that I have enough material for<lb/>
a monograph. When and how I shall publish it I don't know. My first job was to<lb/>
prepare the W. and J. address. That admittedly had a pro-Lazear slant explained<lb/>
by my foot-note. But after all it was a Lazear dedication. My next job is to<lb/>
present to Secretary Ramos of the Cuban Government our documentary evidence re<lb/>
the true site of Camp Lazear. That will be done between now and March when I plan<lb/>
to revisit Havana, again inspect the remnants of Building #1 and make final arrange-<lb/>
ments for its preservation. My third job is to edit and publish the stories of<lb/>
Moran and Kissinger. I hope to do this in 1941 also. My last job is to get to-<lb/>
gether all the material I have (and some I am still trying to get) and put it out<lb/>
as a small monograph.</p>
<p>Thus, in a very small way, the role of medical historian has been thrust<lb/>
upon me. But my sole policy is this: to <hi>glorify</hi>, not villify, <hi>all</hi> those concerned<lb/>
<hi>directly</hi> or <hi>indirectly</hi> with the conquest of yellow fever--from Finlay to Sawyer,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06301058"/>
4.<lb/>
most assuredly including Generals Wood, Kean and Truby. I intend to glorify<lb/>
<hi>all</hi>, and while I must naturally give the respective contributions of each I will<lb/>
not praise one to the detriment of another. Each had his role, each took part in<lb/>
a glorious event. I shall appraise each, not <hi>comparatively,</hi> but on the basis of<lb/>
how well each man carried out the job assigned him. I shall ignore the unhappy<lb/>
later events. I shall not drag out on view the acrimonious debate between Carroll<lb/>
and Agramonte or between Carroll and Finlay. Those things occurred <hi>after</hi> the con-<lb/>
quest and did not affect the conquest. They are useful as background information<lb/>
but I will leave the dirt for <add>a</add> less happily-minded historian. I quite agree that a<lb/>
historian must be true to the facts but I believe that the merits of each man can<lb/>
be so presented that odious comparisons can be avoided.</p>
<p>This brings me to the first paragraph of your material where you do me<lb/>
the honor of asking my opinion as to the merits of Agramonte's contribution. I<lb/>
know that you have believed that he claimed more than he deserved and that, when<lb/>
all the others had died, he wrote statements that you are inclined to doubt and that<lb/>
he perhaps put himself unduly in the limelight. But to explain his later actions<lb/>
let's go back a ways. Let's remember that Agramonte <hi>earned</hi> his appointment to the<lb/>
board because of his interest in yellow fever and his researches on Sanarelli's<lb/>
bacillus as published by him in the Medical News, Feb. 10, 1900, work done in 1898<lb/>
et seq. Let us also remember that Agramonte's first assignment as a member of the<lb/>
board was to do the pathological work--an important job for in so doing it he had<lb/>
to present to Carroll the necropsy material in proper condition for bacteriologic<lb/>
study. Although fate decided that this work of Agramonte's should be much less<lb/>
important than Lazear's fiddling with mosquitos I can see that Agramonte had the<lb/>
right to feel that he was a full time member of the research squad, doing the job<lb/>
assigned to him. In view of the agreement of the board that their work should be<lb/>
reported in toto and considered <hi>always</hi> the work of <hi>the board</hi> and not of this or that<lb/>
man, I can see why <hi>Agramonte was upset when his role was minimized in O'Reily's</hi><lb/>
<add>The statements had not been been published<lb/></add>
(i.e. Gen. Kean's) memorandum to the President (Sen. Doc. p. 17). After all it<lb/>
was Agramonte who discovered the nature of the epidemic at Pinar and it was there<lb/>
that he and Reed (or <hi>Reed alone?</hi>) noted the curious incident of the one prisoner<lb/>
developing yellow fever, a point which favored a winged agent. These things alone<lb/>
would make me feel that Agramonte &ldquo;did his part&rdquo;. But there are other things<lb/>
which make me believe <hi>he had a lot more to do with the experiments than perhaps</hi><add>No</add><lb/>
even some of you who were there were aware of. (While I am entirely deferent<lb/>
to the opinions of the participants and those who saw the work, I must also examine<lb/>
the value of the written documents. I would never dispute you as to something you<lb/>
saw but you will permit me to suggest that some things may have occurred which you<lb/>
were perhaps unable to see because your duties kept you so fully occupied.)</p>
<p>Agramonte did his part as a member of the Board<lb/>
but this does not condone his statements that the assisted<lb/>
Lazear in his work especially in the Dean case, etc</p>
<p>Now why do I think Agramonte probably had more to do with the experiments<lb/>
than may have been apparent to you and others? My main reason is that, having<lb/>
read practically everything written individually and collectively by the board<lb/>
members and also the stories of others (Ireland, Kean, and Kelly, even de Kruif<lb/>
and Lamson) I found some important details in Agramonte's writings not found any-<lb/>
where else. In particular his Scientific Monthly article, Dec. 1915 contains data<lb/>
not found elsewhere. (1) Agramonte is the only one who ever actually named the<lb/>
site of the Camp Lazear. He specifically stated that it was &ldquo;on the San Jose farm<lb/>
of my friend Dr. Ignacio Rojas.&rdquo; Nobody else named the farm and it was my remem-<lb/>
bering this one sentence that led to the re-location of Camp Lazear last Spring.<lb/>
Mrs. Rojas didn't recall how the camp site was chosen but she did say that Agramonte<lb/>
and her husband were old friends. <add>(2)</add> On p. 234 of Agramonte's popular version he tells<lb/>
how the Spanish volunteers were first put to work &ldquo;picking up stones&rdquo; on the camp-<lb/>
site as an excuse for keeping them occupied while being observed under quarantine.</p>
<p>That was<lb/>
easy to do<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06301059"/>
5.<lb/>
This item is not mentioned in any of the scientific or popular versions of Reed,<lb/>
or even of the more verbose Carroll. And yet it is true because it is one of the<lb/>
first things Mrs. Rojas told me although she had never seen or heard of Agramonte's<lb/>
popular article. (3) Agramonte is the only one who published a detailed map of the<lb/>
interior of Buildings 1 and 2. Perhaps the others never felt called upon to do so<lb/>
but the fact remains that the events and details were so clear in Agramonte's mind<lb/>
even after 15 years (the article being published in 1915) that he was able to either<lb/>
dig up an old drawing or reconstruct one from memory. (Dr. Cooke says the drawing<lb/>
is essentially correct although both he and I believe the hole for the stove pipe<lb/>
was in the left, not the right corner of Building #1). (4) On Sen. Doc. p. 86 in<lb/>
the paper &ldquo;Etiology of Yellow Fever--an additional note&rdquo; by Reed, Carroll and Agra-<lb/>
monte it says, &ldquo;During each of Moran's visits (to the infected side of Building #1)<lb/>
<hi>two</hi> non immunes remained in this same building,&rdquo; protected by the screen, etc. In<lb/>
other places also. (Sen. Doc. p. 10 and 100) it speaks of these <hi>two</hi> non-immunes but<lb/>
on p. 99 (last sentence) it says, &ldquo;on the opposite side of the screen were the two<lb/>
&ldquo;controls&rdquo; and <hi>one other non-immune.</hi>&rdquo; Why this discrepancy? For some time it<lb/>
bothered me. It also confused Miss Hallock and Mr. Turner who wrote the pamphlet<lb/>
&ldquo;Health Heroes-- Walter Reed&rdquo; for the Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. in 1926, also<lb/>
a movie strip of the same story. In the movie strip they have <hi>two</hi> figures across<lb/>
from Moran but in the pamphlet (p. 21, figure 2) they have <hi>three</hi> figures all appar-<lb/>
ently in pajamas, separated from Moran by the screen. Now I finally found the reason<lb/>
for Reed's apparent discrepancy and again it was in Agramonte's fruitful story that<lb/>
I found it, nowhere else. On p. 235 (Scientific Monthly, Dec. 1915) the last sen-<lb/>
tence says, &ldquo;during this time two other men and <hi>Major Reed</hi> remained in the other<lb/>
compartment, separated from Moran only by wire-screen partition.&rdquo; Here then is the<lb/>
explanation--the &ldquo;other non-immune&rdquo; was Reed himself who apparently merely entered<lb/>
the room briefly for the purpose of observing Moran being bitten.</p>
<p>See Biograph of<lb/>
Gen Sternberg</p>
<p>These four examples indicate that the <hi>details</hi> of the experiments were<lb/>
not only known by Agramonte but long remembered and perhaps more clearly stated by<lb/>
him than by any one else. How could he have been familiar with these details and<lb/>
remembered them so well had he not been very close to the experiments, indeed<lb/>
probably a close observer and participant therein? When I visited Agramonte's<lb/>
daughter this spring and looked over Agramonte's notes and memoranda there was<lb/>
such evidence of meticulous care in them that I could not doubt their accuracy.<lb/>
I have Miss Agramonte's promise that I may go over them in much more detail when<lb/>
I visit her again in March. (She will not let them out of her house, naturally<lb/>
and I had only <unclear>too</unclear> little time to go over them last spring.)</p>
<p>So much for Agramonte's veracity but there is one thing that troubles<lb/>
me--an apparent <hi>contradiction by Agramonte himself</hi>. In the Scientific Monthly<lb/>
article p. 222 Agramonte tells about Carroll's inoculation and illness--apparently<lb/>
Lazear told Agramonte that he (Lazear) had inoculated Carroll. And on page 210<lb/>
Agramonte describes how Lazear talked to Dean in his (Agramonte's) presence. Thus<lb/>
we are led to believe that Agramonte knew all about the inoculation of both Carroll<lb/>
and Dean. But how can we make this version jibe with two later remarks of Agra-<lb/>
monte? (1) In a letter Agramonte sent to Finlay written April 12, 1905 but just<lb/>
recently published in the book &ldquo;Carlos Finlay and Yellow Fever&rdquo; by Dr. Finlay's<lb/>
son, Agramonte wrote (see p. 222, Finlay's book), &ldquo;He (Lazear) produced the first<lb/>
two cases of yellow fever <hi>unknown to the other members</hi> of the Board.&rdquo; And in<lb/>
Agramonte's unpublished speech given in 1902 on the occasion of a banquet to Drs.<lb/>
Kean and Gorgas I found this sentence, &ldquo;The one of us....who in fact performed the<lb/>
first successful inoculation <hi>unknown</hi> to his co-workers, Jesse W. Lazear, gave up<lb/>
his life.....etc.&rdquo; Now what does this mean? This last sentence about the first<lb/>
inoculation isn't too surprising. Agramonte never said he knew about Carroll's</p>
<p>Agramonte told the truth<lb/>
in 1902 -and in 1905<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06301060"/>
6.<lb/>
inoculation the day it happened. He only knew it later when Lazear told him<lb/>
about it. But in the previous place he says the first <hi>two</hi> cases were unknown to<lb/>
the board. That seems to contradict his statements that he was present when Dean<lb/>
was inoculated. Can we unravel this apparent contradiction? I don't know but here<lb/>
<hi>might be</hi> an explanation.</p>
<p>Kissinger's recollection to me was that Lazear put the mosquito on Dean<lb/>
while Dean was asleep--a completely unauthorized act. Others (Moran, Kean) stren-<lb/>
uously doubt this. Your manuscript shows that you were aware of these versions<lb/>
and that the absence of any squawk on Dean's part convinced you that the first<lb/>
version is incorrect. But supposing it were correct--I can see how Agramonte<lb/>
<hi>might have rushed to defend Lazear's</hi> conduct (Lazear was dead) and might have been<lb/>
so anxious to defend it and share any possible blame that he even &ldquo;remembered&rdquo; what<lb/>
didn't happen. I have absolutely no evidence--this is just a supposition on my<lb/>
part but in view of the fact that Reed's &ldquo;defense&rdquo; of Lazear involved &ldquo;forgetting&rdquo;<lb/>
(for the sake of Lazear's insurance) the data suggesting that Lazear's <add>was a</add> deliberate<lb/>
infection, I can appreciate that there was an <hi>intense loyalty between the members</hi> of<lb/>
the board so that each was apt to rush to the defense of any honorable conduct of<lb/>
another that might be not understood by non-medical authorities.</p>
<p><hi>NO<lb/>
Ask Kean</hi></p>
<p>I should like much to have your opinion of this possible &ldquo;explanation&rdquo; of<lb/>
mine. Probably <hi>it's the bunk</hi> and I don't plan to publish it anywhere. But the<lb/>
two latter statements of Agramonte certainly don't jibe with his former publication.<lb/>
(See later, also, Lazear's letter to his wife saying he <hi>had &ldquo;told nobody&rdquo;.</hi> True</p>
<p><hi>It is</hi></p>
<p>I can understand why Agramonte very specifically told in later papers<lb/>
what he had done in connection with the work of the board. But wasn't that a<lb/>
natural and perfectly fair thing for him to do? After all, he'd been misunderstood<lb/>
three times (1) Gen. O'Reilly's memorandum to the President unfortunately minimized<lb/>
Agramonte's contribution. (I understand that O'Reilly's note was really written by<lb/>
Gen. Kean based on data from <hi>Carroll</hi> who was the one really responsible for this<lb/>
slight to Agramonte. (2) In 1906 Donnally, and in 1908 Hemmeter tried to give<lb/>
Carroll all the credit and ignored not only Agramonte but also Reed. (3) The Cuban<lb/>
government itself consistently ignored Agramonte and has continued to do so. The<lb/>
Cubans consider him more or less a &ldquo;traitor&rdquo; because he defended the U. S. Army<lb/>
board when Cubans began to vilify it in favor of Finlay. In the patio of the<lb/>
Sanitary Dept. stands a splendiferous monument to Finlay with much writing on the<lb/>
pediment but not a word about Reed or even native-son Agramonte. Across the street<lb/>
in Finlay Park is another large statue to Finlay with four small busts adjacent--<lb/>
one to Delgado, Guiteras, Gorgas and Lazear - none to Reed or Agramonte. Just re-<lb/>
cently Secretary Ramos proposed that the <hi>group</hi> of hospital buildings at the<lb/>
Military Center be named the Agramonte General Army Hospital or some such name but<lb/>
since each building has its own name one never hears the group name and Miss Agramonte<lb/>
told me as far as she knew no formal dedication of the buildings under that name<lb/>
has taken place--at least if it did she wasn't invited!</p>
<p>At that time Kean<lb/>
knew what I knew.<lb/>
Of course he did not<lb/>
approve of Carrolls false statements</p>
<p>Reed and Carroll wrote two or three papers later without Agramonte's<lb/>
assistance or co-authorship, (e.g. Prevention of Yellow Fever, Med. Record, Oct.<lb/>
26, 1901; Etiology of Yellow Fever--Supplementary Note. Amer. Med. Feb. 22, 1902).<lb/>
I have no doubt this was entirely O.K.--after all the board wasn't then functioning<lb/>
as a board and Reed couldn't well send his manuscript back and forth to Agramonte<lb/>
in Cuba. But none the less I can see how Agramonte might have felt &ldquo;out of things.&rdquo;<lb/>
And so, &ldquo;neglected&rdquo; by the Americans, attacked by Carroll's friends Donnally and<lb/>
Hemmeter, ignored by his fellow Cubans I can see why Agramonte took the liberty<lb/>
of defending his position with <hi>no little vigour</hi> whenever he had an opportunity. But<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06301061"/>
7.<lb/>
as I read his paper and his statements as to his part I confess I read nothing<lb/>
that strikes me as boasting or selfish. Indeed he repeatedly disavowed any claim<lb/>
to heroism as in the manuscript (speech) I quoted, and as in his article in the<lb/>
Military Surgeon for Nov. 1930. He repeatedly praised Reed and especially credited<lb/>
Lazear. He went to the defense of the board (not <add>just</add> of himself) in his reply to H.H.<lb/>
Donnally (The Relation of Members of the Faculty of the George Washington Univer-<lb/>
sity to Yellow Fever Investigations, George Washington University Publications,<lb/>
Medical Science Series, Vol. 1, No. 7, pp. 51-63, Nov. 1906). I enclose a copy<lb/>
of a letter from Agramonte to Hemmeter (see the latter's attack on Agramonte and<lb/>
praise for Carroll in Janus, 1908).</p>
<p>Yes</p>
<p>of course</p>
<p>But he not only defended the board as a whole against those who favored<lb/>
Finlay as against the board, or who favored Carroll as against Reed and the others;<lb/>
he also defended Finlay when Carroll attacked him too vigorously (see A.M.A.,<lb/>
June 13, 1903, pp. 1661, also Agramonte's paper En Honor de la Verdad in Revista<lb/>
med. Cubana, Dec. 1904.</p>
<p>In summary I think that Agramonte was much more sinned against than a<lb/>
sinner. He has been cut off by the Cubans. It seems unfair to have this generation<lb/>
of Americans treat him similarly. I believe that we can <hi>afford to be generous,</hi><lb/>
as two wrongs won't make a right. I believe that probably most of what he wrote<lb/>
(if not all) was absolutely the truth and that if he can be caught in any errors<lb/>
they were errors which <hi>slipped into his writings</hi> amidst the heat of debate, as he<lb/>
was certainly provoked to defense.</p>
<p>Yes<lb/>
No-</p>
<p>In treating of him in your autobiography may I suggest that you be<lb/>
<hi>generous within the limits of your actual knowledge.</hi> Certainly neither you nor<lb/>
I nor anybody should credit him for activities he didn't do, if we <hi>know</hi> he didn't<lb/>
do them. But when it is his written word against an opinion unsupported by definite<lb/>
facts I think the benefit of the doubt should be resolved in favor of Dr. Agramonte.<lb/>
I personally liked the spirit of dignified humility which I for one caught in his<lb/>
writings and unpublished manuscript. I would appreciate greatly knowing the basis<lb/>
for your ideas that Agramonte claimed too much and I assure you I will treat<lb/>
them confidentially as I suppose some of what I have written to you should be treated<lb/>
with discretion.</p>
<p>See my letter</p>
<p>Now may I proceed to make certain comments and ask some questions regard-<lb/>
ing your most informative manuscript.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. <hi>Your manuscript, page 3</hi> of the <hi>preface:</hi> You say &ldquo;Reed selected the<lb/>
members of the board.&rdquo; I supposed Sternberg did that. Sometime I'd like to know<lb/>
how the members came to be selected. Could you amplify this point?</item>
<item>2. Same page: You minimize Agramonte's work, indicating he was &ldquo;fully<lb/>
occupied&rdquo; otherwise and &ldquo;his services were never needed.&rdquo; As already indicated I<lb/>
am inclined to think he did much more than you were aware of. (Forgive me if I<lb/>
seem impolite in being so frank.)</item>
<item>3. Same page: You say &ldquo;with Agramonte absent in Havana, Reed completed<lb/>
the work.....etc.&rdquo; To an outsider this isn't clear. I suppose you mean &ldquo;With<lb/>
Agramonte downtown in Havana, Reed out in Quemados, etc.&rdquo;</item>
<item>4. Main part of manuscript, page 1. May I suggest you amplify details<lb/>
of your first meeting with Reed; describe his appearance, his bearing as an examiner<lb/>
(friendly or cold, etc.). I think this would be of interest. What were the inci-<lb/>
dents at the examination which aroused Reed's interest in you? It would not be<lb/>
immodest of you to emplify this.<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06301062"/>
8.</item>
<item>5. Main manuscript, page 3, par. 7. Could you obtain a photo of the<lb/>
Florida or another transport in Havana Harbor at that time and use it to illustrate<lb/>
your manuscript? Seems to me I saw some such photo in an old Harper's Magazine of<lb/>
the time or perhaps the War Department or Army Medical Museum would have such a<lb/>
photo. The scene arriving in Havana is a beautiful one. I've entered there two<lb/>
or three times by steamer and the last time via clipper plane--a glorious experience.</item>
<item>6. Same page 3, par. 7. You mention &ldquo;a sanitary order for the command,<lb/>
based on such knowledge as we had regarding tropical diseases especially yellow<lb/>
fever.&rdquo; I suggest you obtain it and abstract or publish (as an appendix or insert)<lb/>
that about yellow fever. It would be very interesting to see what these pre-mosquito-<lb/>
era instructions were. When was the &ldquo;British army wiped out in Havana?&rdquo;</item>
<item>7. Page 4, par. 8. Your regiment &ldquo;marched (from the docks) to Quemados<lb/>
about six miles west of Havana.&rdquo; I have seen this distance (Havana to Quemados)<lb/>
variously called 4 miles, 6 miles, 9 miles. I think it is about 9 <hi>kilometers</hi> or<lb/>
4+ miles. Could you state it accurately? Having ridden the distance several times<lb/>
I'd hate to walk it!</item>
<item>5.6 mi</item>
<item>8. Page 5, par. 10. Do you have any photos of Camp Columbia or of the<lb/>
Medical Hospital, officer's quarters, etc. Do you know where they could be found?<lb/>
They seem to be rare indeed. What was the condition of Camp Columbia as you found<lb/>
it--was it already occupied? What was on it previously?</item>
<item>9. Page 6, par. 12. &ldquo;An attractive hotel&rdquo;--which was it? It may still<lb/>
be standing and its identity would be of slight interest.</item>
<item>10. Page 7, par. 16. I'd love to see your own photo of the departure<lb/>
of the last Spanish soldiers. I think I saw some such photo in one of the army<lb/>
reports I looked through in the New York Public library.</item>
<item>11. May I suggest you insert a paragraph giving the set-up of the<lb/>
military establishment in Cuba. Until I read Gen. Kean's diary I was much confused<lb/>
as to the relative ranks and positions of the men involved. The non-military<lb/>
reader would thank you for a brief explanation.</item>
<item>12. Page 8, par. 18. Would it be of interest to note Reed's later<lb/>
unfavorable report re electrozone and amplify this part a bit?</item>
<item>13. Page 8, par. 19. Where was Gorgas' office? You say &ldquo;the army was<lb/>
establishing a hospital, to be known as &ldquo;Military Hospital No. 1.&rdquo; Wouldn't it<lb/>
be more correct to say &ldquo;the army was taking over the old ______________ hospital and<lb/>
setting it up as the re-named &ldquo;Military Hospital #1.&rdquo; In the Reports of the Gov.<lb/>
Gen. of Cuba I found several army photos of Military Hospital No. 1. But there<lb/>
seemed to be two hospitals so labelled in the report. The photos and descriptions<lb/>
of the two do not agree. Have you seen these reports and photos? Your help in<lb/>
identifying them correctly would be much appreciated. If you don't know the<lb/>
reports I'll look up the exact reference and pages and send them to you. Perhaps<lb/>
they are in the San Francisco public library or at the Presidio. You speak of<lb/>
&ldquo;the vacant Spanish barracks&rdquo;--what barracks, where?</item>
<item>14. Page 9, par. 22. You note &ldquo;the regimental hospital&rdquo; but it isn't<lb/>
located or identified clearly. I take it it was not at Camp Columbia but in Vedado<lb/>
(see par. 12 page 6). Correction--I see on page 7, par. 15 that you had gone back<lb/>
to La Punta and you evidently refer to the same regimental hospital at La Punta<lb/>
noted in par. 13, page 6.<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06301063"/>
9.</item>
<item>15. Page 10, par. 22. Suggest amplify details of your first meeting<lb/>
with Dr. Finlay. How did he impress you, his character, appearance, demeanor with<lb/>
patients and Gorgas, etc. I believe when one puts quotation marks around a word<lb/>
as you have done (e.g. distinguished &ldquo;expert&rdquo;) it means a so-called or self-styled<lb/>
expert and not a bona fide one. To which kind are you referring on pages 10 and 11?</item>
<item>16. Page 11, par. 24. The general reader, even many medical readers<lb/>
will miss the significance of this paragraph unless you comment some on the &ldquo;great<lb/>
debate&rdquo; that was later to occur between Wasdin and Geddings and the army commissioners.<lb/>
I suggest you amplify, also identify the case (it is case 7 page 13 of Wasdin and<lb/>
Geddings' report) and state more clearly that they flatly called it yellow fever.</item>
<item>17. Page 12, par. 25. Do you still have Finlay's reprint or any of<lb/>
Reed's? They are most valuable and you must <hi>not</hi> discard them. I have been trying<lb/>
to purchase some but they are almost impossible to procure. If you have any, any<lb/>
medical library should be proud to receive it from you when you are through with<lb/>
it. (I can assure you the Mayo Clinic library - or I personally - would be most<lb/>
happy to keep them <hi>permanently</hi>.) Although you have mentioned Dr. Finlay several<lb/>
times you do not discuss him in any detail until this paragraph. Shouldn't you<lb/>
transpose this belated comment on him and put it on page 10 in par. 22? Have you<lb/>
gotten a copy of Finlay's son's new book --Oxford University Press, 1940--$4.00<lb/>
(114 Fifth Ave., New York City). Of course he claims that Finlay actually did<lb/>
produce several cases of mild experimental yellow fever. I'm sure you will be<lb/>
much interested in it.</item>
<item>18. Page 15, p. 31. I was at Plattsburg in 1916 and had the pleasure of<lb/>
meeting General Wood. He was in charge of the camp and everyone respected him most<lb/>
highly. It is a pleasure to read your comments on him but could you tell more as<lb/>
to why he was &ldquo;unpopular&rdquo;. Your brief explanation will not satisfy the non-military<lb/>
reader.</item>
<item>19. Page 17, p. 34-35. Do you have any photographs of the hospital<lb/>
buildings at Camp Columbia (aside from the model I found)? Any comments re Lazear<lb/>
or his wife. I believe this is the first time you have mentioned him but as you<lb/>
are now talking about Aug. 1899 I don't think you should mention either Reed or<lb/>
Lazear here unless you make clear what they were doing. The yellow fever board<lb/>
was not yet functioning. Nobody has told much about what either Lazear or Agramonte<lb/>
were doing prior to the formation of the board.</item>
<item>20. Page 20, par. 38. &ldquo;The yellow fever wards were across the railroad<lb/>
tracks.&rdquo; For the sake of proper identification can you be more specific? There<lb/>
is much confusion about this. Kissinger and Moran argued considerably as to whether<lb/>
these were all tents or wooden buildings. How many tents were there? How many<lb/>
patients to a tent? Were any wooden buildings later put up here? Kissinger<lb/>
thought he was cared for in a wooden building. You speak of railroad <hi>tracks</hi>. Can<lb/>
you be more accurate. You mean across the one railroad track (a single track) which<lb/>
connected La Playa with the main railroad. What relation did these tents or yellow<lb/>
fever &ldquo;wards&rdquo; (a confusing word when applied to tents) bear to the small wooden<lb/>
buildings across the railroad track in the photo of the model I sent you? Aren't<lb/>
you a little ahead of yourself here telling of Lazear's death? Why not save this<lb/>
till later? What were some of Ames' practical jokes? You intrigue the reader<lb/>
but don't satisfy the curiosity you arouse.<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06301064"/>
10.</item>
<item>21. Page 21, par. 40. Shouldn't you have used this description of Camp<lb/>
Columbia when you first mentioned the camp on p. 17? Pardon me for emphasizing it<lb/>
but you frequently mention a man or place not mentioned in your manuscript before,<lb/>
but instead of describing him or it then and there so as to introduce the person or<lb/>
place to the reader, you often wait to describe the object pages later. I think it<lb/>
would be better for the reader if you'd transpose parts of your paper to previous<lb/>
paragraphs.</item>
<item>22. Page 21, par. 41. Were the &ldquo;permanent&rdquo; buildings built yet or were you<lb/>
still using tents? When did &ldquo;Camp Columbia&rdquo; actually or officially become Columbia<lb/>
Barracks? I have never seen a photo of Columbia <hi>Barracks</hi> though I sent you photos of<lb/>
the <hi>tents.</hi> What relationship was there between the hospital you have described and<lb/>
the two hospitals in the photos I sent you (Hosp. 1st Div. 7th Army Corps under Major<lb/>
McDill, Mar. 1899; and Hosp. 2nd Div. 7th A.C. Major Brown, Apr. 1899). What was their<lb/>
anatomic relationship to your hospital? The casual non-military reader only thinks<lb/>
of one hospital at Camp Columbia.</item>
<item>23. Page 24, par. 49. You say, &ldquo;In May yellow fever started on General<lb/>
Lee St. This jibes with data in Gen. Kean's diary which states that between May 16<lb/>
and 31 yellow fever attacked Mrs. King, Mr. King, Sergt. Sherwood (who died), Marie<lb/>
Sherwood and Mrs. Sherwood--all living at #20 Gen. Lee St. Then yellow fever jumped<lb/>
to 102 Real St. attacking Pvt. Ballentine May 26, Pvt. Teeter June 1 and Sergt. Reilly<lb/>
June 4--all three living at #102 Real.&rdquo; Do you notice that Reed made a mistake about<lb/>
this? In Senate Doc. 822 page 94 Reed says, &ldquo;We saw the disease pass from #102 Real<lb/>
St. around the corner to #20 Gen. Lee St. (This is also in Med. Record, Aug. 10,<lb/>
1901, page 203.) Reed seems to have erroneously gotten the spread in reverse order.<lb/>
Of course he wasn't there at the time and I assume he got this data from Major Kean<lb/>
or someone else. Is this right? Why were these soldiers living in the town and not<lb/>
in the barracks? What determined their site of residence?</item>
<item>24. Page 26, par. 52. I noted in the various &ldquo;Reports of the Gov. General&rdquo;<lb/>
many photos--photos of almost everything with which the army was concerned: street<lb/>
repairing, bridge building, hospital changes, etc. etc., also barracks and camps. Do<lb/>
you have any idea where the negatives of these photos might be? They are not in the<lb/>
Army Med. Museum. I wondered if one could find photos of Camp Columbia etc. there--<lb/>
perhaps even one of the &ldquo;famous&rdquo; jail at Pinar del Rio where the lone prisoner got<lb/>
yellow fever. Such illustrations would greatly increase the interest of any manuscript.<lb/>
If you don't feel inclined to bother about tracing these down I'd be delighted to<lb/>
follow any leads you might give me. Should I write somebody in the War Dept., in the<lb/>
Quartermaster Corps or where?</item>
<item>25. Diagram--insert p. 26. If you want to be a little more accurate I<lb/>
noticed the model indicated 5 separate sets of steps to the officers quarters--one<lb/>
for each set of rooms apparently. Any photos?</item>
<item>26. Page 27, par. 55. Is Neate the man shown in the photos in Agramonte's<lb/>
Scientific Monthly, Dec. 1915 article. If not, who is he?</item>
<item>27. Page 27, par. 54. I have corresponded with Andrus. He is an invalid<lb/>
confined permanently to bed, but writes very well. His address--J. H. Andrus, 805<lb/>
Cooper St., Camden, N. J.</item>
<item>28. Page 29. Couldn't these paragraphs 57, 58, 59 be better arranged (in<lb/>
more accurate historical sequence)?</item>
<item>29. Page 29, par. 58. What was your impression (and Reed's) of Drs. Durham<lb/>
and Meyers? Although Reed &ldquo;showed them the works&rdquo; apparently they were not much im-<lb/>
pressed. Despite Reed's natural anxiety lest they &ldquo;beat him to it&rdquo; it is my recollection<lb/>
that about the time the board's first report came out Durham and Meyers published a<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06301065"/>
11.<lb/>
paper very wide of the mark, suggesting as I have said, that they hadn't learned<lb/>
anything from Reed.</item>
<item>30. Page 30, par. 60. Here and elsewhere you speak of &ldquo;the bachelor<lb/>
building.&rdquo; I know what you mean but I don't think the general reader will know.</item>
<item>31. Page 31, par. 61-62. It isn't fair to your readers to tantalize them<lb/>
with bits of this &ldquo;juicy morsel&rdquo; and then drop them with a disappointing thud. I<lb/>
suggest omitting it all or giving it with carefully disguised names, etc. etc.</item>
<item><p>32. Page 32, p. 64. Are you sure that what you have written here is the<lb/>
substance of your conversation with Reed at that time? According to Agramonte, Reed<lb/>
at this time had little faith in the mosquito idea--only Lazear believed in it. And<lb/>
according to Lazear's letters to his wife which I have seen (see my W. and J. talk)<lb/>
Reed was still bothering about Sanarelli's work, trying to disprove it (and happy to<lb/>
do so) but still on the lookout apparently for a germ. As Lazear wrote his wife<lb/>
Reed wasn't yet interested in the mosquito work which Lazear had already begun. Thus<lb/>
in Lazear's letter to his wife dated Aug. 23, 1900 (3 weeks after the trip you are<lb/>
just describing) Lazear wrote, &ldquo;I am more interested in this (apparently meaning the<lb/>
mosquito work) than in the yellow fever work (apparently meaning the bacteriologic<lb/>
work). Reed and Carroll have been at that for a long time and they have notions as<lb/>
to what we should do that I don't agree with. They are not inclined to attempt as<lb/>
much as I would like to see done. They are interested in the controversy with San-<lb/>
arelli and they think of that all the time. I would rather try to find the germ<lb/>
without bothering about Sanarelli. The malaria work (apparently meaning the adapta-<lb/>
tion of the malarial work to the problem of yellow fever) on the other hand is my<lb/>
own and they make no suggestions.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This is a very revealing letter of Lazear's and when considered with what<lb/>
Agramonte later <hi>repeatedly</hi> wrote that the board at that time was unenthusiastic about<lb/>
mosquitos (except Lazear) and that Lazear was pursuing the mosquito angle more or less<lb/>
&ldquo;unknown&rdquo; to his colleagues it indicates that more credit should be given Lazear than<lb/>
has been. For example, Lazear's letter to his wife written Sept. 8, 1900 (just a week<lb/>
before he took sick and just after Dean took sick) reads: &ldquo;I rather think I am on<lb/>
the track of the real germ but nothing must be said as yet, not even a hint. I have<lb/>
not mentioned it to a soul.&rdquo; (Does this mean not even to his colleagues? Probably).<lb/>
<hi>But</hi> this does not detract seriously from Reed's fame for it is agreed that the data<lb/>
at Lazear's death were per se insufficient and Reed brilliantly seized the data in<lb/>
hand and proved their value. But in view of this I think you are giving Reed credit<lb/>
he doesn't yet deserve (as of the date noted). Hence it seems doubtful to me that<lb/>
you are accurately giving an account of your conversations during this trip north.<lb/>
You infer that Reed was sold on the mosquito idea and expecting success any moment.</p>
<p>You are also antedating yourself in your statement in the last line (page 32)<lb/>
where you infer that already (as you were travelling north on the Rawlins, August<lb/>
2-8, 1900) Wood had approved the board's request to use volunteers. This wasn't given<lb/>
till Oct. 12 (see Kean's diary).</p></item>
<item>33. Page 34, par. 69. You give the personnel of the hospital staff and say,<lb/>
&ldquo;Dr. Cooke was a newcomer&rdquo; but you have already mentioned him several pages previously<lb/>
(on page 23).</item>
<item>34. Page 34, par. 70. Can't you amplify this. Do you recall what the<lb/>
gossip of the hospital was re Carroll's and Dean's illnesses. Is the official version<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06301066"/>
12.<lb/>
(and Agramonte's story) re Dean's inoculation correct? <hi>Was Carroll skeptical</hi> about<lb/>
the source of his illness; did he anticipate yellow fever or was he (as so many have<lb/>
said) surprised when he got sick (although I believe in a later paper he wrote as if<lb/>
he anticipated his illness and bravely accepted the chances with open eyes and full<lb/>
expectation of illness). He did not expect results-</item>
<item>Carroll was the one member of the board<lb/>
who took no stock in the mosquito theory.<lb/>
He did not want to be bitten however, and would let but one mosquito bite him-</item>
<item>35. Page 35, p. 70. &ldquo;But he admitted that he had been bitten by a mosquito.&rdquo;<lb/>
This is a most important sentence but needs amplification. Was Lazear admitting the<lb/>
mosquito bite he received on Aug. 16 (see Case 6, Table III--Sen. Doc. p. 62, also re.<lb/>
Lazear page 68) as one of the 9 original (unsuccessfully) inoculated persons, or do<lb/>
you infer that he was admitting <hi>another mosquito</hi> bite? <hi>Most important.</hi> Please clarify<lb/>
and amplify.</item>
<item><hi>36</hi>. Page 35, par. 72. What color was the notebook? Do you think there is<lb/>
any remote possibility that it is still in existence in the hands of, perhaps, Carroll's<lb/>
family?</item>
<item>37. Page 36, par. 73-74. I agree that the funeral data are of interest, but<lb/>
why not replace par. 74 and 75 so that the story of the funeral is not interrupted.</item>
<item>38. Page 37, par. 77. What cemetery was it and why was Lazear buried there?<lb/>
What was its name? Was it an army cemetery? I don't think it is there now.</item>
<item>39. Page 38, par. 80. Why did Lazear work two days when he was sick? This<lb/>
hasn't been clarified. Did he think he had yellow fever and was he working against<lb/>
time to get his notes fixed up (as some have said) or wasn't he sufficiently impressed<lb/>
with his illness to report it? Suggest amplify from your own recollections.</item>
<item>40. Page 39, par. 81. You infer that Lazear found &ldquo;XY&rdquo; in the wards and<lb/>
talked to him there. This conflicts with Agramonte's version as explicitly stated<lb/>
not only in Scientific Monthly article, page 210 but also in his letter to Hemmeter<lb/>
(see letter enclosed--page 5) where Agramonte concludes, &ldquo;This is how the second case<lb/>
was produced and all else is pure fancy.&rdquo; Unless you are <hi>sure</hi> that Agramonte is wrong<lb/>
I wonder if your obvious suppositions as stated here aren't weak. Where did Howard<lb/>
get the idea that XY was tricked? Perhaps from Kissinger for K insists that XY was<lb/>
asleep in his bunk after lunch (you recall this in my memorandum to you).</item>
<item>41. Page 41, par. 82. Did Reed really address Dean, &ldquo;My man.......etc.?&rdquo;<lb/>
One hears such conversations on the stage but it seems stilted and undemocratic and<lb/>
not even military.</item>
<item>42. Page 42, par. 83. Can you amplify your &ldquo;distinct recollections&rdquo; re<lb/>
Lazear's entries about mosquitoes applied to himself.</item>
<item>43. Page 43, par. 84-85. Shouldn't these paragraphs be a part of paragraph<lb/>
70, page 34. Wouldn't it be better to give the &ldquo;official&rdquo; (wrong) version on page 34<lb/>
and then the &ldquo;right version&rdquo; later on?</item>
<item>44. Page 45, par. 88. You should put the handwritten matter on page 47<lb/>
(re the visit of Reed and Kean to Gen Wood on Oct. 12) ahead of this story of your<lb/>
visit with Reed to Wood on Nov. 5 or 6. Obviously Reed had already seen Wood (with<lb/>
Kean) on October 12 <hi>before</hi> he went to Indianapolis, and as Gen. Kean has said in his<lb/>

diary (which I have seen) Gen. Wood <hi>then</hi> (Oct. 12) gave Reed permission to erect the<lb/>
camp. While he was in the U. S. Agramonte, Echevarria and Dr. Rojas completed the<lb/>
tentative arrangements to establish the camp on Dr. Rojas' farm. On Reed's return<lb/>
How did Echevarria get mixed up on this?<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06301067"/>
13.<lb/>
he approved the selection and your visit with Reed to see Wood on Nov. 5 or 6 was<lb/>
apparently a <hi>follow-up</hi> visit to tell Wood his plans, and it was not the original<lb/>
visit to get Wood's approval although doubtless Reed wanted Wood's <hi>continuing</hi><lb/>
approval. Am I correct? If so your introductory words in paragraph 88 (&ldquo;The next<lb/>
thing on Reed's program was to find a suitable camp site..etc.) are chronologically<lb/>
inacourate. This had <hi>already</hi> been done and that is why Reed could tell Wood of his<lb/>
plans re a camp <hi>near</hi> Quemados; it had <hi>already</hi> been selected.</item>
<item><p>45. Page 47, par. 88. Would there be any report on the erection of these<lb/>
two buildings in the Report of the Quartermasters Dept. to the Governor General? In<lb/>
the Governor General's Reports which I found in the N. Y. Public Library I saw evi-<lb/>
dences of such minute detail (plans for the erection of very small bridges, for small<lb/>
additions to hospitals, etc.) that I wonder if somewhere there isn't a report of these<lb/>
buildings? Do you know where I might find them or to whom I should write in Washington?<lb/>
Do you know where Agramonte got the drawings of the inside of the two buildings, the<lb/>
plans of which he published in 1915 (Scientific Monthly)? Do you have any idea<lb/>
where Reed's original drawings were? Miss Agramonte thought that her father had<lb/>
<hi>copied</hi> the drawings in 1915 from old ones he had in his possession but she couldn't<lb/>
find them when I was there.</p>
<p>Would the use of <hi>tongued</hi> and grooved lumber in any ordinary Cuban shack be<lb/>
unusual? The wood present in the shack we discovered is tongued and grooved, and two<lb/>
Havana engineers have told us that this is most unusual, that no Cuban shack would<lb/>
have been so built (therefore a strong point in identifying our shack as Building #1).<lb/>
Do you agree? If your detachment erected the tents, etc. at Camp Lazear did you or<lb/>
any superior make an official report to that effect? Would it be in any of the pub-<lb/>
lished reports to the Gov. General? Do you have any personal knowledge of what happened<lb/>
to the tents, wooden flooring of the tents and the wooden buildings?</p></item>
<item>46. Page 48, par. 88. This data (or some of it) re Carroll should be given<lb/>
previously, shouldn't it, where you originally discuss Carroll's illness. Do you<lb/>
know where Carroll convalesced? Did he leave Cuba?</item>
<item>47. Page 48, par. 89. Chronologically you have been talking about events<lb/>
in November. But here you insert data on Reed in October. Shouldn't this paragraph<lb/>
be used earlier in your manuscript?</item>
<item>48. Page 49, par. 89. The last sentences re Lazear should not appear here,<lb/>
but earlier.</item>
<item>49. Page 50, par. 90. May I suggest that each &ldquo;army abbreviation&rdquo; be<lb/>
explained to the reader, if your paper is to interest nonmedical and nonmilitary<lb/>
readers. Some may not even know what &ldquo;Q M corps&rdquo; means, or M C (medical corps). I<lb/>
don't know what &ldquo;G. I. can&rdquo; means. You say it means &ldquo;garbage can&rdquo;, does g.i. mean<lb/>
gastro-intestinal or galvanized iron or what? This paragraph regarding your collecting<lb/>
the mosquitos is most interesting. I believe Finlay (or perhaps it was his son)<lb/>
claimed that the mosquitoes used were all descendants of those he gave Reed.</item>
<item>50. Page 51, par. 91. To whom did Kissinger &ldquo;said he would like to volun-<lb/>
teer.&rdquo; &ldquo;<hi>Then</hi> Moran did likewise.&rdquo; Can you help me on this from your <hi>accurate personal</hi><lb/>
knowledge? Kissinger tells me he went to Reed alone. Moran insists he and Kissinger<lb/>
went together. Neither one recalls going to the particular (end) room of the group of<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06301068"/>
14.<lb/>
5 rooms in the officer's quarters. One thought Reed had occupied the second room<lb/>
(I believe). The other thought they had reported to Reed in some other place than<lb/>
the officer's quarters. Could this have occurred, if so, where?</item>
<item>51. Page 52, par. 92. May I ask the source of Reed's letter to the Surgeon<lb/>
General re Cooke. Did he use the expression &ldquo;terribly infected yellow fever building<lb/>
No. 1.&rdquo; If so he was purposely inaccurate because Cooke proved that it wasn't &ldquo;terribly<lb/>
infected&rdquo; at all. As you know Dr. Cooke is still living--I've corresponded with him.</item>
<item>52. Page 53, par. 95. Was there anyone actually <hi>in charge</hi> of the camp?<lb/>
Kissinger and Moran say no. Cooke was the ranking person who stayed day and night at<lb/>
the camp but as he was actually acting as a volunteer for the experiments Kissinger<lb/>
and Moran say Cooke had the status simply of one of the volunteers. On page 71 of<lb/>
Senate Doc. (paper by Reed, Carroll and Agramonte) it says &ldquo;The personnel of this<lb/>
camp consisted of two medical officers, Dr. Roger P. Ames, acting assistant surgeon,<lb/>
U.S. army, an immune; <hi>in immediate charge:</hi> Dr. R. P. Cooke, etc. Moran disputes this.<lb/>
He <unclear>said</unclear> that Ames stayed at Columbia Barracks and Moran never saw him at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Reed came out at least twice daily but there was no doctor in constant attendance. Is<lb/>
this correct? I will ask Dr. Kean this also.</item>
<item>53. Page 55, par. 97. You left Columbia Barracks, Nov. 30. How often<lb/>
did you actually visit the camp yourself?</item>
<item>54. Page 58, p. 100. I met Albertini several times. For reasons I haven't<lb/>
yet discovered he was <hi>not</hi> very helpful to me while I was in Cuba and has not even<lb/>
answered my letters since then. He <hi>must</hi> have known that the supposed site of Camp<lb/>
Lazear (as now marked) was wrong, yet he did and said absolutely nothing to help me<lb/>
in any discussions with Ramos et al. I can assure you I was diplomatic in my dis-<lb/>
cussions with these men, that is as diplomatic as one could be who was trying to tell<lb/>
them (and get them to admit) that a historical error had been apparently made in the<lb/>
&ldquo;selection&rdquo; of &ldquo;Camp Lazear&rdquo;.</item>
<item>55. Page 59, p. 102. This paragraph is misplaced. It should be on page<lb/>
56 or 57. I would <hi>love</hi> to see your &ldquo;letters, pamphlets, papers and photographs.&rdquo;<lb/>
Would you give me a hint as to what photographs you have. Do you expect to be home<lb/>
in March? I plan to go to Havana to conclude my investigations, etc. but might be<lb/>
able to go via California and the Panama Canal if I have the time and if you plan to<lb/>
be home.</item>
<item>If not<lb/>
this spring<lb/>
I certainly<lb/>
want to visit you sometime soon.</item>
<item>56. Page 61, par. 106. Wouldn't it make the paper more coherent to place<lb/>
this paragraph on page 55 and after finishing your comments on Camp Lazear, etc. start<lb/>
a new chapter on your experiences at Cienfuegas.</item>
<item>57. Pages 62-64. Wouldn't it be better to transpose some, if not most of<lb/>
these, descriptions of Wood, Gorgas, Kean and Stark to places earlier in your manu-<lb/>
script. Why not describe these men when the reader <hi>first</hi> meets each one in your<lb/>
manuscript, instead of describing the men piece-meal at various places.</item>
<item>58. Page 64, par. 112. &ldquo;He put up with our pranks.&rdquo; What pranks? You can<lb/>
enliven and humanize your story by giving some details here, also an example of Reed's<lb/>
attitude toward &ldquo;offenders.&rdquo;</item>
<item>59. Page 65, par. 115. Shouldn't this be put on or about page 54? I am<lb/>
glad to read this about Reed's plans for self-inoculation. In Cuba I found 2 great<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f06301069"/>
16.<lb/>
you probably were in the habit of saying that the ocean (and La Playa) were &ldquo;north&rdquo;<lb/>
of Camp Columbia (as you have it marked on your diagram) as a matter of fact the ocean<lb/>
and La Playa were <hi>northwest</hi> of Camp Columbia and your N-S arrow is erroneously marked<lb/>
on your diagram. This may seem to you like quibbling on my part, but if future histor-<lb/>
ians are to accept our findings of what we believe to be Camp Lazear and Building #1<lb/>
there is need for directional accuracy in both your manuscripts and mine. I would<lb/>
appreciate your reaction to these comments.</item>
<item><p>62. Re the model of Camp Columbia by Yldefonso Perez 1900 formerly in the<lb/>
U. S. Army Med. Museum, now and for some years in the Carlisle Barracks. Please re-<lb/>
call that the small photos I originally sent you I got from the Army Med. Museum.<lb/>
Major Davis there told me to write the C. O. at Carlisle Barracks. Brig. Gen. Roger<lb/>
Brooke, M. C., Commandant answered my inquiry thus: &ldquo;We have this model which has<lb/>
been in storage many years. It is encased in glass and may be taken apart; the base<lb/>
upon which the entire hospital is built has been sawed for shipping purposes, into<lb/>
2 squares and we are in doubt as to just how these squares should be fitted together<lb/>
properly. In order that we may send you the picture desired, can you let us have<lb/>
copies of the two pictures you have? The glass covering the model is 87 1/4 inches long,<lb/>
39 1/4 inches wide and 16 inches high and exactly fits the base. The model was made by<lb/>
Yldefonso Perez.&rdquo;</p>
<p>After I sent Gen. Brooke the U. S. Army Med. Museum photos they sent me the<lb/>
enclosed photos which are clearer than the museum's. But of course they perpetuated<lb/>
the mistake apparently made originally by the museum's photographers when they pre-<lb/>
sumably unpacked it after its journey from Havana to Washington. I wish you'd write<lb/>
on these what the buildings were and I think it would be more impressive if you'd<lb/>
write Gen. Brooke directly telling him of the error and I will write him also asking<lb/>
if he will put the thing together correctly and rephotograph it for me. It is most<lb/>
important as it is about the only detailed photo of Camp Columbia Post Hospital avail-<lb/>
able (even though the various buildings are crowded together).</p>
<p>Please compare your diagram with your identifications written on the two<lb/>
small photos of the model (please return these photos). Note you don't have the<lb/>
non-commissioned officers quarters drawn into your diagram. Note that you have marked<lb/>
the C.o's house differently in photos A and B. Also in photo A you have marked &ldquo;our<lb/>
morgue&rdquo; on one of the buildings which in photo B you have noted &ldquo;not there in 1900.&rdquo;<lb/>
Also in photo B you have marked &ldquo;road to post&rdquo; on the road across the railroad track<lb/>
which should be (as you have corrected it) going &ldquo;north&rdquo;. If that is so, shouldn't<lb/>
this be the road to La Playa and not the &ldquo;road to the post&rdquo;? As for the bridge over<lb/>
the railroad track Gen. Kean told me he remembers well that it was thrown over the<lb/>
track by the Engineering Corp for the convenience of the hospital corps to reach the<lb/>
buildings across the track (where apparently the yellow fever tent hospital was).<lb/>
What were these wooden buildings?</p>
<p>My only concern about your &ldquo;correction&rdquo; of the model (and I don't doubt<lb/>
that your correction is right) is that in photo A the model doesn't look as if it<lb/>
were exactly cut in half. That is, from the red letters A to B is 2 3/8 inches, from<lb/>
B to C is 2 5/8 inches, from C to D is 2 6/8 inches. Whether the two pieces of the<lb/>
model would fit accurately by turning the upper part on a hinge and correcting it as<lb/>
you suggest, is a question in my mind.</p></item>
<item>63. Miss Agramonte is most anxious to have someone's help in identifying<lb/>
the sites where the two enclosed photos were taken (please return them; they are my<lb/>
only copies). C 345-40 is of (R to L) Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte and presumably<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06301070"/>
15.<lb/>
criticisms of Reed. The outspoken criticism used by the Cubans to minimize Reed's<lb/>
work was &ldquo;Reed wasn't even in Cuba when Lazear and Carroll proved the correctness of<lb/>
Finlay's work.&rdquo; The answer to that is easy. It is unfortunate (for Reed's complete<lb/>
glory) that Reed had to go away at this crucial time but I agree that if Reed hadn't<lb/>
done the work at Camp Lazear their preliminary report would have been no more recog-<lb/>
nized than were Finlay's reports. The second criticism was handed out most carefully<lb/>
and was given out more as a hint than a frank criticism; it was that Reed never allowed<lb/>
himself to be bitten. I couldn't answer that criticism as I didn't know the facts.<lb/>
Recently Gen. Kean most kindly gave me a letter from Reed to him (Kean) and I was a<lb/>
bit disturbed to read the following: The letter was written in Washington and dated<lb/>
Sept. 25, 1900 the day Lazear died, although Reed hadn't learned this when he wrote.<lb/>
Reed wrote: &ldquo;He (Lazear) is such a good, brave fellow. I have been so ashamed of my-<lb/>
self for being here in a safe country, while my associates have been coming down with<lb/>
yellow jack. The General has suggested that I do not return, but somehow I feel that<lb/>
as the senior member of a board investigating yellow fever, my place is in Cuba, as<lb/>
long as the work goes on. I shall of course take every precaution that I can against<lb/>
contracting the disease, and I certainly shall not with the facts that we now have<lb/>
allow a &ldquo;<hi>loaded</hi>&rdquo; mosquito to bite me. That would be foolhardy in the extreme. You<lb/>
know that from the beginning of our work I have insisted upon the common sense theory<lb/>
of an intermediate host, such as the mosquito, being a carrier of the parasite of<lb/>
yellow fever but have said that <hi>human</hi> experimentation alone could determine the<lb/>
question.....Perhaps I owe my life to my departure from Cuba, for I had agreed to be<lb/>
bitten along with the others. Being an old man I might have been quickly carried off....<lb/>
I have engaged passage on the Crook which sails next Friday 28th and should reach<lb/>
Havana on Oct. 2 or 3. A matter of some importance--I shall expect to take up my<lb/>
old quarters next to Dr. Pinto provided you think that there is no probability of that<lb/>
being in an infected area. If so I would ask you to engage me a couple of rooms some-<lb/>
where in the vacant sets along the officer's line at Camp Columbia. I should <hi>prefer</hi><lb/>
to be in my old quarters however.&rdquo;</item>
</list></p>
<p>Obviously Reed changed his mind. In Washington knowing so little of the<lb/>
work of Lazear and Carroll Reed thought one thing but when he returned to Havana and<lb/>
having read Lazear's notes saw that more experiments were necessary, I can well believe<lb/>
that he threw aside the caution he expressed in his former Washington letter and<lb/>
decided to go ahead with self-experimentation. I think you can render very valuable<lb/>
service to Reed (to still the Cuban criticism) by amplifying your notes to show that<lb/>
Reed had no choice about leaving Cuba, that he was <hi>ordered</hi> to do so. Also can you<lb/>
tell me where you got this data indicating Reed's frequent desire to be inoculated?<lb/>
Was it from Andrus only? Can you strengthen it by data from other sources? Appar-<lb/>
ently you weren't at Col. Barr. at the time and got this data second hand.</p>
<p>Also please note Reed's remarks about his &ldquo;old quarters next to Dr. Pinto.&rdquo;<lb/>
Has your memory tricked you and was Dr. Pinto's room next to Reed's rather than<lb/>
yours as in the diagram you sent me, or does this mean that while you were in<lb/>
Guanajay Pinto took your room? I suppose the latter is the explanation.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Additional comments</hi></head>
<item>60. Page 47, par. 88. In speaking of the location of Camp Lazear you say<lb/>
&ldquo;such a site was promptly found southeast of Quemados and about one mile from our<lb/>
hospital.&rdquo; If you will consult the little map I enclose (C-708-40) you will see that<lb/>
the spot where we found Camp Lazear is southeast of where Columbia Barracks Post<lb/>
Hospital was, or as a matter of fact east by south, more east than south.</item>
<item>61. Please compare the little map (C-708-40) with the photostat copy of<lb/>
your diagram of Columbia Barracks Post Hospital grounds. You will note that although</item>

<pb n="1" id="f06301071"/>
17.<lb/>
was taken either at Las Animas or at Military Hospital <unclear>#</unclear>1. Do you recognize it?<lb/>
C-840-40 is of Dr. Agramonte on the right. Do you know who is on the left and where<lb/>
it was taken; i.e. do you recognize the building shown?</p>
<p>64. Please note how stubborn Dr. Angles is in his erroneous recollections<lb/>
about Camp Lazear. Note his letter. I think Gen. Kean plans to jog his memory but<lb/>
his letter contains many errors and because of his attitude I had much <unclear>difficulty</unclear><lb/>
in Havana.</item>
<item><hi>In conclusion.--</hi> I think your manuscript contains invaluable information and<lb/>
by all means it must be published in whole or in part, preferably in toto. I do think<lb/>
it can be arranged better. As noted it hops and skips about here and there out of<lb/>
chronological sequence. But doubtless this will be corrected in your subsequent manu-<lb/>
scripts. I feel highly honored that you will return it to me with all these handwritten<lb/>
notes by you and Gen. Kean. It will be a prized part of my collection and I thank<lb/>
you most heartily for it.</item>
<item>What plans do you have for publishing it? Can I help in any way <unclear>with these</unclear><lb/>
plans? There are a couple of medical publishers that favor historical manuscripts:<lb/>
Charles C. Thomas, Publishers, 300 East Monroe St., Springfield, Ill., and C. V. Mosby<lb/>
Co., St. Louis, I am sure either company would be happy to see it. I fear it is too<lb/>
long to publish in one of the medical historical magazines. The two best are Annals<lb/>
of Medical History, Dr. Francis R. Packard, Editor, 304 South 19th Street, Philadelphia,<lb/>
Pa., and Bulletin of the History of Medicine, Henry E. Sigerist, Editor, 1900 East Monu-<lb/>
ment Street, Baltimore, Maryland. Perhaps I am wrong, perhaps they would publish it<lb/>
in toto, but I don't think they pay for manuscripts and there would be no financial<lb/>
return on magazine articles. Would <hi>Military Surgeon</hi> publish it serially? Above all,<lb/>
I beg of you, don't let time or trouble discourage you from publishing it. If your<lb/>
<unclear>pep</unclear> or health should prevent you from finishing it may I <unclear>here</unclear> make this offer unre-<lb/>
servedly, that were you to hand over your data to me I would do my very best to finish<lb/>
it <hi>in your name.</hi> I hope you understand the spirit behind this offer. I find myself<lb/>
fast becoming a repository for data on the yellow fever work and am by way of becoming<lb/>
an objective historian (in contrast to a participant) of the events. The story has<lb/>
fascinated me so much that it is in my blood and I promise to keep at it till a real<lb/>
objective complete and accurate historical survey of it is done: I hope indeed that<lb/>
nothing will stop you in your efforts to publish your own personal story. Nothing in<lb/>
it detracts from my efforts and vice versa. Indeed each enhances the value of the other.<lb/>
I have not a single desire to profit from my own literary efforts with this one reserva-<lb/>
tion. If possible I would like to make a little on it, a few hundred perhaps, in order<lb/>
to help me erect a suitable permanent building over and around Building <unclear>#1</unclear> with suit-<lb/>
able markers, etc. If I can't collect this from friends and institutions perhaps at<lb/>
long last I might make enough on a book to help with this project. The deficit I<lb/>
am prepared to pay out of my own pocket.</item>
</list>

<p>Thanks again for everything and I will await your comments with eager inter-<lb/>
est, only hoping that mine have been of sufficient value to show how how <hi>greatly</hi> I<lb/>
appreciate the use of your data at the W. and J. ceremony.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Philip S Hench</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
