<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06306023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 19, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06306023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-08-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-08-19">August 19, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06306023</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 19, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench insists that in a historical painting, like the yellow fever painting, all figures should be identified. He suggests Carter and Ames be included.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-08-19">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, August 19, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06306023"/>
<opener>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-08-19">August 19, 1941</date>
</dateline><lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I will enclose for your interest a partial list of the data that I found<lb/>
in Washington and I hope to trace more of it down the next time I come. Perhaps<lb/>
I mentioned to you that I am invited to speak before the American Academy of<lb/>
Orthopedic Surgeons in Washington in January and I hope to spend two or three<lb/>
extra days in Washington at that time. I also enclose a copy of Bullard's story<lb/>
which I finally got around to write up. I thought you might be interested in it<lb/>
even though you may not have any comments or corrections to make. However, do<lb/>
you happen to know what the General Wood Laboratory was, mentioned on page 4?<lb/>
I am sending Mr. Bullard a copy for his final correction and approval.</p>
<p>I shall be delighted to do whatever I can in defending the Roll of Honor<lb/>
and I can assure you that I will take this obligation most seriously. I appre-<lb/>
ciate greatly the confidence you express in me to suggest this.</p>
<p>I am anxious to have from you, at your earliest convenience, your consid-<lb/>
eration of the following matter. When the yellow fever painting was first pro-<lb/>
posed, you will remember that it was my thought to avoid controversy by merely<lb/>
including the five top men--Finlay and the four members of the Commission. Others<lb/>
had definite ideas, in particular, General Truby, who wished to see if possible<lb/>
the entire group portrayed. Still others nominated Carter, General Wood and others<lb/>
for the portrait. Mr. Cornwell apparently compromised. He did not originally<lb/>
want a large group as he said it would be too stiff but finally he did include<lb/>
in a tentative drawing which he sent me, thirteen figures. In my correspondence<lb/>
with him and when I visited his studio in New York at his request, on my way home<lb/>
from Cuba, I tried to find out just whom all these figures were supposed to repre-<lb/>
sent. The figures of Finlay, Agramonte, Carroll, Reed and Lazear were obvious;<lb/>
also those of Moran and Kissinger. But they didn't really have any definite idea<lb/>
who the others were. Apparently they were just put in to lend action and balance<lb/>
to the painting. The mustachioed figure next to Moran on Moran's right was to be<lb/>
Jernegan. The reason Jernegan was selected was because he had a picturesque face<lb/>
as seen in the photograph of the hospital detachment on the stairs. I heartily<lb/>
agreed that Jernegan should be included because he submitted to practically every-<lb/>
thing given. I made the suggestion that the figure of one of the Cuban volunteers<lb/>
be inserted in an inconspicuous place and this was done in the later versions.<lb/>
So far as I know, neither Mr. Kellogg nor Mr. Cornwell had definitely identified<lb/>
the two figures seated with Carroll at the table, the two men on the porch railing<lb/>
or the additional soldier volunteer in the background on the right. Please do not<lb/>
misunderstand me. I do not wish to take undue credit and quite possibly others<lb/>
made the suggestion also but I insisted that in such a historical portrait every<lb/>
person should be identified and have a right to be there. Therefore, I suggested<lb/>
that both you (General Kean) and General Truby be included, that General Wood be<lb/>
portrayed and that Dr. Cooke at least be included. In pursuance of this suggestion<lb/>
the seated figure on the left became you (General Kean) and I showed Mr. Cornwell<lb/>
a picture of you which you had so kindly given me. I thought it most appropriate<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06306024"/>
General Kean&nbsp;&nbsp;- 2 -&nbsp;&nbsp;August 19, 1941<lb/>
<lb/>
that General Wood should be the seated figure pondering, with his hand to<lb/>
his mouth. Therefore, the shoulder insignia were changed and in Cleveland we<lb/>
discussed with Miss Reed and General Ireland how much change might have to be<lb/>
made to make this look like General Wood. Mrs. Ireland thought it already looked<lb/>
considerably like him and so Cornwell let it go. The figure on the left, between<lb/>
Finlay and Agramonte in the earlier version, didn't look like anybody but based on<lb/>
General Truby's photograph in the detachment on the hospital stairs, the portrait<lb/>
now is a pretty good resemblance of him and is supposed to indicate him. Which<lb/>
one of the figures in the upper right corner on the porch railing is supposed to be<lb/>
Dr. Cooke, I <hi>do not know</hi>. May I give you my frank opinion that Mr. Cornwell is not<lb/>
a portrait painter. I have been rather amazed to find how difficult it seemed to<lb/>
be for him to imagine how a person looked at one angle when he had photographs of<lb/>
a man from another angle. Mr. Cornwell has the tendency to make the persons in<lb/>
his portrait have rather bold, haggard features with high cheek bones, a thin face<lb/>
and lines which I suppose are meant to lend character to the face.<lb/>
It is the one in <unclear>whats</unclear>.</p>
<p>I just have the first colored proof of the painting. It is much better than<lb/>
the pictures but even so General Truby's and your (General Kean) faces are not as<lb/>
full as I believe they were. I imagine both the faces of Moran and Kissinger look<lb/>
older than they should have been but all I could do was to call this to his atten-<lb/>
tion and abide by the changes or lack of them which he made.</p>
<p>Now to the immediate necessity. The painting has already been reproduced in<lb/>
one newspaper with certain erroneous identification marks. It is to be reproduced<lb/>
in Hygeia and Kellogg was still in the mood not to identify at least three of the<lb/>
figures. When I told him that history would demand more accuracy than that he has<lb/>
now agreed to name these men and has suggested that I name them. I do not feel com-<lb/>
petent to do so without at least your help. Which of the two men on the porch rail-<lb/>
ing do you think looks most like Dr. Cooke? The other one remains unidentified. Do<lb/>
you think that the mustachioed figure which was more or less copied from Jernegan's<lb/>
portrait should be labeled in truth Jernegan (that is, the figure on the <hi>left</hi> of<lb/>
Moran and Kissinger)? Which additional soldier volunteer should have his name assigned<lb/>
to the man in the rear of the group on the right, that is, the man between Moran and<lb/>
the Cuban volunteer--or should we merely state that he is another soldier volunteer?<lb/>
Which if any of the Cuban volunteers deserves to have his name attached, or should<lb/>
we merely call him &ldquo;a Cuban volunteers&rdquo;? Kellogg was in the mood to have the one<lb/>
soldier volunteer in the rear represent Andrus for two reasons: (1) because he co-<lb/>
operated with Kellogg and Cornwell and (2) because he, according to his own story,<lb/>
took Reed's place and volunteered toward the end of the experiments when Reed in-<lb/>
sisted on utilizing an infected mosquito which would not otherwise be utilized. I<lb/>
personally am willing to let the Cuban and the additional soldier volunteer go un-<lb/>
named. I think Jernegan should be named and that leaves still for us to name <hi>one</hi><lb/>
of the two figures on the railing. Please send me your suggestions and comments<lb/>
at once as the key to all these figures must be published in Hygeia in their October<lb/>
issue. It occurred to me that Dr. Carter might be put in or perhaps Dr. Roger Post<lb/>
Ames should be the one.<lb/>
as one <unclear>drews</unclear> the picture</p>
<p>I am delighted that you and General Truby are in it. Both of you have modestly<lb/>
protested to me and signified your surprise that you are in but you both deserve<lb/>
eminently to be in and you should not feel self-conscious about it. I am delighted,<lb/>
General Kean, to have you send me the extract from the Annual Report of the Secretary<lb/>
of War, 1902. I did not need this to feel strongly that you should be in the painting<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06306025"/>
General Kean&nbsp;&nbsp;- 3 -&nbsp;&nbsp;August 19, 1941<lb/>
<lb/>
but I am most interested to have it.</p>
<p>I am sending a carbon copy of this to General Truby. I will write to Mr.<lb/>
Kellogg as soon as I hear from you and tell him of the erroneous title which the<lb/>
New York Mirror gave you.</p>
<p>You will remember that I sent you the enclosed picture given me by Senora<lb/>
Rodriguez-Leon (Miss Agramonte). Dr. Albertini has recently identified the figures<lb/>
as follows: from left to right, seated, Drs. Carlos J. Finlay and Juan Guiteras;<lb/>
standing, Drs. Alfredo Dominguez Roldan, Aristides Agramonte, Taylor, Antonio<lb/>
Diaz Albertini, and American visitor whose name he was not aware of, and Dr. Hugo<lb/>
Roberts, presently Chief of the Quarantine Department of Cuba. Can you concur<lb/>
in this identification? Please return the portrait to me.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P S Hench</signed>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
<seg>
psh:ds<lb/>
Since debating this Mr Kellogg phoned me from Jersey City<lb/>
this am. He must have our answer this next <hi>Monday</hi><lb/>
as the data must go to Hygena them &amp; it is also to be<lb/>
reproduced on the AMA as a colored insert.<lb/>
I suggest we 1) <del>at the</del> name Jernegan 2) Let the Cuban<lb/>
&amp; either US soldier go unnamed &amp; 3) moment<lb/>
perhaps Ames for the figure beside Cooke. Kellogg<lb/>
told me am that Cooke is supposed to be the<lb/>
man in white bend the porch rail - the other is the<lb/>
one we are to name.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
