<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06301121">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 27, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06301121</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-01-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Echeverria, R. F.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital # 1 (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>



<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>12 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-01-27">January 27, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06301121</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 27, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby provides detailed replies to the questions Hench posed about Truby's manuscript on the yellow fever experiments. He doubts the accuracy of Agramonte's accounts of the experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-01-27">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 27, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06301121"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
145 Laurel Street,<lb/>
San Francisco, Calif.<lb/>
<date value="1941-01-27">January 27, 1941.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Here is my reply to your long and much appreciated letter of Janu-<lb/>
ary 7th. I think my last two letters covered the dispute between Kissinger<lb/>
and Moran, and also my general opinion of some of Agramonte's claims.</p>
<p>The preface of my manuscript was intended for the readers of the pre-<lb/>
liminary draft only. I wanted to bring out a discussion regarding Agra-<lb/>
monte's claims to help me decide whether to tell what I know about his<lb/>
work with the board or not. You have seen from my letter to General Kean<lb/>
in 1936 that I agreed with him that we should not bring out the unfortunate<lb/>
details. However, there are many in the profession who want the truth.<lb/>
Someone will bring it up and I think that there are some still living who<lb/>
know more about the subject than I do. They may &ldquo;talk&rdquo; or again they may<lb/>
not. Your quotations from Agramonte's statements in the next to the last<lb/>
paragraph of your W. &amp; J. address may &ldquo;start something&rdquo; as they positively<lb/>
indicate that all of Agramonte's claims about helping Lazear in August,<lb/>
1900, especially in the Dean case, are false. It was not until 1908, after<lb/>
Carroll's death that Agramonte began to present statements which I can not<lb/>
agree with. The big question is, should they be brought out? I do not<lb/>
care to reopen the controversy, but on the other hand I can't publish a<lb/>
true and complete story of what I know, and what a number of prominent<lb/>
medical men want cleared up, without bringing out the facts.</p>
<p>As I see it, the problem is really up to you, as the historian, to de-<lb/>
termine, after a full and very careful investigation, just what should be<lb/>
done. So far, you have only &ldquo;scratched the surface&rdquo; in your investigation<lb/>
of this matter. There is much more information to be found, and quite a<lb/>
number of people to find and interview. I think you should do it, although<lb/>
it will take much time and patience. I will be glad to assist you in every<lb/>
possible way.</p>
<p>Your policy as an historian outlined on pages 3 and 4 of your letter is<lb/>
splendid, but in being &ldquo;true to the facts&rdquo;, you can't very well avoid an<lb/>
exhaustive study of the disputed points and stating your conclusions.</p>
<p>I am sorry you had to put so much time on that crude, messy and badly<lb/>
arranged preliminary draft of my story. I promise you that when it is done<lb/>
over it will be quite different. I will eliminate things about myself, for<lb/>
I am not looking for publicity. The small part I played was of some help<lb/>
to the Reed board, just as Stark's part was. If I had not succeeded Pinto,<lb/>
he would of course have done the same thing as Commanding Officer. Anyone<lb/>
would. It was just a plain duty and deserves no reward or publicity. If<lb/>
you do not mention any of us in your history it will not be considered un-<lb/>
just. The facilities furnished by the Government, i.e. those available at<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06301122"/>
Page two.<lb/>
the Columbia Barracks hospital, including personnel and equipment<lb/>
did make the Board's work possible and stress should be placed on<lb/>
that in any careful review of the work. I think it quite probable<lb/>
that Durham and Myers did not really get started because of poor facil-<lb/>
ities. Reed was an experienced officer of the Army, knew what he needed<lb/>
and how to get it. That is one reason why he chose to work at our hospital<lb/>
instead of in Havana or some other place. No other member of the board<lb/>
was qualified in that respect. They were Contract Surgeons (ranking in<lb/>
the order of date of contract) and none of them had had any Army experience<lb/>
in administration. Kean will tell you this. So much for that, now for<lb/>
replies to your questions: (The numbers refer to your numbered paragraphs)</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Perhaps it would be better to say that Reed selected <hi>the personnel<lb/>
he wanted</hi> as members of the board and the Surgeon General approved and re-<lb/>
quested the necessary orders. Naturally he wanted his laboratory staff,<lb/>
Carroll and Neate. He also wanted Agramonte as he had also been working on<lb/>
the Sanarelli theory and, as an immune, to do autopsy work). In the selec-<lb/>
tion of Lazear I think you will find that Reed went to Baltimore to see<lb/>
Prof. Welch and selected Lazear as the result of that conference. Kean<lb/>
can probably give you more definite information on this visit of Reed and<lb/>
Welch.</item>
<item>(2) Agramonte was pathologist and bacteriologist of Military Hospital<lb/>
No. 1 and also did all of the work of that nature required by the Chief<lb/>
Surgeon of the Department of Havana and Pinar del Rio. He did all of the<lb/>
autopsies. He was a busy man and no one was available to replace him. His<lb/>
services <hi>as a pathologist</hi> were never needed by Reed at Camp Lazear as there<lb/>
were no deaths. I differ with you in your statement in paragraph 2.</item>
<item>(3) The wording you suggest would make that clear. The whole sentence<lb/>
is bad and will be rewritten to make clear just what <del>Carroll</del><add>Agramonte</add> did at that<lb/>
time.<lb/>
<p>Remarks: Some of the information in the tentative preface should<lb/>
I think go into the main part of the story. An entirely new preface with<lb/>
a different object in view, together with an introduction by someone else;<lb/>
and a bibliography, are indicated.</p></item>
<item>(4) I had the details all written out in long hand, but crossed them<lb/>
off as immaterial and too lengthy. I still have the original and can in-<lb/>
clude it.</item>
<item>(5) Sorry I have none, but I have a photo taken from the deck of the<lb/>
Florida the morning we entered Havana Harbor. It shows some of our officers<lb/>
(8th Inf.) but it is not very good as the light was poor. Sun was still low.</item>
<item>(6) Our regimental sanitary order was drafted by me with the advice<lb/>
and help of the Chief Surgeon of the Camp at Huntsville. He was also of<lb/>
great help in seeing that I was well provided with medical supplies. I<lb/>
haven't a copy of that sanitary order, but can quote some that we had early<lb/>
in Havana. When I have time I will find out when the British Army met with<lb/>
disaster in and around Havana. It was in the 17th century.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06301123"/>
Page Three.</item>
<item>(7) On page 6 of General Wood's report for 1901 you will find the dis-<lb/>
tance from Camp Columbia to Havana given as <hi>6 miles.</hi><lb/>
9 Kilometers - approximately 5.6 miles, not 4+(6 miles = 9.6 K.)</item>
<item>I have<lb/>
this</item>
<item>(8) Yes, I have a few, including one of our bachelor Medical Officers<lb/>
qrs., taken from official reports. They will be a part of my finished mms.<lb/>
Don't want to send them to you, but you can see them when you come here. In<lb/>
par. 10, mms., I describe our first camp at Buena Vista which later became<lb/>
the Eastern End of Camp Columbia. The land was absolutely bare except for a<lb/>
dry short grass. From a short distance north of the main highway (Calle Real)<lb/>
to the Gulf the whole area was bare. From E. to W. the camp area must have<lb/>
been about 1 mile. From N. to S. there was a flat area about 1/4 mile wide<lb/>
and then sloped gradually to the Gulf. I will improve my description in the<lb/>
mms.</item>
<item>a few lone<lb/>
trees here<lb/>
&amp; there.</item>
<item>(9) El Trocha. Good meals with fine wines. The hotel was small and<lb/>
not attractive from the modern standpoint, but I think it was about the only<lb/>
one in Vedado. General O'Reilly lived there later.</item>
<item>(10) You shall see it. There were splendid photos in the U. S. pictorial<lb/>
magazines of the time, which I saw. They could undoubtedly be found in the<lb/>
Library of Congress.</item>
<item>(11) I have it and can include it.</item>
<item>(12) I suppose it could be found in the S.G.O., but the findings were as<lb/>
I stated in par. 47, page 23. (mms)</item>
<item>(13) At first (1899) it was in the same building occupied by General Lud-<lb/>
low and his staff. It was a modern looking building, close to the Segundo<lb/>
Cabo, and facing the Plaza. The Governor General's Palace was on the opposite<lb/>
side of the same Plaza. The buildings of Military Hospital No. 1 that I re-<lb/>
member were newly constructed by the U.S. It is quite probable that permanent<lb/>
Spanish constructed buildings in the vicinity were also used. Think I could<lb/>
identify the buildings in the photos you mention. The reports are probably<lb/>
not available in San Francisco as the fire in 1906 destroyed most of such re-<lb/>
cords. The 8th U.S. Infantry occupied barracks (Spanish) in various parts of<lb/>
the city, viz. La Punta, Maestranza, Belascoaine Bks, and one other, the name<lb/>
I have forgotten.</item>
<item>(14) The Regimental Hospital went wherever the troops went. The whole<lb/>
command was in tents. When the regiment moved the patients were placed in<lb/>
ambulances and immediately upon arrival at a new camping place the hospital<lb/>
tents were pitched and the hospital started to function.</item>
<item>(15) Will amplify on Finlay. We had many &ldquo;experts&rdquo; who were self-styled<lb/>
ones and generally they did <hi>not</hi> make good. Some of them were not even immune<lb/>
although they claimed to be. It was an oversight on my part to use the word<lb/>
and quotation marks in connection with Finlay. The word specialist would be<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06301124"/>
Page Four.<lb/>
better I think. Thanks for the remarks on this point.</item>
<item>(16) Will amplify and make this clear.</item>
<item>(17) I can't find the Finlay reprint. I have Reed's with corrections<lb/>
in his own hand writing. I know that they are precious. When I rewrite<lb/>
the mms. all subjects will be grouped together that are related. This<lb/>
could not be done originally as I was in too much of a hurry to have it<lb/>
typed for you and Kean. The typist could not take dictation and I turned<lb/>
my hand written pages over to her. It took her a week to do it. I have<lb/>
not seen Finlay's son's new book, nor Kelly's new edition.</item>
<item>(18) Wood was unpopular in Military circles because he was a young<lb/>
<hi>Medical Officer</hi> and his promotion from a Captain, M.C. to a Major Generalcy<lb/>
in the line over the heads of all senior line officers, was considered a<lb/>
bad precedent.</item>
<item>(19) Yes - Two of the Ward buildings, one of the bachelor Medical<lb/>
Officers buildings. Also a picture of a party of us in the moat of Caba&ntilde;a<lb/>
fortress. Lazear and his wife and my sister were in the group. I took the<lb/>
picture myself. It is not very good. I think my mms. tells all about the<lb/>
work of Lazear and Agramonte prior to their detail on the board. Perhaps<lb/>
I can amplify.</item>
<item>(20) Will be more specific about location of yellow fever hospital. The<lb/>
whole subject of the yellow fever hospital will be rewritten as I have ob-<lb/>
tained more detailed information from one of the men who was on duty there<lb/>
with Ames. His pet trick was to bring black vomit and other foul specimens,<lb/>
in large open mouth bottles (without cover), and let them stand in his quarters.<lb/>
When they became foul smelling he would place them on the railing of the<lb/>
porch. <hi>I had to stop it.</hi> Ames had a real sense of humor. His stories, how-<lb/>
ever, were usually of a foul type. Ames was fat and sloppy in his personal<lb/>
appearance. I would hesitate to put much of this in print. He was a good<lb/>
doctor, and while he belonged to the &ldquo;expert&rdquo; class, he was one of them where<lb/>
the quotation marks should be removed.</item>
<item>(21) I concur and will place things where they belong.</item>
<item>(22) This was covered in par. 35. Camp Columbia became Columbia Bks.,<lb/>
by Dept. orders, on July 22, 1899. That is about the time the new barracks<lb/>
were finished. The 8th Infantry moved into the new buildings in August, 1899.<lb/>
The bachelor building for Medical Officers had recently been finished when I<lb/>
arrived there. The 7th Army Corps occupied tents and its two hospitals, the<lb/>
1st and 2nd Division hospitals, were also in tents, but they had a few wooden<lb/>
buildings. The 7th Army Corps had left before I arrived at Camp Columbia in<lb/>
August, 1899. I think that the 2nd Division Hospital under Major Brown occupied<lb/>
the site that became the Columbia Barracks hospital. Several of the buildings<lb/>
we used were built for the division hospital. Among them Reed's laboratory<lb/>
and the long, narrow barrack-buildings shown in the Perez model. The three<lb/>
large hospital ward buildings were built after I arrived.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06301125"/>
<item>Page Five.</item>
<item>(23) I will explain this more thoroughly, but first I must be sure<lb/>
that it was Brown's or McDill's. I knew them both very well in later<lb/>
years. Reed's error was, no doubt, due to the fact that this sequence of<lb/>
events was probably not available in writing.<lb/>
<p>Department Hqrs. used a large number of soldiers as clerks,<lb/>
orderlies, etc. They were detailed for these duties by order. The most of<lb/>
them slept in their own quarters at the Barracks, but worked at Quemados.<lb/>
Married Non-commissioned Officers lived in town as there were no suitable<lb/>
quarters for them at the post.</p></item>
<item>(24) If any such negatives exist they are in the War Department, but<lb/>
it would take much time and real work to find them. This is true of many<lb/>
other valuable records that are buried there. At this hectic time the War<lb/>
Department would probably not make any effort to find them. Almost every<lb/>
department (Q.M., S.G.O., A.G.O., and Signal Corps) must have some valuable<lb/>
old records. It requires someone who knows what to look for and how and<lb/>
where to find what he wants. I estimate from past experience, that it would<lb/>
take a month or longer to make a thorough search.</item>
<item>(25) My photo of our quarters shows the steps very well.</item>
<item>(26) Will try to find that article and advise you.</item>
<item>(27) I frequently hear from him and know him very well. He was one of<lb/>
our youngest and brightest men. His memory is still excellent, and I find<lb/>
his information very valuable.</item>
<item>(28) I think so.</item>
<item>(29) I saw them at lunch time and have remembered them as typical Eng-<lb/>
lish scientists. I was especially interested then in their English accent,<lb/>
ways and clothes. What Reed's impression was at the time I do not know,<lb/>
but I can assure you that Reed took no chances when it became time to write<lb/>
his Preliminary Report. I believe that disaster met the two Englishmen in<lb/>
their work in South America. Someone told me in later years (I think it was<lb/>
F. F. Russell) that one of the two died while their work in South America was<lb/>
in progress. I have not seen the report you mention, but your suggestion<lb/>
that they &ldquo;hadn't learned much from Reed&rdquo; is I think pure conjecture. If<lb/>
you will look at the Preliminary Report where Reed, referring to an article<lb/>
in the British Medical Journal, <hi>September 8, 1900</hi> says:- &ldquo;Drs. Durham and<lb/>
Myers, to whom we had the pleasure of submitting Carter's observations, have<lb/>
been equally impressed by their importance&rdquo;. What I said about the haste<lb/>
with which Reed prepared his Preliminary Report can hardly be questioned in<lb/>
view of the evidence and the fact that most medical men thought that he had<lb/>
&ldquo;gone off half cocked&rdquo;. If Reed had not been hasty for the reasons given,<lb/>
I think you will agree that any scientific man, of Reed's calibre, would<lb/>
have gone on with the experiments before trying to submit a report.</item>
<item>(30) Will clear that up early in the text.</item>
<item>(31) I agree.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06301126"/>
<p>Page Eight.</p>
<p>Pinto might elucidate. He was there and in command.</p></item>
<item>(40.) I am <hi>sure</hi> that Agramonte is wrong. Ask Pinto. I do not know<lb/>
where Howard got that idea. Certainly not from me. I doubt if Kissinger<lb/>
knew anything but &ldquo;soldier gossip&rdquo; on this. <hi>Pinto again.</hi></item>
<item>(41) Yes. That was a very common way of addressing a soldier, in<lb/>
those days. It was usually said in a kindly way. I don't know how or<lb/>
when it originated.</item>
<item>(42) There were entries which could not be understood. Perhaps they<lb/>
were incomplete or no name given. I can not remember the details, but I<lb/>
know that some entries perplexed Reed.</item>
<item>(43) A good suggestion.</item>
<item>(44) I will rearrange and amplify on the many visits he made to<lb/>
Havana.<lb/>
<p>I am quite certain that the camp site was not selected until<lb/>
Reed's plans were perfected <hi>after</hi> his return from the U. S. November 3.<lb/>
Has anyone made a statement to the contrary except Agramonte? I don't<lb/>
know that Echevaria was mixed up in it at all. I think that General Kean<lb/>
can tell you that Reed was too busy getting his Preliminary Report ready<lb/>
to make any definite plans for future investigations until his return on<lb/>
November 3. Also see my remarks regarding this in par. 59, and Dr. Agra-<lb/>
monte's letter to Dr. Hammeter on page 5. Reed's visit to Wood on Nov. 5th<lb/>
and 6th was to report on his doings at Indianapolis and to tell him of his<lb/>
plans for further investigations, and whether his ideas met with approval.<lb/>
The camp site and equipment were definitely on his mind. Does Kean's diary<lb/>
say anything about the selection of a camp site?</p></item>
<item>(45) The Chief Quartermaster was required to account for all funds<lb/>
disbursed for such purposes and, no doubt, there was such a record. It<lb/>
might be in the Governor General's report for 1902. I haven't that report.<lb/>
It might be in the Chief Quartermaster's inclosures to his report for 1901.<lb/>
I haven't them either. They doubtless are available in Q.M. General's<lb/>
office. I do not know where Agramonte got the details. <hi>The two buildings<lb/>
were still intact in 1906 when our troops were again in Cuba.</hi> Agramonte<lb/>
could readily have gotten all the details on the spot or he may have had<lb/>
copies of the original plans. Copies may be available in the Q.M. G.O.<lb/>
You can readily see why Reed insisted on tongue and grooved lumber being<lb/>
used. I don't think T. and G. was used by the Q.M. in the construction<lb/>
of barracks or other buildings, except possibly for floors. Have <hi>all</hi> of<lb/>
the Camp Columbia buildings been destroyed? Surely some of the same type<lb/>
are still standing somewhere in Cuba. They were all alike in a general<lb/>
way. I am sure it should be easy to identify Building No. 1. I saw it<lb/>
built and was in it with Reed after it was finished.<lb/>
<p>Wrote Truby about this<lb/>
on a P. S. to my letter of Mar 18, 1941</p>
<p>We would not have been required to make such a report, as the<lb/>
buildings were not erected for the Post of Columbia Barracks. An entry<lb/>

about it might be found in the <hi>Medical History of the Post</hi>, if that volume<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06301127"/>
Jan 27, 1941<lb/>
Page Nine.<lb/>
can be found. I will give you a list of records that should be searched<lb/>
for, and where to find them, if they are still in existence. All Govern-<lb/>
ment equipment had to be accounted for. Consequently, tents, etc., were<lb/>
unquestionably returned to the hospital or turned back to the Q.M. Colum-<lb/>
bia Barracks. The tent floors and wooden buildings were probably aban-<lb/>
doned and left on the site <hi>with the consent of the property owners</hi>. Of<lb/>
course, I was not there and my views are only conjectures based on the<lb/>
army custom in such cases.</p></item>
<item>(46) Yes, and I want to amplify a bit on Carroll as some of my re-<lb/>
marks on him failed to get typed. I think he went to Washington to see<lb/>
his family, but have no dates on him, or his trip, except the date of his<lb/>
return. All this, of course, was in the official records of the hospital<lb/>
and they, too, should be searched for.</item>
<item>(47) Yes.</item>
<item>(48) Yes.</item>
<item>(49) There are so few abbreviations that they can all be eliminated.<lb/>
Finlay, and all others who say that, are wrong. I can prove it.</item>
<item>(50) Kissinger probably saw Reed personally. All I can state positive-<lb/>
ly is that Reed was deeply impressed by Kissinger's action and told us<lb/>
all about it. Then when Moran volunteered a day or two later he was keen-<lb/>
ly excited and happy. Kissinger may have gone with Moran when the latter<lb/>
volunteered. I do not know about that or where they found Reed. They<lb/>
could have found Reed on the porch of our quarters or at his laboratory.</item>
<item>(51) See Reed's personal letters to General Sternberg, published in<lb/>
Mrs. Sternberg's biography of General Sternberg, pp. 220-227. My quota-<lb/>
tion is correct except &ldquo;terribly&rdquo; should be <hi>horribly</hi>, see p. 227. The<lb/>
biography was published by the American Medical Association in 1920. I<lb/>
will ask for permission to quote from the letters, or to quote them in<lb/>
toto, if possible. They are most illuminating and will confirm much I<lb/>
have said and answer many of the questions you have asked me. Until you<lb/>
asked me this question I was not aware that you had not seen those letters.<lb/>
As I have said before, there is still much authentic information available<lb/>
but it must be unearthed. Reed was a very active correspondent all the<lb/>
time he was in Cuba. Many more of his letters should be found. It's up<lb/>
to <hi>you</hi> to find them. For example, the correspondence with Dr. Welch and L.O.<lb/>
Howard. Dr. Welch, undoubtedly, left his to the Welch Library at Johns<lb/>
Hopkins.<lb/>
<p>Mantha F<lb/>
Sternberg<lb/>
231 or 331 pp<lb/>
1920<lb/>
5<hi rend="superscript">00</hi></p>
<p>I have not written to Dr. Cooke, but may do so. How is his memory?</p>
<p>While Building No. 1 was not infected with yellow fever it cer-<lb/>
tainly was infected with all sorts of organisms from the decaying organic<lb/>
filth. At that time most authorities still considered yellow fever in-<lb/>
fectious, although at this time, (Dec. 16, 1900) Reed knew better.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06301128"/>
<p>Moran still insists that up to Dec 25, 1900 Ames was not in charge actually, &amp; was<lb/>
only there on a very occasional visit- not more than twice<lb/>
Lambert</p></item>
<item>Page Ten.</item>
<item>(52) Ames was definitely in charge as Reed states in the &ldquo;Additional<lb/>
Note&rdquo;. From Ames' most reliable <hi>helper</hi>, I learned that Ames stayed at<lb/>
Camp Lazear most of the time and that when cases developed and were trans-<lb/>
ferred to his yellow fever hospital he would visit them and then go back<lb/>
to Camp. However, he slept at the yellow fever hospital when he had a<lb/>
serious case there. I don't think Moran knew. Others should be ques-<lb/>
tioned. Of course, I knew nothing regarding this as I was not there.</item>
<item>(53) I detailed a Non-commissioned officer to take charge of the<lb/>
work of getting the camp in order. It was probably Acting Steward <hi>Cook</hi><lb/>
or <hi>Burton</hi> (See photo of H.C. Detachment). Reed gave them instructions as<lb/>
the work progressed, but I was there when other duties permitted. I<lb/>
can't say how many times I was there, but it was quite often. I saw the<lb/>
Camp well organized and occupied before I left at the end of the month.<lb/>
Ames was in charge and I believe he slept there at that time.</item>
<item>(54) I think I can explain why Albertini was not helpful to you.<lb/>
He probably never went to Camp Lazear more than once, or possibly not<lb/>
at all. Reed got his cases out of Camp Lazear as soon as Ames could make<lb/>
a diagnosis. The yellow fever board always saw the cases at the <hi>yellow<lb/>
fever hospital at Columbia Barracks</hi>.</item>
<item>(55) O.K. You shall see everything I have. I have indicated else-<lb/>
where what the photos are. I shall look forward to seeing you in March.<lb/>
Wish I could go on with you to Panama and to Havana. Both are old stamp-<lb/>
ing grounds of mine.</item>
<item>(56) O.K.</item>
<item>(57) O.K.</item>
<item>(58) I think so.</item>
<item>(59) Of course when Reed went to the U.S. in August, neither he,<lb/>
Lazear, nor anyone else expected the sudden results obtained by Lazear.<lb/>
Finlay had bitten many persons over a long period of time with practically<lb/>
no results. I can't see that there should be any reflection on Reed be-<lb/>
cause he was away at that time. Reed's letter to Kean (September 25th)<lb/>
comes as a surprise to me. He and General Sternberg had, no doubt, been<lb/>
overwhelmed by the news regarding Carroll, XY and Lazear, and they may<lb/>
have concluded that the &ldquo;theory&rdquo; was practically proven by Lazear's work.<lb/>
At that time they probably had no details to indicate that the first cases<lb/>
were not &ldquo;foolproof&rdquo;. When Reed returned to Cuba he soon saw that the<lb/>
evidence was not conclusive enough to definitely convince the medical pro-<lb/>
fession. Likewise he saw that the work would have to be carried on to a<lb/>
definite conclusion and that it was his job. When he returned from Indianap-<lb/>
olis (about November 3rd) he was ready to carry out the plans he had in<lb/>
mind. He wrote to General Sternberg on November 13th (see p. 222, Biography<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06301129"/>
Page Eleven.<lb/>
of General Sternberg), giving some of the plans and troubles. Please<lb/>
note that he states:- &ldquo;Have secured a good location&rdquo;, for Camp Lazear.<lb/>
While this is no proof that he selected the camp site, it is evidence<lb/>
in that direction. The question of taking the test himself was con-<lb/>
stantly on his mind, and while common sense told him it was &ldquo;foolhardy&rdquo;<lb/>
to do it (as he wrote to Kean) he felt morally obligated to take the<lb/>
test after he had reached the point where he could definitely show that<lb/>
the mosquito was the infective agent. He reached that point on January<lb/>
25th. I have more on this which I do not wish to put on paper, but will<lb/>
tell it to you when you come here. Will amplify my paragraph on this<lb/>
in the mms. I expect Reed's letter is confidential and not for publica-<lb/>
tion so I will carefully avoid any reference to it on its contents.<lb/>
<p>ask Truby</p>
<p>I was probably wrong about Reed taking the East End set of<lb/>
quarters after I left it to go to Guanajay. Reed's letter to Kean con-<lb/>
vinces me that Pinto must have had the center set and that Reed at that<lb/>
time had the set East of Pinto's. We changed around so much with chang-<lb/>
ing personnel and other conditions that I can not be sure. I do feel<lb/>
quite sure that when I returned to Cuba, on September 18th, that I felt<lb/>
that Reed should have the choice East End set and that I took the one<lb/>
next to Pinto's which Reed asked for in his letter. Ask Pinto.</p></item>
<item>(60) East by South of Columbia Barracks Hospital is better. I had<lb/>
no map when I wrote it.</item>
<item>(61) I still think our buildings in the Main Post, as well as at the<lb/>
hospital, faced N. &amp; S. This can only be determined by one of the old<lb/>
maps.</item>
<item>(62) This was covered in a recent letter of mine.</item>
<item>(63) Sorry I can't identify the photos. They looked more like the<lb/>
shacks around Military Hospital No. 1, than Las Animas. They were not at<lb/>
Columbia Barracks.</item>
<item>(64) I do not remember Dr. Angles.</item>
<item>(65) Thanks for your concluding remarks. As stated in one of my<lb/>
recent letters, I still have no plans about publication of the story. I<lb/>
see no need to hasten as I prefer to take my time and get doubtful points<lb/>
straightened out. Then if your investigations give credence to the main<lb/>
points it will really have some value. Your offer to help me is greatly<lb/>
appreciated, and when the time comes to consider publication I will wel-<lb/>
come your advice and assistance.</item></list></p>
<p>I have just found a reference (in an official report) to Major R.F.<lb/>
Echeverria, Surgeon U.S.V. On June 16, 1900, he was attached to the Dept.<lb/>
of Havana and Pinar del Rio in charge of a <hi>non immune</hi> camp. I think that<lb/>
previously he had been on duty with Gorgas in Havana. On June 18th, such<lb/>
a camp was established near Quemados &ldquo;for such persons as it was deemed<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06301130"/>
Page Twelve.<lb/>
necessary to move from their present place of abode&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Now a few remarks about Agramonte's letter to Dr. Hemmeter. I<lb/>
have never before seen Agramonte's letter and have never seen the<lb/>
article in JANUS, 1908 by Hemmeter, although I have heard something<lb/>
about it. I have also heard Hemmeter criticised for backing Carroll<lb/>
in his statements, not considered true. The statements of both Carroll<lb/>
and Agramonte can, I think, be readily proven as untrue in quite a<lb/>
number of instances. I will place an F on the margin of that letter<lb/>
where I think the statements are in error, and O.K. others. Please note<lb/>
especially Agramonte's statement in this letter of his (Feb. 2, 1913) about<lb/>
the establishment of Camp Lazear, &ldquo;upon ground selected by Major Reed and<lb/>
myself&rdquo;. You have stated somewhere, I think, that Agramonte selected the<lb/>
camp before Reed returned to Cuba on November 3rd. Personally I think,<lb/>
(but I do not know) that Agramonte had nothing to do with the selection<lb/>
of the camp. I think it was all done at General Lee's Headquarters by<lb/>
Kean and Reed, with the help of local Cuban residents, many of whom were<lb/>
employed at Headquarters.</p>
<p>F=False</p>
<p>Carroll's false statements naturally aroused Agramonte's ire, and<lb/>
then, Carroll having passed out of the picture, Agramonte made statements<lb/>
which aroused the ire of many people who knew they were worse than Carroll's.<lb/>
Please consider my remarks regarding this as confidential. I do, however,<lb/>
want you to have my views on this so you can go ahead and reach your own<lb/>
conclusions. You have now found Agramonte's contradictions <del>himself</del> in two<lb/>
things, (1) Selection of site of Camp Lazear. (2) His part in Dean's case.</p>
<p>You will get much information from the Biography of General Sternberg,<lb/>
pp. 213-227. In reading it over just now I found on p. 215 a statement that<lb/>
Kissinger was the <hi>first</hi> volunteer. I do not remember seeing that before and<lb/>
that statement was not the source of my information when I wrote about it<lb/>
in my mms.</p>
<p>I will have this typed as I think General Kean should have a copy and<lb/>
I want one myself. I think you will find it quite interesting and I hope,<lb/>
useful, just as I found your long letter of January 7th useful- </p>
<p>A list of records etc., to search for is attached.</p>
<p>For many years I have wanted to make a thorough search for all of the<lb/>
records myself for I knew how and where to find anything that still exists<lb/>
in Washington. My duties never permitted as it is a tremendous job. Old<lb/>
records of 40 years ago have been moved repeatedly as the various depart-<lb/>
ments have moved from building to building. Still, some very important<lb/>
things can, I know, be found. They should be found and their importance<lb/>
deserves that they be permanently preserved in the Archives Building or<lb/>
Army Medical Library. If I am ever again assigned to active duty in Wash-<lb/>
ington I shall undertake to find them myself, if no one else tackles the<lb/>
job. I don't think you could do it yourself and, as stated elsewhere, the<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06301131"/>
Page Thirteen.<lb/>
War Department has too much on its hands to undertake it now. I par-<lb/>
ticularly want to find the old sick and wounded reports, and the Medical<lb/>
History of the Post.</p>
<p>If you get as much pleasure out of this as I have in writing it,<lb/>
I shall be delighted.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Sincerely Yours,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
Enclosures:<lb/>
1. Your original, Jan. 7.<lb/>
2. Agramonte's letter to Hammeter.<lb/>
3. Angles' letter.<lb/>
4. List of Records to find.<lb/>
5. Revised list of men in H. C. Photo<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I have your letters of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 29<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-<lb/>
Am sorry you think you will not come<lb/>
out here in March. However, I realize<lb/>
you can't do it all at once.<lb/>
I was back at Columbia Bks in 1906<lb/>
for a very short time. <del>in 1906;</del> but was in the<lb/>
main post. Made one visit to the hospital<lb/>
and it was about as we left it in 1902.<lb/>
Your letter to Kean (Jan 12) was most interesting<lb/>
to me, Especially the part about Carroll. I<lb/>
wonder if you noticed my remarks (mms) about<lb/>
his being a &ldquo;physical &amp; mental wreck&rdquo; after<lb/>
his yf attack. It lasted for weeks and he<lb/>
was quite a problem for Reed and me too. I am<lb/>
very anxious to see his letters, I dont wonder<lb/>
(over)<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06301132"/>
AC<lb/>
T<lb/>
you thought they were queer- In so<lb/>
far as I know, nothing has been written<lb/>
about Carroll's condition. I mentioned it to<lb/>
my old Prof. of pathology (Juan Guiterao)<lb/>
<del>in 1906</del> when I saw him in Cuba in<lb/>
1906, and he said it was most unusual-<lb/>
Kissinger was, I think, the man who recieved<lb/>
the watch. I am sure it was by Reed's direction.<lb/>
I would like very much to see Kean's answers<lb/>
to the questionaire.<lb/>
Please tell Mrs. Hench that I am much<lb/>
flattered by the remarks about my photo.<lb/>
Forty years have, however, made some<lb/>
real changes. I am happy that they are<lb/>
not as bad as they might be.<lb/>
Very Sincerely<lb/>
AET<lb/>
Jan 31, 1941<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
