<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06306119">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, October 7, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06306119</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-10-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Louise Young</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-10-07">October 7, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06306119</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, October 7, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean enjoyed the &ldquo;Hygeia&rdquo; article and the reproduction of Cornwell's painting, of which he requests copies. He discusses some of the men on leave during the Yellow Fever Board experiments.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-10-07">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, October 7, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06306119"/>
<opener>
<dateline>2804 N St. Washington, D. C. <date value="1941-10-07">Oct.7 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr. Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>Believe it or not, the temperature for the last<lb/>
four days has had an average Max. of 92&deg;F and<lb/>
it is in the 90s this, the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day, while I write, but I<lb/>
have sworn by the Great Horn Spoon, (which is a yale<lb/>
oath which I acquired from my brothers-in-law) that I<lb/>
will write to you today- Mrs. Kean and I are concern-<lb/>
ed that you should have troubled yourself about the<lb/>
photo of my picture in Cuba- She says that the copy<lb/>
you send is just as good as the original and she<lb/>
is entirely satisfied with it. And she has no doubt<lb/>
that you have already returned the original and<lb/>
that I will come across it some day- Of this she<lb/>
is the more confident since I found in a drawer<lb/>
of my desk some unopened letters, one of them to<lb/>
her, with postmarks of Sept. 1 &amp; 2- I think they were<lb/>
stuck in there when my desk was being &ldquo;straightened<lb/>
up by some friendly but ill-advised hand, while I was<lb/>
sick about labor day- There was no letter from you<lb/>
in them however- How you can carry on your Rheumatism<lb/>
Review and all the other things you do is a source<lb/>
of wonder and admiration to me- Yesterday came<lb/>
the Hygeia with your excellent article and the colored<lb/>
reproduction of Cornwell's painting- It makes a very<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06306120"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
2<lb/>
<add>striking</add> picture and I feel much indebted, primarily to you,<lb/>
and then to Mr. Kellogg and the artist, that I should be<lb/>
included in it- I am sure that Gen. Truby feels the<lb/>
same way- I think you will bear witness that it was<lb/>
not due to any promptings on our part- As I wrote<lb/>
Truby recently I find from my diary that the Starks<lb/>
left Cuba on leave on <hi>Sept. 3</hi> on the transport <unclear>Roulingo</unclear><lb/>
(which Gen Lee called the Rollings from the way she rolled)<lb/>
He went on this same trip on leave also- The Starks re-<lb/>
turned on Oct. 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and were so away during a very impor-<lb/>
tant part of the Episode-</p>
<p>Col. Havard went on leave Nov. 14 and I took his office<lb/>
until his return on January 8, 1901-</p>
<p>Somehow Stark is not particularly associated in my mind<lb/>
with the activities of the Y. F. Board- He was a very<lb/>
clever and amusing companion and much interested<lb/>
in his professional work, especially on the Surgical side-<lb/>
He was a great talker and I think that Reed, tho. he<lb/>
was fond of Stark did not talk to him much of the<lb/>
things that he wanted to keep quiet- Truby will however<lb/>
know more about this than I do-</p>
<p>I am so much pleased at the pleasure that you found<lb/>
in Trubys narrative- It was my experience and Gen.<lb/>
Ireland's too that where we began it we did not<lb/>
want to put it down- When I write to him I will<lb/>
tell him what you say as it will give him great<lb/>
pleasure- To go back to Hygeia are they going to make you<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06306121"/>
3<lb/>
a bunch of reprints?</p>
<p>I think they ought to do so without charge, for the<lb/>
poor editing they did in scattering it, in little dabs,<lb/>
all through the number- It is worse than the Saturday<lb/>
Evening Post- Of course the Post has to count on its advertis-<lb/>
ing to carry it, but a magazine gotten out by the A. M. A.<lb/>
ought to be above that, just as it should be above having<lb/>
a nude female, rubbing her behind with a fake cure<lb/>
for steatopygia, on the front cover- It lacks dignity painfully.<lb/>
If, as I understood from the copy of one of your letters to<lb/>
Mr Kellogg, you are going to get a large lot of colored<lb/>
reproductions of the picture I would be very much pleased<lb/>
to have a few for family distribution - not the twenty<lb/>
or more that you mention but half that number - 8 or 10-<lb/>
I will see that General Ireland gets his copy of the<lb/>
Kodak snapshot of us together and returns it to you with<lb/>
his autograph- Perhaps it would be better to have<lb/>
him do this the next time he drops in and<lb/>
return them both together-</p>
<p>I have been going through my old papers from time to<lb/>
time lalety and discarding those that can have no future<lb/>
value- I shall think of you if I find any that<lb/>
refer to the y. f. Episode or any other that may be<lb/>
of possible interest to you- I read last night a<lb/>
letter from Dr. Juan Guiteras, written after the second<lb/>
intervention, ice which he shows the difficulties of<lb/>
establishing a two-party government in Cuba, which<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06306122"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
4<lb/>
I found of interest, as showing his philosophical mind<lb/>
and also for the find, and I think well deserved,<lb/>
compliment which he pays to the group of Americans<lb/>
mainly army officers, who ran the two governments<lb/>
of Intervention- The only scandal that I remember<lb/>
involved a postal official who came down to<lb/>
show the Cubans how to run their post offices- Gen-<lb/>
Wood had him Fried and sent to the Penitentiary,<lb/>
thereby incurring the wrath of the Senator from Ohio<lb/>
whose appointe'e he was- When the time came<lb/>
for Gen. Wood to have the promotion that was due<lb/>
him this Senator held it up- It was only by the<lb/>
valiant defence of the Sec'y of War, Mr Elihu Root,<lb/>
that Gen. Wood who was then in the Philippines<lb/>
won out. I do not know that I have ever<lb/>
thanked you for the Proceedings of the Mayo<lb/>
clinic which come to me every week and<lb/>
which I read with much interest- It is pleasant<lb/>
for me to get these glympses of where and how<lb/>
far the <unclear>Ulhaus</unclear> of Science are scouting-</p>
<p>Cant you arrange to send us down a chunk<lb/>
of cold air from Medicine Hot, or where ever<lb/>
it is that blizzards are made up your way-</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially Yours</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
