<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06301020">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 12, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06301020</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-01-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-01-12">January 12, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06301020</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 12, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby suggests several corrections for Hench's article. He maintains that Kissinger volunteered before Moran and mentions his plans to work on his own paper. He invites Hench to visit him.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-01-12">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 12, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06301020"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
145 LAUREL STREET<lb/>
SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA<lb/>
<date value="1941-01-12">Jan. 12/41</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your lengthy and most welcome<lb/>
letter (via. Air Mail) came this morning and<lb/>
I have also received the W. &amp; J. program and<lb/>
your letter of the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> <unclear>ult</unclear>-</p>
<p>I think one of my letters to you must<lb/>
have gone astray for I acknowledged<lb/>
receipt of the first W. &amp; J. <unclear>programs</unclear> you sent<lb/>
and also asked you some questions which<lb/>
I felt sure you would promptly answer-<lb/>
That was probably about the middle of Nov.<lb/>
As I had also sent you two letters<lb/>
which should have been awaiting your<lb/>
return from the East (About Nov 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>) I could<lb/>
not imagine why I did not hear from<lb/>
you. So I wrote again, early in Dec.,<lb/>
and then when I did not <unclear>hear</unclear> from<lb/>
you after about <unclear>13</unclear> days I was really<lb/>
disturbed. Then I wrote a Christmas letter<lb/>
to our grand old friend Kean and<lb/>
asked him what had happened as you<lb/>
failed to answer my letters. I think<lb/>
I told him, though, that I had received<lb/>
the W. &amp; J. program-</p>
<p>The brochure from W. &amp; J. has arrived<lb/>
and I am, of course, much pleased to <unclear>have</unclear><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06301021"/>
Ac<lb/>
T<lb/>
2<lb/>
it. I have been over it with a &ldquo;fine <unclear>bath</unclear><lb/>
comb&rdquo; and in your article, <hi>which is splendid</hi>,<lb/>
there are <del>a from</del><add>two</add> mistakes which should be<lb/>
corrected before it is republished, as I suppose<lb/>
it will be- Both occur in the quotation from<lb/>
my story:- (1) Lazear was taken sick on <hi>Sept</hi> 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> not<lb/>
<hi>August</hi>. (2) &ldquo;On the same day (Sept 18) his house<lb/>
was immediately sealed up <unclear>&amp;</unclear> fumigated.&rdquo; That<lb/>
really should read. On the next day (Sept 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>)<lb/>
or <unclear>better</unclear>, yet, change the <hi>preceeding</hi> sentence<lb/>
so that it would read thus:- <del>He was then</del><add>In the morning</add> (<hi>Sept 19</hi>)<lb/>
he was carried on a litter to <del>the</del><add>our</add> Yellow Fever hospital<lb/>
across the La Playa railroad track from the Post Hospital.<lb/>
On the same day (Sept. 19) his house was immediately<lb/>
sealed up <hi><unclear>&amp;</unclear> fumigated.</hi></p>
<p>When I telegraphed you a few days before<lb/>
you started for W. &amp; J. I perpetuated that error<lb/>
in dates as I had your <unclear>mms,</unclear> before me.<lb/>
Within a day or so I realized the error<lb/>
and wrote you about it (About Nov 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>)<lb/>
My retained copy of my m.m.s. shows the correct<lb/>
dates so I do not know how the mistake was<lb/>
made- Sometime I will discuss some of<lb/>
the other details of your article- I concur<lb/>
in almost all of it.</p>
<p>I did not know until recently that<lb/>
there was any controversy on between Moran<lb/>
&amp; Kissinger. I obtained Kissingers address<lb/>
from you hoping to get a few points<lb/>
cleared up, by him and he then told me<lb/>
of Moran's claims. Kissinger gave<lb/>
me no help and I think I told you<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06301022"/>
3<lb/>
ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
145 LAUREL STREET<lb/>
SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA<lb/>
in one of my letters how surprised<lb/>
I was at his <unclear>aparent senility</unclear>.<lb/>
However, I am prepared to convince you,<lb/>
later on, that Kissinger did volunteer<lb/>
to Reed first and that Moran followed<lb/>
him a day or two later.</p>
<p>Naturally I have not followed the<lb/>
various controversies. All I know about<lb/>
them is what I have picked up in my<lb/>
casual reading. Of course I have <unclear>devoured</unclear><lb/>
everything that came my way on the subject-<lb/>
Agramonte's letter to <add>Dr.</add> Hemmeter is most<lb/>
interesting. This and other inclosures,<lb/>
<del>I</del> (including photos). I will return as,<lb/>
soon as I can study them and write<lb/>
out my comments. I am awfully handicapped<lb/>
by not having a Stenographer. I could<lb/>
dictate by the <unclear>hour</unclear> on this subject. However,<lb/>
if you can read my writing without<lb/>
too much trouble it won't matter, for<lb/>
I, personally, have plenty of time to do it<lb/>
this way-</p>
<p>Your comments on my M. M. S. are fine<lb/>
and very much appreciated. I knew that<lb/>
many items were out of their chronological<lb/>
order and that the whole thing was very<lb/>
messy. On that account I hesitated to<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06301023"/>
Ac<lb/>
T<lb/>
(4)<lb/>
let you see it, but General Kean urged<lb/>
me to do so as he felt sure it contained<lb/>
much info. you wanted. When I received<lb/>
your first letter early in July '40,. I had<lb/>
the article written out in long hand. It could<lb/>
not be sent out in that shape so I had the<lb/>
parts about Lazear typed and sent to you.<lb/>
Then Kean urged me to have it typed<lb/>
so that he could see it. He said that he<lb/>
was 80 and that life at that age was uncertain.<lb/>
So I had the original, <unclear>crude</unclear> thing, copied-<lb/>
Now with the benefit of your constructive<lb/>
criticism I can go at it again, and<lb/>
then with the help of a good stenographer,<lb/>
I think it can be properly arranged<lb/>
and dressed up so that it wont be too bad-<lb/>
The original mms. was much longer and<lb/>
I <unclear>eliminated</unclear> many things that I felt would<lb/>
be of no interest. I still have some of<lb/>
the original pen pages and when I return<lb/>
<del>my</del> your papers, will inclose the <unclear>part</unclear><lb/>
which <unclear>covers</unclear> your question as to why<lb/>
Walter Reed became a bit interested in me.</p>
<p>I have absolutely no plans about publishing<lb/>
my story. I appreciate your suggestions.<lb/>
I agree that our stories are entirely<lb/>
of a different <add>scope and</add> nature. You are the logical<lb/>
man to sift the thing out thoroughly and<lb/>
I am anxious to give you every possible<lb/>
help. I am not hostile to any of the<lb/>
people who are, <unclear>or</unclear> have been, mixed up<lb/>
in the controversies. I do know a lot<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06301024"/>
5<lb/>
ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
145 LAUREL STREET<lb/>
SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA<lb/>
about Agramonte and on that account did<lb/>
not want to write the story at all. I <hi>know</hi><lb/>
much more than I have told on paper<lb/>
and when I see you will give you<lb/>
an <unclear>earfull</unclear> (all confidential, however) Kean knew<lb/>
it, too, when he wrote O'Reilly's article for the<lb/>
Senate Document. There is no desire on<lb/>
my part to make any of it public, unless<lb/>
there is a real demand on the part of<lb/>
others, including yourself, for the facts<lb/>
as I know them. The things I know have<lb/>
not been distorted by controversies, discussions<lb/>
or anything else. They are as clear to<lb/>
me now as they have been since they<lb/>
were originally observed- No one was more<lb/>
shocked than I was when Agramonte<lb/>
began to talk (about 1908)</p>
<p>I know of no reason why I will<lb/>
not be able to see you out here in March.<lb/>
Of course I am still subject to call<lb/>
for active duty in the Army. I doubt,<lb/>
however, that I will be molested<lb/>
unless things get out of hand in<lb/>
the Medical Dept. If the War Dept. <unclear>starts</unclear><lb/>
off the main portion of the draft <unclear>until</unclear><lb/>
late spring I think nothing very important<lb/>
will happen. If, however, they fill up<lb/>
the unfinished camps with thousands of new<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06301025"/>
Ac<lb/>
T<lb/>
men during the next three months anything<lb/>
can and probably will happen- Everything<lb/>
will be new and the personnel all inexperiences.<lb/>
Under such conditions <unclear>epidemics</unclear> of severe<lb/>
influenza, <unclear>Cerebro Spinal</unclear>- measles, etc<lb/>
would rage-</p>
<p>I do hope you can come out here<lb/>
and if so plan to stay long enough<lb/>
to listen to what I can tell you and<lb/>
to see what I have. I have a few<lb/>
photos and other things that will <unclear>be</unclear> of<lb/>
interest and besides I think I can help<lb/>
you to find invaluable material in Washington.<lb/>
You must come!</p>
<p>In the next week or two I will work<lb/>
up the <del>question</del> answers to the questions<lb/>
in your long letter and mail everything<lb/>
back to you.</p>
<p>Again with many thanks for<lb/>
your very acceptable and comprehensive<lb/>
review of my paper,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Sincerely Yours</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
<seg>
P. S. I wont send this Air Mail as<lb/>
it is very stormy between here and Salt<lb/>
Lake, Planes may be grounded and<lb/>
not be any too reliable<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
