<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06302007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06302007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Angles, Eduardo</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-05">March 5, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06302007</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses a book he is reading about Finlay. He agrees to write a letter to Ramos.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-05">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, March 5, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06302007"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Washington <date value="1941-03-05">March 5- 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Dr- Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been reading casually from time to<lb/>
time in Dr. Francisco Dominguez's book <hi>Carlos J.<lb/>
Finlay Son Centenaire (1833) Sa Deconverte 1881</hi><lb/>
which is very well written-in french- and has a<lb/>
number of errors and many interesting things<lb/>
in it. I note on page 122 (I translate as I dont know<lb/>
what facility you have in french).</p>
<p>&ldquo;The American Commission, to make its experiments,<lb/>
established itself at Los Quemdos in the San Jos&eacute;<lb/>
estate where Finlay had formerly made his experi-<lb/>
ments and where in 1883 he had inoculated the Rev.<lb/>
Father Urra, a case which was seen by many doctors<lb/>
and accepted by all as positive for yellow fever-&rdquo;</p>
<p>I wonder if this is a fact- The son Dr. Carlos E-<lb/>
Finlay in his recent book, which you have, says (on<lb/>
page 82) that the Urra case was at a property owned<lb/>
by the Jesuits called La Asuncion- If it was a fact,<lb/>
it is odd that Finlay Jr, did not refer to it in his<lb/>
book- There is also an account in Dominguez's<lb/>
book pages 132-133 of the famous dinner given<lb/>
by the physicians of Havana in honor of Finlay<lb/>
to celebrate the demonstration of his mosquito theory by<lb/>
the Reed Board - My diary says that it was gotten up<lb/>
by Dr Guiteras, but he says that Gen. Wood proposed it, and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06302008"/>
2<lb/>
send Guiteras to him (Dominguez) asking him to join him <add>Wood</add><lb/>
in getting it up- At any rate it was a five occasion- Reed<lb/>
and his assistants were there and Finlay and of course<lb/>
Gen. Wood - Gorgas was there also and Dominguez<lb/>
evidently thought that he was the Chief Surgeon of<lb/>
Cuba and so states in <add>this &amp;</add> several places in this book. In<lb/>
fact however he was only the Chief Surgeon of the <hi>City<lb/>
of Havana</hi>. Col. <unclear>Valery</unclear> Havard was the Chief Surgeon<lb/>
<hi>of Cuba</hi>, but was at this time absent on leave in the U.S.<lb/>
and I was Acting Chief Surgeon in his place- It was<lb/>
for this reason, I suppose, that I was seated by Dr.<lb/>
Finlay at the dinner- The note about the drinner in<lb/>
my diary is very brief and does not mention either<lb/>
Dr. Dominguez or his presentation of the bronze &ldquo;La<lb/>
Pens&eacute;e&rdquo;, His account is also not complete in that<lb/>
it does not mention the praises given to Dr. Reed<lb/>
But the aim of the book is clearly to minimize the impor-<lb/>
tance of Reed's work- He has opposite page 192 a good<lb/>
picture of the Schuler bust of Reed which is evidently<lb/>
to bring in the inscription which names Reed as the<lb/>
&ldquo;head of the Commission that <hi>discovered</hi> and <hi>demonstrated</hi><lb/>
the transmission &rdquo; This sounded queer to me, so<lb/>
I phoned to find out what is the inscription under the<lb/>
bust which has been since 1934 at Walter Reed<lb/>
Hospital- The inscription is simply WALTER REED not<lb/>
a word more- Then I inquired what inscription<lb/>
is under the bronze replica, made also by Schuler at the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06302009"/>
3<lb/>
Army Medical Museum- That has <hi>no</hi> inscription, not<lb/>
even the name- So I was puzzled to find out<lb/>
where he got it, and finally got the Curator of<lb/>
the branch of the National Museum <add>on Independence Ave -</add> to see what<lb/>
he could find in his records- The bust was<lb/>
deposited there when first made- He finally<lb/>
found a photograph of it with a record of the<lb/>
inscription which Dominguez has quoted- So when<lb/>
I wrote to thank Dr. Dominguez for his book I men-<lb/>
tioned that I could not recall the inscription and<lb/>
on inquiry found that it had been removed<lb/>
from the bust, <hi>before the publication of his book-</hi><lb/>
I have written this out fully because you may hear of<lb/>
this tale in Cuba and I want you to be able to contra-<lb/>
dict it. Dr Angle's wrote me that this bust and<lb/>
inscription were at the Capitol - so I have set<lb/>
him straight on that also-</p>
<p>Before finishing the above the afternoon mail arrived<lb/>
with your big air envelope containing your letter to<lb/>
me of yesterday &amp; the copy of your letter and report to<lb/>
Dr. Domingo Ramos with the numerous photographs<lb/>
photostats &amp; so on- You have certainly not omitted<lb/>
anything in the way of evidence to convince him &amp;<lb/>
all Cuba of the correctness of your contentions-<lb/>
I will write the letter tomorrow to Dr Ramos and<lb/>
return the inclosures with that. This I will get off<lb/>
in a few minutes. I <del>would</del><add>will</add> send it by air mail<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06302010"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
I had a phone message from the Army Medical<lb/>
Museum this noon saying that they have found<lb/>
the contract between Walter Reed and Antonio<lb/>
Benigno which I had framed &amp; hanging on<lb/>
the wall of my office as Seey Mil. Surgeons-<lb/>
It was removed by some unknown person and<lb/>
a picture pasted over it so it could not be<lb/>
recognized when search cards was made for it-<lb/>
Col. Siler will have a photograph of it made<lb/>
for you.</p>
<p>You are a wonder! How you can do so<lb/>
much and so thoroughly I cannot imagine</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
