<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06302001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, March 4, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06302001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Rojas, Maria Teresa Loma viuda de</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06302001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, March 4, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Truby that he is planning a trip to Havana, and so would like Truby and Kean to write letters of introduction to Ramos.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-04">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, March 4, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06302001"/>
<opener>
3/6/41-Sent<lb/>
Clippings, <unclear>Come</unclear><lb/>
etc<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I plan to leave Rochester about March 21 and go (via a stopover at Palm Beach)<lb/>
to Havana, to be in Havana at the Hotel Nacional about the last week in March or the<lb/>
first week in April. I hope to interview the owner of the shack (Building #1) and make<lb/>
final arrangements for its preservation. But my immediate concern is to draft a final<lb/>
copy of my report on the true location of Camp Lazear which Dr. Ramos, Minister of De-<lb/>
fense, asked me to prepare. I have documented this report with about 50 exhibits<lb/>
(photographs, maps and photostated letters, etc.) Because I have quoted you and Gen-<lb/>
eral Kean so often I feel that I must submit a preliminary copy to you both so that<lb/>
I have your approval. I am also sending Mr. Moran a copy to show to Senora Rojas and<lb/>
to Senor Pogolotti. Because our photographic department is so busy at the moment I<lb/>
simply haven't had the nerve to ask them to make 5 copies each of these 50 exhibits<lb/>
(i.e. 250 prints) but if you will consult the list of them I think you will remember<lb/>
many of them as you have either seen most of them or I have sent them to you previously.<lb/>
I enclose a few prints which I don't believe you've seen. I am most anxious for your<lb/>
reaction to this report. If you agree with it <hi>in general</hi> (I can't ask you to vouch<lb/>
for every word I've said) would you be willing to write me a letter addressed to<lb/>
His Excellency, Dr. Domingo Ramos, Minister of National Defense, Government of Cuba<lb/>
and state that you have been familiar with my investigations, have helped me in much<lb/>
of it, have read my report to him and can give it your general approval (or whatever<lb/>
wording you think suitable). I will ask General Kean to do the same. I know that if<lb/>
I can <hi>send with my report</hi> these two letters from you and General Kean he will doubtless<lb/>
pay much more attention to it. But there is one hitch. I've been so busy I'm late<lb/>
now in getting this report done. Could you possibly review my report <hi>at your very<lb/>
earliest convenience</hi> and return it to me airmail special delivery (stamped folder<lb/>
enclosed) so that I can change it as necessary and try to get it in Dr. Ramos' hands<lb/>
by about March 15 so that perhaps he (or a deputy) can look it over before my arrival.</p>
<p>Of course I hope that the report will be accepted by Dr. Ramos and his colleagues<lb/>
and that some day (manana) they may act on it. But that is one matter, and the placing<lb/>
of this report on record is a more important matter. Whether they act on it or not<lb/>
I shall publish a synopsis of it (with Moran and Pogolotti as co-authors) in some<lb/>
American medical journal and if possible a Cuban journal also. I cannot tell you how<lb/>
grateful I am for all your help.</p>
<p>I hope soon to answer your last letters in detail but I have to write two<lb/>
medical papers in the next three weeks, one for an English journal and one for the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06302002"/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
March 4, 1941<lb/>
medical department of the War Department (a brief synopsis of current concepts on<lb/>
rheumatic diseases). Since neither is started I'll have to get busy. Permit me to<lb/>
send you a reprint of an article which just appeared.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
<seg>
P. S. How soon do you want the extra copies of my W. and J. talk? As soon<lb/>
as I return from Havana I will conclude arrangements to have it republished, at<lb/>
which time I can send you as many reprints as you want (at no expense to you, of<lb/>
course). If you want a few sooner all I can send you is photostat copies of the<lb/>
talk as it appeared in the W. and J. brochure as I could get no extra copies.<lb/>
You might return the report and photographs by ordinary mail at your<lb/>
earliest convenience but please airmail special your comments and suggestions on<lb/>
the report and the separate letter of general approval which I hope you will<lb/>
address to Ramos, and send me, enclosed with the report. Unfortunately, the War<lb/>
Department couldn't find the key to the 1902 map but I think I have quoted you<lb/>
correctly on what you thought the little buildings to the west of the railroad<lb/>
track were. In your last letter you spoke of the &ldquo;1900 map&rdquo; also of &ldquo;the original<lb/>
one in 1899-1900&rdquo;. Please see enclosed a letter from me to Mr. Freer, Chief Clerk<lb/>
of the Office of the Chief of Engineers, and his reply. Do you have any suggestions<lb/>
as to where we could trace the map I mentioned to him and the one you mentioned<lb/>
to me, or trace the key to the 1902 map? Would it do any good if you wrote to<lb/>
Freer or to the Chief of the Engineers? It seems to me, however, that he has<lb/>
probably done a very conscientious job of hunting.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
