<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06301001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 12, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06301001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-01-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Hutchison, Ralph Cooper</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Pogolotti, Luis B.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Louise Young</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Jose Farm (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Military Hospital # 1, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-01-12">January 12, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06301001</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 12, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench poses questions regarding the yellow fever experiments because he knows that Kean had connections with Reed.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-01-12">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 12, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06301001"/>
<opener>
Letter begun<lb/>
<dateline>
Sunday, <date value="1941-01-12">January 12, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have at last been able to finish and send off an 18 page single spaced<lb/>
typewritten letter of comments and suggestions re Gen. Truby's manuscript. Because<lb/>
you two have collaborated so often and because I am quoting you frequently in my<lb/>
letter to him, I am herewith sending you a carbon copy of it, and have told Gen.<lb/>
Truby that I was doing so. I am sure he would not object. I want to be sure I<lb/>
am quoting you correctly, and also it is likely that you may be able to answer<lb/>
some of the questions I have asked him which he might not be able to answer.</p>
<p>In particular I'd like your reaction to my argument that Agramonte had<lb/>
more to do with the affair than Truby believes. Also will you kindly note especially<lb/>
the following comments (numbered in my letter to Gen. Truby): 1-8-13-22-<hi>23</hi>-24-26-<hi>32</hi>-<lb/>
35-<hi>44</hi>-<hi>45</hi>-50-<hi>52</hi>-<hi>59</hi>-61-<hi>62</hi>-63. In reference to my comment 44 could you tell me who<lb/>
Dr. Echevarria was, his rank and job and how it happened that he mediated with Dr.<lb/>
Rojas in the leasing of the San Jose Farm for the site of Camp Lazear?</p>
<p>I enclose one of the photos which Miss Agramonte found and which she is<lb/>
anxious to have identified as to site. Do you recognize the little building?</p>
<p>I hope you received the W. and J. booklet with the various talks therein.<lb/>
I was entirely unaware that they were publishing mine. Dr. Hutchison had previously<lb/>
told me they had no place to publish it and it suited my purpose better anyhow to<lb/>
reserve it for medical literature. Hence I was surprised to see it published in the<lb/>
brochure sent out to alumni and friends of W. and J. I wasn't sent any proof--hence<lb/>
had no chance to out out the expression which you found objectionable (re Finley<lb/>
being slightly &ldquo;touched&rdquo;, an expression I copied from his son's own book). Nor did<lb/>
I have a chance to correct one or two other misspelled words (they had epidemiologic<lb/>
spelled wrong, also Pogolotti's name was missppelled). Also the data of Lazear's<lb/>
illness should have been Sept 16, not Aug 16.</p>
<p>Now permit me to send you some belated comments on your most interesting<lb/>
and valuable diary. As I read it I jotted down items therein which I thought it would<lb/>
be helpful for me to know. Let me number my comments and refer to the dates in<lb/>
your diary.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p>1. Aug. 14, 1898. You were &ldquo;relieved as medical inspector of the Second<lb/>
Division&rdquo; by being put in charge of the hospital at Camp Cuba Libre, Jacksonville,<lb/>
Florida. What was the name of the hospital and your rank and title?</p>
<p>For Keans additional answers see his long letter<lb/>
of Jan 23, 1941</p></item>
<item>2. Aug. 26, 1898 (addendum). You met the famous Typhoid Fever Board --<lb/>
Reed, Vaughan and Shakespeare. Had you met Reed before? What was he like then?</item>
<item>3. Fri. Jan. 6, 1899. What hospitals do you mean referring to those where<lb/>
Jackson worked and McDill erected? 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Division Hospital 7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Army Corps<lb/>
<unclear>interests</unclear></item>
<item>4. Jan. 26, 1899. Was this the first case of yellow fever you ever saw? Yes</item>
<item><p>5. Feb. 7, 1899. You mention Military Hospital #2, Vedado. I was con-<lb/>
fused by the photographs of &ldquo;Military Hospital #1&rdquo; in the various &ldquo;Reports of and to<lb/>
the Surgeon General&rdquo;. Please see comment #13 of my letter to Gen. Truby. Can you<lb/>
help me out?</p>
<p>My recollection is that Military Hospital No. 1.<lb/>
was the Spanish Army Hospital in Havana called Alfonso Treci<lb/>
(XIII)</p></item>
<pb n="2" id="f06301002"/>
<item>#2.<lb/>
No I think not</item>
<item>6. Feb. 25, 1899. You mention receiving a letter from Reed. Do you<lb/>
have this and other letters from Reed or other members of the Board? I would give<lb/>
a great deal to see them or be allowed to photostat and study them at leisure. It<lb/>
is amazing how much help I have already gotten about disputed points by being allowed<lb/>
to study a very few letters of Lazear (loaned me by Mrs. Lazear), Carroll (as published<lb/>
by Hemmeter in Janus, 1908) and a couple of Reed letters I've seen (yours and one of<lb/>
Gen. Truby). I strongly suspect you would hate to lend them to me even via the little<lb/>
tin box. Would it be possible to have them photostated for me (and for yourself) in<lb/>
the Surgeon General's office? I'd be willing to pay the cost if it weren't too much.<lb/>
If this isn't possible perhaps I may see them in your home sometime. Where was Reed<lb/>
when he wrote you the letter noted on this date?</item>
<item>7. Apr. 11, 1899. <add>He was still in his tent in <unclear>Cause</unclear> at Buena Vista</add><lb/>
I am not sure where the headquarters of Gen. Lee were<lb/>
at this time. Were they in the building on Real St. which I visited and photograph? <del><unclear></unclear></del> <add>see it below</add><lb/>
Where did you live and eat? Why was Gen. Lee street named after Gen. Lee when his<lb/>
headquarters were on Real Street eventually? I do not know date in March or April I think<lb/>
I lived &amp; kept house at 27 Gen. Lee St. until Nov. 29, 1899. Then Major <unclear>Edmunds</unclear> took the<lb/>
house &amp; died there of y. f.</item>
<item>8. May 4, 1899. &ldquo;Today Reed came out to lunch.&rdquo; What was he doing in<lb/>
Cuba then? He had been sent to Cuba to investigate an outbreak of<lb/>
typhoid fever at Puerto Principe in east Cuba</item>
<item>9. May 10, 1899. You mention the &ldquo;Toledo House&rdquo;. Is that the house on<lb/>
Real Street I noted in #6? You mean #7- Yes-</item>
<item>Probably news published - said all</item>
<item>10. May 26, 1899. Where is Reed's report published and what did it<lb/>
concern? The cases were typhoid not malaria or yellow fever- Reed <unclear>was</unclear><lb/>
sent down from wash to see- see my memo attached as to Reed's visits to Cuba-</item>
<item>11. June 7, 1899. You wrote to Reed, Where was he, in Washington? Yes<lb/>
<del><unclear>I find no reason in doing of writting to Reed on June 7- He was of want</unclear></del></item>
<item><p>12. July 17, 1899. In your published papers and in the margined note<lb/>
beside the entry of July 1, 1900 you say that when Reed called to see you sick of<lb/>
yellow fever June 25, 1900 yours was the &ldquo;first case of yellow fever&rdquo; that Reed ever<lb/>
saw. But here in your entry of July 17, 1899 you note that Reed who was again in<lb/>
Cuba (doing what?) called you to the hospital (what hospital?) to see a post-mortem<lb/>
on a case of yellow fever. Apparently he had seen posts of yellow fever cases before<lb/>
seeing you as the <hi>first living patient</hi> (?) with yellow fever. Is this so?</p>
<p>That not <hi>not</hi> Major Walter Reed but Capt. Reed who showed me the yellow fever<lb/>
case<lb/>
at Post Hospital</p></item>
<item>13. Aug. 2, 1899. What was Dr. Carter doing in Cuba? Is the correct<lb/>
spelling &ldquo;doherty&rdquo; as you have it or as Gen. Truby called it &ldquo;Dougherty wagons of<lb/>
Indian days&rdquo;? Speaking of this I understand Reed drove from Camp Columbia to Camp<lb/>
Lazear generally twice daily in a doherty wagon. Is that correct so far as you<lb/>
know? Of course that would only take about 15-20 minutes each way, but I under-<lb/>
stand you all often rode to Havana and back that way. It was a long, tiresome ride,<lb/>
wasn't it, being 9 kilometers from Havana to Quemados.</item>
<item>14. Aug. 18, 1899. Where were you living in Quemados on this date?<lb/>
27 Gen Lee street or <unclear>Cavojal</unclear> St. as it was called then</item>
<item>15. Sept. 10, 1899. The Carter mentioned here was not Dr. Henry<lb/>
Carter, I believe. No Major W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Fitzhugh Carter was in Med Corps of Army- He was a <unclear>cousin</unclear><lb/>
of Dr. Henry Rose Carter of the Marine Hospital Service now the Public Health Service</item>
<item>16. Sept. 13, 1899. Where was Dr. Ducker's &ldquo;yellow fever hospital&rdquo;? It was<lb/>
a small affair outside Havana in Gorgas's department- He was not in the Med Corps of Army</item>
<item>17. Dec. 3, 1899. You mention Gen. Lee's house in Maceo Street where<lb/>
you also lived. How many headquarters did he move into? He had only one Headquarters<lb/>
in Marianao after he left the camp- It was the big house on the Calzada Real<lb/>
which you know - the house in Maceo St. he rented for his family when they<lb/>
came down- The Hdqrs moved into the big house on the Calzada (Toledo House)<lb/>
on May 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> see p 115 of diary as I moved into the house on Maceo St. Nov. 29<lb/>
&amp; the Lee family on Dec. 2 1899- When they went to U.S. May 17, 1899- Gen. Lee<lb/>
and I then moved over to the Hdqrs at the Casa Toledo &amp; Took bedrooms upstairs-</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06301003"/>
<item>The plan for Reed to go to the Philippines was given up-<lb/>
I do not know who planned it or why it was abandoned- Gen Sternberg<lb/>
was a long student of yellow fever and greatly interested in it- He and<lb/>
Reed were the highest authorities on preventive medicine in the Army-<lb/>
Such a high authority as Victor C. Vaughan of <unclear>Aun Arbor</unclear> was <unclear>willing 3.</unclear> to serve<lb/>
under Reed on the Typhoid Board.</item>
<item>18. Dec. 15, 1899. You had a letter from Reed. Where from? You say<lb/>
he expected to go to Philippines and then &ldquo;return next November to Cuba to tackle<lb/>
yellow fever.&rdquo; I have never seen this statement before. It infers that it was<lb/>
Reed's original idea and not Sternberg's to do the yellow fever work. Is this<lb/>
correct? I gather that Reed was sort of a bacteriologic &ldquo;trouble-shooter&rdquo; for the<lb/>
U.S. Army Medical Corps. He was-</item>
<item>19. Mar. 10, 1900. Reed was in Cuba. How<del><unclear>a</unclear></del>was that, <add><unclear>see</unclear> above</add> did he go and return<lb/>
from the Philippines so quickly? I undertand he came to Cuba to study electrozone.</item>
<item>Reed came to Havana to determine the bacteriocidal value of electrozone March<lb/>
10-1900<lb/>
I have us record when he left but his stay was short, not over 2 weeks. I think-</item>
<item>20 May 27, 1900. You note the outbreak of yellow fever at 20 Gen. Lee<lb/>
St. and (in your entry of June 8) it spread to 102 Real St. Please see my comment<lb/>
#23 in my letter to Gen. Truby. Reed was in error in stating the spread the other<lb/>
way about, wasn't he? Reed wasn't yet in Havana; he got this data from whom? from<lb/>
you? Where were the &ldquo;isolation wards&rdquo; to which King was taken?</item>
<item>21. June 8, 1900. Please orient me as to the addresses of the victims<lb/>
listed here. I gather that cases 1-5 lived at 20 Gen. Lee St. What was the name<lb/>
and address of case 6? I can't make it out. Where did case 7 (<unclear>Ballentino</unclear>) live?<lb/>
102 Real St.? Apparently cases 7 and 8 lived at 102 Real and cases 9-10- and 11 lived<lb/>
at 89 Real St. was it case 12 <unclear>Hamberger</unclear> or case 13 Schenck who lived at 102 Real?<lb/>
Where were you living at this time? I am interested in trying to check the spread of<lb/>
the disease as given by you with the comments in Dr. Angles' letter (see enclosed.<lb/>
I believe I sent you one before; please return this one). I am glad to have received<lb/>
your correction of Dr. Angles' letter that it was Major and Mrs. Edmunds and not you and<lb/>
Mrs. Kean who got sick at #20 Gen. Lee St.</item>
<item>22. In your entry of June 14, 1900 you mention Carter H. C. Does this<lb/>
mean Dr. Henry Rose Carter; does the H. C. mean &ldquo;hospital corp&rdquo;? The story you told<lb/>
me about your secret visit to the front porch of Major Edmund's house was such an<lb/>
interesting human one, illustrating a conflict between the military man in you (ordered<lb/>
to keep away from the major) and the humans physician who scorned self-quarantine.<lb/>
I'd appreciate it very much if you'd be willing to write this out in detail and permit<lb/>
me to use it sometime. Surely it can do no harm and it redounds to your credit as<lb/>
a <hi>physician.</hi></item>
<item>23. July 1, 1900. Do you have any recollection of Reed's visit to you on<lb/>
June 25, conversation, etc.? I'd like very much to use later (in my monograph) what-<lb/>
ever details you can give me. It is very interesting to think that Reed saw you under<lb/>
these circumstances his first day on his mission. Where were you cared for?</item>
<item>24. Sept. 1, 1900. You lived at Columbia Barracks. I have found no<lb/>
photos of the Barracks except the one of the model of the Post Hospital and another<lb/>
one Kissinger gave me but none of the rest of the barracks. When, where and why did<lb/>
Godfrey commit suicide? Should this incident be kept hidden or is it generally known?</item>
<item>25. Sept. 3, 1900. How soon did you know the source of Carroll's illness,<lb/>
and of Dean's? Do we have the right to conclude from the letters of Lazear to Mrs.<lb/>
L., and from Agramonte's twice-stated remarks that the first one or two cases were<lb/>
produced by Lazear &ldquo;unknown to his colleagues&rdquo;) that Carroll had no expectation of<lb/>
becoming ill? How soon after Dean's illness did you learn the facts from Lazear or<lb/>
others? (I believe you wrote me this before.)</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06301004"/>
<item>#4.</item>
<item>26. Sept. 25. Your personal version of Lazear's death would be most<lb/>
interesting. When did you first hear that perhaps he had died from deliberate<lb/>
infection?</item>
<item>27. Oct. 7, 1900. When did you add the question mark at the end of<lb/>
your sentence &ldquo;This probably caused his death(?).&rdquo;</item>
<item>28. Oct. 13, 1900. You have described briefly in print your visit with<lb/>
Reed to see Gen. Wood but can you not amplify your written description? This visit<lb/>
was of considerable historical interest and I'd like much to use an amplification<lb/>
of your story.</item>
<item>29. Oct. 20, 1900. In my short story and monograph would it be permissible<lb/>
to use the names of Major and Mrs. Peterson, of Major Cartwright, Edmunds, etc.? I<lb/>
believe they have been used in stories already published.</item>
<item>30. In the notes on the back page of your diary you stated "Reed returned<lb/>
to Washington, Feb. 7-10, 1901. What do these 2 dates mean?</item>
<item>- - - - - - - - - - - - -</item>
<item>&para;31 I am sure I will learn much and will certainly enjoy reading such data as<lb/>
you will let me have from subsequent diaries. Being as intimately connected with<lb/>
Reed you must recall many data that have never been published. I would very much<lb/>
like to have a generous amount of &ldquo;General Kean data&rdquo; in any monograph I ever write.<lb/>
You have been too modest and I hope your wife will &ldquo;take my side&rdquo; and encourage you<lb/>
to be less &ldquo;modest&rdquo; and let me have more of your own personal information and ideas.</item>
<item>&para;32 When you met Moran in Charlottesville did he have time to tell you of our<lb/>
(and his) investigations re Bldg. #1? How did they sound? Please tell me if you<lb/>
think we are right or are you skeptical? Have you any comments re my plan to<lb/>
memorialize it? I will go to Cuba in March, satisfy myself fully and then act<lb/>
accordingly, getting a deed, seeing Sec. Ramos as to how my ideas will best fit<lb/>
into his plans, etc. If it is necessary for me to do so (i.e. if I can't raise the<lb/>
money among a dozen friends) would you approve the idea of my forming an advisory<lb/>
committee to investigate our data, approve our findings and aims and lend their<lb/>
names on a letter to be sent to interested (?) institutions, etc. I should like you,<lb/>
Gen. Truby, perhaps Gen. Reed and others.</item>
<item>&para;33 Let me now refer to some of our recent correspondence. In your letter of<lb/>
October 9 to me you noted the &ldquo;violent attack on the scheme published in the Havana<lb/>
newspaper La Lucha.&rdquo; Do you know the approximate date of this attack? I spent<lb/>
several hours in the New York Public Library trying to find it in their copies of<lb/>
La Lucha but I couldn't locate it in Spanish. I suspect I was looking at the wrong<lb/>
file as their files were incomplete.</item>
<item>&para;34 Have you ever seen Hemmeter's article in Janus (Vol. 13, 1908, pp. 57-72<lb/>
and 150-176) in which he gives practically all the credit to Carroll as the real<lb/>
master mind? The article contains many letters from Carroll to his wife. Some of<lb/>
them make rather strange reading. It is difficult to understand how he could<lb/>
so casually dismiss Lazear's death in his letter of Sept. 26 (the date must have<lb/>
been printed wrong; it was presumably written the day Lazear died which was Sept. <hi>25</hi>).<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06301005"/>
#5.<lb/>
His letter of Nov. 25, 1900 referring to a party given by Mrs. Kean is rather<lb/>
&ldquo;sticky&rdquo;. Without meaning to detract from the honor of your friendship I do not<lb/>
react well to Carroll's gloating over the fact that you actually sat with your arm<lb/>
on the back of <hi>his</hi> chair! That doesn't strike me as being a normal male's reaction<lb/>
or that of a true scientific extrovert. But I suppose one must discount such reactions<lb/>
as mine because after all one's personal letters to one's wife would probably always<lb/>
look queer in cold print.</item>
<item>&para;35 May I ask especially about his letter of Dec. 30, 1900. He wrote, &ldquo;I<lb/>
went to the city yesterday and drew $950 from the bank to pay the men upon whom we<lb/>
have experimented. Out of that I paid $129.00 for a watch chain and charm to be<lb/>
presented to one of these men for his courage in submitting to the inoculation....&rdquo;<lb/>
Is this true? Did he do that? I suppose he did it on orders from Reed or from you<lb/>
as disbursing officer but he (Carroll) (or at least Hemmeter, the author) gives the<lb/>
impression that Carroll was in charge of more or less everything, the disbursements,<lb/>
handing out of largesse, etc.</item>
<item>&para;36 Notice an additional error. The letter on page 161 dated Aug. 27, <hi>1900</hi><lb/>
was not written in 1900, of course, but in 1901.</item>
<item>&para;37 [Why so many errors as to the date of Lazear's death? The clinical<lb/>
records clearly show that he died Sept. 25 but the date is given as Sept. 28 in at<lb/>
least 3 places: in Carroll's letter quoted above; in Kelly's book, first edition,<lb/>
page 271 (and presumably on the bronze tablet at Hopkins!), and on the temporary<lb/>
memorial tablet erected at Las Animas Hospital; I hope they don't perpetuate the<lb/>
mistake in final bronze!]</item>
<item>&para;38 Have you been able to find the &ldquo;little bundle of retained papers&rdquo;? I<lb/>
only wish I could help by putting on old clothes with you and searching. It would<lb/>
be a real treasure hunt. If you find one of the contracts I would be more than glad<lb/>
and proud to have it, I assure you.</item>
<item>&para;39 I think it would be fine if you could write Dr. Angles and straighten<lb/>
him out. It might make my March visit much more profitable and easy. Also a letter<lb/>
to Secretary Ramos (whom you have met) would do wonders in preparing him to receive<lb/>
me again. His address Dr. Domingo Ramos, (His Excellency, etc.), Secretary for<lb/>
Defense, Havana, etc. Also if Dr. Albertini knew you were sympathetic with my<lb/>
investigations I know my mission would be much easier and more successful.</item>
<item>&para;40 I shudder when I think how much work I am asking you to undertake in<lb/>
looking over all these notes and answering so many questions, especially if you persist<lb/>
in answering in long hand. I would be so glad to help you locate a stenographer and<lb/>
pay for her services in taking down your answers and thoughts as you may dictate them<lb/>
to her in as much detail as possible. My only defense in asking so much of you is<lb/>
that I know you are much more interested in the perpetuation of the truth about all<lb/>
this even than I am. The only way I can show you my appreciation is to use the<lb/>
material you send me as honestly and faithfully as I can. This I promise to do.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Mrs. Hench and I were very pleased to receive your Christmas card.<lb/>
We thought the little snapshot of you and Mrs. Kean with the two faithful servants<lb/>
hovering nearby was so nice.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
