<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06301156">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean and Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06301156</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean,Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-02-20">February 20, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06301156</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean and Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains the painting of Walter Reed proposed by the John Wyeth Company. He criticizes the dominant role of Finlay in their preliminary sketches and offers suggestions to improve upon the scene.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-02-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean and Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06301156"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-02-20">February 20, 1941</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Generals Kean and Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Permit me to send you each this same letter, to save time and hasten<lb/>
this letter along. I have just recovered from a nasty seige of the flu. The only<lb/>
pleasant thing that happened while I was sick was that one day I received a wonder-<lb/>
ful long letter from General Kean and the next day the grand letter of General<lb/>
Truby. I cannot today answer these letters, but will only say how grateful I am<lb/>
for them.</p>
<p>Permit me to write you about another but related matter, of which General<lb/>
Kean knows something but you, General Truby, do not. The John Wyeth Co., an old and<lb/>
reputable pharmaceutical house in Philadelphia, has begun a series of fine paintings<lb/>
on medical subjects, painted by a nationally known artist. Two have already appeared,<lb/>
one on Dr. Beaumont and one on Dr. Osler; thousands of colored reproductions of each<lb/>
have been disseminated throughout the country to physicians and the original paintings<lb/>
are being exhibited in various medical institutions. Of course this is a form of<lb/>
advertising but it is the highest type of advertising. Already the two paintings<lb/>
have been copied in books and the Beaumont painting was copied in the magazine TIME<lb/>
two weeks ago. In other words, these paintings may probably serve as classical re-<lb/>
presentation of their subjects for some time to come. When I heard that they planned<lb/>
to do one on Walter Reed, I wrote the company hoping that I might procure the origin-<lb/>
al or an oil copy of the original, or at least a fine colored reproduction, to hang<lb/>
in the small museum in Havana which I hope to see built in memory of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
When Mr. George Kellogg of the Wyeth Co. learned of my interest, to my surprise he<lb/>
wired that he and an associate were coming the whole way out to see me as they were<lb/>
interviewing various men who might help them make these paintings historically<lb/>
accurate. In their desire to accomplish the latter they had spent some days in Cuba,<lb/>
where they had fallen under the spell of Mrs. Finlay, Albertini and others and had<lb/>
decided to give Dr. Finlay, Sr. a dominant role in the painting. I spent many hours<lb/>
trying to give them a correct version of the conquest of yellow fever, with the re-<lb/>
sult that I believe they plan to revise their painting entirely. The enclosed<lb/>
snapshot of their preliminary sketches show Finlay in the dominating role with the<lb/>
American physicians led by Reed who stands, hat in hand, listening to the oracular<lb/>
words of the great Cuban sage. In the one picture Lazear's role is so minimized<lb/>
that he almost didn't get in the door. I did not believe that the American medical<lb/>
profession would accept this version kindly. You, General Kean, have already seen<lb/>
these pictures. What is your candid opinion?</p>
<p>I took the privilege of telling them that you, General Truby, had informa-<lb/>
tion in addition to that of General Kean. I told them of your dramatic three or<lb/>
four pages from your diary in which you described Lazear's death, the discovery of<lb/>
the little notebook and the eagerness with which Dr. Reed studied this notebook.<lb/>
Mr. Kellogg is most anxious to obtain further information from you both and I believe<lb/>
will write to you further. I told them that my idea of such a painting would be to<lb/>
portray Lazear inoculating Carroll with the other members of the commission, and also<lb/>
Finlay looking on. When this happened of course Reed was actually in Washington<lb/>
and Finlay was probably not on the scene but certainly artistic license would permit<lb/>
Reed and Finlay to be put in this painting by all means. The portrayal of any<lb/>
later scene would necessitate the absence of Dr. Lazear, which would seem unfair.<lb/>
The inoculation probably took place within Dr. Reed's little laboratory. Mr. Kellogg<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06301157"/>
was afraid that the interior of a small wooden laboratory would not be interesting<lb/>
enough to satisfy the artist. As an alternative, it was suggested that the scene<lb/>
be portrayed on the veranda of the officers' porch where so many of their conferences<lb/>
took place. I have written you, General Truby, telling you of my continued vain<lb/>
search for photographs of the officers' quarters. After two years of searching I<lb/>
have found a fairly good photograph of it in one of the reports of the Governor<lb/>
General of Cuba. Is this similar to the one you have? I showed it to them, and<lb/>
also identified the general location of Reed's little laboratory, and showed them<lb/>
a photograph of the model of Camp Columbia. They now write me that Mr. Cornwell,<lb/>
the artist, much prefers to protray the scene just in front of the officers' quarters<lb/>
with the latter in the immediate background and perhaps with Kissinger and Moran<lb/>
sitting or standing on the steps--all of this for the sake of proper lighting of the<lb/>
scene in the painting. This is a technical point I can't quite understand but the<lb/>
important point is to know whether you feel that this is taking entirely too much<lb/>
license from historical accuracy. In such a scene the drabness would be relieved by<lb/>
some palm trees and Cuban foliage.</p>
<p>The Wyeth people have gone to great extremes to insure accuracy and detail.<lb/>
They are anxious to know the nature of the boarding of the officers' quarters, the<lb/>
color of its paint, and the nature of the uniforms worn by those involved. I loaned<lb/>
them a photograph of the hospital corps on the steps of the ward. This shows a<lb/>
variety of uniforms, yours, General Truby, probably represents that of a regular<lb/>
medical officer and differs from that of Drs. Pinto and Amador who as contract<lb/>
surgeons apparently were a different uniform. I was puzzled by the uniform of Dr.<lb/>
Cooke, which seems to be like that of Dr. Pinto except for the shoulder straps which<lb/>
resemble that of Dr. Truby.</p>
<p>I am sure that both of you will wish to see an honest portrayal of the<lb/>
scene, and as long as such a painting is going to be made and so widely exhibited I<lb/>
felt that those of us who are no interested in the story should be as helpful as<lb/>
possible. I shall be most interested in your reaction to this proposition and I<lb/>
shall bavvery glad to receive carbons of such letters as you may write to Mr. Kellogg<lb/>
and deem it proper for me to see.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I forgot to mention that my suggestion was to have the scene<lb/>
portray Carroll with his shirt sleeve rolled up and Lazear placing the test tube con-<lb/>
taining the mosquito on Carroll's forearm. This action would be the focal point of<lb/>
the scene. Major Reed would be presumably looking on most earnestly and occupying<lb/>
a prominent position, Drs. Agramonte and Finlay would be included in appropriate<lb/>
poses. It was suggested that two or three additional figures occupying less prominent<lb/>
roles would fill out and relieve the scene. If there were to be other figures I suggested<lb/>
that Kissinger and Moran be given the compliment of being included as representative of<lb/>
the enlisted men. Would they be sitting down in the presence of their superior officers?<lb/>
Could they accurately be portrayed as standing in the background looking on? To relieve<lb/>
the monotony of several male figures it was suggested that a woman's figure be included,<lb/>
that of an army nurse, and the idea was to have Miss Maas in the scene even though her<lb/>
work didn't come until later. Was she around there at the time?<lb/>
</seg>
1&sol;28<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
