<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06310207">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, November 24, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06310207</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-11-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E. </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Carson (Colo.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-11-24">November 24, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06310207</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, November 24, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench makes recommendations for some corrections and possible deletions from Truby's manuscript.  He encourages him to take steps to have the book published sooner rather than later.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-11-24">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, November 24, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06310207"/>
<opener>
STATION HOSPITAL<lb/>
Camp Carson, Colorado<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-11-24">November 24, 1942</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Although I have read your manuscript three or four times in<lb/>
the past, I once more got quite a thrill reading it again. I have<lb/>
very few suggestions to make. I am like you, I hate to see any of<lb/>
the photographs omitted, but if necessary, and I am afraid it will be<lb/>
necessary, I would agree with you to omit photographs 2, 6, 7, 13,<lb/>
23, 24, 35, 38, and 40. If necessary I would suggest six more that<lb/>
might be omitted: photographs 3, 5, 12, 22, 42, and 44. Photograph<lb/>
3 must be of considerable interest to you, but it would be of less<lb/>
interest to your readers, especially those chiefly interested in the<lb/>
Cuban phase of your life. Photograph 5, if I might say so, is not<lb/>
a very good photograph; the trees are cut off and there is much too<lb/>
much foreground. If you want to include this, I would suggest that<lb/>
you have it printed enlarged so as to bring out the figures of the<lb/>
horses and men and then cut of the foreground. But I really do be-<lb/>
lieve it is not a very good picture. Photograph 12 is also none too<lb/>
good for reproductive purposes and I suspect that the publishers<lb/>
would suggest omitting it. Photograph 22 is not actually a part of<lb/>
the story, perhaps it could be omitted. Photograph 42 - somewhere<lb/>
I have seen a photograph of this mosquito cage in actual use with a<lb/>
bed and patient inside the cage. If you have seen such a photograph,<lb/>
it would be better then this. Photograph 44 - this table could of<lb/>
course be set up in type and not used as a photograph and that would<lb/>
save money.</p>
<p>Incidentally, on photograph 19 at the bottom the work<lb/>
&ldquo;marianao&rdquo; is spelled wrong.</p>
<p>I am only concerned about two things: You claim that photo-<lb/>
graph 30 is of the Surggry Second Division Hospital and that this<lb/>
Surgery later became Walter Reed's Laboratory. You will remember that<lb/>
in my previous correspondence, I pointed out the directions of this<lb/>
building in connection with General Lee's headquarters which shows<lb/>
up on the original of this large photograph from which you have cut<lb/>
out the photograph of the Surgery. If one studies the relationship<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06310208"/>
-2-<lb/>
of the maps to the little building which you call the Surgery, this<lb/>
either is not the surgery or it must have been moved; it could not be<lb/>
the Surgery and bear the relationship to General Lee's headquarters<lb/>
which appear in the photographs as checked by the maps. It is your<lb/>
opinion that the Surgery must have been moved. It is a little diffi-<lb/>
cult to accept this explanation. We have hundreds of buildings around<lb/>
here that are exactly the same. Is it not possible that this building<lb/>
resembles or is almost identical with Walter Reed's Laboratory but is<lb/>
not actually the latter. Secondly, it is difficult for me to believe<lb/>
that they would have gone to the trouble of putting a building on<lb/>
wheels and moving it. I just can't believe that that is Walter Reed's<lb/>
Laboratory.</p>
<p>The second point with which I cannot agree is where you insist<lb/>
in your footnote to page 102 that the New York Academy of Medicine<lb/>
Laboratory Book &ldquo;contains the handwriting of Reed, Lezear, and Neate&rdquo;.<lb/>
I have been over this book scores of times and have a copy of abso-<lb/>
lutely everything in it. Ninety-nine per cent of the writing is that<lb/>
of Lezear and Reed; there are only one or two little scratch notes in<lb/>
unidentifiable handwriting and these were merely little pieces of paper<lb/>
lying loose in the notebook. It is possible that they may be in Neate's<lb/>
handwriting but nobody knows for sure. I am sure that even General<lb/>
Russell who presumably identifies the hand as that of Neate is wrong<lb/>
and that he would agree he is wrong if he could see Lezear's and Redd's<lb/>
handwriting with that which I have of <del>Neate's</del><add>them</add>. I would suggest that<lb/>
you change the note to read &ldquo;with notes in the handwriting of Lezear<lb/>
and Reed. I put the names in that order because that is the order<lb/>
the handwriting appears in the notebook. Whatever you decide to do<lb/>
about these two points is of course your privilege. They are the only<lb/>
two points which disturb me.</p>
<p>I think the book will look swell in printing and I encourage<lb/>
you to let it be published at once. I don't want to be Macabre but I<lb/>
am so anxious that you see this book and enjoy the reaction of the<lb/>
readers and, after all, you are getting along in years. Practically<lb/>
all publishers offer ten per cent royalty. I will admit that I be-<lb/>
lieve at times this is ten per cent of the retail price and they are<lb/>
offering you ten per cent of the wholesale price, but maybe this is<lb/>
the usual arrangement. At any rate I would urge you to accept it.<lb/>
While you would like to make a little money on it, your main satisfac-<lb/>
tion will come from seeing the book in print and the material on the<lb/>
on the record and of receiving the reaction of the readers to it.<lb/>
Naturally you would like to get enough money to cover the expenses<lb/>
of typing, etc., but everything else is subsidiary to the importance<lb/>
of having the matter printed and in the records. I warn you that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06310209"/>
-3-<lb/>
some literary minded critics may criticize the literary style of the<lb/>
book; critics have to do that, but you will not be disturbed by a few<lb/>
harsh voices and I know you will be very gratified at the reception<lb/>
which it will receive at the hands of your colleagues, friends, and<lb/>
the medical public. I have never seen a book yet, even the best,<lb/>
that did not receive some bad criticism.</p>
<p>I am expressing the manuscript as you have directed and will<lb/>
properly insure it. Naturally, I will not let you pay for the trifling<lb/>
expense that I have had - it was worth very much more than that for<lb/>
me to read the manuscript and to have the pleasure of being connected<lb/>
with your work in some way. Your autograph on one copy will more<lb/>
than repay me for whatever trouble I might have gone to. I will want<lb/>
to buy a number of copies and only wish that the book will be out by<lb/>
Christmas.</p>
<p>I am very busy here and my experiences in the Army Medical<lb/>
Corps have added to my appreciation of your book, because I can now<lb/>
compare the Medical Corps' work of your day and how it now works.<lb/>
I am snowed under with paper work and the amount of medical work<lb/>
that I can do is almost nil. This disappoints me greatly but this<lb/>
apparently cannot be changed. Please keep me informed as to the<lb/>
progress of the book.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. HENCH</signed>
Lieut Colonel, M.C.<lb/>
PSH:ra<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
