<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06310159">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Essay: Introduction to Albert E. Truby's Memoir, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 15, 1942 [Enclosed in 06310156]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06310159</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-09-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient"></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-09-15">September 15, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06310159</idno>
<title>Essay: Introduction to Albert E. Truby's Memoir, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 15, 1942 [Enclosed in 06310156]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean introduces Truby's Memoir on the yellow fever experiments, providing background information on the experiments themselves, as well as background on the author.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1942-09-15">
<head>Essay: Introduction to Albert E. Truby's Memoir, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, September 15, 1942 [Enclosed in <xref id="t06310156">06310156</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06310159"/>
<p>Sept. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>
-----<lb/>
1942</p>
<p>INTRODUCTION. To Gen. Truby's Memoir.</p>
<p>Yellow fever, which is now believed to have come to us from Africa<lb/>
with the Slave trade, has been always a thing of mystery, tragedy and<lb/>
dread. The whimsical way in which it spread gave rise constantly to new<lb/>
theories as to its cause and prevention, each of which was soon upset by<lb/>
other observations. The theory of its transmission by a variety of<lb/>
mosquito was published in 1881 by Dr. Carlos J. Finlay of Havana but made<lb/>
no converts in nineteen years although stoutly maintained by him in many<lb/>
publications both in Spanish and English. True to the record of yellow<lb/>
fever for the unusual, his theory after so many years of incredulity, upon<lb/>
its verification by the Reed Board, was accepted by all the world. The<lb/>
brilliant clarity of Reed's carefully controlled experiments, made on human<lb/>
subjects who volunteered from a love for humanity and also probably from<lb/>
a spirit of adventure; the tragic death of Lazear; the prompt acceptance<lb/>
of the Finlay theory after its demonstration by the Reed Board, all con-<lb/>
stitute a dramatic episode without precedent in medical history. It has<lb/>
so intrigued the popular imagination that doctors, teachers, playwrights,<lb/>
newspapermen, magazine writers and artists have kept alive interest during<lb/>
more than forty years. Many errors, misunderstandings, and partisan<lb/>
statements have become current during that time, some of which have shown<lb/>
great tenacity of life. Several years ago, by a fortunate incident, a<lb/>
born researcher, Dr. Philip L. Hench of the Mayo Clinic, became interested,<lb/>
first in the work of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear as a member of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board and finally in the whole episode and all the individuals concerned<lb/>
therewith. Captivated by the moving features of this historic work,<lb/>
1.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06310160"/>
Dr. Hench, though a very busy man as an author, editor and member of the<lb/>
clinic, has done a vast amount of research work which has taken him twice<lb/>
to Cuba, many times to Washington and to every part of the country where<lb/>
he could interview a survivor of the brave men who volunteered for the<lb/>
famous experiments. His objective is to clear up all doubtful or disputed<lb/>
points, to evaluate, as far as possible, the part played by each of the<lb/>
chief actors and to make an authentic and factual history of the great<lb/>
demonstration. His tireless pursuit of details has had a stimulating<lb/>
influence on all who met him and underwent his categorical inquisitions.<lb/>
The author of this Memoir and the writer of the Introduction have had to<lb/>
study many old papers and to furnish up old memories of our service in<lb/>
Cuba in 1900 at his requests.</p>
<p>Brigadier General Albert E. Truby, U.S.A., our author, when he<lb/>
retired for age in 1935, had completed 37 years of active service in Cuba,<lb/>
the Philippines, Panama, and the four quarters of the United States.<lb/>
This is not the place, nor have we the space to mention the various<lb/>
interesting duties of his long and most creditable career. It may fairly<lb/>
be said, however, that he had performed efficiently the duties of each<lb/>
grade from Lieutenant to Brigadier General before the promotion to such<lb/>
grade came to him. General Truby was assembling his data and putting on<lb/>
paper his reminiscences before the added stimulus of Dr. Hench's<lb/>
researches came to him. The end result has been this Memoir which has<lb/>
delighted those who have had the privilege of reading it in manuscript.<lb/>
The charming story of his experience before the Army Medical Examining<lb/>
2.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06310161"/>
Board of 1898 is especially pleasing to the old timers of the Medical<lb/>
Corps who are proudly reminiscent of surviving this ordeal, which<lb/>
served a good purpose on its day, but has been now fortunately replaced<lb/>
by a better and less painful method of selection.</p>
<p>It was fortunate that when Reed and Carroll landed in Cuba in<lb/>
June, 1900, and came to live at the Post Hospital of Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
Reed should find Lieutenant Truby, for whom he had a high regard, on<lb/>
duty there as Executive Officer and at times in charge of the hospital.<lb/>
He saw Truby constantly at the Medical Officers' Mess and was able to<lb/>
make use of his knowledge in many ways and especially because of Truby's<lb/>
acquaintance with the characters and qualifications of the enlisted men<lb/>
of the Hospital Corps who later were to furnish his most valuable<lb/>
volunteers for the famous experiments. As Columbia Barracks was under<lb/>
rigid military quarantine against yellow fever and its Commanding Officer<lb/>
was known to be a parlous person, the members of the Board were wisely<lb/>
reticent as to their work and Lieutenant Truby had more intimate<lb/>
knowledge of what was being done than anyone else in Cuba. So closely<lb/>
was he in touch with their work that Reed desired to take him as a member<lb/>
of the Board in Lazear's place, but this was not done because Truby was<lb/>
suddenly sent to the South Coast where conditions had arisen which called<lb/>
for the qualities of efficiency and good judgment that his superiors knew<lb/>
him to possess. Therefore this memoir is a precious source of inside<lb/>
information and rarely do we find a story of personal experience told so<lb/>
modestly and with such intrinsic charm.</p>
<p>JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN.<lb/>
3.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
