<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06310024">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 26, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06310024</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-01-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gawne, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Charlotte C.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Springer, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-01-26">January 26, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06310024</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 26, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Kean that Lazear's niece took him to the old family home where he found letters from Lazear to his mother and other personal items. Hench notes that he has also found Agramonte's leave of absence papers indicating he left Cuba several days before Lazear died.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-01-26">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 26, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06310024"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
<date value="1942-01-26">January 26, 1942</date>
</dateline>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was completely distressed by the fact that you were under the weather<lb/>
when I was in Washington. I had been looking forward so long to seeing you and having<lb/>
a nice long conversation with you. Indeed, I had spent considerable time collecting<lb/>
material which I thought you would like to see and I had a list of questions which<lb/>
I wanted to ask you. I brought along several documents and items for your perusal<lb/>
but when I heard that you were having most of your teeth out and on top of it had<lb/>
a little heart attack I realized that it was no time for me to visit you and tire you<lb/>
out. I thought I might run around to say goodbye to you and Mrs. Kean the day after<lb/>
our little party at the Willard but I had so many things to do that I was not able<lb/>
to call on you and I knew that if I did it would just tantalize both of us to have<lb/>
such a short conversation. However, all of this is a matter of fate and I will<lb/>
try to write out my questions and send them to you so that you can answer them at<lb/>
your leisure, I hope with the services of Mrs. Franck.</p>
<p>We were so honored to have you and Mrs. Kean dine with us and Mary and I<lb/>
hope that the food went down alright. I should have liked to talk to you about the<lb/>
movies. I imagine many of the old sites looked strange to you in their present con-<lb/>
dition.</p>
<p>Did I tell you that Mrs. Gawne, Lazear's niece, took me to the old family<lb/>
home outside of Baltimore and in the attic I found one hundred thirty-four letters of<lb/>
Lazear to his mother, thirty-three of which were the letters he wrote to her from<lb/>
Cuba, up to the very day of his last illness, September 18. We also found some inter-<lb/>
esting old photographs of him never published, some of his school books and other<lb/>
personal items of tremendous sentimental value. When I get a breather and can summarize<lb/>
the material I got in the various governmental buildings, I will write you again in<lb/>
more detail. Two of the most important things were the following:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. I found Agramonte's formal leave of absence, indicating that he did actually<lb/>
leave Cuba two or three days before Lazear died and was gone for two or three weeks.<lb/>
This confirms General Truby's statements to me. I am having Agramonte's personal<lb/>
record regarding that leave of absence photostated just for my own information.</item>
<item>2. The New York Academy notebook indicates that a man not listed on the Honor<lb/>
Roll took a minor part, but nevertheless a part, in the Camp Lazear experiments. In<lb/>
Reed's handwriting, the name &ldquo;Springer&rdquo; appears. He was inoculated with culex pungens<lb/>
and of course did not get yellow fever. But the muster and pay rolls which I examined<lb/>
indicated that he was ordered to Camp Lazear and was there for some time. I wonder whether<lb/>
he was primarily sent as a cook or solely as a volunteer. In either event, Reed seems<lb/>
to have used him for one control experiment, the significance of which later apparently<lb/>
seemed so unimportant that Reed did not include him. I will send you his full name,<lb/>
source of enlistment, etc. It will be interesting to look him up and I suspect that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06310025"/>
General Kean<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
January 26, 1942<lb/>
his relatives some time could make a claim for him--a more legitimate claim than<lb/>
has been made for some others.</item>
</list></p>
<p>Enroute home, I had a nice visit with Lambert and with the mother of Forbes<lb/>
in Chicago.</p>
<p>Let me again say what a pleasure it was to have you and Mrs. Kean at our<lb/>
dinner.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Philip Hench<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
psh:ds<lb/>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 &ldquo;N&rdquo; Street N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
Did I send you the enclosed version of the YF talk?<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
