<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06310080">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 10, 1942</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06310080</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1942-04-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Osgood, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew</name>
<name type="person">Roper, Laura Wood</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Crain, Darrell C.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Rochester (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">San Francisco (Calif.)</name>
<name type="place">Omaha (Neb.)</name>
<name type="place">Milwaukee (Wis.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Buffalo (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Pittsburgh (Pa.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1942-04-10">April 10, 1942</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06310080</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 10, 1942</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench tells Kean of an upcoming trip to see various people connected with the yellow fever experiments and of having recently seen Emilie Lawrence Reed. He recounts having given his yellow fever talk at a medical meeting and thanks Kean for his previous letter and the enclosed clippings.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1942-04-10">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 10, 1942</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06310080"/>
<opener>
MAYO CLINIC<lb/>
ROCHESTER, MINNESOTA<lb/>
DR. PHILIP S. HENCH<lb/>
DR. CHARLES H. SLOCUMB<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1942-04-10">April 10, 1942</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am sending you by separate post a program of a course on rheumatic<lb/>
diseases which I am conducting here for about fifty visiting doctors, beginning<lb/>
Monday. The preparation of this course has been, as you may suppose, rather<lb/>
arduous and that has kept me from writing you or from riding my yellow fever hobby.</p>
<p>On April 23, I hope to leave here, to see Dr. Pinto in Omaha on the<lb/>
24th, General Truby in Frisco about the 27th or 28th and Mrs. Lazear thereafter.<lb/>
I am making a very rapid trip, expecting to be back in Milwaukee to speak on the<lb/>
8th of May, so it won't be much of a vacation. My wife is not even going with<lb/>
me.</p>
<p>I am taking my movies of Havana, Camp Lazear out, also much of my<lb/>
collected material, including photographs to be better identified, certain letters,<lb/>
my photostatic copy of the Lazear-Reed notebook, etc. to discuss with Drs. Pinto<lb/>
and Truby and with Mrs. Lazear. I shall take pictures and movies of these people<lb/>
and hope indeed to show them to you on my next visit to Washington so that you can<lb/>
see what they look like. Which reminds me that although I have a nice photograph<lb/>
of you, I have no movie. That must be rectified the next time I come.</p>
<p>I am delighted that you were satisfied with our article in the Army<lb/>
Medical Bulletin for January. Of course we had to leave out a great deal. I wrote<lb/>
the original draft with a few changes from Osgood and Wainwright. I was interested<lb/>
indeed to hear that Dr. Osgood took care of your son. I am sure that he did all<lb/>
that could have been done. He is a fine man. I have been associated with him<lb/>
very closely in our American Rheumatism Association for fifteen years.</p>
<p>I too liked Miss Wood's manuscript very much. I thought it was a little<lb/>
over the heads of children, but think it was really excellent.</p>
<p>I wonder how frail Mrs. Reed really is. For months and months in various<lb/>
letters I have heard from Blossom that her mother was failing badly but when I saw<lb/>
her in Washington she was remarkably alert and whispered out of the corner of her<lb/>
mouth, &ldquo;You know, my children think I am not all here and am sicker than I am!&rdquo;<lb/>
In other words, I wonder if they aren't overly solicitous of her. Dr. Crain, who<lb/>
recently saw her, was inclined to feel that she was more alert than they gave her<lb/>
credit for. So perhaps a visit from you might be a pleasant experience for both.</p>
<p>I am anxious indeed to see General Truby's manuscript published. I<lb/>
have had much correspondence with Mrs. Ames and believe I have at last uncovered<lb/>
the original fever charts which seem to have been loaned from the Surgeon General's<lb/>
office about 1905 for use for a prospective paper which never got published. I have<lb/>
got much from her, not only regarding her husband's illness but many other general<lb/>
details. Last week at a medical meeting here I was asked to give my yellow fever<lb/>
talk. I call it my &ldquo;standard version&rdquo;. It takes fifty minutes and is illustrated<lb/>
with about 75 slides which are shown rapidly but apparently effectively. I was<lb/>
certainly delighted with the reaction. As after my previous talk before the staff<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06310081"/>
General Kean &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; April 10, 1942<lb/>
here, the applause was really unusual in its length and sincerity. It was a<lb/>
tribute not to me but to the story. In passing, I noted briefly the yellow<lb/>
fever notebook and the Lazear letters. The reporter picked that out of the<lb/>
talk as the newsworthy part and asked me to amplify it briefly. In a way<lb/>
I hesitated to call attention to the yellow fever notebook until I had a chance<lb/>
to write it up in some detail but perhaps it is just as well, as it is in the<lb/>
record as to how it was discovered. I was glad to give Miss Wood the credit.<lb/>
Some day you must see the really extensive material I found in the Archives<lb/>
Building. I have had photoprints made of much of it and plan to send some parts<lb/>
of it to you in my little steel box after I return from California so that you<lb/>
can peruse it at your leisure.</p>
<p>In the meantime, thank you so much for the clippings which I am<lb/>
delighted to keep. Please do not throw away any letters of General Gorgas,<lb/>
even if they do not concern yellow fever. They have much sentimental value<lb/>
and I should be delighted to have anything from any of these men. By the<lb/>
way, have you ever got together the &ldquo;little bundle of retained papers&rdquo; which<lb/>
I think you were about to send me some weeks ago?</p>
<p>I just returned from a pleasant but hasty trip to Buffalo where I<lb/>
spoke before six hundred physicians. I took my little eight-year old girl<lb/>
along to see Niagara Falls and then to stop in Pittsburgh to see her grandmother.<lb/>
We had a grand time.</p>
<p>Please accept our very best wishes and pass them on to Mrs. Kean.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P S Hench</signed>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
psh:ds<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
