<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06403098">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, December 1, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06403098</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-12-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwall, Dean</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-12-01">December 1, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06403098</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, December 1, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench describes his visits with the Keans and Ramos. An exhibit of the Cornwall painting is planned in Cuba. He describes a mural by a Cuban artist entitled, &ldquo;The Martyrs of the Conquest of Yellow Fever.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-12-01">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, December 1, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06403098"/>
<opener>
PSH/cb<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1944-12-01">1 December, 1944</date>
</dateline>
Brigadier General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have been meaning to write to you for a long time, but have<lb/>
been very busy. Last month we gave an exhibit on Arthritis from this hos-<lb/>
pital, at the meeting of the Association of Military Surgeons in New York and,<lb/>
thereafter, I spent two days in Washington. I had such a nice visit with<lb/>
General and Mrs. Kean. In New York, I met Doctor Ramos, former Secretary of<lb/>
War in the Cuban Government, now Director of the Finlay Institute. He is try-<lb/>
ing to arrange an exhibit of all the Cornwell paintings in Cuba sometime this<lb/>
next Spring. We visited Cornwell, and saw the newest painting in the series,<lb/>
an excellent one of Oliver Wendell Holmes. Ramos hopes to commission Cornwell<lb/>
to paint something approaching the &ldquo;Cuban version&rdquo; of the Yellow Fever painting<lb/>
for the Finlay Institute.</p>
<p>Had I told you that, this Summer, a young Cuban artist, Raquel<lb/>
Romero, flew here to see me and to show me her preliminary sketch of &ldquo;The<lb/>
Martyrs of the Conquest of Yellow Fever&rdquo;, which she was commissioned to do as<lb/>
a mural in a lecture room or auditorium in a large new National hospital being<lb/>
built on the grounds of the military city (Old Camp Columbia)? I enclose a<lb/>
little picture of Miss Romero and her sketch. It is rather simple, but I think<lb/>
the conception is interesting. It is supposed to represent two episodes that<lb/>
occurred in Las Animas Hospital. On the left is a yellow fever patient, with<lb/>
Doctor Lazear infecting a mosquito. The nurse standing by is Miss Mass. On<lb/>
the right is Doctor Guiteras, infecting Miss Mass, and behind her stand the<lb/>
other two Cubans who, with Miss Mass, died of experimental fever in the late<lb/>
series of Doctor Guiteras. The large figure in the foreground is allegorical<lb/>
and has aroused a little controversy. Miss Romero wanted to tie the two ep-<lb/>
isodes together, and also wanted to indicate that the efforts of these people<lb/>
and their martyrdom were receiving the accolade of humanity. The large figure,<lb/>
therefore, is supposed to represent Humanity. Her classical robe is colored<lb/>
yellow, the color allocated for the medical degree in Cuba. I feared that when<lb/>
this mural appeared, in its large size, this figure in the foreground would be<lb/>
mammoth and overpowering. I suggested that she tone it down; also, I suggested<lb/>
a little relief from the austerity of the rest of the panel, and she was planning<lb/>
to put a little decorative motif in the upper right and left corners, and poss-<lb/>
ibly in the center, perhaps composed of a little draping with the Cuban and<lb/>
American flags, and perhaps the Caduceus. She may change her mind on the latter,<lb/>
however. Doctor Ramos tells me that the mural is practically finished, and<lb/>
it will be interesting to see how it turns out.</p>
<p>I am enclosing an interesting article about Cornwell. I regret<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06403099"/>
Sheet Two<lb/>
To: Brig. Gen. A. E. Truby<lb/>
PSH/cb<lb/>
1 December 1944<lb/>
that I must ask you to return it to me. If you should want one, it might<lb/>
be possible to write to the magazine for a copy, and you will find the<lb/>
address at the bottom of the next to the last page.</p>
<p>I have had so little time to spend on the Yellow Fever hobby.<lb/>
I notice your request to give you a photostat copy of the remarks that<lb/>
Doctor Reed made about you in one of his letters. In your letter of October<lb/>
3rd, you date this letter as November 20, 1899. I thought I had sent you a<lb/>
copy, but obviously I have not. I have here in my room all of Walter Reed's<lb/>
letters to his family and can not find one dated November 20, 1899. Perhaps<lb/>
that letter is one that General Kean may have given me, one of the letters of<lb/>
Reed's which I have in a bank vault in Rochester. Do you remember when I<lb/>
mentioned it? I tried, one evening, to find mention of it in my voluminous<lb/>
correspondence with you, but could not do so. If you could give me the date<lb/>
of my letters about it, it will help me to find the Reed letter. In any<lb/>
event, I will look through the other Reed letters I have at home, when I go<lb/>
home in about three weeks, for Christmas.</p>
<p>I am glad you agree that the one officer in the group by the<lb/>
tree at Camp Lazear is Doctor Cooke. I was sure that it was he, and I be-<lb/>
lieve you were right that figure No. 4 is Kissinger. I can't quite see<lb/>
figure No. 7 as Walter Reed, and General Kean could not, either. General<lb/>
Kean was disturbed to see the children in the photograph, and wondered how<lb/>
they got there. As you know, he did not believe the picture was taken at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, but I can not mistake the tree, and in the center background<lb/>
is the tent. Can you explain why the children are there? I am going to send<lb/>
a copy of the photograph to Doctor Cooke for his identification, and, also,<lb/>
probably to Mr. Kissinger.</p>
<p>Would you like to have any more copies of my article in Hygeia,<lb/>
with the colored reproduction of the Yellow Fever painting? I have quite a<lb/>
lot of them at home and would be delighted to send you as many as you wish,<lb/>
25, 50, even 100, as many of them as you want.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>PHILIP S. HENCH, Lt. Col., M.C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service</signed>
Enc - Photographs (2)<lb/>
Magazine, &ldquo;American Artist&rdquo;<lb/>
dtd April 1942.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
 
