<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06403104">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, December 6, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06403104</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-12-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Presno, Jose A.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-12-06">December 6, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06403104</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, December 6, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In a letter of introduction to the Cuban Minister of Public Health and Sanitation, Hench requests assistance in protecting a building at the site of Camp Lazear. He discusses his plans to create a museum dedicated to the conquest of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-12-06">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jose A. Presno, December 6, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06403104"/>
<opener>
PSH/cb<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1944-12-06">6 December, 1944</date>
</dateline>
His Excellency Doctor Jose A. Presno<lb/>
Minister of Public Health and Sanitation<lb/>
Habana, Cuba<lb/>
<salute>Your Excellency:</salute>
</opener>
<p>For several years I have been greatly interested in the story<lb/>
of the conquest of yellow fever and the work of Doctor Finlay and the<lb/>
American Yellow Fever Commission. I believe our mutual friend, Mr.<lb/>
John J. Moran, has told you how we discovered the long lost Camp Lazear<lb/>
and the remains of the little building where so much of the experimental<lb/>
work was done. It is a curious and most happy coincidence that that same<lb/>
plot of ground, the Finca San Jose, was the site of at least a few of<lb/>
Doctor Finlay's own early experiments. I have proof of this, as it was<lb/>
told me by Doctor Finlay's own son and is mentioned by the latter in his<lb/>
book about his father. For these many reasons, it has been my hope that<lb/>
a sufficient amount of money might be collected to memorialize the remains<lb/>
of Camp Lazear and the little building. I have been collecting some money<lb/>
in this country. I don't have much but it is a start; I have about $1200<lb/>
on hand and the Mayo Clinic and Mayo Foundation have promised that, contin-<lb/>
gent on the receipt of other funds, they will contribute up to $10,000.<lb/>
We will need more than that, as it is my hope that we can enclose the<lb/>
remains of the little shack in a nice permanent structure, which will con-<lb/>
stitute a museum to the conquest of yellow fever. I am so hopeful that in<lb/>
this museum, we can display many interesting and historically valuable<lb/>
souvenirs, not only of the work of Doctor Finlay, but also of the work of<lb/>
the American Commission. I have already collected many items for such a<lb/>
future display.</p>
<p>I have discussed these plans on more than one occasion with<lb/>
Doctor Domingo Ramos, and once with Senor Macia, the present owner of the<lb/>
property. My furtherance of this venture has been interrupted markedly<lb/>
since my entrance into the military service; nevertheless, I have been<lb/>
keeping slowly at the project, and Mr. John Moran of Habana, has given me<lb/>
invaluable support. I have asked him to act as my agent in any plans that<lb/>
we can make in Habana.</p>
<p>At present, I am greatly concerned about the condition of the<lb/>
little building. Mr. Moran has assured me it survived the recent hurricane,<lb/>
and I am most anxious to have it properly supported, either by a strong,<lb/>
completely enveloping semi-permanent, temporary wooden structure, or in<lb/>
some other equally effective manner, so that it may be protected until such<lb/>
time as we can properly house it in a permanent building.</p>
<p>Permit me to send you a reprint of a little article that I published<lb/>
three or four years ago. Also, permit me to tell you that I am not at all<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06403105"/>
Sheet Two<lb/>
PSH/cb<lb/>
To: His Excellency Doctor Jose A. Presno<lb/>
6 December 1944<lb/>
interested in any argument as to who deserves the greater honor, Doctor<lb/>
Finlay or any member of the American Commission. There is great glory<lb/>
for all, and it is my hope to enlist the American Medical Profession in<lb/>
this country in this historical venture, to the end that we may honor<lb/>
Doctor Finlay and his Cuban colleagues equally and in their proper place<lb/>
in relation to members of the American Commission. I am so hopeful that<lb/>
this little venture will lead to a closer union of spirit of the Medical<lb/>
Profession of this country and of Cuba.</p>
<p>If you have any suggestion or advice you could give me by<lb/>
correspondence or to be given to me by direct communication with Mr. Moran,<lb/>
we would be most grateful. To identify myself, may I say that I have been<lb/>
on the staff of the Mayo Clinic since 1921 and have been in the Army since<lb/>
1942. I am Chief of the Medical Service and Director of the Army's Rheumatism<lb/>
Center here at the Army and Navy General Hospital, which happens to be the<lb/>
oldest general hospital in the United States Army. Some months ago I had<lb/>
the honor to present an illustrated lecture on the conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
before the staff of this hospital, and it was received with a very enthusiast-<lb/>
ic reception.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>PHILIP S. HENCH, Lt. Col., M.C.<lb/>
Chief of the Medical Service</signed>
Enc. - &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo;<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
