<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06405109">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, May 11, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06405109</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-05-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E. </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-05-11">May 11, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06405109</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, May 11, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench thinks that Reed was independent of Sternberg in his yellow fever investigation and is trying to decide how much credit Sternberg deserves. Hench believes that Reed and Lazear worked out the project on their own.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-05-11">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, May 11, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06405109"/>
<opener>
Y.F.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-05-11">May 11, 1946</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I believe that I wrote you that I was going east to medical meetings<lb/>
and will be in Washington for five days. I expect to see General Kean,<lb/>
General Reed, General Ireland and others. I have been so busy the last<lb/>
four years that I have had little time indeed to devote to the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Story. To catch up on unfinished professional work will take me<lb/>
most of this year. Nevertheless, I do spend a few hours every now and then<lb/>
trying to check up on unfinished Yellow Fever business.</p>
<p>I recently reviewed my entire correspondence with General Kean and<lb/>
have made out a questionnaire, a copy of which I enclose. As questions<lb/>
came to my mind, I wrote them down, but later found that I had answered<lb/>
them, or in some cases have answers. I have found it extremely valuable<lb/>
to get the answers in the very words of the person I am interviewing.</p>
<p>Frankly, I have been trying to find time to prepare a somewhat<lb/>
similar questionnaire for you, with the thought that we might, while I am<lb/>
in San Francisco, spend a couple of hours together with some public steno-<lb/>
grapher or other stenographic secretary whom you perhaps might know and let<lb/>
her take down our conversation, questions and answers. So far I haven't<lb/>
been able to review my entire correspondence with you and see what unfinish-<lb/>
ed business I have. At the moment, I am trying to unravel and solve the<lb/>
problem as to just how independent Reed was in the matter of his Yellow Fever<lb/>
investigation and whether the Surgeon General actually did (as claims are<lb/>
made) precisely outline to Reed the lines of investigation to follow. You<lb/>
know my primary opinion is that Reed and Lazear worked out the details and<lb/>
that Reed originated the broad outline, independent of Sternberg. Undoubt-<lb/>
edly Sternberg deserves some credit and I am trying to find out just how<lb/>
much. Would you kindly look over the enclosed data. When I arrive in San<lb/>
Francisco, I may have with me General Kean's answers and we can discuss the<lb/>
whole matter then.</p>
<p>At times it will seem to you that I am asking the same question over<lb/>
again. In some cases, this is true, as I have had some conflicting answers<lb/>
or because I have found the answers incomplete. Please forgive me for this<lb/>
apparent repetitiousness. Incidentally, I apologize for the apparent im-<lb/>
politeness of my questionnaire where I speak Kean doing this and Reed that.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06405110"/>
General Albert E. Truby &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; May 11, 1946<lb/>
My secretary copied it just as I had jotted it down from time to time<lb/>
and we did not, unfortunately, take the time to smooth it up and make it<lb/>
polite.</p>
<p>It will be so nice to see you and Mrs. Truby again. I am anxious<lb/>
to have you meet my wife and visa versa. She is a wonderful person and,<lb/>
incidentally, this is her forty-first birthday today. We have reserva-<lb/>
tions at the Mark Hopkins and expect to spend four or five days in the<lb/>
second week of July at the El Encanto Hotel in Santa Barbara, where I hope<lb/>
to see the Lazears.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:kw<lb/>
Enc.<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. The above letter of May 11 didn't get sent as I have been<lb/>
in a tizzy trying to get ready to go East for a month. Meanwhile, your<lb/>
nice letter of the fourteenth has arrived.<lb/>
I am very anxious to have you and Mrs. Truby meet Mary. She is<lb/>
your sort of people and vice versa. We don't want Mrs. Truby to bother<lb/>
much. Mary has been in San Francisco on several occasions, but by all<lb/>
means, we must meet and all &ldquo;get drunk together&rdquo;! We are fortunate to<lb/>
have rooms at the Mark Hopkins Hotel. I certainly want to spend part of a<lb/>
day, if possible a whole day, with you and my thought at the moment would<lb/>
be that at least we could spend the afternoon together, and if you and Mrs.<lb/>
Truby would do us the honor of dining with us at the Mark Hopkins, that would<lb/>
be grand. (Now, don't persuade Mrs. Truby to have us there. I am an old<lb/>
married man and I know how the ladies of the house love to go out for dinner,<lb/>
so if it is alright with you, please accept the invitation.) As to the exact<lb/>
date, could we wait until our arrival?<lb/>
It will be indeed a pleasure to see General Kean, General Reed<lb/>
and others on June 2, and should you wish to write me, I will be at the<lb/>
Statler in Washington at that time.<lb/>
P.S.H.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
