<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06405071">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, January 18, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lambert, Gustaf E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06405071</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-01-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-01-18">January 18, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06405071</idno>
<title>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, January 18, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lambert expresses great disappointment for the lack of recognition, in Truby's book, of his work at the yellow fever camp.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-01-18">
<head>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, January 18, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06405071"/>
<opener>
FROM GEN. ALBERT E. TRUBY<lb/>
<dateline>
Chicago, Illinois<lb/>
<date value="1946-01-18">January 18, 1946</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have often thought of writing a few remarks on your book.<lb/>
Now when I know it from cover to cover, have read it at least<lb/>
twenty times, if I am going to write must do it now as I am<lb/>
going blind (left eye has been dead for over 20 years, right<lb/>
is going fast).</p>
<p>If it was in my power to change, I would change it to read that<lb/>
Dr. Ames had yellow fever contracted during the work. I have his<lb/>
service record from the Adj. General's Office. I would mention<lb/>
that Dr. Ames was carried on his bed when he himself was sick<lb/>
with yellow fever a quarter of a mile to attend one of the ex-<lb/>
perimental cases when patient was neglected by the doctor in<lb/>
charge. I would scratch off buildings 17, 18, 19 &amp; 20 from the<lb/>
hospital plan because they were never there. The drawing I sent<lb/>
was correct. I volunteered to go down there <hi>two weeks before<lb/>
Maj. Kean came down,</hi> when packmaster and his wife came in with<lb/>
yellow fever and lived there until March 2nd, and <hi>could not help<lb/>
but see the buildings if they had been there</hi>. I was outside of<lb/>
the quarantine line only the two nights Dr. Ames sent me to help<lb/>
with Dr. Carroll. There was a 36-36 box without door put up<lb/>
over a hole for a toilet after Christmas. Oh yes, I <hi>was on Dr.<lb/>
Carroll's case all right, although only two nights</hi>, but I think<lb/>
they were criticial nights. Dr. Carroll was in great distress<lb/>
and out of his head, wanted to get out of bed. I came in the<lb/>
room and put him back. The nurse only said &ldquo;Dr. Carroll you<lb/>
shouldn't get out of bed.&rdquo; Could Dr. Carroll, if he had been<lb/>
allowed to get up and walk around, have strained himself and<lb/>
brought on black vomit? As described in Book &ldquo;Maj. Reed and<lb/>
Yellow Fever&rdquo;, told by <hi>Warner how she hung on Dr. Lezear's<lb/>
back</hi>. I might be wrong, but I claim a little credit in Carroll's<lb/>
recovery.</p>
<p><unclear>117-118-119-120</unclear></p>
<p><unclear>M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Cord'</unclear></p>
<p>If I could I would like to change the statement on page 81, the<lb/>
word &ldquo;most&rdquo; I would replace with &ldquo;all&rdquo; and there were no other<lb/>
non-immunes. There were two women, Gillen and <hi>McCook</hi>, both<lb/>
immunes, there to care for female patients, of which we had only<lb/>
two, one before and one right after Maj. Kean, and I took care<lb/>
of them. I can't remember if Gillen and McCook came down right<lb/>
after Christmas or not. Most likely the toilet was put up on<lb/>
their account, but I do know they were there long enough to<lb/>
transform one-half box of new sheets into ladies' underwear.<lb/>
Silk was not for common people in those days. Dr. Ames never<lb/>
put them to work but the Doctor who substituted for Ames did,<lb/>
taking care of Andrus. How they performed their duty, the en-<lb/>
closed carbon copy will tell in part. Andrus has made a mis-<lb/>
take where he states I was on night duty and Gillen and McCook<lb/>
took care of him. I <hi>had Folks and Forbes in &ldquo;15&rdquo;, Ames in &ldquo;13&rdquo;</hi><lb/>
for three days only. <hi>Andrus was in &ldquo;16&rdquo;</hi> when Gillen came and<lb/>
asked me to come over and tie Andrus because he was &ldquo;awful&rdquo;,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06405072"/>
-2-<lb/>
and I found the boy in great distress due to not passing any<lb/>
urine in over eight hours. When I asked if she had tried to<lb/>
catherize. I did not hear if she said &ldquo;I couldn't do that&rdquo;<lb/>
or &ldquo;I wouldn't do that. Anyway, I went after a catherer and<lb/>
drew 710 c.c. from the boy. I remember the quantity because<lb/>
I later reported to Dr. Ames. He always preached &ldquo;Watch<lb/>
the urine.&rdquo; When called three day's later by Gillen, she<lb/>
said she <hi>knew</hi> that he was only cranky. I thought he was<lb/>
real sick but did not know the trouble. I ran up to the hospital,<lb/>
with Ames' permission, and the help of McCarthy carried Ames down<lb/>
to look at Andrus. Dr. found a rectal carbuncle that needed<lb/>
cutting. When I took Dr. Ames out of the room the nurse was not<lb/>
there, but when we came back an hour later both the nurse and<lb/>
Maj. Stark acted as a reception committee. As soon as the bed was<lb/>
on the floor the storm broke loose. I never had a better calling<lb/>
down in all my life. Maj. Stark was really angry. Maj. Stark<lb/>
took care of Ames after he was sent up to the hospital. Maj.<lb/>
Stark's anger was only temporary. He was very kind to me after<lb/>
I was released from quarantine. I was the last man he operated<lb/>
on before leaving Cuba. I went on the table at 9 A.M. At 1 P.M.<lb/>
he left for Washington. I never had a chance to thank him for<lb/>
ridding me of a rupture. Even the review article in &ldquo;The Military<lb/>
Surgeon&rdquo; took the credit away from me, if any credit was due, by<lb/>
saying &ldquo;did not undergo any hazardous test.&rdquo; That might have<lb/>
pertained to Neate. It would have been his own fault if he had<lb/>
been careless with the mosquitos but the formitos test, I had<lb/>
more of that than all the rest of the men put together. Besides<lb/>
we had a few bad mosquitos too. Dr. Carroll gave me two test<lb/>
tubes with 8 or 10 mosquitos in them to be turned loose with<lb/>
Martinez. He wouldn't let them feed any on him while he was awake.<lb/>
They were all lost but two. I will never believe anything else<lb/>
but that it was one of those lost mosquitos that inoculated Dr.<lb/>
Ames.</p>
<p>Black vomit by which the Stark boys were messed up, came from a<lb/>
man named Sullivan. He wasn't an experimental case but Dr. Ames<lb/>
told me to save some for Dr. Carroll's laboratory. The autopsy<lb/>
mentioned, which Dr. Carroll attended shortly after his recovery,<lb/>
was on a Sargeant of the 2nd Art. Dr. Reed, Carroll, Ames and<lb/>
Agramonte were there. I assisted Agramonte in the work. After<lb/>
the doctors had what they wanted, I prepared the body for burial.<lb/>
When ready I went to the door. (Battery and band lined up for<lb/>
immediate funeral). I asked someone to give me a hand placing<lb/>
body in casket but none would come in so I had to dump the body<lb/>
in and then straighten it out. These two cases were not experi-<lb/>
mental cases but they were both used by the commission in the<lb/>
experiment. When Sullivan had black vomit the third time Maj.<lb/>
Gorgas was standing longside the bed. When I reached under the<lb/>
bed for the pan he spewed over my head. Maj. Gorgas grabbed a<lb/>
towel hanging on the bed and threw over me so I could wipe my<lb/>
face. I was blinded. Maj. Gorgas asked if I had any disinfectant<lb/>
to go and wash at once. Three days later Maj. Gorgas called and<lb/>
asked why the last death hadn't been reported. When I told him<lb/>
we hadn't had any he mentioned Sullivan's name. I answered that<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06405073"/>
-3-<lb/>
he was sitting up in bed. The Major couldn't believe it so had<lb/>
to come out and see for himself. The Major told Sullivan that<lb/>
he had never before seen a man his age (64) have black vomit<lb/>
three times and recover. The four men who took formito tests<lb/>
only volunteered after being offered extra pay. None would volunteer<lb/>
to go in as nurse when first patient came to pesthouse.</p>
<p>Senator Thomas of Utah was right when he wrote in Senate report<lb/>
on my bill, &ldquo;This man should have quit when the first case of<lb/>
experimental yellow fever came in. He would then have been asked<lb/>
to volunteer to nurse the experimental cases as he had previously<lb/>
volunteered to nurse natural cases.&rdquo; I was no &ldquo;heel&rdquo;. Men were<lb/>
sick and needed care. If Maj. Reed had been alive when bill to<lb/>
grant recognition was passed, I know my name would have appeared<lb/>
with the rest. I was wrong. Dr. Pinto did not attend Andrus<lb/>
and would have known so if I had only looked at the group picture.<lb/>
The enclosed carbon copy will show where Andrus wrote in the name<lb/>
Pinto, 3rd line from bottom. Little Andrus was a prince. He<lb/>
plugged for my bill by writing to many Senators and members of<lb/>
the House. It was a real disappointment to him, as well as to<lb/>
myself, when bill after passing the Senate, both committees of<lb/>
the House, was returned to committee for reconsideration and<lb/>
allowed to die there.</p>
<p>The doctor who attended Andrus was dark complected, somewhat<lb/>
pale, Dr. Lezeare's height, lean, it seems to me he had dark<lb/>
beard and wore glasses. Please tell me if you can name him<lb/>
after this description. Could I have been Dr. de Poorter men-<lb/>
tioned in the book? Enclosed to show how Andrus felt about my<lb/>
bill. Please return carbon copy. Carbon copies sent just to<lb/>
show how Andrus felt<lb/>
regarding my work</p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully,</salute>
<signed>(signed) Gust E. Lambert<lb/>
8009 Avalon Ave.<lb/>
Chicago 19, Ill.</signed>
GL:MO<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
