<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06403106">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 6, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06403106</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-12-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ramos, Domingo F.</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos E.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-12-06">December 6, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06403106</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 6, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses Finlay's mosquito theory and Reed's experimentation. He comments on a planned mural depicting the story of yellow fever in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1944-12-06">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 6, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06403106"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2804 N St. u. w.<lb/>
Washington 7, D C<lb/>
<date value="1944-12-06">Dec. 6/44</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Colonel Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was about to begin a letter to you<lb/>
yesterday where the mail came with<lb/>
your good letter and inclosing yours to<lb/>
Gen. Truby of Dec. 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>- Various things inter-<lb/>
vewed to stop me until this morning, which<lb/>
was just as well as I have been able<lb/>
to think over and look up several matters.<lb/>
What I had on my mind was a letter from<lb/>
Truby inclosing back to me, one from Dr-<lb/>
A. Diaz Albertini to him, mailed in my<lb/>
care, at the suggestion of our friend Dr<lb/>
Domingo Ramos, as neither of them knew<lb/>
Truby's address- There was also in it a note<lb/>
from Dr. Ramos to me- The subject of the<lb/>
correspondence was as follows:<lb/>
Dr. Albertini is the only surviving member<lb/>
of the Havana Board of Yellow Fever experts<lb/>
which confirmed the diagnoses of Reed's<lb/>
cases of experimental yellow fever at Camp<lb/>
Lazear- He has read in Truby's book, Reed's<lb/>
letter to Truby of Dec. 10, 1900. In this he tells<lb/>
the good news of his first experimental case<lb/>
which was fully controlled (Kissinger), in which<lb/>
Reed said &ldquo;The case is a beautiful one, and<lb/>
will be seen by the Board of Havana experts<lb/>
Today, <hi>all of whom except Finlay consider the<lb/>
theory a wild one&rdquo;</hi>- On that board was the noted<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06403107"/>
2-<lb/>
Surgeon General William C. Gorgas"--page 158.<lb/>
He takes exception to Major Reed's statement<lb/>
and as the only living members of the Com-<lb/>
mission expresses &ldquo;my nonconformity with<lb/>
such an assertion, not only in that which<lb/>
refers to me, but also to my fellow workers<lb/>
no longer living: Drs Major Gorgas and<lb/>
Juan Guiteras&rdquo;- He calls upon Gen Truby to<lb/>
publish his letter &ldquo;in some scientific magazine<lb/>
of your great country&rdquo;. Truby is troubled and<lb/>
worried at this demand and has sent it<lb/>
all to me to handle- He has written to<lb/>
Dr. Albertini stating that he has done so<lb/>
as he is ill and not able to discuss the<lb/>
matter- I have written a rather long and wordy<lb/>
letter to Dr. Ramos in which I try to point<lb/>
out the unreasonable nature of this requests-<lb/>
I have done this as politely as I can because<lb/>
I have a sincerely regard for Dr. Albertini-<lb/>
In the first place if Dr. Albertini is willing<lb/>
to assert that he was a convert to the Finlay<lb/>
theory before he had seen even the first one<lb/>
of Reed's Camp Lazear cases, I do not see how<lb/>
we can dispute his memory, though I am<lb/>
quite surprised at it. It has always been my<lb/>
1.<lb/>
understanding that before the Camp Lazear demon<lb/>
stration Dr. Finlay's faithful follower and disciple<lb/>
<add>Dr. C. Delgado</add> was his &lsquo;sole disciple&rsquo;- And Dr. Carlos E. Finlay his<lb/>
son (whose recent death I have been sorry to learn)<lb/>
so states in his book Carlos Finlay and Yellow Fever<lb/>
Chap V pp. 94 and 95. 2 As to Gorgas he has put on<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06403108"/>
3<lb/>
July 12 1902<lb/>
record in his Final Official Report to Gen. Wood<lb/>
with admirable frankness, his disbelief <add>at that time</add> in the mosquito<lb/>
theory being the only <hi>or even the usual way</hi> of its<lb/>
transmission- This is also stated in Dr. Carlos E.<lb/>
Finlays book p. 119- And Gorgas said this to me<lb/>
in practically the same words when I asked him<lb/>
to back up Reed's paper at the Pan American<lb/>
Medical Congress in Havana Feb 4 1901- He would<lb/>
not state his adhesion to the Finlay theory after<lb/>
all the evidence was in- It was <unclear>his</unclear> own<lb/>
work which finally convinced him-<lb/>
So we have left only Dr. Juan Guiteras<lb/>
unaccounted for- It is my belief that he was<lb/>
convinced by the Camp Lazear experiments.<lb/>
Dr. Guiteras said of Finlay's epedemeological<lb/>
work in the long period before 1900: &ldquo;If he fail-<lb/>
ed to convince us, the fault was ours and not<lb/>
of his prevision&rdquo; This does not sound like the<lb/>
language of a convinced disciple-</p>
<p>I cannot see that Gen. Truby is called<lb/>
upon to justify a statement by made by<lb/>
Major Reed which was certainly a matter<lb/>
of common belief at the time he made it,<lb/>
although after the Commission on Board <unclear>saw</unclear><lb/>
Kissinger's case Dr. Guiteras may have become<lb/>
a convert- It is evident that Dr. Albertini<lb/>
has <unclear>erred</unclear> in his letter as to Gen. Gorgas. If<lb/>
he or Dr. Ramos has any evidence as to the<lb/>
data of Dr. Guiteras's conversion Dr. Albertini<lb/>
or Dr. Ramos might publish it if they think<lb/>
it desirable- To me it does not seem that<lb/>
it is at all to their discredit to have shared the<lb/>
common belief of the medical profession until con-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06403109"/>
Ac<lb/>
k<lb/>
4<lb/>
vincing proof of the <unclear>to them</unclear> new theory was<lb/>
laid before them- <del>If</del> Gen. Truby I think agrees<lb/>
with me that if the Director of the Instituto Finlay<lb/>
can find every documentary evidence of the accep-<lb/>
tance by Dr. Guiteras of the Finlay theory before Dec. 10-<lb/>
1900 it should be presented to you who are the person<lb/>
in the world most familiar with the details of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Episode of 1900-1901- Then you and Dr<lb/>
Ramos can consider what form the letter should<lb/>
take and how it should be published- I hope<lb/>
that you may be willing to accept this judicial posi-<lb/>
tion- Personally I do not think a case can be made<lb/>
out. Also I admire Gen. Truby's book too much to<lb/>
appear to criticise anything in it, especially I do not<lb/>
see that any one's reputation is involved in the matter</p>
<p>I am so pleased to know that you saw<lb/>
S&ntilde;a Raquel Romero and discussed her plan<lb/>
of the mural with her- I was uneasy about the<lb/>
prominence of the female figure which is intended<lb/>
to bring together the two incidents which tell the<lb/>
story- This figure was much more prominent<lb/>
in the sketch which I saw and as I told her<lb/>
was more suggestive of Hollywood than of<lb/>
the Muse of History- As regards the use of<lb/>
the caduceus I told her that in my opinion<lb/>
it has no medical connotation whatever-<lb/>
It was selected by the U. S. Medical Dept.<lb/>
because it was used by heralds to secure<lb/>
immunity from attack in war, and it<lb/>
signifies medical immunity under the<lb/>
Geneva treaties- I am returning your<lb/>
article on Moran at Rochester- It had<lb/>
apprently been handled a little roughly and<lb/>
one small piece is torn out. I have patched<lb/>
it up as well as I could-</p>
<p>SNA = Senorita<lb/>
I am much pleased to get the snapshots of Sna</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours</salute>
<signed>J. R. K.</signed>
I will send a P. S. tomorrow in answer to your letter.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
