<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06402001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 6, 1944</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06402001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1944-01-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Springer, Adolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>18 pp.</extent>
<date value="1944-01-06">January 6, 1944</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06402001</idno>
<title>Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 6, 1944</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench questions Kean about the yellow fever experiments at Camp Lazear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1944-01-06">
<head>Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, January 6, 1944</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06402001"/>
<opener>
INTERVIEW <add>by P S Hench</add> WITH GENERAL J. R. KEAN, U.S. Army, RET.<lb/>
<dateline>
WASHINGTON, D.C.<lb/>
<date value="1944-01-06">January 6, 1944.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #1</hi> Adolph <hi>Springer</hi> was a soldier whose name I found in<lb/>
the Walter Reed notebook owned by the New York Academy of Medicine.<lb/>
He is a man who was bitten by a pungens mosquito. His name does<lb/>
not appear in any of the official documents. Do you know who he<lb/>
was and why he did not get on the roll of honor?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Springer was a member of the Detachment Hospital Corps<lb/>
at Camp Columbia and his name appears as No. 35 on the nominal list<lb/>
of that Detachment made by General Truby to go with the group photo-<lb/>
graph of it. I am sure that you have a copy of it (marked photo. 14).<lb/>
When General Ireland and I helped make out the qualifications for the<lb/>
roll of honor, we decided not to include any one who did not actually<lb/>
get experimental yellow fever, with the exception of those who took<lb/>
the fomites experiment. Therefore Springer would not have qualified.<lb/>
I think he was probably a Hospital Corps man. Look at the picture<lb/>
and Truby's identification list.</p></item>
<item><p>QUESTION #2: Who was Sergeant Neate? Answer: He was Reed's labor-<lb/>
atory assistant brought down from Washington by him-</p>
<p>ANSWER: Reed decided to try the pungens on a few patients. He<lb/>
knew that the pungens mosquito was common in places where there was<lb/>
never any yellow fever and did not think that it had any connection<lb/>
with it, but he wanted to try and see, and so he gave Sergeant Neate,<lb/>
who was an excellent laboratory assistant and very faithful soldier,<lb/>
the benefit of being on the list of volunteers in order that he might<lb/>
get the money. This was, of course, before there was any definite<lb/>
- 1 -<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06402002"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
determination as to who should get on the roll of honor and who<lb/>
should not. This was arrived at many years later (about 1929)<lb/>
in my consultation with the Surgeon General.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #3</hi> Why then does not Neat's name appear in any of Reed's<lb/>
papers, and why is not his experiment mentioned in any of Reed's<lb/>
papers, and why didn't he get the money - or did he?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> He did - $100.00. Reed and I decided how to expend<lb/>
the Cuban Yellow Fever Fund, and Neate was bitten by a pungens mos-<lb/>
quito. This was not done at Camp Lazear, but was done at the yellow<lb/>
fever ward at Columbia Barracks for the following reason: The pun-<lb/>
gens is a nervous mosquito which could not be made to bite an indi-<lb/>
vidual when in the test tube, so they were placed inside of a mos-<lb/>
quito net of a patient sick with yellow fever to be inoculated.<lb/>
The technique of applying this mosquito was different from the yellow<lb/>
fever mosquito. Reed would release several pungens under the mos-<lb/>
quito netting of a yellow fever patient in the first few days. He<lb/>
would leave them there over night, catching them in test tubes against<lb/>
the mosquito netting, and put the mosquitoes back in their jars for<lb/>
a variable number of days, and then release them under the mosquito<lb/>
net of those apparently few non-immunes on whom Reed tried this ex-<lb/>
periment. Neate is the only one I actually know who received this<lb/>
experiment, but as you say Springer must have also received this<lb/>
experiment. Apparently Reed omitted from his papers reference to<lb/>
these pungens experiments because they were negative and not im-<lb/>
portant. Whether Springer got $100.00 for volunteering, I do not<lb/>
remember. He certainly did if Reed recommended him for it.</p></item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06402003"/>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item><p>QUESTION #4: This Spring when I visited Mrs. Lazear I told her that<lb/>
it was the generally accepted story that Dr. Lazear kept from her the<lb/>
knowledge of his work in order that if anything happened to him his<lb/>
insurance would not be forfeited. Mrs. Lazear was surprised at this,<lb/>
and it was very difficult for her to believe this version as she had<lb/>
no recollection that Dr. Lazear left any insurance. It was her idea<lb/>
that <hi>Dr. Lazear kept the matter secret simply in order not to worry<lb/>
her.</hi> What is your reaction to the &ldquo;insurance story&rdquo;?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> If she did not get any insurance I would accept the<lb/>
explanation that there was none. There was no government insurance<lb/>
in those days like there is today. It was only assumed as a guess<lb/>
that Lazear had this reason for not putting his own experiment on<lb/>
record.</p></item>
<item><p>QUESTION #5: In my interview of May 8, 1941 in Question #28, I<lb/>
asked you what kind of a stove they probably had in Building #1.<lb/>
You thought it was probably not an army stove, but suggested it might<lb/>
have been a coal oil stove. Some one has said that a coal oil stove<lb/>
would not have a stove pipe. Do you have anything further to say<lb/>
on that? What kind of a stove would be appropriate to put in<lb/>
Building #1 when we reconstruct it? Moran does not remember seeing<lb/>
the stove, but thinks it might have been a big bellied iron with an<lb/>
isinglass window and a little flat top on which to put a pan of<lb/>
increase B<lb/>
water to relieve humidity.</p>
<p>ANSWER: I really do not know. I thought it might have been<lb/>
a Franklin stove, but I never saw a Franklin stove in Cuba. Why not<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06402004"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
ask the Cubans what kind of a stove might have been purchased there<lb/>
at that time? I still think it might have been a coal oil stove,<lb/>
as this oil makes no smoke, but it might have had a stove pipe never-<lb/>
theless to carry off the products of combustion. Probably army wood <unclear>over<lb/>
B</unclear>.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #6</hi>: In Reed's letter to General Sternberg July 24, 1900<lb/>
Reed speaks about &ldquo;the stupid blunder of Godfrey and his assistants&rdquo;.<lb/>
Who were Godfrey's assistants? I thought Cooke was the only one.</p>
<p>See Hench <unclear>called</unclear></p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> The number of regular medical officers was exceedingly<lb/>
short in Cuba and most of the medical service was done by Contract<lb/>
Surgeons. Godfrey was the only regular surgeon at Pinar del Rio.<lb/>
General Truby states that one of them might have been A.A. Surgeon<lb/>
Pilsnell (I think it should be spelled Presnall). There was also<lb/>
no one <unclear>knows it</unclear> was Y. F<lb/>
one named Alden. Cooke was the one in charge of the <hi>yellow fever</hi><lb/>
ward. When I returned to Marianao on August 13, 1900 from sick<lb/>
leave in the United States, I found that Captain Stark, who had been<lb/>
post surgeon, had investigated the matter and had not recommended any<lb/>
He did not in his letters!<lb/>
punishment for negligence. <hi>Stark's excusing Cooke</hi> made the likli-<lb/>
hood of court martial of Cooke and Godfrey impossible. I went up<lb/>
to Pinar del Rio to decide about the disposition of infected property.<lb/>
I recommended to the Surgeon General that Dr. Cooke's contract be<lb/>
annulled. Although he was in charge of the ward, he had not kept<lb/>
records of the urine, temperature and pulse according to the circu-<lb/>
lars of instructions - at least he had not done enough to make a<lb/>
diagnosis. Cooke felt very badly about it and came down to Marianao<lb/>
and offered himself to Reed as an experimental case. He made no de-<lb/>
fense to me. Major Reed came to me and asked if I would object to<lb/>
- 4 -<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06402005"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
his taking Cooke on as a volunteer for the yellow fever tests. I was<lb/>
glad to say that I would not object. Thereafter I wrote, or cabled,<lb/>
the Surgeon General withdrawing my previous recommendation to void<lb/>
Cooke's contract.</p>
<p><hi>QUESTION #7</hi>: Why were you so angry at Cooke? Did you not realize<lb/>
that he had only been in the Army, and had only been in Cuba a very<lb/>
short time - I believe in Cuba only a couple of weeks? He has told<lb/>
me that he knew nothing of yellow fever, had never seen a case, and<lb/>
that Captain Godfrey, his superior, had not corrected his mistakes.<lb/>
He considered his mistake quite explainable and never had any feeling<lb/>
of guilt although he was, of course chagrined.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I did not know that Cooke had been such a short time in<lb/>
Cuba and supposed that he knew the standing instructions about exami-<lb/>
nation of all fever cases. Now it seems to me distinctly to his<lb/>
credit that he did not try to avoid my censure. He did not try to ex-<lb/>
cuse his delinquency; he has always been a very modest and manly gentle-<lb/>
man.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #8</hi>: What was your reaction to Godfrey who was even more re-<lb/>
sponsible and whose ignorance is more blameable?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think he was entirely inexcusable, but as he had been<lb/>
examined and reprimanded by Captain Stark (this was only a verbal<lb/>
reprimand) I felt that nothing could be done in his case, but I knew<lb/>
that he could never get a promotion in the Medical Department. I<lb/>
always felt that he should have been court-martialed.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #9:</hi> When you wired Mrs. Lazear that Dr. Lazear had died<lb/>
- 5 -<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06402006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
your wire is very short, and simply says that he had died and gave the<lb/>
hour of death. Mrs. Lazear did not even know he was sick. Looking<lb/>
at the wire now, the telegram looks very brief and cold and almost<lb/>
militarily cruel. Why was that sort of a wire sent?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: Those were the days of strict economy. I should have<lb/>
written, if I did not. I assumed that someone else had informed her<lb/>
of his illness, because I had been away on an inspection trip during<lb/>
his illness. Incidentally, when I had yellow fever Captain Stark<lb/>
sent a cable to my family every day. I had to pay for these messages<lb/>
at the rate of $2.00 or $3.00 a word, and I regretted that he had<lb/>
issued so much information.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #9:</hi> In your diary and elsewhere you have stated that on<lb/>
October 12, 1900 you went with Reed to see General Wood, and so far as<lb/>
you know this is the first time that Reed suggested using and paying<lb/>
Spanish immigrants for experimental purposes as volunteers.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> If Reed had before this discussed with General Wood the<lb/>
use of Spanish volunteers, he never told me, and I do not believe that<lb/>
he did. As regards American volunteers I think the question had<lb/>
never been raised, and was a personal responsibility with Reed. The<lb/>
American soldier had a right to volunteer, and the only responsibility<lb/>
involved would be a violation of the quarantine regulations. In re-<lb/>
porting the case of XY in his preliminary report he was anxious not to<lb/>
reveal that XY was a soldier because it would have been a violation of<lb/>
the quarantine orders. Reed had not used XY, but his assistants had,<lb/>
and if Colonel Baldwin had wanted to he could have censured Reed severe-<lb/>
- 6 -<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06402007"/>
- 7 -<lb/>
ly for that experiment. I laughed and told Reed that unless he ad-<lb/>
mitted that XY was a soldier he would have a hard time making it clear<lb/>
that he had had no previous exposure. Reed admitted this and took<lb/>
the chance. Later when a Captain of an Artillery Company made an of-<lb/>
ficial complaint through channels to General Wood that one of his men<lb/>
had been infected with yellow fever as an experiment, he was given to<lb/>
understand that this was not a military matter. Nothing came about<lb/>
the matter of XY as far as Reed and the Commanding Officer were con-<lb/>
cerned. Probably nothing was heard of the facts in the case until<lb/>
it was too late to take any action.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #10</hi>: It is generally accepted that it was decided on August<lb/>
1, 1900 to use human volunteers. Reed and Agramonte had returned<lb/>
from Pinar del Rio, and on August 1 the four met at Camp Columbia on<lb/>
the veranda of the Officers' Quarters and decided, or at least offi-<lb/>
cially decided to use human volunteers. Most of the stories infer<lb/>
that the matter was first considered then and was decided on that day,<lb/>
but in Reed's letter to General Sternberg July 24, 1900 Reed definite-<lb/>
ly mentions the probable necessity of experimentation on human beings.<lb/>
Obviously, although it might have been finally decided on August 1 to<lb/>
use volunteers, at least Reed had had that in mind for some time.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> That is perfectly clear. However, whether Reed had dis-<lb/>
cussed his ideas on human volunteers with the others, that I do not<lb/>
know.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #11:</hi> In Mrs. Reed's scrap book about her husband, I have found<lb/>
a newspaper article dated April 11, 1905 (city and name of paper not<lb/>
identified) with a photograph of the isolation buildings of the yellow<lb/>
- 7 -<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06402008"/>
- 8 -<lb/>
fever hospital at Columbia Barracks. Do these little buildings look<lb/>
familiar to you; do you think this is where you were sick with yellow<lb/>
fever?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I think that I was treated in one of these buildings,<lb/>
but I am not now able to identify each one.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #12</hi>: In looking at these old photographs, and also comparing<lb/>
them with the 1902 map of Columbia Hospital, where do you think the<lb/>
road was, and also the railroad?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not know, but it would appear since the back of one<lb/>
faces the front of another that they were all probably facing the rail-<lb/>
road tracks, that is northeast. As I remember it, there was a narrow<lb/>
footbridge, which I remember very well, across the Marinao railroad<lb/>
track, probably passing half way between the road and the rows of little<lb/>
buildings, and I believe that the wagon road approached the little<lb/>
buildings from the south and then may have gone down between the two<lb/>
rows of little buildings, but your guess is as good as mine.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #13:</hi> Supplementing your answer to question 16 as given in our<lb/>
interview of May 8, 1941 about the presentation ceremony when a watch<lb/>
was given to Kissinger and not to Moran, may I say the following:<lb/>
When I saw Moran at Walter Reed Hospital in August, 1943, Moran stated<lb/>
his impression was that when Kissinger was cited he received not only<lb/>
a watch, but a purse. Moran thought that the hospital corps men had<lb/>
made a collection and enough was left over ($115.00) from the price of<lb/>
the watch to give him that much money extra. Moran was also under<lb/>
the impression that <del>General Kennedy</del><add>Maj Kean</add> was not present at the ceremony,<lb/>
- 8 -<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06402009"/>
- 9 -<lb/>
and that Reed presented the watch. Do you have any further remarks<lb/>
about this?</p>
<p><unclear>Sen Ted</unclear> Kean wrote &ldquo;There was no General Kennedy in<lb/>
Cuba &amp; no General at the ceremony. My <unclear>recollection</unclear> is that the only officers present were medical officers.&rdquo; (Kean).</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I believe that I was present at the ceremony, and I am<lb/>
sure that Havard, and not Reed, presented the watch. He was given<lb/>
no extra money at that time. The date of this ceremony you can find<lb/>
approximately by looking up the letter of Carroll in which he told<lb/>
his wife that he had bought the watch for Kissinger. It might be a<lb/>
good idea to write to Kissinger, as the date of the ceremony might<lb/>
be on the watch. The watch and chain cost about $115.00, and probably<lb/>
in a week or ten days Kissinger came to me and asked if the watch cost<lb/>
all of the $200.00, and when I said &ldquo;No&rdquo;, he asked if he could have the<lb/>
balance. (Just off the record - you can <hi>see that Kissinger went back<lb/>
on his original intention to volunteer without reward.</hi> Despite this,<lb/>
all these years Kissinger has allowed everyone to believe he never ac-<lb/>
cepted a reward. However, Moran stuck to his agreement and never ac-<lb/>
cepted any reward until the Government rewarded him years later, and is,<lb/>
therefore, in a separate class from Kissinger). It was because of<lb/>
Moran's insistance that he be not rewarded, that it never occurred to<lb/>
me to get him a watch or any other reward.</p>
<p>The watch ceremony was undoubtedly held on the parade ground of<lb/>
the hospital, that is between the wards and the Bachelor Officers'<lb/>
quarters, and there were probably present only the men on duty that<lb/>
day - maybe twenty five or so.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #14</hi>: Moran also feels a little hurt that when he was invited<lb/>
to attend the ceremony, he simply stood by himself in the rear some-<lb/>
where. General Truby explained this to me about this way: &ldquo;There is<lb/>
- 9 -<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06402010"/>
- 10 -<lb/>
no place for a civilian in a military ceremony&rdquo;. However, my re-<lb/>
action is that since Moran had been in the army just a few weeks be-<lb/>
fore and had done such a meritorious thing, he might have been invited<lb/>
to stand in a special place. What is your reaction to this?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I believe that would have been a very proper thing to<lb/>
do, but apparently no one thought of it.</p>
<p>(Comment by Dr. Hench: This recalls to me Moran's statement in<lb/>
one of his early letters to me that through the years he has never<lb/>
willingly sought any monetary reward, although he has been a perennial<lb/>
candidate for any medal from leather to gold. Obviously Moran did<lb/>
not want the money, but even at that date he would have been very<lb/>
happy to receive a watch or any other non-monetary reward, and his not<lb/>
getting a watch has hurt him all these years.)</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #15:</hi> Have they told you what Lambert told me that in the be-<lb/>
ginning Lambert believes that Reed was afraid of yellow fever?</p>
<p>(Here Dr. Hench told Lambert's story about Reed using camphor in<lb/>
the autopsy room and not approaching the body, and also how Lambert<lb/>
interfered with Reed's putting a mosquito on one of Lam<add>b</add>ert's very<lb/>
sick patients).</p>
<p>What is your reaction to this story?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not believe most of it. I am sure I would be afraid<lb/>
of things, but it would not prevent me from doing my duty. Reed un-<lb/>
doubtedly did not want to expose himself needlessly to yellow fever,<lb/>
but I am sure he was ready to check the experiments, if and when it be-<lb/>
came necessary, and would take any exposure which was justified.<lb/>
- 10 -<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06402011"/>
- 11 -<lb/>
I do not believe anything of the camphor story.</p>
<p>(OFF THE RECORD: (Dr. Hench) Here I told General Kean about<lb/>
Lambert's supposed little episode when Major Kean asked to see the<lb/>
thermometer. General Kean remembers nothing about this, and although<lb/>
Lambert may have been his nurse, he does not remember for sure; al-<lb/>
though Major Kean does (not)<add><unclear></unclear></add> recall that he was very sick, nevertheless<lb/>
he appears to remember very little about his yellow fever illness).</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #16</hi>: Have you any further recollection of your conversation<lb/>
with Reed before he died? Can you amplify what you told me about<lb/>
your last visit to Walter Reed the night of his death?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Very little. I took Blossom down to see her father.<lb/>
We were living in the same apartment at 1603 - 19th St., N.W. (I<lb/>
think we lived on the third floor, and the Reeds on the second floor on<lb/>
the south side of the hall). We stayed about ten minutes at the hos-<lb/>
pital. I saw that Reed was dying; he was perfectly conscious and re-<lb/>
cognized both of us at once. Blossom was overcome and left the room<lb/>
immediately. Reed knew he was dying and wanted to say goodbye to her.<lb/>
I found Blossom completely overcome and unable to go back into the room;<lb/>
therefore I made some excuse to Reed why she did not go back. I told<lb/>
him I thought it was the odor of the room that made her sick, and he<lb/>
said, &ldquo;Well take her home, Kean&rdquo;. We talked just a few minutes more,<lb/>
and it was then I told him that I learned the Secretary of War had put<lb/>
in his report just about to go out a recommendation that he should be<lb/>
made a Colonel in the corps, and the Act also recommended Gorgas for<lb/>
Lt. Colonel, but Reed replied, &ldquo;I do not care for that now&rdquo;. Then<lb/>
he spoke about how little he was leaving his family, and was worried<lb/>
- 11 -<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06402012"/>
- 12 -<lb/>
over that. (See Dr. Kelley's book. I undoubtedly gave him that<lb/>
story years ago when my memory was better.)</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #17:</hi> About three weeks ago when I visited Mrs. Reed at Blue<lb/>
Ridge Summit, Blossom stated to me that her father would have become<lb/>
the Surgeon General in a few months had he lived. I am sure that this<lb/>
is wrong. I know that you suggested the nomination of Reed by writing<lb/>
a letter to the Army and Navy Journal.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: Obviously Blossom is wrong. O'Reilly was already<lb/>
Surgeon General three months before Reed died.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #18</hi> Maybe Blossom thought her father might become Surgeon<lb/>
General after O'Reilly served his term.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> If so he would have had to wait eight years for O'Reilly<lb/>
was Surgeon General for about that long.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #19:</hi> How were the Spanish immigrants approached?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> General Wood had been shocked at the Spanish immigrants<lb/>
coming over and going into the city of Havana and becoming infected<lb/>
with yellow fever, so he established a camp for Spanish immigrant<lb/>
laborers on the heights of Cabana. That camp was under the quarantine<lb/>
officer Menocal, and it was through Menocal that these men were pro-<lb/>
cured. He apparently just went to them and told them of the offer of<lb/>
employment and those who accepted were taken out to Camp Lazear, and<lb/>
while they were being interned under initial quarantine they were<lb/>
utilized to pick up stones. The owners of the large sugar plantations<lb/>
- 12 -<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06402013"/>
- 13 -<lb/>
would send over to Cabana for these Spaniards to work on the plantations.<lb/>
They would take the train outside, thus avoiding Havana entirely, and<lb/>
go out to the plantations where there was no danger of yellow fever.</p>
<p>A little later there was an article in <hi>La Discus<del>s</del><add><unclear></unclear></add>ion</hi> about the<lb/>
cruel experiments being made on the Spaniards, but the Consul General,<lb/>
a very nice man, told Reed not to worry, but to go ahead, but not to<lb/>
take any under twenty four years. (The Spaniards do not become of<lb/>
age until twenty four). The experiments were proposed to them, I<lb/>
think, after they reached the camp.</p>
<p>(See my notes on General Kean's Diary, Nov. 23, 1900, also<lb/>
Nov. 25).</p>
<p><hi>QUESTION #20</hi>: Describe Lazear's funeral as much as you can.</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> There was a group of funerals of yellow fever cases in<lb/>
the Autumn of 1900 that were superimposed in my mind so that I find<lb/>
it difficult to get any separate picture of one as distinguished from<lb/>
another. General Lee attended these funerals, and as he always liked<lb/>
to go on horseback, he always turned out with his staff mounted although<lb/>
the distance was not over about half a mile from headquarters, and a<lb/>
quarter of a mile from the hospital. We rode in a group behind the<lb/>
Red Cross ambulance carrying the coffin, and sat on our horses through<lb/>
the very brief ceremony in the road on a very small plot - about 150<lb/>
feet square. Such nurses not on duty, and a number of the hospital<lb/>
corps men were present, but no general turnout of troops. There was<lb/>
no turnout of troops on account of the nature of the disease. There<lb/>
were probably forty or fifty. There was no band; there may have been<lb/>
a drummer, and undoubtedly a bugler to blow taps. I do not believe<lb/>
- 13 -<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06402014"/>
- 14 -<lb/>
I do not believe there were drummers. Probably the corps men fell<lb/>
in columns of twos behind the headquarters staff on horseback.</p>
<p><hi>QUESTION #21:</hi> What is your reaction to Dr. Pinto's remark in his<lb/>
letter to Truby, August 16, 1941: &ldquo;We know that Agramonte was a dud&rdquo;?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think that Agramonte probably did all the work that<lb/>
was expected and required of him. He was not relieved from other<lb/>
duties, and his work on the Board was in combination with his other<lb/>
work in his laboratory in Havana. That statement is too strong.</p></item>
<item><p>QUESTION #22: Do you think that Ames had yellow fever? (See your<lb/>
letter to me of December 27, 1941 and June 26, 1942).</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not believe he ever had yellow fever while in Cuba.<lb/>
He claims to be immune, and it was for that reason that he was freely<lb/>
admitted to Camp Lazear. See Major Reed's statement in the &ldquo;Additional<lb/>
Note&rdquo; of the Yellow Fever Board in describing Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>also <unclear>on</unclear> Stark's <unclear>d</unclear> note</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #23:</hi> In Reed's letter to Mrs. Reed December 16, 1900 he<lb/>
humoursly refers to when he might become Surgeon General. What is<lb/>
the significance of this?</p>
<p>no <unclear></unclear></p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Just a jest.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #24:</hi> Who was Madame Abreu?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> She had a very beautiful home at Las Dilicias where she<lb/>
entertained a great deal. She had a regular menagerie, among which<lb/>
was a thoroughly trained chimpanzee which she called Chimpar. She<lb/>
was a very public spirited woman, and I suppose offered Chimpar for<lb/>
- 14 -<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f06402015"/>
- 15 -<lb/>
experiment. Agramonte told me that he got Chimpar and tried to give<lb/>
him yellow fever, but he was perfectly immune. General Kean says, &ldquo;I<lb/>
do not think African monkeys can get yellow fever.&rdquo;</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #25:</hi> What evidence do you know of that Reed was interested<lb/>
in the mosquito before going to Havana? (I suspect strongly that he<lb/>
was; however I find it very difficult to find any proof that he was.)</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Dr. L. O. Howard, 45 Pondfield Road, West Bronxville,<lb/>
N.Y., knows more about that than anyone else. I personally have no<lb/>
knowledge on this point. He said that Reed and Carroll came to his<lb/>
laboratory to study mosquitoes before they started to Cuba.</p>
<p><hi>QUESTION #26</hi>: In Reed's letter to General Sternberg, July 24, 1900,<lb/>
Reed criticises Godfrey unmercifully. I am surprised at the intensity<lb/>
of this criticism. Godfrey had made a mistake, and a bad mistake, but<lb/>
doctors can often make bad mistakes - even good doctors. Do you think<lb/>
this criticism was too emphatic?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Not a bit. Every physician down there was constantly<lb/>
sent circulars and instructions concerning yellow fever and the chief<lb/>
diagnostic problem. After all Godfrey had eleven post-mortems and<lb/>
should certainly have known he was dealing with yellow fever. I<lb/>
thought at the time that he should have been court-martialed, and I<lb/>
still think so.</p>
<p>(The following is confidential and is not to incriminate General<lb/>
Kean. However, I am anxious to have it as a part of a meager evidence<lb/>
that I think that Reed really was interested in the mosquito theory<lb/>
before yellow fever.)</p>
<p>- 15 -</p>
<pb n="16" id="f06402016"/>
<p>- 16 -</p>
<p><hi>GENERAL KEAN</hi>: Reed told me of his conversation with General Sternberg;<lb/>
my recollection is that he told me in the summer of 1902. I saw him<lb/>
quite often that summer. He told me that he asked General Sternberg<lb/>
before he went to Cuba whether he should pay any attention to the<lb/>
study of the theory that the mosquito was a conveyor of yellow fever.<lb/>
Sternberg said, &ldquo;Well, you can do it if you want, but I think you will<lb/>
be wasting your time&rdquo;. Reed was very much irritated when he <add>late</add> heard<lb/>
that General Sternberg claimed to <add>have</add> <unclear>advise</unclear> him to study the mosquito.<lb/>
(See Mrs. Sternberg's Life of General Sternberg). Also this was<lb/>
mentioned by Dr. Kober somewhere - possibly in his Autobiography.</p>
<p>So there a<lb/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
autobiography</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #27</hi> In the original Special Order AGO 122, May 24, 1900,<lb/>
paragraph 34, photographs of which I have, and which I got from the<lb/>
Archives Building, the statement is made &ldquo;............for the purpose<lb/>
of pursuing scientific investigations with reference to infectious<lb/>
diseases, <hi>especially yellow fever</hi>, prevailing in the Island of Cuba&rdquo;.<lb/>
However, the order that appeared finally under date of the same day,<lb/>
left out the words <hi>especially yellow fever</hi>, and in my photograph the<lb/>
order is corrected in pencil to leave out these words. Somewhere I<lb/>
was told that this may have been done for diplomatic reasons, not to<lb/>
insult the Cubans, or at least not to emphasize to Americans who had<lb/>
sons in Cuba they had yellow fever there. Have you ever heard any<lb/>
explanation of why these words were left out?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I do not know any reason; I never heard it.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #28</hi>: The original army photographs of Camp Lazear give the<lb/>
impression that the camp was quite flat in all directions. As a<lb/>
- 16 -<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f06402017"/>
- 17 -<lb/>
matter of fact my own photographs taken in the same direction as the<lb/>
army photographs show the land relatively flat, but just a few hundred<lb/>
yards in the opposite direction it is quite hilly, with little va.lleys<lb/>
and hills. General Truby recollected that this was the condition at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, that there were hills and valleys near by. What is your<lb/>
recollection?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> My recollection is that it was a rolling country right<lb/>
near the camp.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>QUESTION #29</hi>: Let me show you a photograph which Blossom Reed loaned<lb/>
me three weeks ago. It shows her father on the boat on the way to<lb/>
Cuba. She thinks it was taken on one of his first trips to Cuba on<lb/>
his way to the yellow fever work. Why is he not in uniform?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> We did not travel in uniform except with troops when<lb/>
the country was not at war. In the first World War we had to wear<lb/>
the uniform until the end of the war.</p>
<p><hi>QUESTION #30</hi>: The one thing that puzzles me in General Truby's book<lb/>
is his identification of the Surgery, or Walter Reed Laboratory figure<lb/>
19 facing page 87, the same as figure 11 facing page 56. In figure<lb/>
11 you can see on the right horizon a large building, which is un-<lb/>
doubtedly General Lee's headquarters, Duranonia Building. If that<lb/>
is so the picture was taken looking southeast. The 1902 map of<lb/>
Camp Columbia would indicate Walter Reed Surgery facing west. In this<lb/>
photograph it is facing north; in other words, its long axis seems to<lb/>
have been changed. General Truby persists in his identification,<lb/>
but admits the logic of my argument. However, he says that this<lb/>
little building might very well have been moved or turned after the<lb/>
- 17 -<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f06402018"/>
- 18 -<lb/>
rest of the Second Division Hospital and tents were removed, and when<lb/>
this little building became part of the permanent wooden buildings of<lb/>
the Columbia Base Hospital. It is difficult for me to see why they<lb/>
would move a little building like this. Today we would not bother<lb/>
to move such a building; we would build a new one as an easier way.<lb/>
What is your recollection of this?</p>
<p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think that the house is so nearly square that we cannot<lb/>
be certain which is the long axis. Probably the building was not<lb/>
moved at all; however it might very well have been moved. It would<lb/>
have been no trouble to put a little house like that on rollers and<lb/>
move it. &ldquo;It was often done&rdquo; (Kean)</p></item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
