<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06409004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, June 5, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06409004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-06-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Magoon Charles E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Rojas family</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Major</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lawrence [Walter L.]</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Rojas farm, San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>19 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-06-05">June 5, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06409004</idno>
<title>Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, June 5, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean provides his recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, in response to Hench's questions.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-06-05">
<head>Interview of Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, June 5, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06409004"/>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head>QUESTIONING OF GENERAL KEAN BY DR. HENCH</head>
<item><p><hi>Q. #65</hi> In your letter of September 17, 1940 you said &ldquo;........Be-<lb/>
cause Agramonte had come to me and complained that I had done him a<lb/>
great injustice in a formal Senate document&rdquo; I inserted a statement<lb/>
of his over the signature of the Surgeon General.</p>
<p>Did Agramonte actually visit you about this so-called injustice,<lb/>
or just write to you.</p></item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I am sure he just wrote to me. I have found a letter from<lb/>
Agramonte in which he takes up this matter and discusses it with a great<lb/>
deal of feeling. The statement was from the Surgeon General to sup-<lb/>
port a bill to give pensions to the widows of Dr. Lazear and Dr. Carroll<lb/>
and was written in 1908. There is some ground for complaint of the<lb/>
statement which I prepared for the Surgeon General and it went out in<lb/>
his name, but not as much as Agramonte seems to think. In one place a<lb/>
paper is alluded to as written by members of the Board, but his name is<lb/>
left out. I imagine that this was an accidental omission by the sten-<lb/>
ographer. It is true, however, that I did an injustice to Agramonte<lb/>
by stating that he had nothing to do with the mosquito work after La-<lb/>
zear's death. I got that statement from Dr. Carroll. Agramonte<lb/>
states that he took Lazear's cultures and jars of infected mosquitoes<lb/>
down to his laboratory - I think military hospital No. 1 - and kept<lb/>
them there until Camp Lazear was established. Agramonte did not seem<lb/>
to realize that the Surgeon General memorandum had special reference to<lb/>
the work of the two men whose widows were asking for the pension, so<lb/>
special emphasis was laid on the services of these two men. (Agramonte's<lb/>
letter is dated July 3, 1908).</item>
<item>- 1 -</item>
<pb n="2" id="f06409005"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>Q. #66: When was your painting which is hanging in Havana painted -<lb/>
in 1909 as one of your letters says, or 1911 as one of my notes says?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> In 1911, painted by to be looked up my diary <unclear>VII</unclear> p. 78<lb/>
says that crayon portraits of Gov. Magoon, Dr Findlay and me were unveiled in the sa<lb/>
sala of the <unclear>Junta</unclear> Nacional March 7, 1908- The oil portraits were <unclear>doubtless</unclear> made later</item>
<item><unclear>file</unclear> in<lb/>
name</item>
<item>Q. #67: I have told you that Mrs. Rojas told me that Major Reed<lb/>
used to visit Camp Lazear, and then sit on their front porch. He liked<lb/>
it there very much, and expressed his liking of it, and one day her<lb/>
husband suggested that if Major Reed really did want to come back to<lb/>
Cuba to live, he would give him a part of the Finca <del>of</del> San Jos&eacute; to<lb/>
build a little home and go there and retire. What is your impression of<lb/>
that?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi> Reed had a lovely place in Pennsylvania where he <add>went</add> on vacations<lb/>
and visits. I do not know why he would want to live in Cuba in view of<lb/>
this, I am sure. Reed was probably making conversation with the Rojas<lb/>
family.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #68</hi>: On page 1 of our interview of May 8, 1941 there is mention of<lb/>
a request of Carroll to have a check for $950.00. Don't you think that<lb/>
should have been #150.00?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi> Certainly - $150.00</item>
<item><hi>Q. #69</hi> In the old book which mentioned the expenses of Camp Lazear,<lb/>
there is a check for $150.00 for Kissinger, and later on the same day<lb/>
another check for $50.00 for Kissinger. Do you remember what that was<lb/>
for?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER</hi> My recollection is that the $150.00 was to get Kissinger a<lb/>
gold watch and chain to be presented to him by the Chief Surgeon as a<lb/>
mark of appreciation for his submitting himself to the yellow fever ex-<lb/>
periments<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06409006"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
The check was, I think, endorsed by Kissinger.</p>
<p>Why was it not made out to Carroll instead of Kissinger if Carroll<lb/>
was going to buy the watch?</p>
<p>expenses</p>
<p>I do not know just why this was. I always mentioned those exper-<lb/>
iences to Reed, and it is possible I gave the check to Reed. I have no<lb/>
recollection of Carroll entering into it at all.</p>
<p>What was the additional $50.00?</p>
<p>That was the balance of the $200.00 which was a gratuity for men who<lb/>
had the yellow fever.</p>
<p>You told me before that Kissinger came back and asked for it.</p>
<p>Kissinger had expressed a desire to me for the balance of the money,<lb/>
and so I gave him a check for it, apparently on the same day. The check<lb/>
was drawn on the same day.</p></item>
<item>Q. #70: This morning in the Army Medical Museum I saw in a cabinet<lb/>
the small cloth container which Mrs. Reed presented to the Museum in<lb/>
which, according to Mrs. Reed, all of the gold pieces given to the vol-<lb/>
unteers who got yellow fever were held. Did he give the gold pieces, or<lb/>
did you? Perhaps Mrs. Reed's note is in error. The checks were drawn<lb/>
by you in the name of the men who received the money. Where did the<lb/>
gold pieces come in if you gave the men checks?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: The only gold pieces that I have any recollection of I drew<lb/>
myself from the bank and took out to one of the early Spanish volunteers -<lb/>
Antonio Benigno. My recollection is that I drew the money, and I re-<lb/>
call his delight at receiving the great gold pieces (<del>seven</del><add>ten</add> $20.00<lb/>
American gold pieces), and the nurses told me that he spent the whole<lb/>
day playing with the gold pieces. One of the nurses, I was told,<lb/>
made him a little bag to hold them. That is the only bag for gold pieces<lb/>
of which I have any knowledge. What the other bag is for I do not know.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06409007"/>
<item>- 4 -</item>
<item>Q. #71 Do you know whether you or Dr. Reed cashed any of the other<lb/>
checks and converted them in gold pieces and presented the volunteers<lb/>
with gold rather than check?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I did not give gold pieces to any other of the volunteers.<lb/>
Whether Major Reed did or not, I do not know.</p>
<p>These checks made out by you in the name of the volunteers, were they<lb/>
given directly to the volunteers, or did they countersign them and you<lb/>
cashed them?</p>
<p>Most of them were made out to the volunteers and presented to Reed.<lb/>
It is possible that he had the volunteer countersign the check, and he<lb/>
had the pleasure of handing the money to the volunteer.</p></item>
<item>Q. #72: On page 1 of our interview of May 8, 1941 you mentioned that<lb/>
Lazear on June 1st pointed out to you the difference between the male<lb/>
and female mosquitoes. What kind of mosquitoes?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> My impression is the stegomyia, afterwards identified as<lb/>
the yellow fever mosquito.</item>
<item>Q. #73: Do you think that at the time Lazear was interested in the<lb/>
stegomyia even then as the cause of yellow fever in view of the fact that<lb/>
you were visiting a yellow fever house and he pointed these mosquitoes<lb/>
out to you?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I think so; it looks like it. In the light of subsequent<lb/>
events I would think that even then he suspected that these mosquitoes<lb/>
were the cause of yellow fever.</item>
<item><hi>REMINISCENCE</hi>: In our conversation about the Starks on Monday night I<lb/>
failed to mention an act of kindness and courage of Mrs. Stark's that<lb/>
made a deep impression on me. When Major <del><unclear></unclear></del> Edmunds, who lived<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06409008"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
with his wife and two children in the house on General Lee St. in Que-<lb/>
mados which I had formerly lived in, when he died of yellow fever and<lb/>
his wife had come down with it, Mrs. Stark had the two children brought<lb/>
to her and took care of them with her children although we all believed<lb/>
at that time that yellow fever was <add>a</add> highly contagious disease.</item>
<item><p><hi>Dr. Hench:</hi> I visited Mrs. Stark yesterday and asked her about this<lb/>
story. She laughed and said that she remembered the incident as follows:<lb/>
She was in her house one evening and heard you (General Kean) and her<lb/>
husband conversing in the next room. She overheard one of you say &ldquo;<lb/>
what shall we do with the little girl&rdquo;. You kept talking about the<lb/>
problem at hand, and she interrupted you and asked you &ldquo;what is wrong,<lb/>
what is worrying you&rdquo;? You then told her about the serious illness of<lb/>
Major Edmunds who was apparently dying and that his wife was also sick,<lb/>
and that the little girl was alone except for the Cuban housemaid. She<lb/>
immediately said &ldquo;bring her over here&rdquo;, and it appears that either you<lb/>
or her husband hesitated about bringing the child from the yellow fever<lb/>
house to her house, whereupon she said &ldquo;let's go after her right away&rdquo;,<lb/>
whereupon you and her husband, and Mrs. Stark went over to Major Edmund's<lb/>
house, and the little girl went in the room where her father lay dying,<lb/>
and was allowed only to take out her tooth brush, the rest of her cloth-<lb/>
ing she had to leave as they were in the room where her father was dying.<lb/>
It was Mrs. Stark's recollection that <del>her</del><add>the child's</add> father died later that evening.<lb/>
(General Kean's recollection is that the girl was 8 or 10 years old). It<lb/>
is Mrs. Stark's recollection when Major Edmunds died, Mrs. Edmunds was<lb/>
removed from the house and cared for in the yellow fever huts. Mrs.<lb/>
Stark had to make elaborate arrangements so that the little girl would<lb/>
not notice the funeral procession the next day when the Major was buried.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06409009"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
They were not prepared to tell the child, they preferred to have the<lb/>
mother tell her. Later when Mrs. Edmunds recovered the child of course<lb/>
went back with her mother. <unclear>'</unclear>It was Mrs. Stark's impression that the<lb/>
little <add>Edmunds</add> boy was not in Havana at the time.</p>
<p>Mrs. Stark told me the following anecdote about her two young sons<lb/>
who were then about four years of age. One day one of these two boys<lb/>
got in Major Reed's room - the end room in the bachelors' quarters. In<lb/>
this room Reed happened to have some tubes or vials of black vomit.<lb/>
Reed came into the room and found the two boys sitting sheepishly on the<lb/>
floor with the black vomit all over their little white suits and the<lb/>
vials broken. He grabbed them, one under each arm, and hurried them to<lb/>
the hospital. He got in touch with their father and they were thoroughly<lb/>
scrubbed with a disinfectant solution. Nothing was said to Mrs. Stark.<lb/>
Later that evening the Stark's Cuban nurse told the two boys to get ready<lb/>
to take their bath. They objected because they had already had a bath<lb/>
in the afternoon. The mammy said something like this: &ldquo;nonsense, when<lb/>
did you have a bath&rdquo;. They replied Reed had given them a bath at the<lb/>
hospital. The nurse then said &ldquo;don't be so foolish, why would he give<lb/>
you a bath&rdquo;? &ldquo;Go along with you and take your bath&rdquo;. Mrs. Stark knew<lb/>
nothing about this for ten days. Dr. Stark took their temperature for<lb/>
ten days, and when there was no danger Mrs. Stark was told.</p>
<p>I have also heard another story. These two boys <unclear>mischievouslyy</unclear><lb/>
swiped some postmortem specimens from Dr. Carroll's laboratory and held<lb/>
him up for a bribe before they would give them back. Mrs. Stark did not<lb/>
remember this story. She did not know whether these two stories were in<lb/>
a sense the same story told in a different way, or whether they were two<lb/>
different occurrences. She admitted her boys were mischievous enough<lb/>
to have many things happen to them. Do you recall these two incidents,<lb/>
or do you remember any similar episode?</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06409010"/>
<p>- 7 -</p>
<p>What I remember is the second episode; that they got a bottle with<lb/>
some pathological material in it from Carroll's room. They crawled<lb/>
<unclear>The floor slanted somewhat &amp; Carroll couldn't go in after<lb/>
them</unclear><lb/>
under the floor of the bachelors' quarters. They would not surrender<lb/>
the material until Carroll agreed to buy them some candy.</p>
<p>Would he keep material in his room? (Dr. Hench)</p>
<p>Apparently he did. (Gen. Kean)</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. 74:</hi> What was the name of Menocal of whom you often spoke, and who<lb/>
was he?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Francisco E. Menocal, Commissioner of Immigration.</item>
<item><hi>Q. 75:</hi> In regard to Question 11 on page 2 of our interview of May<lb/>
8, 1941, did you hear that Carroll was upset about Lazear having put the<lb/>
mosquito on him from Carroll himself or do you only know of it from<lb/>
Hemmeter's book?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> My impression is that I heard Carroll say it.</item>
<item><hi>Q. 76:</hi> Can you tell me any more details about your visit to Dr. Reed<lb/>
with Blossom when he was dying? You mentioned <add>that you visited him</add> about 8 P.M. November 24<lb/>
Blossom was only in the room two minutes and burst in tears and ran out.<lb/>
You stated that you were distressed that she could not control herself as<lb/>
Reed had been anxious to see her. You went out and talked to Blossom<lb/>
and asked her to come back in, but she said she could not. You then went<lb/>
back in Reed's room and made up the excuse that she was made sick by the<lb/>
odor from the wound. You were in the room only about ten minutes and Mrs<lb/>
Reed was at home in her apartment. <del><unclear>Did</unclear></del> Do you remember any other con-<lb/>
versation with Reed except his remark about the Colonelcy? He said he<lb/>
was leaving so little. Do you remember?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I think that he said that when he was going under the anes-<lb/>
thetic.</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06409011"/>
<p>- 8 -</p>
<p>Did he expect to die when he went under the anesthetic, or was that<lb/>
the remark of any man who was having an operation?</p>
<p>My impression is that it was when he went under the operation.</p>
<p>Do you remember anything else he said, or that you talked about?</p>
<p>No, I do not.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. #77:</hi> In what building in <del>Indiana</del><add>Indianapolis</add> <del>is</del><add>was</add> the Preliminary Note <unclear>read</unclear>?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> <unclear>Ravenal</unclear> could tell you that.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #78:</hi> What was the Army's reaction to Reed's work?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> They accepted it promptly.</p>
<p>What was the reaction of non-medical officers?</p>
<p>I do not know.</p>
<p>General Lee was devoted to me, and he took me aside and said<lb/>
&ldquo;do not tie yourself up to this theory of Reed's about mosquitoes. I<lb/>
am older than you are, and if they are disproved I am sure it will in-<lb/>
jure your professional standing if you should be too enthusiastic about<lb/>
it.&rdquo; I told General Lee there was nothing I would rather <del><unclear></unclear></del> risk my<lb/>
reputation on than the proof of this theory.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. 79</hi> In what connection did he say this and when?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER</hi>: It was in the Fall <add>1900</add> when I was getting mosquito orders out.<lb/>
He was a little uneasy about the proof of the theory as far as I was<lb/>
concerned - it was about October or November <add>1900</add>.</p>
<p>General Lee was the Commanding General, of the 7th Army Corps<lb/>
until the end of December 1898. Then he was made the Commanding General<lb/>
of the military department of Havana and then Pinar del Rio was added;<lb/>
they discontinued Pinar del Rio as a separate department and gave him<lb/>
both; then later they divided all Cuba into two departments and he was<lb/>
given western Cuba.</p></item>
<pb n="9" id="f06409012"/>
<item>- 9 -</item>
<item><hi>Q #80</hi>: What was the reaction of the town physicians in Marianao?</item>
<item>ANSWER: <unclear>Ang<del>e</del>l&eacute;s</unclear> was the only one I knew and he was always friendly.<lb/>
We consulted them about yellow fever, but I think they probably thought<lb/>
that we were a little snooty because we thought we knew their job better<lb/>
than they.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #81:</hi> What was the reaction of the women folks when the yellow<lb/>
fever epidemic began in the Spring of 1900. Did they have a feeling of<lb/>
quiet fear or were they panicky?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: I think everybody had some fear and uneasiness about it ex-<lb/>
cept General Fitzhugh Lee, but there was never any panic.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #82:</hi> When the yellow fever began did you send your wives away?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> The officers were encouraged to send their wives and families<lb/>
away. It made things easier for the Medical Department. Looking after<lb/>
a case of yellow fever was a terrible thing as the facilities were not<lb/>
good.</p>
<p>Did you send your family away before the epidemic, or when<lb/>
it began?</p>
<p>I sent them North for the summer; my wife went North in May <add>1900</add>.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. #83</hi> You remember the story in Kelly's book where Reed said,<lb/>
&ldquo;Gentlemen, I salute you&rdquo;? As you know, it never happened.</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER</hi> I am quite sure it never happened. There was nothing dramatic<lb/>
about Reed. <unclear>Son Wihammia was awe</unclear> it did.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench</hi>: When I told Mrs. Reed and General Lawrence Reed that story<lb/>
was not true, General Reed was rather sorry to hear it. Knowing his<lb/>
father as he did, he thought he might have said something like that, but<lb/>
not so dramatic.</p>
<p><hi>General Kean</hi>: He may have said it; in the pictures of it he is saluting<lb/>
without a cap.</p></item>
<pb n="10" id="f06409013"/>
<item>- 10-</item>
<item><hi>Q. #84:</hi> Can you tell me anything more about Lazear's funeral?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> It was held about eleven o'clock in the morning the day<lb/>
after he died. There were only about 40 or 50 at the funeral- perhaps<lb/>
10 or 12 officers on horseback, hospital corpsmen, six or eight nurses<lb/>
and perhaps twenty enlisted men. It is my recollection that they had<lb/>
a band, but you told me that General Truby tells otherwise. The<lb/>
Episcopal commitment service was used, I believe.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #85:</hi> Who was Madame Abreu's husband?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> She did not have any husband when I was around there. She<lb/>
had a number of animals in her beautiful plantation &ldquo;Las Delicious&rdquo;.<lb/>
Agramonte said that she had a chimpanzee that was very gentle and in-<lb/>
telligent and very well trained; she very often had him as a companion<lb/>
to dinner. It was quite a well known animal. Agramonte said that he<lb/>
got him and took him down to the ward and that the chimpanzee was im-<lb/>
mune to yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench</hi>: Why did the monkey not get yellow fever?</p>
<p><hi>General Kean:</hi> The monkey had lived in Cuba for quite a while, but he<lb/>
may still have been immune. African monkeys are immune, because that<lb/>
is the home of the disease, and they have developed a racial immunity.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench</hi>: How did Agramonte happen to ask her for the animal?</p>
<p><hi>General Kean:</hi> She was the only one who had a chimpanzee; she was a very<lb/>
friendly person in good standing, and she would be apt to do what she<lb/>
wanted.</p></item>
<item>Q. #86: Where did Walter Reed die?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Walter Reed died in the hospital at Washington Barracks.</p>
<p>Dr. HencH Do you remember what room he died in?</p>
<p>Gen. Kean: It was on the second floor and on the left hand side of the<lb/>
hall, but it was not the front room; the next room to the front<unclear><del>.</del></unclear> I think</p></item>
<pb n="11" id="f06409014"/>
<item>- 11 -</item>
<item><hi>Q #87:</hi> Do you have any recollection of where the prison was in<lb/>
Pinar del Rio where the <del>solder</del><add>soldier</add> was who got yellow fever and died?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> No I have not.</item>
<item>Q. #88 Do you think that prison is still there?</item>
<item><p><hi>Answer:</hi> They were pretty substantial buildings - I guess so.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench:</hi> Is that garrison still there?</p>
<p><hi>Gen. Kean:</hi> <del>It might be.</del>The buildings probably are-</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. #88:</hi> Did Reed tell you anything personally about the experience at<lb/>
Pinar del Rio?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> That was very familiar to me. I think that Reed did tell<lb/>
me. Reed used to laugh at me a great deal about Pinar del Rio. I was<lb/>
sent there to dispose of military property about September 1900 after I<lb/>
came back from my sick leave. The army people were full of this idea of<lb/>
fomites and they did not want to buy from the commissary at Pinar del<lb/>
Rio, and I recommended that the commissary <add>supplies</add> be sold to the Cubans. The<lb/>
Cubans were very glad to get most of the stuff. (<unclear>They</unclear> were mostly immune to Y F).</item>
<item><hi>Q. #89</hi> What did you have to do with the disposal?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I just made a recommendation to the Commanding General. I<lb/>
went up to Pinar del Rio and spent several days and recommended that it<lb/>
be taken in a storehouse and then disposed of. Walter Reed asked me,<lb/>
"Kean, what did you do with that stuff, what did you burn up and what did<lb/>
you sell to the Cubans. He was full of fun. This was many months later<lb/>
after I had joined him in Washington.</p>
<p>Reed never went back to Cuba after early Spring of 1901. He came<lb/>
out of Cuba Feb. 9, 1901, and never went back.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. #90:</hi> In Reed's letter of June 5, 1901 he says, &ldquo;I do not share<lb/>
your hopefulness concerning finding some immunizing method&rdquo;. Apparently<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06409015"/>
- 12 -<lb/>
you had some ideas about immunity that you expressed to Reed.</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I had rather vague general ideas; I thought that when you<lb/>
were working on a disease like that you should find some way to give<lb/>
people immunization. I had nothing special in mind.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #91:</hi> In one of General Truby's letters to you in 1914, he<lb/>
chided slightly about Agramonte.</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: Truby had some prejudice against Agramonte. I pre-<lb/>
ferred Agramonte to Carroll, and he preferred Carroll to Agramonte. We<lb/>
had seen different aspects of the work, and I found he was a straight<lb/>
forward and reliable man. Carroll did a number of improper things, and<lb/>
<del>if</del><add>thought</add> Reed robbed him of his credit in the matter, Reed had made Carroll.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #92:</hi> In one of your letters to me you talked about Noguchi.</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> He went over to Africa to the experimental station, and he<lb/>
took big chances there. He would never have gone there except for the<lb/>
experiments.</p>
<p>Hench: Someone remarked to me once they thought Noguchi committed<lb/>
suicide. (I think <unclear>we did. WBC</unclear>)</p>
<p>or was just stupid.</p>
<p><hi>General Kean:</hi> I see no reason that Noguchi committed suicide; it is<lb/>
perfectly possible, but I see no reason.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #93:</hi> When you went with Reed to see General Wood on October<lb/>
12 and suggested to Reed to use Spanish volunteers, did Reed tell you<lb/>
that he had already planned to use humans - not necessarily Spanish -<lb/>
but humans?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not remember that matter. It was perfectly well assumed<lb/>
by him and me that he was going to have experiments on humans.</p>
<pb n="13" id="f06409016"/>
<p>- 13 -</p>
<p>(Confidential): One time when I was in Washington - I do not quite re-<lb/>
member when - but it was while the experiments were going on, I began<lb/>
to talk over with Mrs. Reed her husband's work, and she was very much<lb/>
shocked at the idea of inoculating human beings. She thought it was<lb/>
terrible, and I said &ldquo;I did not think so at all, and I am surprised that<lb/>
you should think so; it has turned out wonderfully, and is a great piece<lb/>
of work, and will save many lives.&rdquo; Then she shut up.</p></item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #94:</hi> Do you remember of your own knowledge anything about<lb/>
Reed's reaction to Carter's paper?</item>
<item><p><hi>ANSWER:</hi> He told me that he had read this paper with interest,<lb/>
and that Carter had shown that if a man is exposed to yellow fever in<lb/>
New Orleans and came up to his home in a town in Mississippi and had<lb/>
yellow fever, a secondary case of yellow fever would not occur for three<lb/>
weeks, but after that a case from that man would occur in a week, and he<lb/>
wanted to know why it was it took three weeks for the first man to pass<lb/>
on the infection, and afterwards it took only one week. I said I do not<lb/>
know why. He said &ldquo;don't you see that the difference was caused by the<lb/>
development of the infection in an insect. We have biting insects, but<lb/>
in Virginia we have the mosquito in lower Virginia, and the bedbug and<lb/>
the flea, but the bedbug and the flea have never been accused of carrying<lb/>
yellow fever, but the mosquitoes are down in Tidewater, and that is where<lb/>
the yellow fever appears; it does not go up in the Piedmont country.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The following is confidential, meaning that General Kean doesn't<lb/>
wish to be quoted directly, but is willing for me to use the material<lb/>
without quoting him:</p></item>
<item>#94: You have read the abstracts from General Sternberg's Biography in<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06409017"/>
- 14 -<lb/>
which Mrs. Sternberg includes quotations from General Sternberg's<lb/>
remarks of Agramonte to the effect that when the Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
was formed, Sternberg in the very first conversation with Reed out-<lb/>
lined to Reed in a very precise fashion the various steps to be carried<lb/>
out in the investigation of yellow fever. Dr. Howard in his book ex-<lb/>
presses another attitude, and states that he first believed the same<lb/>
thing, but later was corrected by Reed, and therefore Howard in a later<lb/>
paper corrected the impression, and stated that Reed was the one who<lb/>
had all the ideas to study out. How much do you think Sternberg told<lb/>
Reed in the original instructions?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: It should be divided into the general instructions about the<lb/>
cause of yellow fever, and a particular one about an animal host. I<lb/>
have no doubt that Sternberg had been quite minute along the line of<lb/>
work of which he was so familiar, but I do not believe that he suggested<lb/>
the transmission by the mosquito.</item>
<item>Q. #95: Will you repeat what Reed told you and when.</item>
<item><p>ANSWER: I think in the summer of 1902 Reed <add>told me that he</add> asked General Sternberg<lb/>
whether he should investigate the mosquito theory of Finlay and General<lb/>
Sternberg replied &ldquo;You can do so if you wish, but I think you will be<lb/>
wasting your time&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench: Do you remember this conversation distinctly?</p>
<p>Gen. Kean: I do. There are very few conversations from which I can<lb/>
repeat words, but I can do it in that statement of Reed's. Reed thought<lb/>
Sternberg was getting over on his territory.</p></item>
<item>Q. #96: Was it understood by many of you that Sternberg was trying<lb/>
to bring too much credit to himself?</item>
<item>Answer: No I do not think that many people thought about it, or<lb/>
it; it was just along a margin of credit, and of course I was a champion<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f06409018"/>
15 -<lb/>
of Reed's and I shared his <unclear>feelings</unclear>. There was no particular discussion<lb/>
among the various medical officers.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #97</hi>: On page 277 of Sternberg's Biography, Sternberg is quoted as<lb/>
follows: &ldquo;The written instructions given by me to this selective Board<lb/>
were as follows&rdquo;; did you ever know that Sternberg gave Reed written<lb/>
instructions? I have never been able to find any written instructions<lb/>
<hi><del><unclear></unclear></del></hi> in the <add><unclear>National</unclear></add> Archives after considerable search. On page 278 &ldquo;In<lb/>
addition to these written instructions I talked freely with Major Reed<lb/>
etc.&rdquo; Isn't it peculiar that this is the only reference we can find<lb/>
to any written instructions. Is it possible that this is a false memory<lb/>
on his part?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think it must be a slip of memory.</item>
<item>Q.#98: What is your general reaction in this whole matter of the<lb/>
controversy between Reed and Sternberg - Sternberg, his wife and others<lb/>
saying so explicitly that Sternberg gave written instructions?</item>
<item><hi>Answer:</hi> It is a perfectly natural thing for him to do to give him<lb/>
instructions, and as Sternberg had devoted a great part of his life in<lb/>
work on yellow fever, it is perfectly natural that he would be explicit.<lb/>
The only question is that he made any suggestion regarding investiga-<lb/>
tion of the mosquito theory, and I think there is no evidence he did,<lb/>
and Reed denies explicitly that he did.</item>
<item>Q. #99: Why did Agramonte write so precisely and give such specific<lb/>
credit to Sternberg?</item>
<item><p>Answer: Agramonte knew nothing more than I do.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench: Remember General, that in retrospect everybody calls this<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Commission; as a matter of fact the original orders do<lb/>
not even mention yellow fever. It was a Commission to study various<lb/>
contagious diseases. Sternberg says in his discussion here that they<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06409019"/>
- 16 -<lb/>
were to study various diseases, and it was only because the commission<lb/>
took yellow fever and became famous that the Board was called the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board. W<add>h</add>o decided that the Board was to work on yellow fever?<lb/>
From what I can see they were to investigate a number of things, and it<lb/>
was up to Walter Reed what to study first. If that is the case I do<lb/>
not see that we have any concrete evidence that Sternberg emphasized<lb/>
yellow fever any more than any other diseases.</p>
<p><unclear>a Board</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Gen. Kean:</hi> You must remember that Kober was a great admirer of Stern-<lb/>
berg's and the book about him was written by his wife and Kober.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. 100:</hi> You remember that Howard stated in his book that Reed and<lb/>
Lazear and Carroll had visited him (Howard) to learn about mosquitoes<lb/>
before they went down to Cuba.</item>
<item><p><unclear>Those don't contradict</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Gen. Kean:</hi> It is my opinion that Lazear did not know Reed. I do not<lb/>
think there was any evidence that Lazear knew Reed before he went to<lb/>
Cuba.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Hench</hi>: I agree with you; it says that in his book, but the other<lb/>
<unclear>Howard</unclear><lb/>
day when I visited him he decided he had been wrong, and he told me<lb/>
that Lazear had come alone several times from Baltimore.</p>
<p><hi>Gen. Kean:</hi> I think he is right about that.</p></item>
<item><hi>Q. #101:</hi> When did you first hear the suggestion that Lazear had in-<lb/>
surance and did not want to risk it?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Very soon after his death. I think I got that impression<lb/>
from Reed.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #102:</hi> Who started the story about Lazear's insurance? Reed did<lb/>
not arrive in Cuba until about a week after Lazear's death. Therefore<lb/>
it would seem to me that Reed did not start the insurance story, but<lb/>
somebody must have suggested it to Reed.</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER</hi>: This is my impression, but I am not positive.</item>
<pb n="17" id="f06409020"/>
<item>- 17 -</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #103:</hi> Referring to Page 6 of our interview of January 6,<lb/>
1944, what were the quarantine regulations referred to?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> The orders of the Post Commander. They were somewhat<lb/>
different in different places, but in general terms no one should go<lb/>
into an infected town, or to any source of yellow fever infection.<lb/>
They were forbidden to go to Havana and forbidden to go to Marianao.<lb/>
Reed commanded his men not to go to Havana or Marianao. I never saw<lb/>
any orders that no one should bring mosquitoes in. The Post Commander<lb/>
has every authority.</item>
<item><hi>Q. #104:</hi> Where are the heights of Caba&ntilde;a?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> They would be south of Morro Castle, east of Havana Harbor.<lb/>
Caba&ntilde;a was the name of the fortress, but the region was behind it</item>
<item><hi>Q. 105:</hi> Quite a number of Spanish immigrants arrived, how many be-<lb/>
came infected?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> The immigrants were numbered in <del>dozens</del><add>hundreds</add>, but how many got<lb/>
yellow fever I do not know. A considerable number were infected in Havana.<lb/>
Records are given in reports of Dr. Finlay and Gorgas.</item>
<item><hi>Q. 106:</hi> In our interview of May 8, 1941, page 7 you say &ldquo;Reed<lb/>
probably would have been arrested&rdquo;. If Reed was there under orders of<lb/>
the Surgeon General to do a job how could he possibly be arrested by a<lb/>
local commanding officer?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> If he broke the orders of the Post Commander at a post<lb/>
there is not an order from the Surgeon General to protect him. The<lb/>
Post Commander has great authority. It was a favor to Reed to be allowed<lb/>
to be on the post.</item>
<item><hi>Q. 107:</hi> Did Reed ask the Commanding Officer to be allowed to live<lb/>
on the post and do this work?</item>
<pb n="18" id="f06409021"/>
<item>- 18 -</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not think Reed asked the Commanding Officer, but I do<lb/>
not know. It would certainly have been the proper thing for him to call<lb/>
on the Commanding Officer. Whether he did or not, I do not know. I<lb/>
<unclear>do<del>m</del>not</unclear> know what happened the<del>re</del><add>n</add> because I was sick.</item>
<item><hi>Dr. Hench</hi>: The whole thing was rather secret, and I think they regarded<lb/>
it more or less a secret, and kept it even from the Commanding Officer.</item>
<item><hi>General Kean:</hi> Yes, it was a great deal of a secret - Reed was very<lb/>
<del><unclear></unclear></del><add>cautious</add> about everything relating to these infections. He did not want<lb/>
any trouble made about it.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #108:</hi> Let me ask you again. When Reed got back in Cuba early<lb/>
in October and you met him when you were on the inspection trip at Ma-<lb/>
tanzas, did Reed know before you saw him that Lazear had died?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not think so. So far as I know, Reed left Washington<lb/>
or New York the day Lazear died. Reed left in the afternoon and Lazear<lb/>
died at night. I told him that Lazear had died; he felt very sad about<lb/>
it and spoke very feelingly; he expressed his regret. I went on board<lb/>
the boat at Matanzas and met Reed.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #109:</hi> Who else went with you to see Reed?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I think I went <del>down</del><add>to Matanzas</add> with Havard, but I do not think he went<lb/>
out on the boat.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #110:</hi> Do you remember any of the conversation when Reed ex-<lb/>
pressed to you his indignation that Carroll having offered himself for<lb/>
the experiment should then break quarantine and go to Havana?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do not remember the specific details of the conversation<lb/>
but he talked to me privately about it, and later when Reed and I went<lb/>
to see General Wood, Reed was rather embarrassed to have to admit not<lb/>
one of the three cases was controlled perfectly.</item>
<pb n="19" id="f06409022"/>
<item>- 19 -</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #111:</hi> Tell me the story about Reed offering XY money if he<lb/>
would admit he broke quarantine.</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> Reed sent for XY and had a long talk with him, and Reed said<lb/>
he offered him a gold piece that he had in his pocket if he would admit<lb/>
he left the post, and XY stated he would like to have it, but he had to<lb/>
state the fact that he had not left the post. Reed told me this, and<lb/>
he said he would like to have the money, but it was a fact that he had<lb/>
not left the post.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #112</hi>: What was Reed's relationship with Carroll. Was it a<lb/>
close friendship, or one of professional association?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> I do no think there was any intimacy, but I think that Reed<lb/>
liked Carroll and took a great interest in him, and done a great deal to<lb/>
improve Carroll's aspirations and to improve himself.star* I do not think<lb/>
there was any affectionate feeling. Lazear was a much superior man to<lb/>
Carroll, but Lazear was reserved.</item>
<item><hi>QUESTION #113:</hi> Was Carroll jumped a rank when he was promoted?</item>
<item><hi>ANSWER:</hi> He was first contract surgeon with the relative rank of<lb/>
Lieutenant in the Volunteers, which was the same relative rank for<lb/>
Volunteers or Regulars. The he was a Lieutenant in the Regular Army and<lb/>
by a special act of Congress was promoted to Major In the Regular Corps.</item>
</list></p>
<p>star* Carroll came to Reed's office as an enlisted man,<lb/>
half educated and not of social standing in the Army<lb/>
and he never entirely was quite of the same social<lb/>
status with Reed and his friends- Of course we<lb/>
had social <hi>caste</hi> in the Army and I think it will<lb/>
always exist in any Regular Army that is fit to<lb/>
fight-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
