<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06401035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 25, 1943</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06401035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1943-02-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E. </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kellogg, George A.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Carson (Colo.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1943-02-25">February 25, 1943</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06401035</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 25, 1943</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench is anxious to see Truby's book. Hench then mentions that he read Finlay's book, which supports the Cuban perspective that the Americans only confirmed, not proved, the mosquito theory.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1943-02-25">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 25, 1943</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06401035"/>
<opener>
STATION HOSPITAL<lb/>
Camp Carson, Colorado<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1943-02-25">February 25, 1943</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It must be a real thrill to see your book in proof, and I<lb/>
am very anxious indeed to see it. I think the suggestion that you<lb/>
use Cornwell's picture is excellent, and I know that Mr. Kellogg<lb/>
will be delighted to let you have the colored prints. As a matter<lb/>
of fact, I believe he will not only let you have the prints, but will<lb/>
probably have them printed for inserts. Months ago when he was ask-<lb/>
ing me how my own book was coming, he very eagerly offered me the<lb/>
colored prints, but of course mine will not appear for a fairly long<lb/>
time. I suggest that you write him at once, or better yet, wire him,<lb/>
requesting either the prints or the actual inserts. I know that all<lb/>
they will want will be the printed line - Courtesy of John Wyeth and<lb/>
Brothers. There is absolutely no reason why you shouldn't use it.<lb/>
Their other pictures, especially the one on Beaumont, have been used<lb/>
in many high grade publications. You have, therefore, an excellent<lb/>
precedent for using the yellow fever painting - it will add much to<lb/>
your book and, with you actually in the painting, it will be of re-<lb/>
ciprocal value, giving your friends pleasure, and also lending more<lb/>
authenticity to your book (if any more authenticity is needed). So<lb/>
far the yellow fever painting has been reproduced not too many times.<lb/>
As you know, I used it in the Hygea article. A picture becomes<lb/>
famous not just because it is a good picture, but because it becomes<lb/>
a familiar oft-reproduction. I think Cornwell's picture deserves to<lb/>
become familiar to every one. Kelly might want to use the reproduc-<lb/>
tion as a frontespiece rather than having the reproduction back in<lb/>
the appropriate chapter. That is for you to decide. I am delighted<lb/>
that you will be allowed to have so many pictures in your book.</p>
<p>Finley's book is very nice, and of course stresses the<lb/>
Cuban view point that the American physician merely confirmed what<lb/>
Finley had already proved. Finley himself pointed out one or two min-<lb/>
or errors in it, but these are a small matter.</p>
<p>General Kean is still fine. I had a very nice long letter<lb/>
from him just a few days ago. He is still reminiscing most happily<lb/>
on the receipt of the Gorgas Medal, and is apparently still getting<lb/>
letters of congratulation from friends from whom he has not heard<lb/>
for years. It was all a very happy event.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06401036"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>You will be surprised to know that our young buck pri-<lb/>
vate decided to arrive in Colorado rather than in Rochester. Mary<lb/>
came out to visit me about two and a half weeks ago, and had made<lb/>
reservations to leave this last Sunday evening, as it was not to be<lb/>
until March 13. Just 24 hours before she had planned to leave the<lb/>
youngster decided to do something about it, with the result that he<lb/>
was born Sunday evening, February 21, one minute before midnight,<lb/>
on my father's birthday - a very happy coincident, as he was named<lb/>
after my father. Mary is doing splendidly and the little fellow is<lb/>
very cute indeed. We are very, very happy as we have long wanted<lb/>
two of each and now have two boys and two girls. One of my associa-<lb/>
tes raised the question, &ldquo;Is this merely a seventh inning stretch<lb/>
for Colonel Hench or the end of the ball game?&rdquo; - only time will<lb/>
tell.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. HENCH</signed>
Lieut Colonel, M. C.<lb/>
PSH:RA<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
