<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06405142">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06405142</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-06-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-06-25">June 25, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06405142</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Kean that he has decided not to publish a preliminary memorial volume, and that he is unable to finish a full study anytime soon. He hopes to acquire a few important missing items concerning the yellow fever episode.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-06-25">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06405142"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-06-25">June 25, 1946</date>
</dateline>
General J. R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N Street, N. W.<lb/>
Georgetown<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so much for sending me the corrected answers. I believe<lb/>
that I have the uncorrected copy to all of them, but only your corrected<lb/>
answers to the last part, however, I have already received a lot to follow<lb/>
up from these questions and answers when I see General Truby this next<lb/>
Sunday, June 30. I cannot tell you how much I appreciate the wonderful<lb/>
help you gave me in Washington. I am afraid I took a great amount of your<lb/>
time and I fear I must have tired you. What a wonderful collection of items<lb/>
you found and gave to me. There will be invaluable and I cannot thank you<lb/>
enough.</p>
<p>We are leaving this Thursday for San Francisco and after a week there<lb/>
will spend four or five days resting at Santa Barbara, where I hope to see<lb/>
Huston Lazear. Perhaps it won't be a rest after all, but I badly need one.<lb/>
I am giving two talks at the American Medical Association and have been<lb/>
working busily on them for the last forty-eight hours.</p>
<p>Your letter of June 19, in which you frankly expressed your opinion<lb/>
that it would not be wise for me to publish a preliminary memorial volume,<lb/>
has really relieved me a great deal. Frankly, I have never been very anxious<lb/>
to do that and have been worried lest the publication detract materially from<lb/>
the full work. I more or less evolved the idea for a preliminary memorial<lb/>
volume chiefly to satisfy my very real sense of obligation to those of you<lb/>
who have helped me so much. I wish indeed that I could promise to finish<lb/>
my full volume in the next couple of years, but I fear that this is impossible<lb/>
because of the pressure of my daily work and the urgent need for me to get<lb/>
along with my, to me important and promising, research.</p>
<p>I keep plugging away on the Yellow Fever story whenever I can on free<lb/>
evenings and week-ends, but there is still some unfinished business and<lb/>
there are still a few important missing items, in addition, of course, to the<lb/>
missing Lazear-Reed data which John Carroll has and which I still hope to get.<lb/>
I believe that the Fiftieth Anniversary could be memorialized by an appropriate<lb/>
article which would take only a fraction of the work that the publication of<lb/>
a memorial volume would. I am very, grateful for your frank opinion about this.<lb/>
Permit me to discuss it with General Truby and Doctor Hewitt, head of the<lb/>
editorial staff of the Mayo Clinic, and you will hear from me further about this.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06405143"/>
<p>General J. R. Kean</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>June 25, 1946</p>
<p>I had a pleasant interruption this week. Into my office walked<lb/>
Mr. Gust Lambert. I was snowed under with consultations, therefore I put<lb/>
him up for the night at a hotel and interviewed him for three or four hours<lb/>
the next morning with the help of a secretary. Frankly, he told me a few<lb/>
things that it is difficult for me to believe. I believe I have mentioned<lb/>
one or two of them before. When his interview is typed up, I will send you<lb/>
a copy for your perusal and comments.</p>
<p>Please see the enclosed letter to my friend, Dr. Darrell Crain.<lb/>
Because I am leaving, I do not want his reply to me to be held up; therefore,<lb/>
I am asking him to telephone you direct. I am sure he will help you out.<lb/>
I only wish I know enough about Washington clinics and hospitals to give<lb/>
you the information directly. I was very glad indeed to help your cook<lb/>
and perhaps I can help her further on my next visit in the fall.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:lcg<lb/>
Enclosure<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
