<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06403049">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Book Review: Memoir of Walter Reed: the Yellow Fever Episode, December 4, 1943 [Enclosed in 06403047]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06403049</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1943-12-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1943-12-04">December 4, 1943</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06403049</idno>
<title>Book Review: Memoir of Walter Reed: the Yellow Fever Episode, December 4, 1943 [Enclosed in 06403047]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This review of Truby's book, Memoir of Walter Reed: the Yellow Fever Episode, is sent to Hench by Kean.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1943-12-04">
<head>Book Review: Memoir of Walter Reed: the Yellow Fever Episode, December 4, 1943 [Enclosed in <xref id="t06403047">06403047</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06403049"/>
<p>You can keep this if you want it for your records.<lb/>
If you do not<unclear>,</unclear> you may return it at your convenience</p>
<p>BRITISH MEDICAL JOURNAL, Dec. 4, 1943</p>
<p><hi>REVIEWS</hi></p>
<p>WALTER REED AND YELLOW FEVER</p>
<p><hi>Memoir of Walter Reed: the Yellow Fever Episode.</hi> By Albert E.<lb/>
Truby, Brigadier-General, United States Army (ret.). (Pp. 239.<lb/>
$3.50.) New York: Paul B. Hoeber, Inc. 1943.</p>
<p>The story of the United States Army Yellow Fever Board under the<lb/>
leadership of Walter Reed, which began its work in Cuba in June,<lb/>
1900, and before the end of the year had demonstrated conclusively<lb/>
the role of the mosquito Aedes aegypti in the transmission of the<lb/>
disease, has been told on a number of occasions. The book under<lb/>
review gives another account of this epoch-making discovery, but<lb/>
from the pen of an onlooker who, though not actually taking part<lb/>
in the investigations, was nevertheless closely associated with<lb/>
them and the many others who made contributions in one way or<lb/>
another to the success of the undertaking.</p>
<p>The author begins his story with an account of his experiences<lb/>
before the Army Medical Examining Board in 1898, when he was a<lb/>
candidate for the U. S. Army Medical Corps. This was an ordeal<lb/>
well calculated to disconcert any but the toughest and most self-<lb/>
reliant of aspirants. Soon after his admission to the corps he<lb/>
was posted to the army of occupation in Cuba when that country was<lb/>
formally handed over by the Spaniards to the United States on Jan.<lb/>
1, 1899. There he had ample opportunity to observe the ravages of<lb/>
such diseases as typhoid fever and malaria, and finally yellow<lb/>
fever, which broke out in the following year. The veteran Carlos<lb/>
Finlay, who clung tenaciously to his opinion that yellow fever was<lb/>
carried by mosquitoes in spite of his own failure to transmit it<lb/>
experimentally, was there and rendered signal service in diagnosis<lb/>
and treatment. Other experts, including Gorgas, Agramonte, Pinto,<lb/>
and Lazear, were also present, the majority of them being confirmed<lb/>
disbelievers in Finlay's theory. Here there was a great opportunity<lb/>
for the study of the aetiology of yellow fever, and, influenced by<lb/>
Walter Reed, Surgeon-General Sternberg persuaded the War Department<lb/>
to appoint the board consisting of Walter Reed, Carroll, Agramonte,<lb/>
and Lazear, which started its work at the Columbia Barracks, Que-<lb/>
mados, on June 25, 1900. Reed first directed his attention to the<lb/>
claims of Sanarelli that his Bacillus icteroides was the cause of<lb/>
yellow fever. These were quickly exploded, and the way was then<lb/>
clear for the study of mosquito transmission. This was first<lb/>
effected by Lazear, who produced the disease in himself and two<lb/>
volunteers while Reed was temporarily absent in Washington. The<lb/>
death of Lazear had a profound effect on the other members of the<lb/>
board. On Reed's return he found that though there was little<lb/>
doubt that mosquito transmission had actually been effected there<lb/>
was the possibility that, owing to incomplete isolation of those<lb/>
- 1 -<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06403050"/>
BRITISH MEDICAL JOURNAL, Dec. 4, 1943: Reviews<lb/>
experimented upon, other sources of infection had not been ex-<lb/>
cluded. There were loopholes upon which the critics of the<lb/>
theory, of which there were many, were sure to seize. Reed<lb/>
quickly planned and organized experiments which would be beyond<lb/>
criticism, and established once for all the correctness of<lb/>
Carlos Finlay's hypothesis. On Dec. 10, 1900, Reed wrote to<lb/>
the author informing him of the success of his experiments, and<lb/>
making the statement, &ldquo;The theory is all right!&rdquo;</p>
<p>This romantic story as told by General Truby in his <hi>Memoir of<lb/>
Walter Reed</hi> makes fascinating reading, not only because the<lb/>
author is a good story-teller but because he throws much new<lb/>
light upon the great discovery of mosquito transmission of<lb/>
yellow fever--a discovery which must ever rank in importance<lb/>
with that of the mosquito transmission of malaria established<lb/>
shortly before this.<lb/>
<unclear>Fine</unclear><lb/>
JRK</p>
<p>Isn't it an admirable review!<lb/>
J.R.K.<lb/>
- 2 -</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
