<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06408001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 25, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06408001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-05-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Lister, Gen.</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Stitt, Edward R.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez, Juan [Francisco?]</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Principe (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-05-25">May 25, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06408001</idno>
<title>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 25, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses the Yellow Fever Commission, in response to Hench's questionnaire.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-05-25">
<head>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 25, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06408001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-05-25">May 25, 1946</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>QUESTIONS FOR GENERAL KEAN PREPARED APRIL, 1946</hi></head>
<item><p>Question #1: Comments on remarks of Dr. L. O. Howard published in his<lb/>
&ldquo;History of Applied Entymology&rdquo; 1930.</p>
<p>Your comments in regard to the quotation are entirely in accord with<lb/>
my impressions on the subject. I cannot furnish any authoritative veri-<lb/>
fication, however. I doubtless told you that Howard gave Reed some<lb/>
<unclear>Lazear</unclear><lb/>
instructions on mosquitoes before Reed and Howard went to Cuba. This is<lb/>
in accordance with what I understood from Reed. I have no recollection<lb/>
of Carroll being included.</p></item>
<item>Question #2: What Lazear's reasons were for joining the Medical De-<lb/>
partment, I do not know. If it was to do any special work, and if the<lb/>
intention came from higher authority, it should have come to me because<lb/>
I was the Chief Surgeon under whom he worked. I had made requests for<lb/>
a laboratory man to be sent for service in my department, and understood<lb/>
that Lazear was the man.</item>
<item>Question #3: I think that you are right in thinking that Lazear first<lb/>
met Reed when Reed came to Cuba to investigate electrozone. I have a<lb/>
strong impression however that Professor Welch of Johns Hopkins had re-<lb/>
commended Lazear to Reed as a man who knew about mosquitoes. We all<lb/>
knew, some years before, about the use of kerosene to fight mosquitoes<lb/>
from Howard's publications (Key West). I recommended it to the town<lb/>
authorities in Key West when I was post-Surgeon there about 1895-</item>
<item>Question #4: I have no means of knowing who initiated the formation<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Commission. It was, however, a matter that pertained<lb/>
to the Surgeon General and not to Reed. I think the credit under Army<lb/>
rules would belong to the Chief. He would naturally consult Reed, how-<lb/>
ever, so as to get men who were <hi>personae gratae</hi> to him.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f06408002"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item>Question #5: I am inclined to agree with Truby that Reed may have se-<lb/>
lected Lazear on Professor Welch's recommendation. As to Agramonte,<lb/>
I think that the Surgeon General would have been more likely to think<lb/>
of him as he was a laboratory man and was already on duty in that work<lb/>
in Cuba. Carroll was already Reed's handy man in the laboratory. Reed<lb/>
had trained him.</item>
<item>Question #6: I had never heard, until you wrote me of it, that the<lb/>
words &ldquo;especially yellow fever&rdquo; were omitted from the order creating the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board. Your guess is as good as mine as to the reason for<lb/>
omitting it.</item>
<item>Question #7: I do not know why Lazear went to Cuba via Tampa. I think,<lb/>
however, that the line of big steamers from New York to Havana was<lb/>
established after Lazear arrived in Cuba. I think that the Morro Castle<lb/>
Ward Liner was <add>one of</add> the first of these fine new boats, and its first trip was<lb/>
after February 1900. It is, however, I think a matter of no importance.</item>
<item>Question #8: I doubt whether the passenger lists of the Army transports<lb/>
in those years would be now available. They would be buried under the<lb/>
accumulated records of the last World War. Below is a list of Reed's<lb/>
comings and goings as shown in my diaries:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>May 4, <add>Reed></add> <del>1900</del> lunched with me. Investigated typhoid outbreak in<lb/>
Puerto Principe - Diary Vol 4. p 113</item>
<item>Comes to investigate Electrozone Plant, March 10, 1900 diary IV. <unclear>p.</unclear> 160</item>
<item>Returns to U.S.... ... no record - Probably about April first-</item>
<item>Arrived with Carroll Yellow Fever Board, June 25 1900</item>
<item>Reed goes to Washington, Typhoid Report, Aug. 2, 1900</item>
<item>Reed returns to Havana, October 4, 1900</item>
<item>We go to see General Wood, October 12.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06408003"/>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<item>Reed goes to Washington, October 13, 1900</item>
<item>He returns to Havana, October 28 (Diary p. 191)</item>
<item>He returns to Wash. finally, Feb. 9, 1901 (7 to 10)</item>
<item>Diary IV P. 116 saw Reed's report on Puerto Principe 1899</item>
<item>Wrote Reed about typhoid at camp (p. 119) 1899-</item>
<item>(Y.F. Diary pp 128-133-135-138-Reed to Manila p. 140 <unclear>Kanned</unclear> <add>1899</add> did not go)</item>
<item>O'Reilly goes to U.S. 11th Nov. P. 143</item>
<item>Y.F. Diary IV P. 145</item>
<item>We moved into General Lee's house Maceo St. P. 147</item>
<item>Reed to Manila P. 149</item>
<item>Gen. Wood arrived in Cuba to command it, Dec. 23, 1899</item>
<item>Reed came March 10 and came to lunch with me on 11th (see also<lb/>
p. 161</item>
<item>(See order for Gorgas and me p. 164)</item>
<item>Y.F. 166, 168, 169, 172</item>
<item>Question #9: I have not a copy of the photograph of Reed, but as<lb/>
officers did not travel in uniform in time of peace, I would certainly<lb/>
accept Blossom's statement in the matter.</item>
<item>Question #10: I have no recollection of when I heard of the formation<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Board. It would doubtless have struck me as a<lb/>
natural and appropriate thing to do.</item>
<item>Question #11: It was obvious to me that the work of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board should be a secret. By making it so they avoided all sorts of<lb/>
vexatious interruptions. It was entirely within the authority of the<lb/>
Commanding Officer at Columbia Barracks to order them all off the mili-<lb/>
tary reservation at Columbia Barracks if he knew that they were ex-<lb/>
perimenting with yellow fever. His authority to do this would never<lb/>
be contested by anybody in the Army at that time.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06408004"/>
<item>- 4 -</item>
<item>Question #12: Knowing the character of the Commanding Officer of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks as I did, I think that he would not have hesitated for<lb/>
one instant to disregard any orders and wishes of the Surgeon General<lb/>
in any sanitary matter. I have not at hand my interview of May 8, page<lb/>
7 marked &ldquo;Confidential&rdquo; so that I do not remember what I said and so<lb/>
cannot amplify.</item>
<item>Question #13: I did not know that the Finca San Jose had been visited<lb/>
by Finlay until I read it in his son's book. It is certainly a very<lb/>
interesting coincidence.</item>
<item>Question #14: The interview of Kean and Reed with General Wood occured<lb/>
in General Wood's office, which was in the first story above the ground<lb/>
floor at the front of the Palacio looking out on the square. There<lb/>
were, as I recollect, <unclear><del>four</del></unclear> <add>6</add> large rooms, possibly <del>six</del><add>8</add>, in the front which<lb/>
faced north, and General Wood's office was in the second from the right<lb/>
of these rooms. The two windows of that room looked out on the Palace<lb/>
and the entrance to the harbor, and as I recollect, Morro Castle in the<lb/>
distance. This is the picture which I have in mind.</item>
<item>Question #15: It would be difficult for me to designate except in a<lb/>
general way the space where was located the Detention camp for the Span-<lb/>
ish immigrants who poured into Cuba in 1900. There is, or used to be,<lb/>
a large level area to the east and south of the Caba&ntilde;a fortress. It<lb/>
was under the service of the Marine Quarantine, which was under a man<lb/>
named Manocal, and he did business with the U.S. Quarantine service<lb/>
and was I think desirous to comply with their wishes in every respect.<lb/>
I never visited this camp. Whether Major Reed went over there to get<lb/>
his Spanish volunteers I do not know, but I think he did business with<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06408005"/>
- 5 -<lb/>
Manacol about getting them. He employed them for general labor, and<lb/>
made his proposal later at Camp Lazear. about the experiments</item>
<item>QUESTION #16: I have no direct knowledge as to how Reed established<lb/>
contacts with his Spanish volunteers or what the &ldquo;certain&rdquo; difficulties<lb/>
were. Probably Agramonte helped him in this.</item>
<item>Question #17: I do not think that you could find out anything about<lb/>
the interview of the Spanish Consul General in Havana and Major Reed on<lb/>
the subject of these experiments by contacting the Spanish Legation in<lb/>
Cuba now. I called him a &ldquo;very nice man&rdquo; because he was courteous and<lb/>
sympathetic with Reed. I never knew him and do not remember his name.</item>
<item>Question #18: The idea that Dr. Lazear was so reticent about the char-<lb/>
acter of his investigation on account of his having insurance was not<lb/>
my guess. I think I got the idea from Reed, but if Mrs. Lazear said<lb/>
he had no insurance I think that settles it. I think that Lazear was<lb/>
naturally a very self-contained, reserved man.</item>
<item><p>Question #19: You ask where are the survivors of Carter, Gorgas, Stern-<lb/>
berg, General Lister and Neate. They are all five dead. The only one<lb/>
who has a descendant, as far as I know, is General Gorgas, whose daughter<lb/>
married a sanitary engineer named Wrightson. They are living somewhere<lb/>
near Washington, and I had a long talk with her when I was presented<lb/>
with the Gorgas Medal some years ago. She is a fine woman. Her name is<lb/>
Aileen</p>
<p>Dr. Henry R. Carter's daughter, Laura A. Carter, married Admiral<lb/>
Stitt retired Surgeon General of the Navy - his second wife. She died<lb/>
some years ago without issue.</p></item>
<item>Question #20: I wish I could give you some details about Major Reed's<lb/>
visit to me when I was sick with yellow fever on June 25, 1900. My<lb/>
mind, however, is quite blank about the incidents of my illness.<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06408006"/>
- 6 -<lb/>
Whether it was an effect of the disease or not, I do not know, but I<lb/>
simply remember that he came and stood by my bed and said a few words<lb/>
to me. He was probably told not to make a long visit because I do not<lb/>
remember him as sitting down. I cannot repeat any word of the conver-<lb/>
sation. I do not think I knew when Reed was expected, or if he would<lb/>
come to see me.</item>
<item>Question #21: I have no recollection of knowing Agramonte before the<lb/>
formation of the Yellow Fever Board. I used to call on Lazear to go<lb/>
with me to see fever cases because he was familiar with the symptoms<lb/>
of the various fevers and could examine the blood for malaria. I<lb/>
remember well his showing me how to recognize the male and female<lb/>
stegomyia mosquitoes when we visited the yellow fever cases at 102<lb/>
Calsada Real and other cases in Marianao. Lazear recognized the<lb/>
stegomyia (the common house mosquito of Cuba) but at that time did not<lb/>
know it was the carrier of yellow fever.</item>
<item>Question #22: I had no official connection with the yellow fever com-<lb/>
mission until September 1900 when General Wood turned over to me the<lb/>
money which he gave Major Reed for the purposes of his commission. He<lb/>
did that, as he told Major Reed, because I was a permanent officer of<lb/>
his staff and knew how to account for Cuban funds. How the money<lb/>
should be spent was left entirely to our discretion. I had never at<lb/>
any time any suggestion that I should help Reed or the Board in any<lb/>
way, and it is certain that none was necessary. My good friend and<lb/>
Commanding Officer, General Fitzhugh Lee, once advised me not to be<lb/>
too enthusiastic about Reed's findings because he had observed that<lb/>
all discoveries about yellow fever were soon afterwards disproved, and<lb/>
he feared my reputation would be injured if I were identified with the<lb/>
findings of the Reed Board. I told him that I was perfectly willing<lb/>
to risk my professional reputation upon their accuracy.</item>
<pb n="7" id="f06408007"/>
<item>- 7 -</item>
<item>Question # 23: I know nothing about the planning of Camp Lazear.<lb/>
Reed knew what he wanted and drew his own plans. I do not imagine that<lb/>
they were copied in any way from those of the Italian students of<lb/>
malaria.</item>
<item>Question #24: My attitude towards Reed's plans were entirely voluntary<lb/>
and with enthusiasm.</item>
<item>Question #25: I was deeply distressed over Lazear's death. It happened<lb/>
that I was away on an inspection trip with the chief surgeon, Colonel<lb/>
Havard during the period of his illness. I got back to Columbia Barracks<lb/>
only a few days before his death, and as I found out from Dr. Ames that<lb/>
he was very ill, I never saw him. I do not understand the question<lb/>
&ldquo;Did Kean suspect that Lazear's death was unusual&rdquo;. There is certainly<lb/>
nothing unusual about such a termination in a severe case of yellow<lb/>
fever.</item>
<item>Question #26: I see no reason why you should hesitate to tell the<lb/>
facts about Dr. Godfrey's failure to meet his professional obligations<lb/>
at Pinar del Rio. Whether it is necessary to mention his name, I can-<lb/>
not say. It might be a certain protection to his assistants to do so.</item>
<item>Question #27: The instructions regarding yellow fever which Godfrey<lb/>
<unclear>ignoried</unclear> were sent out from time to time by the Chief Surgeon in Havana<lb/>
and by the Chief Surgeon in Marianao. They were explicit and in my<lb/>
inspection of the hospitals I usually inquired as to whether they were<lb/>
carried out in all cases of fever. I will <hi>enclose one</hi> which I think I<lb/>
can put my hand on. I gave you one-</item>
<item>Question #28: As to the room that Reed died in, I think you will be<lb/>
safe to follow Truby's sketch. I recall when I visited him when he<lb/>
was dying and took Blossom down to see him that I went up a flight of<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06408008"/>
- 8 -<lb/>
stairs and the room was on the left. The south side as I recollect-</item>
<item><p>Question #29 <add>&amp; 30</add>: It never occurred to me that Moran's feelings would<lb/>
be hurt by the honors paid to Kissinger. When Moran declined the<lb/>
gratuity of $200 which I offered him, I thought it settled the matter<lb/>
and that he was content. With Kissinger, I was not so sure and when<lb/>
I offered to give him a watch and chain from the gratuity he was<lb/>
much pleased. He afterwards asked me if there was any balance, and<lb/>
when I told him &ldquo;yes&rdquo; he said he would be glad to have it. It was,<lb/>
I think, <del>$40.00 or</del> $50.00. The watch was presented to him and his<lb/>
promotion to Acting Hospital Steward was announced to show the ap-<lb/>
preciation of the medical officers for the gallantry shown by men<lb/>
of the hospital corps in submitting to these experiments.</p>
<p>The ceremony was probably in the last ten days of January 1901.<lb/>
It is my recollection that Colonel Havard was present and made a few<lb/>
remarks, but they were, I am sure, quite extemporaneous and were not<lb/>
made of record. There would have been no point that I can see in<lb/>
inviting Moran to this little ceremony.</p></item>
<item>Question #31: Your guess is as good as mine as to why a picture was<lb/>
pasted over the old framed Benigno contract. My idea is that it<lb/>
was to conceal its identity so that it could not be found when looked<lb/>
for and it would have been easy to carry it off later.</item>
<item>Question #32: It was simply about the odd ideas that dear old Dr.<lb/>
Finlay got when he became senile. Gorgas told me this story, and I<lb/>
will tell it to you when I see you. It is of no importance.</item>
<item>Question #33: No.</item>
<pb n="9" id="f06408009"/>
<item>- 9 -</item>
<item>Question #34: I cannot amplify the statement about Reed's vexation<lb/>
that Carroll after being inoculated by a yellow fever mosquito should<lb/>
have gone to Havana, and of all places to Agramonte's laboratory<lb/>
where he was conducting an autopsy, during the period of incubation.<lb/>
Of course it destroyed the value of Carroll's case as an experiment.<lb/>
Whether Reed said anything to Carroll about it, I do not know. The<lb/>
damage had been done and Carroll was still sick. He expressed himself<lb/>
to me as being much disgusted with Carroll. Whether it was on the<lb/>
transport at Matanzas or when he came to see me later at Marianao,<lb/>
I am not quite certain.</item>
<item>Question #35: I cannot give you any data about the camp for Spanish<lb/>
non-immune immigrants at Cabanao.</item>
<item>Question #36: The Gorgas-Guiteras yellow fever experiments which<lb/>
resulted so disastrously occurred long after Reed had finished his<lb/>
yellow fever work and left Cuba. They occurred in Aug. 1901. Carroll<lb/>
told me about them when Reed sent him down to Cuba to make tests of<lb/>
filtered yellow fever blood to determine whether the cause of the in-<lb/>
fection was bacterial or a virus. They were so much rattled over<lb/>
these deaths that they would not allow Carroll to take blood from any<lb/>
of their experimental yellow fever cases. He told me about it when<lb/>
he came to lunch at my house about August 16th. I can give you the<lb/>
dates of the deaths of these cases if you want them. They were re-<lb/>
ported I think in Dr. Finlay's annual report. The American nurse,<lb/>
Miss Maas was the last one to die on August 23. I never heard Reed<lb/>
say anything about these cases.</item>
<item>Question #37: I do not know anything about the Roll of Honor file<lb/>
kept by General Reynolds. The official Roll of Honor file is pub-<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06408010"/>
- 10 -<lb/>
lished every year in the Army Register. I can give you a copy of the<lb/>
official file if you want it.</item>
<item>Question #38: I do not know anything about Reed having said that he<lb/>
wished Pinto had a mild attack. I think that must be Truby's story.</item>
<item>Question #39: Mrs. Lazear's story is very nice and I see no reason<lb/>
why it should not be accepted. I have very vague recollections about<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear's coming to Cuba.</item>
<item>Question #40: Well what about it?</item>
<item>Question #41: I am sorry that no one wrote to Mrs. Lazear after her<lb/>
husband's death. I think Truby, who was his Commanding Officer, should<lb/>
have done it.</item>
<item>Question #42: I would be glad to see the editorial on aviation<lb/>
(Harboard's article) I read it</item>
<item>Question #43: As regards Carroll's promotion to Major, it must have<lb/>
been by a special act of Congress - I do not recall.</item>
<item>Question #44: I will try to find Reed's letter of July 1900. I have<lb/>
not been able to find any of Reed's letters in the search I am now mak-<lb/>
ing. (I showed you what I had when you were here)</item>
<item>Question #45: Reed told me, as I recall, in a quizzical way that he<lb/>
was puzzled over the report of XY's case. It was important to show<lb/>
that he had been under quarantine during the period of incubation,<lb/>
but if he gave his name and company, he was afraid he would get into<lb/>
trouble with the Commanding Officer. I am not very certain what I<lb/>
told him, but I think it was that line officers do not read medical<lb/>
reports and by the time it got around to the Commanding Officer, if<lb/>
it ever did, it would be too late to do anything about it. It was<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="f06408011"/>
- 11 -<lb/>
not an Infantry Captain who complained through channels about one of<lb/>
his men, but an Artillery Officer stationed at Santa Clara Battery.<lb/>
I do not think Colonel Baldwin ever heard of this incident.</item>
<item>Question #46: No one accompanied Kean and Reed on their visit to<lb/>
General Wood on October 12th.</item>
<item>Question #47: Truby has told the story substantially, as I recall<lb/>
it, in his book. Why don't you stick to that?</item>
<item>Question #48: Truby knows more about this than anyone else. Why<lb/>
don't you accept his story which is substantial, as I recall it?</item>
<item>Question #49: I do not think I can shed any light on the story of<lb/>
Lazear's so-called accidental inoculation in Las Animas.</item>
<item>Question #50: As you know, Colonel Gorgas remained in Cuba after<lb/>
General Wood and the American forces and government left Cuba on the<lb/>
2nd of May <add>1902</add>. I presume that Gorgas had some sort of trouble over the<lb/>
disinfection of clothing coming from Havana to the United States. He<lb/>
probably let the old regulation continue in operation in spite of the<lb/>
action of the military authorities as to the disinfection of fomites<lb/>
being unnecessary. I remember that Reed told me here in Washington<lb/>
that he had written a letter of congratulation to Gorgas when Gorgas<lb/>
had reported to him that he had ceased to disinfect fomites in Havana.<lb/>
It may be that the Public Health Service has some record of when dis-<lb/>
infection of clothing (yellow fever) stopped in Havana. They had<lb/>
supervision over this matter.</item>
<item><unclear>Some</unclear> file</item>
<item>Question #51: I think that I heard Gorgas' expression of Finlay's<lb/>
&ldquo;wonderful scientific clairvoyance&rdquo; used in <add>his</add> talking to me about<lb/>
Finlay. It may, however, <del>be</del><add>have been</add> used in his article on &ldquo;Warfare Against<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06408012"/>
- 12 -<lb/>
Mosquitoes&rdquo;. I will look and see. The S. Y. asked Gorgas to write<lb/>
this article-</item>
<item>Question #52: I think it is perfectly obvious that Gorgas could not<lb/>
ask for a volunteer majority to be given to a man on duty in Washing-<lb/>
ton. It would certainly be less questioned if the man was at that<lb/>
time on duty in Cuba. The U.S. Volunteers were authorized for<lb/>
service abroad-</item>
<item>Question #53: The general reaction was to accept the danger of yel-<lb/>
low fever as one of the incidents of the service. This was the atti-<lb/>
tude of medical officers as far as I saw them. It was the business of<lb/>
the officers to avoid infection and they did so as far as they could.<lb/>
There was no panic at any time although most of the officers sent<lb/>
their families north.</item>
<item>Question #54: I do not know in what building in Havana the Pan<lb/>
American Medical Congress met. Much to my disappointment I was sent<lb/>
to Washington for examination for promotion just at that time and<lb/>
never attended the congress.</item>
<item>Question #55: I never have seen Dr. Guiteras' speech at the Finlay<lb/>
dinner in print. A year or two ago Dr. Francisco Dominguez sent me<lb/>
his book written in French and published in Paris- &ldquo;The Centenary of<lb/>
Dr. Finlay.&rdquo; He describes that dinner quite fully, but states that he<lb/>
got up the dinner at the request of General Wood and ran things gener-<lb/>
ally. I do not think he mentions Dr. Guiteras. I know he does not<lb/>
mention me although I was sitting next to Dr. Finlay, and I have no<lb/>
<del>remark</del><add>recollection</add> of meeting him at the dinner. It is a curious example of how<lb/>
differently two persons recollect the same event after forty years.</item>
<item>Question #56: The idea of testing petroleum oils of various densi-<lb/>
ties with respect to their power to kill mosquito larvae was my own.<lb/>
I do not know of any other experiments that were conducted about it.<lb/>
I satisfied myself that the heavier oils did not spread over the<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06408013"/>
- 13 -<lb/>
surface of the water rapidly enough to be efficient. My objective<lb/>
was to be able to answer any questions of my examining board on that<lb/>
subject.</item>
<item>Question #57: I do not know what has become of the various letters<lb/>
I had from Walter Reed. I will look again before you get here.</item>
<item>Question #58: There is no difference between an Assistant Surgeon<lb/>
General and a Deputy Surgeon General. It is probable that the latter<lb/>
term was used in Secretary Root's act reorganizing the Army.</item>
<item>Question #59: I have found one letter from you written from New<lb/>
Orleans not long ago which I will give you when you come in June.</item>
<item>Question #60: The bound volume of addresses, articles etc. relating<lb/>
to Cuba in which the speech of Dr. Lopez del Valle was printed is at<lb/>
the Alderman Library, University of Virginia. When you go to see your<lb/>
brother there, go to Dr. Harry Clemons, the Librarian, and ask for it;<lb/>
he will find it for you.</item>
<item>Question #61: I will look again for the packet of letters of Guiteras.<lb/>
Finlay etc.</item>
<item>Question #62: No, I do not want any more copies of Hyg<add><unclear>i</unclear></add>ea with your<lb/>
fine article and the picture. I think that Mrs. Kean has sent one to<lb/>
every one of her friends or mine.</item>
<item>Question #63: (a) I will try to find that letter<lb/>
(b) Both refer to the same letter<lb/>
(c) I destroyed that as Ireland thought it would<lb/>
not give a correct idea of Reed.</item>
<item>Question #64: I will get your longhand letters for you.</item>
</list></item></list></p>
<p>These I gave you in June</p>
<closer>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
