<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06405211">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 27, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06405211</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">LaGarde, Louis A.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-27">November 27, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06405211</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 27, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench reports on his family. He also doubts Lambert's story. He describes efforts to contact James Carroll's son, George. He also hopes to find some records from Carter.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1946-11-27">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 27, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06405211"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-11-27">November 27, 1946</date>
</dateline>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N Street, North West<lb/>
Washington 7, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You are exceedingly prompt indeed. I just re-<lb/>
turned yesterday morning after a delightful two and one-<lb/>
half days with my boy at <unclear>Mercersburg</unclear>. He is doing very<lb/>
nicely there, adjusting beautifully, and maturing. He<lb/>
is on the honor roll, likes the school very much, and<lb/>
seems quite happy. On my return I found your two letters<lb/>
and the memoranda which I am delighted to have. May I<lb/>
hasten to remind you again that I never took Lambert's<lb/>
remarks seriously, except that I knew he was spreading<lb/>
that information around and was receiving sympathetic<lb/>
attention in certain quarters; and, therefore, it was only<lb/>
proper that you should be permitted to see what he had<lb/>
in mind and to answer it for the sake of the record. Your<lb/>
answer is satisfactory and dignified. I forgot to tell<lb/>
you that in the Arobives Building two or three years ago<lb/>
I was able to find an old series of special orders relating<lb/>
to men temporarily assigned to Camp Lazear and I have<lb/>
microfilms of all of them.</p>
<p>Do you think that I should write to Doctor Brumby<lb/>
and try to set him straight? He is probably a rank<lb/>
sentimentalist who would not be particularly amenable to<lb/>
reason. He has never written me. I am debating whether<lb/>
or not I should let him alone and assume that his work<lb/>
will come to nothing or whether I should politely correspond<lb/>
with him and (gently) disagree with his viewpoint. I<lb/>
could do this by sympathizing with the viewpoint of him-<lb/>
self and Lambert but telling him frankly that he has mis-<lb/>
interpreted the facts. I shall abide by your decision in<lb/>
the matter.</p>
<p>Miss Schnurr and I had a very pleasant and<lb/>
profitable evening with the Reeds. They both gave us a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06405212"/>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
November 27, 1946<lb/>
lot of interesting information, some of which I did not<lb/>
have before. General Truby thought that I should contact<lb/>
Colonel La Garde who might be able to persuade Carroll<lb/>
to co-operate. I missed Colonel La Garde at the Pentagon<lb/>
Building but I had a nice telephone conversation with<lb/>
him at his home. He has not seen Carroll since the<lb/>
latter was a child and believes he has no particular in-<lb/>
fluence with him but will give the matter further thought.<lb/>
I got in touch with Mr. Reed who is the son-in-law of<lb/>
Sergeant Tracy, who worked with Carroll. I had seen him<lb/>
on a previous visit when he had been optimistic about being<lb/>
able to get Carroll's co-operation. To his amazement and<lb/>
disappointment Mr. Reed got the same response from Carroll<lb/>
that I did. He hardly got in the front door and is inclined<lb/>
to believe that the man is crazy.</p>
<p>On my return I found a nice letter from<lb/>
Major Gilhus, with whom General Truby put me in contact,<lb/>
and I am having an interesting correspondence with him.</p>
<p>I enjoyed very much meeting the Members of the<lb/>
Board. On my way downstairs I asked Admiral Stitt two or<lb/>
three questions which opened a flood of reminiscences and<lb/>
he kept talking to me until almost two o'clock down in the<lb/>
lobby of the bank. I think, however, that through him<lb/>
I may find some old records of Doctor Carters. I hope,<lb/>
indeed, that my little snapshots come out all right and<lb/>
I will certainly send you a copy.</p>
<p>You state that you feel that you made no proper<lb/>
arrangements for my entertainment. Dear General Kean,<lb/>
how could you entertain me more than you did? You gave<lb/>
me hours of your time--the most valuable thing you could<lb/>
give me. It is so much more convenient for all concerned<lb/>
when I visit Washington for me to go to a hotel. In that<lb/>
way I can come and go to the numerous appointments that<lb/>
I always seem to be making. You have never been anything<lb/>
but extremely generous and kind.</p>
<p>Please give Mrs. Kean my kindest regards.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Always sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alp<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
