<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06407001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 11, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06407001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-05-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Maass, Clara Louise</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Key West (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Principe (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-05-11">May 11, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06407001</idno>
<title>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 11, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses the Yellow Fever Commission, in response to Hench's questionnaire.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-05-11">
<head>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, May 11, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06407001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-05-11">May 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1946</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p><hi>Questionaire for Gen. Kean</hi></p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head>Memo of Answers-</head>
<item>1. I knew from Major Reed that he was in contact with<lb/>
Dr. L. O. Howard of the Dept. of Agriculture before he came<lb/>
to Cuba- I had learned from him when he visited me<lb/>
at Key West I think in 1896 of Howard's use of kerosene<lb/>
to combat the breeding of mosquitos and had recom-<lb/>
mended it to the municipal authorities to control the<lb/>
mosquito pest in the numerous shallow ponds,<lb/>
on the upper end of the island near the U. S. Mil.-<lb/>
Reservation, where it could easily have been applied, but<lb/>
they were accustomed to mosquitos and took no action-<lb/>
Whether Lazear knew Dr. Howard I doubt- He had studied<lb/>
<unclear>(no)</unclear><lb/>
mosquitos and malaria in Italy- My impression is that<lb/>
<unclear>(c</unclear><lb/>
Dr. <unclear>Welsh</unclear> of Johns Hopkins knew of his work and<lb/>
mentioned his name to Dr. Reed as a mosquito expert-<lb/>
Dr. Reed was my only source of knowledge as to his<lb/>
study of mosquitos with Howard- I dont know<lb/>
about Carroll, who I think was not interested in<lb/>
mosquitos-</item>
<item>2. I do not know</item>
<item>3- My notebook (REF) says p. 38 that Reed came to Havana<lb/>
to inspect Electrozone plant March 10, 1900<lb/>
He came again to investigate typhoid outbreak in Puerto Principe<lb/>
in May 1900 &amp; lunched with me May 4, 1900-<lb/>
(<unclear>Meree</unclear> to tell Dr. Hench story of Electrozone-)</item>
<item>4 I do not know who initiated the formation of the Y. F. Board<lb/>
I have always believed that Gen- Sternberg initiated it</item>
<item>5 I think that Trubys idea was correct about Welch recommending<lb/>
Lazear to Reed but have no definite authority for it-</item>
<pb n="1" id="f06407002"/>
<item>Ac<lb/>
K<lb/>
Page 2- J. R. K. to P. S. Hench-</item>
<item>6- I do not know-</item>
<item>2</item>
<item>7. I do not know except that the N. Y. line to Havana had<lb/>
put on much larger and steadyer boats</item>
<item>8. I think that most of Reeds trip were by merchant<lb/>
lines - would it be worth the trouble to try to get the<lb/>
transports passenger lists? I doubt it. I will put<lb/>
down the dates I know-<lb/>
Reed came to Cuba about May 3 1900 typhoid in Puerto Principe<lb/>
" " " " March 10 to look in Electrozone plant<lb/>
" " " " June 25 with Carroll for Y. F. <unclear>Con</unclear> <unclear></unclear><lb/>
" left Cuba for U. S. Aug. 2 1900<lb/>
" returned to Cuba Oct. 4, 1900 on transport &ldquo;Crook&rdquo;<lb/>
" left " for U. S. <del>Feb. 1901</del> Oct. 14, 1900<lb/>
Returned to Cuba early in Nov (Truby) 1900 - see above</item>
<item>9- Where is the photograph of Reed.</item>
<item>10- See page 76 Truby's book about Reed's return to study<lb/>
yellow fever- I do not remember when I had the<lb/>
first news of the appointment of the Reed Board<lb/>
Truby says with reference to the selection of the Reed Board<lb/>
p. 181. "About the middle of May 1900 Sternberg and Reed<lb/>
had a conference and at that time they planned the<lb/>
Campaign and selected the members of the Board</item>
<item>11- Camp Columbia was under <unclear>quarantine</unclear> and military authories<lb/>
<del>would</del><add>might</add> not permit infected mosquitos to be brought in to the<lb/>
laboratory if they knew about it-</item>
<item>12. Reeds authority from the S. Y. would not prevent the local control<lb/>
of the Camp C. O. from stopping the work of the Board on the reservation<lb/>
unless the Board were backed by higher <hi>line</hi> authority-</item>
<item>13. No not in 1900-</item>
<item>14 Second floor front room at right center-</item>
<item>Palace</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06407003"/>
<item>3</item>
<item>15 It was the Immigrant Detention Camp under the<lb/>
authority of Menocal- It needs a map to locate it.</item>
<item>16- The Spaniards were engaged by Reed thru <unclear>an interpreter</unclear><lb/>
I do not know details-</item>
<item>17 I dont know</item>
<item>18- I do not know</item>
<item>19- I do not know</item>
<item>20- My memory is hazy as to details</item>
<item>21 My acquaintance with Lazear was rather casual until<lb/>
we went together to inspect y. f. suspects in Marianao<lb/>
where he examined with interest the mosquitos in the<lb/>
buildings no. 20 Gen Lee St. where Sergt <del>King</del> Sherwood<lb/>
lived- Also a <unclear>packer</unclear> named King</item>
<item>23- I do not think so. They were very simple structures</item>
<item>22. There was no official connection until Gen Wood<lb/>
placed the money for Camp Lazear &amp; the Commission<lb/>
to Kean's account for disbursement-</item>
<item>24 It was quite enthusiastic</item>
<item>25 It was not regarded as unusual as it was well<lb/>
known that he had yellow fever. Kean sailed <del>Monday</del><lb/>
Wed 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Sept on Sedgwick for <unclear>Crenpingos</unclear> with Col Howard<lb/>
returned to Havana Sept 24 Monday when we heard of <unclear>Cartwright</unclear><lb/>
death- Dr. Lazear was very ill and died on 25<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-<lb/>
On Oct 3 Kean went to <unclear>Matanja</unclear> with Col Havard and saw<lb/>
Reed returning from Wash on the Transport Crook &amp; told<lb/>
him of Lazears death-</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06407004"/>
<item>Ac<lb/>
K</item>
<item>4</item>
<item><hi>26</hi> I think so- In history we must not<lb/>
conceal people's mistakes in writing history</item>
<item>27 Look up the <unclear>med</unclear> circulars of instructions formal<lb/>
from Ch Surg Office- They required a record<lb/>
of temperature pulse and urine to be kept in each<lb/>
case of fever. Special attention to certain diagnostic<lb/>
features which would put the doctor on guard<lb/>
us a slow pulse with fever and early appearance<lb/>
of <unclear>albumen</unclear> in the urine- These instructions were formal<lb/>
and compliance was expected in all <del>wards</del> cases-</item>
<item>28- My recollection is in accord with Gen Trubys</item>
<item>29 Kean is probably responsible for failure to do something<lb/>
special for Moran- It seemed natural to reward<lb/>
with a promotion the first member of the H. C.<lb/>
who had a case of experimental y. f. but not every<lb/>
other man- The gold watch was bought from the money<lb/>
which Kissinger declined (but he was willing to take<lb/>
the watch and the balance of the money) I would have<lb/>
been glad to buy a watch for Moran on the same<lb/>
times but he diclined any reward- I never<lb/>
knew that his feelings were hurt until Col. Hench<lb/>
told me of it. The ceremony must have occurred betw Jan 9 &amp; Jan 29<lb/>
Col. Havard Chief Surgeon left Cuba Nov. 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-1900<lb/>
articles in Discussion Diary V p 13- Kissing was bitten<lb/>
Nov 22. So <del>could not</del><add>may</add> have been Havard who was the<lb/>
Chief Surgeon He returned Jan 8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and may have given it <unclear>between cor<lb/>
Med</unclear> 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-Jan<lb/>
10-20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi><lb/>
I wrote Dec. 19 to Surg. Gen. recommending Carroll as <unclear>Major Surg</unclear>. Vols<lb/>
<del>Col Havard</del> I left Havana Wed Jan 30 for Wash. Returned Feb. 20 1901,</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06407005"/>
<item>Ac<lb/>
K</item>
<item>Questionnaire-</item>
<item><hi>5</hi></item>
<item>Q 31- Any one's guess is as good as anothers<lb/>
mine is it was pasted over to hide it in case search was<lb/>
made for it-</item>
<item>Q. 32 Incidents about Dr Finlay- Gorgas's story-</item>
<item>Q 33 About what?</item>
<item>Q 34- Reed was greatly disgusted that Carroll should go into<lb/>
infected localities- Havana (Agramontes autopsy room)<lb/>
after being bitten by infected mosquitos in this way <unclear>viciating</unclear><lb/>
the experiment- I do not know if he reproached Carroll<lb/>
the damage was done-</item>
<item>35- I do not know, I was never there</item>
<item>36. The death of Miss <unclear>Maas</unclear> occurred June 23, the first experimental<lb/>
death was June 15 190<hi rend="superscript">0</hi> Carroll was in Cuba and <unclear>duced</unclear><lb/>
with me on June 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> He was conducting blood infection tests<lb/>
under Reed's orders- I never heard Reed mention those<lb/>
Cases of Guiteras and Gorgas-</item>
<item>37. I dont know, in the S. G. O. perhaps but it will not have any informa-<lb/>
tion that we do not know- I probably made it-</item>
<item>38 I dont know</item>
<item>39 Very interesting and doubtless true</item>
<item>40 What about the lost Finlay book?</item>
<item>41- I <unclear>fear</unclear> that it true</item>
<item>42 would like to see it</item>
<item>43. Yes it seems so- I do not remember how it was done - probably<lb/>
by a special act- I was probably in Cuba then</item>
<item>44 Reed's letter of July 1900</item>
<item>45- It was an Artillery Captain from Sta. Clara Battery<lb/>
He made no official complaint I think-</item>
<pb n="6" id="f06407006"/>
<item>(6</item>
<item>46- No one-</item>
<item>47- Reed told me of the talk with XY and in much the same<lb/>
words as it is told by Truby in his book p. 122<lb/>
&ldquo;I think I would like that coin <unclear>but</unclear> I have not been off the<lb/>
post-&rdquo;</item>
<item>48- It has always puzzled me that he should have <unclear>apparently</unclear><lb/>
accepted it-</item>
<item>49</item>
<item>50- There was an exchange of letters when Reed work to Gorgas<lb/>
congratulating him on his <unclear>conversion</unclear> -<lb/>
(mem to March for date)</item>
<item>51. Will try to locate that date too I got it from Gorgas<lb/>
There may have been some correspondence between<lb/>
the Health Dept of Cuba and the U S Pub Health<lb/>
about it- I do not know.</item>
<item>52 Policy-</item> 
<item>53 It was different in different individuals but no panic<lb/>
Wives and children of American usually went to U S<lb/>
The soldiers were in quarantine and did not seem<lb/>
to worry</item>
<item>56 ? Explain- I was study up various points with reference<lb/>
to my examination This was one on which I had<lb/>
no data</item>
<item>57.-</item>
<item>59 Letter from N. O. Oct. 1941</item>
<item>60. It is at Univ. Va</item>
<item>61 no</item>
<item>62 no</item>
<item>63 Look up-</item>
</list></p>
<pb n="7" id="f06407007"/>
<p>Memo<lb/>
Talk with Colonel Hench about the three<lb/>
grades of y. f. and Finlays idea of immunization<lb/>
See Dr Fr. Dominguez letter to me and his book</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
