<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06409042">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Albert E. Truby, June 30, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06409042</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-06-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-06-30">June 30, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06409042</idno>
<title>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Albert E. Truby, June 30, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby discusses the Yellow Fever Commission in response to Hench's questionnaire.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-06-30">
<head>Recollections of the Yellow Fever Commission, by Albert E. Truby, June 30, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06409042"/>
<opener>
For Dr Hench.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1946-06-30">June 30 /46</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>Truby's Remarks on Questionnaire for General Kean</hi></head>
<item>No. 1 *<lb/>
I think that you and Kean have the right slant on this.<lb/>
There are some discrepancies in Howard's statements about Reed,<lb/>
Carroll, and Lazear which I have noted in pencil on the copy<lb/>
you sent me. Howard's quotation from Reed &ldquo;I went into this<lb/>
line of work without instructions&rdquo; is very important. Howard<lb/>
believed Reed and so do I. <del>After Carrolls death I found<lb/>
that I could not <unclear>audit</unclear> Agramonte's statements. Before that<lb/>
date his published statement were o.k.</del></item>
<item>No. 2 *<lb/>
I think Mrs. Lazear was right and as we had applied for a<lb/>
laboratory man at Camp Columbia, where we had both malaria and<lb/>
dengue fevers, Lazear and the Surgeon General probably decided<lb/>
that this was an ideal place for him to work. (See my book,<lb/>
pages 57, 82, and 83.</item>
<item>No. 3 *<lb/>
I feel confident that Reed first met Lazear at Camp Columbia.<lb/>
Reed became interested in Lazear's work there and when Reed returned<lb/>
to the States, someone told me (perhaps Reed himself) that when<lb/>
the question of organizing the Board was considered, Reed consulted<lb/>
Dr. Welch about <del>it.</del><add>Lazear-</add> (Page 57).</item>
<item>No. 4<lb/>
See my book, Page 76 <add>&amp; <unclear>181</unclear></add>. When Reed reported to the Surgeon<lb/>
General about his work on electrozone, he was ready to start a<lb/>
real investigation of yellow fever and he no doubt recommended to<lb/>
the Surgeon General in strong terms that he be sent back to Cuba<lb/>
with proper assistance and facilities to do that work. Sternberg<lb/>
naturally would concur and the Surgeon General deserves the credit<lb/>
for <del>organizing</del><add>creating</add> the Board.</item>
<item>No. 5<lb/>
See my book p. 76 &amp; p. 38<lb/>
Reed naturally selected Carroll as one member of the Board.<lb/>
I think he/also/selected Lazear on Welch's recommendation and<lb/>
because he had seen the fine work which Lazear was doing in Cuba.<lb/>
Perhaps both Reed and Sternberg agreed on Agramonte as a member.<lb/>
I have always understood that Reed wanted an immune to do autopsies<lb/>
on yellow fever cases. He knew Agramonte and knew he was doing<lb/>
this kind of work in Havana. Agramonte did Patrick Smith's<lb/>
Autopsy and Reed knew about that.</item>
<item>No. 6<lb/>
I never knew that the words &ldquo;especially yellow fever&rdquo; were<lb/>
ommitted from the orders creating the Yellow Fever Board until<lb/>
you told about it. Those words may have been deleted in the<lb/>
AGO so as not to alarm people at home.</item>
<item>No. 7<lb/>
I do not know.</item>
<item>No. 8<lb/>
That would, I think, be impossible.</item>
<pb n="2" id="f06409043"/>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<item><unclear>Kissinger is then in a N C U<lb/>
blue uniform. It was cold<lb/>
Reed is dressed in warm<lb/>
clothes probably ready to<lb/>
leave Camp Lazear<lb/>
right then</unclear></item>
<item>No. 9<lb/>
You will remember that I wrote you that <add>the</add> &ldquo;distinguished&rdquo;<lb/>
man in citizen's clothes was Reed. That was before I knew that<lb/>
Blossom Reed had identified it as a photograph of her father.<lb/>
The picture must have been taken in January or early in February,<lb/>
1900, just as Reed was ready to leave for the U.S. I consider that<lb/>
a very important photograph and I hope you will include it as an<lb/>
illustration in your book. I was evidently taken on a cold day<lb/>
as some of the personnel were wearing heavy blue uniforms. Kissinger<lb/>
appears in his new acting steward's uniform. That alone practically<lb/>
fixes the date of the photograph.</item>
<item>No. 10<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 11 *<lb/>
There was no secrecy about the nature of the Board's work<lb/>
except while Lazear was working alone on human guinea pigs. The<lb/>
experiments with mosquitoes naturally was secret at that time<lb/>
because <del>authority had not been obtained to</del><add>the <unclear>C. O.</unclear> had not been consulted about</add> jeopardiz<del>e</del><add>ing</add> human<lb/>
lives even with their consent. When Camp Lazear was opened, there<lb/>
was no necessity for secrecy because the work had been approved<lb/>
by General Wood and <add>the experiments <hi>were not</hi></add> conducted at Camp Columbia. (Off the Post)</item>
<item>No. 12<lb/>
The Surgeon General can only recommend and cannot <del><unclear>xx</unclear></del> give<lb/>
orders to personnel except in his own Department (See my book,<lb/>
Page 120).</item>
<item>No. 13<lb/>
I never knew about Finlay's work at the Finca San Jose.</item>
<item>No. 14<lb/>
I will give you a photograph of the building which I took myself.</item>
<item>No. 15<lb/>
My recollection is that the Spanish immigrants were camped<lb/>
near Regla across the bay near Cabana.</item>
<item>No. 16 *<lb/>
I recollect<del>ed</del> distinctly that Reed made several trips to Havana<lb/>
to consult with General Wood's Headquarters and possibly the Spanish<lb/>
Consul about using Spanish volunteers for his experiments. (See my<lb/>
book, page 182.)</item>
<item>No. 17 *<lb/>
The Spanish Consul-General in Cuba <del><unclear>made</unclear></del> might have some corres-<lb/>
pondence and records about the Spanish volunteers. It would be<lb/>
worth trying.</item>
<item>No. 18<lb/>
I certainly got the &ldquo;insurance&rdquo; ideas from Reed. Of course,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06409044"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear was not present and nobody knew whether Lazear<lb/>
had insurance or not. Possibly Reed himself, who probably did<lb/>
have <del><unclear>x</unclear></del> insurance, wondered if they would jeopardize it by being<lb/>
innoculated with infected mosquitoes. See p. 123</item>
<item>No. 19<lb/>
Kean has answered that fully.</item>
<item>No. 20<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 21<lb/>
No comment except the reference on Page 82 of my book.</item>
<item>No. 22.<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 23 *<lb/>
Reed did not need any plans for the buildings. He knew what<lb/>
he wanted in order to make his experiments fool-proof. Then he<lb/>
wrote out the detailed specifications and <del><unclear></unclear></del> also supervised the<lb/>
work of construction personally. <add>See p. 140</add></item>
<item>No. 24.<lb/>
Kean was not only enthusiastic, he was also efficient and did<lb/>
everything he could to help Reed with his plans.</item>
<item>No. 25<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 26<lb/>
I concur with Kean.</item>
<item>No. 27<lb/>
I concur with Kean. Also see my book Page 32.</item>
<item>No. 28<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 29 " "</item>
<item>No. 30 " "</item>
<item>No. 31 " "</item>
<item>No. 32 " "</item>
<item>No. 33 No.<lb/>
No.</item>
<item>No. 34<lb/>
Carroll did not believe in <add>the</add> mosquito theory. He did not want to<lb/>
be bitten and in that frame of mind simply went on and did his routine<lb/>
work regardless of consequences. No wonder Reed was disturbed.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06409045"/>
<item>- 4 -</item>
<item>No. 35*<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 36<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 37<lb/>
It must be in the Surgeon General's Office but I think not<lb/>
under the title &ldquo;Roll of Honor&rdquo;. As I understood it, it contained<lb/>
information pertaining to these yellow fever experiments and<lb/>
posibly the corresponence in the Roll of Honor.</item>
<item>No. 38*<lb/>
Kean thinks that I gave him that story. I doubt it although<lb/>
I think Reed did say that about Pinto. Reed liked Pinto and<lb/>
as Pinto rarely left the post, he would have been a good case<lb/>
and would have <hi>substantiated XY's case</hi>. Carroll's case, of<lb/>
course, proved nothing.</item>
<item>No. 39*<lb/>
No comment. I know nothing <unclear>on</unclear> that.</item>
<item>No. 40<lb/>
No comment.</item>
<item>No. 41<lb/>
I know that I wrote to Mrs. Lazear after her husband's death.<lb/>
A few days later Kean came to see me at the Hospital (after the<lb/>
funeral) and I told him I had written to Mrs. Lazear and then he<lb/>
said <add>&ldquo;That's fine</add> I have written her also&rdquo;. This <add>is</add> one thing I am positive about.</item>
<item>No. 42.<lb/>
I know nothing about it.</item>
<item>No. 43<lb/>
I do not know.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06409046"/>
<item>Page 5.</item>
<item>From here on I will omit questions about which I can add nothing important.<lb/>
The page numbers refer to <hi>my book</hi>.</item>
<item>47. See page 122.</item>
<item>48. See page 123.</item>
<item>50. See page 185.</item>
<item>51. See page 233, Senate Document.</item>
<item>53. See page 113. I think that the doctors were more depressed than anyone<lb/>
else because in spite of all of our efforts we had an epidemic in our midst.</item>
<item>Truby's answers to your questionnaire for Kean, June 5, 1946:</item>
<item>65. Possibly Kean did do Agramonte an injustice when he stated that Agramonte<lb/>
had nothing to do with mosquito work after Lazear's death, but Kean knew<lb/>
in 1904 or 1905 (when he probably wrote Chapter 2 of the Senate Document)<lb/>
that Agramonte &ldquo;did <hi>not</hi> participate in the early mosquito work.&rdquo; (Page 16).<lb/>
See the same statement on page 21, Senate Document, also probably written<lb/>
by Kean. I knew those facts also, so from the time I first saw Agramonte's<lb/>
statement of 1908 (on page 26, Senate Document) I lost all my respect for<lb/>
Agramonte. Likewise, I had previously lost all respect for Carroll for<lb/>
similar statements re his work. Carroll made no false statements before<lb/>
Reed died. Likewise, Agramonte made none that I know of until Carroll was<lb/>
dead. (Dr. Hench, please read Chapter 2, Senate Document very carefully<lb/>
and you will find answers to several important questions you have asked<lb/>
Kean and me). (Unclean conditions, Carter's findings, human experiments,<lb/>
General Wood's action). The <hi>last sentence on page 16</hi> may be very important.<lb/>
I don't know that I have ever seen that article. Chapter 2 probably con-<lb/>
tains the most reliable information available on the points mentioned as<lb/>
the subject was fresh in Kean's mind then and no controversies had arisen.</item>
<item>73. I think so. Both he and Reed, with Carter's findings and Ross' work<lb/>
before them, saw the possibility or probability that yellow fever was<lb/>
mosquito-borne. I have heard the story of Mrs. Stark's courage re the<lb/>
Edmunds child. That is essentially true. Mrs. Stark's story about her<lb/>
two boys spilling black vomit over themselves is okay except that I am<lb/>
sure the specimens belonged to Ames and <hi>not to Reed</hi>. I think they were<lb/>
standing on the porch railing as I told you. I don't know anything re the<lb/>
Carroll laboratory specimens.</item>
<item>75. The doctors all knew that Carroll was disgruntled and sore because he had<lb/>
to permit an infected mosquito to bite him. He did not believe in the<lb/>
theory; likewise, he did not want to have anything to do with it. He<lb/>
refused to let Lazear put more than one infected mosquito on his arm.</item>
<item>77. Ravanel gave us the answer.</item>
<pb n="6" id="f06409047"/>
<item>Page 6.</item>
<item>78. Kean and the doctors at Camp Columbia accepted it at once <add>(after Lazear's results)</add> and our en-<lb/>
thusiasm was promptly transmitted and accepted by the whole garrison.<lb/>
Likewise, when the information came out in the papers the Cubans accep-<lb/>
ted it also. (After the Additional Report was read.)</item>
<item>81. They were very brave, not panicky.</item>
<item>84. See page 111. We had a band and the casket was draped with a flag and<lb/>
carried on a <hi>caisson.</hi> Lazear's body was not taken to the cemetery in an<lb/>
ambulance as you seemd to think.</item>
<item>86. He died at the &ldquo;<hi>U.S.A. General Hospital,</hi>&rdquo; Washington Barracks, D. C. Reed's<lb/>
operation was performed in the operating room of that hospital. A picture<lb/>
of that room and the general conditions, including most of the personnel,<lb/>
is shown on page 195 of my book.</item>
<item>91. See my reply to Question 65 above. I never had any trouble with Agramonte.<lb/>
The Contract Surgeons, however, disliked him. He was very pompous and<lb/>
aggressive and senior to all the other doctors. He never let them forget<lb/>
that fact. I know that Lazear and Agramonte <hi>were not close friends,</hi><lb/>
although they were classmates.</item>
<item>92. General Frederick F. Russell can tell you all about Dr. Noguchi. Russell<lb/>
was in charge of the Health Department work of the Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
at the time Noguchi was with them. I am sure that Russell had more to do<lb/>
with the early Rockefeller yellow fever research work than anyone else.<lb/>
Russell and I were very close friends throughout his service in the Army.<lb/>
We were often stationed together and he told me all about Noguchi and his<lb/>
peculiarities. I think that I have seen it in print also. Be sure and<lb/>
communicate with Russell and meet him if you can. He can give you much<lb/>
information.</item>
<item>93. See page 19, Senate Document. When Reed found out exactly what Lazear had<lb/>
done with his mosquitoes just prior to his death, I think he must have<lb/>
consulted Gen. Wood and they then decided to publish Lazear's experiments<lb/>
as described in the Preliminary Note. No doubt it was also then decided<lb/>
by these two great men to continue the same line of experiments on human<lb/>
subjects in order to prove Lazear's unconclusive results. (See my book,<lb/>
pages 127 to 134 and page 19, Senate Document). XY's case convinced Reed<lb/>
that he could prove the theory and Gen. Wood must have told him to go ahead at that time.</item>
<item>94. See Senate Document, pages 9, 15 and 16, and my book, page 91. See also<lb/>
Dr. Victor Vaughan's remarks on page 178 in his book &ldquo;A Doctor's Memories.&rdquo;</item>
<item>95. See my book, pages 89 to 90. I think, however, that Kean's quoting of<lb/>
Reed's remarks gives us the true answer to the way Sternberg felt about<lb/>
the insect theory.</item>
<item>96. Personally, I had never questioned Sternberg's statements even as late as<lb/>
when I wrote my book. I even felt surprised and somewhat shocked at Reed's<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06409048"/>
Page 7.<lb/>
statement in his letter to his wife on December 11, 1900, predicting that<lb/>
Dr. X__ would state that he had considered the mosquito theory as the most<lb/>
probable cause of yellow fever. See Kelly, page 143, First Edition.</item>
<item>97. See <hi>Note, page 217</hi> of the Sternberg Biography. Agramonte quoting a letter<lb/>
from Reed written in 1900, says &ldquo;<hi>verbal</hi>instructions&rdquo; as to the cause of<lb/>
yellow fever. Personally I have never seen any written instructions except<lb/>
those referred to above and in the reprint of the Popular Science Monthly<lb/>
of July 1901, which I gave you when you were here in 1943. Also see my<lb/>
book, pages 89 to 90.</item>
<item>98. I concur with Kean's answer.</item>
<item>99. I concur in Kean's answer. Regarding your remarks about this question, I<lb/>
think that a scientific board of that kind would naturally be directed to<lb/>
study all diseases which were causing mortality and morbidity among our<lb/>
troops in Cuba. Of these diseases, however, yellow fever was the great<lb/>
monster which we knew so little about and as Reed was already investigating<lb/>
that disease, naturally he wanted to finish the work and discover the<lb/>
etiology of yellow fever if possible. Regarding Kober, I told you what<lb/>
close friends he and Sternberg were and I think Agramonte was close to<lb/>
both of them.</item>
<item>100. Lazear, while he was still living in Baltimore, was deeply interested in<lb/>
malaria and no doubt that fact took him to see Howard in Washington regard-<lb/>
ing mosquitoes.</item>
<item>102. Reed started that story when he was writing the Preliminary Report. The<lb/>
&ldquo;Insurance story&rdquo; was just a surmise on his part as he knew nothing of<lb/>
Lazear's personal affairs. I have explained that elsewhere.</item>
<item>106. Reed was living at Camp Columbia by <hi>War Department orders</hi>. See Sternberg's<lb/>
Biography, page 214. Therefore, the Commanding Officer could not interfere<lb/>
with that. However, if the CO found him jeopardizing the lives of his men<lb/>
or if Reed was actually introducing yellow fever to the Post, he could<lb/>
have stopped the work at once unless Gen. Wood had previously directed<lb/>
otherwise. When Camp Lazear was established it was not near the reser-<lb/>
vation and was therefore beyond the control or jurisdiction of the CO. By<lb/>
that time, too, the Military Governor (Wood) had authorized experimentation<lb/>
on volunteers. That fact was generally known and the papers made a fuss<lb/>
about it. Reed and the CO, Col. Baldwin, were on friendly terms. Reed<lb/>
frequently went to the Post parties and you may be sure that he officially<lb/>
called on the CO very promptly - that was a very strict requirement in<lb/>
those days.</item>
<item>107. I have given the answer in the preceding paragraph. I hold that nothing<lb/>
was secret until Lazear started his experiments on soldiers with infected<lb/>
mosquitoes. No doubt Gen. Wood had approved their doing that but Lazear,<lb/>
in his haste, had probably not consulted the CO on this important matter.<lb/>
<del>This</del><add>Things</add> went faster than he had anticipated. Neither he nor Reed probably<lb/>
expected any results in the early stages of the experiments with mosquitoes.</item>
<item>112. I concur in Kean's answer.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
