<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06406001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Questionnaire for Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, April 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06406001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-04-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Finca San Jose (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-04-00">April 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06406001</idno>
<title>Questionnaire for Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, April 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench lists questions he has for Kean.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-04-00">
<head>Questionnaire for Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, April 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06406001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Prepared <date value="1946-04-00">April, 1946</date>
</dateline>
Take <unclear>section</unclear> of book<lb/>
</opener>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<head><hi>QUESTIONS FOR GENERAL KEAN</hi></head>
<item><p>1. <hi>Comment</hi> on the remarks of Dr. L. O. Howard, published in his &ldquo;History of Applied<lb/>
Entomology&rdquo;, <hi>1930.</hi>.</p>
<p>p. 470 - &ldquo;As a matter of fact, before going to Cuba for this work, Reed and<lb/>
Lazear spent some time in my office studying mosquitoes in order that they<lb/>
might most easily identify the old &lsquo;Culex Fasciatus&rsquo; with which Carlos Finlay<lb/>
of Habana had done his earlier work; and during their investigations Reed fre-<lb/>
quently wrote me and sent me mosquitoes for examination.&rdquo;</p>
<p>p. 481 - &ldquo;Years later I became well acquainted with Walter Reed, James Carroll,<lb/>
and Jesse W. Lazear. They came to the entomological offices in the Department<lb/>
of Agriculture to study mosquitoes before they went to Cuba where their immortal<lb/>
discoveries were made.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>My Comment:</hi> Howard must have been in error when he wrote this in <hi>1930.</hi> Lazear<lb/>
went to Cuba in February, 1900, and already knew a lot about mosquitoes, which<lb/>
<unclear>and</unclear><lb/>
was months before the Yellow Fever Commission was formed and, so far as I know,<lb/>
when Lazear was in the United States before going to Cuba he didn't know Reed or<lb/>
Carroll and never went to visit Howard. He went to Cuba as soon as he accepted<lb/>
his first assignment which was Cuba.</p>
<p>Kean once told me that Howard gave Reed and Carroll some instructions on mosquitoes</p>
before Reed and Carroll went to Cuba. Source of this data?</item>
<item>2. Did Lazear join the Medical Corps for any <hi>special</hi> reasons? to do any special work?<lb/>
(Mrs. Lazear says to do research on <hi>malaria</hi>).</item>
<item>3. What evidence that Lazear ever me<del>e</del>t Reed in the United States? (I think they first<lb/>
met when Reed visited Cuba regarding the disinfectant.--See Lazear's letter to his<lb/>
mother, dated March 23, 1900). Lazear wrote &ldquo;I saw his very long lately many had has no <unclear></unclear><lb/>
<unclear>Havana</unclear> on a special moments <unclear>events job</unclear> a <unclear>desinfectant and I have been</unclear> detailed to <unclear>assist him</unclear> <unclear>It has balance</unclear> a great deal of my time.&rdquo;</item>
<item>4. What were the circumstances behind the formation of the Yellow Fever Commission?<lb/>
Did Reed initiate its formation, (as Howard says) or did Sternberg?</item>
<item>5. Who do you suppose chose Agramonte and Lazear for the Board? Was it probably the<lb/>
suggestion of Reed or of Sternberg? (Truby thinks Reed went to Baltimore to see<lb/>
Welch and selected Lazear as a result of that conference. Kean agrees. Any data?</item>
<item>6. Why was the original write-up of the order creating the Yellow Fever Board changed<lb/>
to leave out &ldquo;--especially yellow fever&rdquo;?<lb/>
(Already answered in interview of Jan. 6, 1944- see p. 16. question 27)</item>
<item>7. Why did Lazear go to Cuba via Tampa (on his first assignment) and Reed via boat from<lb/>
New York when Reed always got so sea sick?</item>
<item>8. Could I check some of the disputed dates of Reed's comings and goings by finding any<lb/>
data on the passenger lists of the Army transports?</item>
<pb n="2" id="f06406002"/>
<item>9. Please identify the photograph of Reed in the derby hat, which Blossom Reed gave me.<lb/>
Blossom thinks it was taken when he left for Cuba on the Yellow Fever investigation.<lb/>
(See interview with General Kean Jan. 6., 1944 -p. 17)</item>
<item>? not in<lb/>
Hench<lb/>
collection<lb/>
<unclear>B</unclear></item>
<item>10. Any recollection of when General Kean first heard that a Yellow Fever Board was to<lb/>
be formed, that Reed was to arrive, that Lazear and Agramonte were to be on it?</item>
<item>11. Comment on &ldquo;secrecy&rdquo; of Board's work. Just how secret was it and why?</item>
<item>12. How much interference would the Camp C.O. have dared to express in view of the fact<lb/>
that Reed's authority came direct from the Surgeon General <add>or did it?</add> If very little, then<lb/>
why the &ldquo;secrecy&rdquo;? was it just a matter of expediency, to let well enough alone?<lb/>
See General Kean's interview of May 8, 1941 -p 7.(&ldquo;confidential&rdquo; ) amplify. Any<lb/>
repercussions?</item>
<item>13. Had Kean ever known that the Finca San Jose had once been visited and used by Finlay?</item>
<item>14. Identify building and, if possible, the room (from the outside) where Reed went<lb/>
with Kean to see General Wood - &ldquo;They faced each other in the embrasure of a window<lb/>
of the palace looking out in the Plaza de las Armes&rdquo;. (Military S. March 1928).<lb/>
show photo <unclear>in &amp;</unclear> out</item>
<item>15. Identify place where the Spanish immigrants were held &ldquo;on the heights of Cabana&rdquo;<lb/>
(Jan. 6, 1944). p 12</item>
<item>16. How were Spanish volunteers acquired? any direct knowledge?<lb/>
See interview of May 8, 1941 p 3 - answer to question %15. What were the &ldquo;certain<lb/>
difficulties&rdquo;?</item>
<item>17. Could I find out the name of the helpful Spanish consul-general (who refused to<lb/>
interfere with the acquisition of the Spanish volunteers) and other data if I con-<lb/>
tacted the Spanish legation in Cuba?<lb/>
Kean called the consul-general a &ldquo;very nice man&rdquo; -Interview of Jan. 6, 1944 p 13.</item>
<item>18. Show him my letter regarding Mrs. Lazear's comments on &ldquo;no insurance&rdquo;. How about<lb/>
&ldquo;insurance&rdquo;? Kean's interview of Jan. 6, 1944 -&ldquo;It was assumed as a guess&rdquo; by whom?<lb/>
Conversation?</item>
<item>19. Where are the survivors of Carter, Gorgas, Sternberg, General Lyster, Neate? In<lb/>
November, 1928, Laura A. Carter (daughter) lived at the Westmoreland, Washington, D.C.<lb/>
Manuel Admiral <unclear><hi>sterl</hi></unclear></item>
<item>20. More data on Reed's visit to Kean's sick bed. Did Kean know ahead of time that<lb/>
Reed was going to visit him?, How long a visit? etc. Conversation?<lb/>
(See Kean's letter of Jan. 23, 1941 p. 7 answer to question #23)<lb/>
How <unclear>comes</unclear> an <unclear>imagenary conversation go</unclear>?</item>
<item>- 2 -</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06406003"/>
<item>21. Kean's first recollection of the work of Lazear and Agramonte before the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Board formed: after the Yellow Fever Board formed, but before Reed's arrival?</item>
<item>22. Kean's relationship to the Commission; to what extent was it official; any order<lb/>
to Kean to cooperate? If so, orders from whom?</item>
<item>23. Kean's recollections regarding the planning of Camp Lazear; did Reed plan the<lb/>
buildings after those of the Italian malaria investigators?</item>
<item>24. To what extent was Kean's relationship and help regarding Camp Lazear enthusiastically<lb/>
voluntary?</item>
<item>25. Kean's reaction to Lazear's death? How soon did Kean suspect (on his own) (or<lb/>
from Reed) that Lazear's death was &ldquo;unusual&rdquo;. See question #48</item>
<item>26. Should I frankly name Godfrey and even quote Reed's letter of condemnation of him -<lb/>
for the sake of historical accuracy?</item>
<item>27. What &ldquo;instructions regarding Yellow Fever&rdquo; did Godfrey ignore? Were they from<lb/>
Washington, or from Havana; &ldquo;formal&rdquo; or &ldquo;informal&rdquo;?</item>
<item>28. What room in Washington Barracks did Reed die in (Show General Kean Truby sketch-<lb/>
Truby said second floor, back corridor, first room on left).</item>
<item>29. Comment regarding Moran's hurt feelings when Kissinger was given watch, etc.<lb/>
Moran invited to watch ceremony but not given anything. (Truby says Kissinger was<lb/>
first to volunteer; furthermore you<del>r</del> couldn't hold formation for a civilian.<lb/>
My comment: They certainly held formations for civilians in this war. E.g-<lb/>
Colonel Benjamin and Doctor Meyer; the medals, etc., to civilians in this war )</item>
<item>30. About when (month,etc.) was Kissinger given the watch at the ceremony? Was<lb/>
Colonel Havard the &ldquo;Chief Surgeon&rdquo;? Would his remarks be a matter of record any-<lb/>
where?<lb/>
(See <del>Kissinger's</del><add>Kean's</add> interviews of May 8, 1941, p-3 question #16 and January 6, 1944<lb/>
p-9).</item>
<item>31. Why was &ldquo;something pasted over&rdquo; the old framed Benigno contract, lost and later<lb/>
(May 1941) found? What possible explanation?</item>
<item>- 3 -</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06406004"/>
<item>Finlays <unclear>sends<lb/>
reaction short notes<lb/>
infast</unclear>!</item>
<item>32. In one of General Kean's letters &ldquo;I could tell you some amu<del>z</del><add>s</add>ing incidents about<lb/>
Doctor Finlay if we had a chat&rdquo;. Amplify.</item>
<item>33. Would there be any data in the files of the Military Surgeon?</item>
<item>34. Amplify answer to question #13 (p 9-interview of May 8, 1941) regarding Reed's<lb/>
indignation about Carroll. What does Reed say? Where did he say it to Kean -<lb/>
on the transport when Kean met Reed at Matanzas? Did Reed discuss the matter<lb/>
with Carroll himself or let it go? (Carroll was still sick)</item>
<item>35. Amplify answer to question 22 (May 8, 1941) Where was the &ldquo;camp across the harbor&rdquo;<lb/>
- the camp for the Spanish non-immune immigrants? How many in it at a time?<lb/>
see question 15</item>
<item>36. Did Reed make any comments about the confirmatory studies of Doctor Guiteras, etc.<lb/>
or regarding the death of Miss Maas?</item>
<item>37. In Kean's letter to Truby May 22, 1936, Kean speaks of a file kept by General<lb/>
Reynolds regarding the Roll of Honor, etc. Where is the file now?</item>
<item>38. Why did Reed ( in ) say &ldquo;I wish Pinto had had a mild<lb/>
attack&rdquo; -was he for Pinto, against him? or was this a reflection on Carroll?<lb/>
did he like Pinto (or Reed)?</item>
<item>39. Tell Kean Mrs. Lazear's recollection that when Reed came to Cuba to work on<lb/>
electrozone ( and Lazear was assigned to help him) one evening, while Doctor<lb/>
Lazear and Reed were talking, Lazear suddenly turned to Mrs. Lazear, who was<lb/>
only vaguely listening, and said &ldquo;I have another convert. Major Reed also believes<lb/>
in the mosquito theory of Yellow Fever&rdquo;. Mrs. Lazear added &ldquo;I think the incident<lb/>
occurred about the first of March&rdquo;. Mrs. Lazear repeated this story to me two<lb/>
or three times and was very emphatic about it and her date -the first of March-<lb/>
is almost correct.</item>
<item>40. My &ldquo;lost&rdquo; Finlay book - tell Kean about it.</item>
<item>41. Mrs. Lazear said she never heard from Kean or Truby after Doctor Lazear's death.<lb/>
Tell about her reaction to Mrs Truby's letter &ldquo;Now he is talking to the <unclear>angels</unclear>!&rdquo;<lb/>
<unclear>me</unclear> I and "I quickly threw it in the fire!'</item>
<item>42. Show General Kean the editorial on aviation 1926 Med. Surg. (Harbord article)</item>
<item>43. From Kean's 1902 memorandum (cut out pages) &ldquo;Gorgas afterwards asked for and was<lb/>
given a Colonelcy (the one meant for Reed?) and the Lt. Colonelcy (originally for<lb/>
Gorgas) was not filled. Carroll was given a commission (1st Lt.) and four years<lb/>
later was made a Major&rdquo;. (Circumstances of Carroll's entry into regular Army. Did<lb/>
he skip a grade?</item>
<item>- 4 -</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06406005"/>
<item>44. Borrow Reed's letter of July <add>24</add>, 1900, to Sternberg, to photograph last page regarding<lb/>
need for using volunteers. (What will he do with the Reed letters?)</item>
<item>45. Can Kean put into conversation Reed's concern over XY. See Kean's interview of<lb/>
Reed<lb/>
January 6, 1944, p 7. &ldquo;I laughed and told <hi>him</hi> ---&rdquo;.<lb/>
When the infantry captain complained through channels about &ldquo;one of his men&rdquo;<lb/>
being experimented on, who was the captain, was the man XY? and did the complaint<lb/>
through official channels arouse Colonel Baldwin? When was &ldquo;later?&rdquo;</item>
<item>46. Did anyone (Carroll or Agramonte) accompany Kean and Reed to visit Wood (October 12)<lb/>
to get Wood's approval for the Board's experiments? Kean says Carroll and <del>Reed</del><add>Agramonte</add><lb/>
did not go.</item>
<item>47. Ask Kean to dictate in detail the story of Reed's offering Dean a ten dollar gold<lb/>
piece to admit he'd broken quarantine.</item>
<item>48. The &ldquo;secret&rdquo; story of Lazear's self-inoculation. I <del>just</del><add>first</add> heard the story (garbled)<lb/>
from Miss Agramonte, then I asked Moran who knew little but said that the men had<lb/>
suspected it and then asked General Kean who said he'd heard it from Truby. When<lb/>
did Kean hear this story? and from any other source? ( In his letter of September<lb/>
12, 1940 to me - p 12 - he says &ldquo;within the last few years from Truby&rdquo;).</item>
<item>49. In the light of question #48 review the entry of Oct. 7, 1900, in General Kean's<lb/>
diary. How definite or convincing was Reed when he told Kean the story of Lazear's<lb/>
so-called accidental bite in Las Animas?<lb/>
(See also Kean's letter of September 17, 1940-p 12)</item>
<item>50. In Kean's personal memorandum of dates connected with the Yellow Fever episode, he<lb/>
states &ldquo;Gorgas ceases disinfection of bedding and clothing for Yellow Fever-<lb/>
August 15, 1901.&rdquo; Where can I substantiate this data? Was there an order issued<lb/>
by Gorgas on that date?</item>
<item>51. When did Gorgas first use the expression about Finlay's &ldquo;wonderful scientific<lb/>
clairvoyance&rdquo; mentioned in Kean's letter to Mr. Clemons, September 22, 1939.?</item>
<item>52. Significance of the following letter: Sternberg to Reed, January 8, 1901 -&ldquo;Will it<lb/>
not be best for Carroll to stay for a while? It is my intention to recommend him<lb/>
for the position of Major and Surgeon, U. S. Volunteers as soon as a vacancy occurs;<lb/>
but I could not very well do this if he was on duty in Washington.&rdquo; Why not?</item>
<item>53. What was the general reaction of citizens, soldiers, and doctors to the Yellow<lb/>
Fever epidemic in Marianao in the spring of 1900 - was there much panic, quiet<lb/>
fear, or just fatalism? Population of Marianao?<lb/>
Was <unclear>N like as of there was a few cases of polio in a small town</unclear></item>
<item>- 5 -</item>
<pb n="6" id="f06406006"/>
<item>54. In what building in Havana was the Pan-American Medical Congress held (February<lb/>
4-7, 1901) where Reed gave his paper.</item>
<item>55. Do you know whether the speech of Doctor Guiteras at the banquet for Finlay,<lb/>
December 22, 1900, was ever published?</item>
<item>56. General Kean's diary-entry of January 14, 1901 - &ldquo;Experimenting all day with<lb/>
petroleum oils of various densities to test their diffusibility in water and their<lb/>
power to kill mosquito larvae&rdquo;. Amplify. Who all were doing these experiments?</item>
<item>p 4</item>
<item>57. In Kean's letter of January 23, 1941, he said he'd given away to institutions and<lb/>
writers most of Reed's letters to him. To whom probably?</item>
<item>58. Regarding Secretary Root's report of 1902: What is the difference between <add>assistant</add> Surgeon<lb/>
General and deputy Surgeon General?</item>
<item>59. Borrow for copy <hi>my</hi> letter to Kean from New Orleans, October, 1941. I have no copy.</item>
<item>60. Let me see his <del>borrowed</del><add>bound</add> volume of various items, including the speech of Lopez del<lb/>
Valle at the unveiling of the portraits of Finlay, Magoon, and Kean.<lb/>
<unclear>It is Vg Va</unclear></item>
<item>61. Did I ever get the packet of letters of Guiteras, Finlay, etc?<lb/>
Mentioned in several letters October-December, 1941, and in January, 1942, September<lb/>
1944, December 1944, and November 1945.</item>
<item>62. Does he want fifty more copies of Hygea?</item>
<item>63. Let me copy the Walter Reed letter, mentioned in Kean's letter of September 14, 1944<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>a) When Kean wanted to go to the front.</item>
<item>b) Regarding succeeding Sternberg.</item>
<item>c) What was in the destroyed one -&ldquo; a humorous account of the attitudes and the<lb/>
claims of the various candidates&rdquo; (candidates for Surgeon General?)</item>
</list></item>
<item>64. Eventually I would like my longhand letters to Kean between 1942 and 1945.</item>
</list></p>
<p>- 6 -</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
