<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413079">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413079</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-06-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Albertini, A. Diaz</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">de Kruif, Paul</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-06-25">June 25, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413079</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran discusses Cuban politics in general. He notes that the Finlay-Reed controversy is still ongoing, and there are strong anti-American sentiments connected with it.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-06-25">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, June 25, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413079"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
JOHN J. MORAN<lb/>
HAVANA, CUBA<lb/>
<date value="1947-06-25">June 25, 1947.</date>
</dateline>
Gen. Jefferson R. Kean,<lb/>
U. S. Army - Retired,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am most grateful to you for your six-page letter of<lb/>
May 25th, repeating what you wrote to me back in 1939. I was<lb/>
foolish enough to relinquish that letter to the secretary of the<lb/>
Rotary Club, for translation, with the express condition that it<lb/>
be returned to me. As frequently happens elsewhere, but always<lb/>
in Cuba, some people are not very scrupolous in matters of that<lb/>
nature. The good intentions may be there at the moment, only to<lb/>
be immediately forgotten. I could never get your original letter<lb/>
back, so that I could not even make a copy of it. Your letter, I<lb/>
well recall, was translated in &ldquo;running&rdquo; fashion by a Cuban who<lb/>
was well versed in English. After your letter was read, the<lb/>
next speaker at the lunch was our old friend and enemy, Dr.<lb/>
Francisco Dominguez Roldan, the self-appointed champion of Finlay<lb/>
and author (in French) of Finlay's biography. Your clear and<lb/>
concise statements made no impression on him. He went on to claim<lb/>
all the glory for Finlay. I regret to record that ALL Cuban<lb/>
medicos want to see eye to eye with the late Finlay biographer.<lb/>
That work was a sad travesty on historical accuracy and truth.<lb/>
It had a limited circulation in France, just enough to confuse<lb/>
French scientific opinion and cloud Reed's accomplishment. To add<lb/>
to the confusion, Dr. Juan Guiteras, who knew all the facts, later<lb/>
on claimed all the glory for Finlay. Due to his enmity towards<lb/>
General Crowder, American Ambassador during the Zayas regime, he<lb/>
became violently anti-American. As Secretary of Sanitation, he<lb/>
incurred the displeasure of General Crowder through his lack of<lb/>
cooperation with the Public Health Service of the U. S. in matters<lb/>
of quarantine. He had exaggerated views on the sovereign rights<lb/>
of Cuba in quarantine matters, holding that Cuban sanitation was<lb/>
superior to that of the U. S. He wanted no suggestions from the<lb/>
U. S. in his department. Without shadow of a doubt, he was a real<lb/>
Cuban patriot but he ignored the part played by the U. S. in making<lb/>
Cuba a health resort. The upshot of it all was his removal from<lb/>
the &ldquo;Honest Cabinet&rdquo; which Zayas was obliged to name by Crowder.<lb/>
Once Zayas got the $50,000,000 loan for Cuba from the U. S., he<lb/>
promptly disposed, one by one, of Crowder's HONEST CABINET. He<lb/>
put one over on Crowder and flagrantly violated his word of honor<lb/>
to the effect that he would stick to the Honest Cabinet.</p>
<p>You are entirely correct in assuming that your letter to<lb/>
Dr. Noguera will not change his attitude in the Reed-Finlay matter.<lb/>
By the way, he is no longer Director of Public Health. His resign-<lb/>
ation was called for a few weeks after his return to Cuba. Since<lb/>
my letter to you was <unclear>xxx</unclear> not sealed when I handed it to him, I could<lb/>
not well tell you this. You cannot convince a man who does not<lb/>
have an open mind and when it comes to the Reed-Finlay matter I do<lb/>
not know of but one Cuban doctor who did have an open mind. That<lb/>
man was the late Dr. Albertini, one of the signers of my yellow<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413080"/>
JOHN J. MORAN<lb/>
HAVANA, CUBA<lb/>
<hi>General Jefferson R. Kean</hi>.<lb/>
-- 2 --<lb/>
<hi>June 25, 1947.</hi><lb/>
fever certificate and the junior member of the Yellow Fever Board<lb/>
of the City of Havana, of which Dr. Finlay was President, with<lb/>
Gorgas and Guiteras. He admitted to me personally, several years<lb/>
ago, that it would be equivalent to suicide for him or any other<lb/>
Cuban medico to combat the <hi>FINLAY ONLY</hi> school, headed by Dr. Francisco<lb/>
Dominguez Roldan. At that time, Dr. Albertini was director of the<lb/>
Instituto Finlay. This clique of Cuban medicos got to work on<lb/>
Dr. Juan Guiteras, Dr. Aristides Agramonte and others, with the<lb/>
result that they all finally considered it the better part of wisdom<lb/>
to fall in line. The younger generation of Cuban medicos have<lb/>
learned their lesson so well that it would be &ldquo;Love's Labor Lost&rdquo;<lb/>
to try to convince them that THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER was a<lb/>
REED-FINLAY accomplishment. I reckon that you and I are the only<lb/>
living witnesses of actually what happened in Cuba in the last six<lb/>
months of 1900 and the first two months of the 20th Century - in<lb/>
the Yellow Fever field. It is regrettable that you never wrote<lb/>
the story. General Truby, I regret to state, deals too much with<lb/>
Truby and too little with Reed, in his book. You could have done<lb/>
a much better job of it. Please do not think I am prejudiced<lb/>
against General Truby. I have nothing against him. I remember<lb/>
him best as a chubby-faced &ldquo;shave-tail&rdquo;. At Columbia Barracks<lb/>
Post Hospital I reported directly to Major Stark whom I assisted in<lb/>
the operating room. There were but two regular army medicos, viz:<lb/>
Stark, with temporary rank of Major and Truby, 1st Lieutenant &amp;<lb/>
Asst. Surgeon. All the rest of them were Contract Surgeons or<lb/>
Acting Asst. Surgeons, the latter being their formal titles.</p>
<p>I am not sure whether you know it or not, but if you do<lb/>
it will do no harm to repeat it. I have made a start on an article<lb/>
bearing the tentative title of &ldquo;<hi>Memoirs of a Human Guinea Pig</hi>&rdquo;, the<lb/>
main object of which will be to offset Cuban propaganda <hi>ALL-OUT-</hi><lb/>
<hi>FOR-FINLAY-WITH-NOTHING-FOR-REED</hi>. I have no intention of invading<lb/>
the scientific field but to confine myself strictly to the layman's<lb/>
point of view, based on facts and actual experience, making every<lb/>
effort to stifle my well known sympathies for the master mind who<lb/>
engineered and carried out the series of experiments which brought<lb/>
fame and glory to REED and FINLAY. I had high hopes that Dr.<lb/>
Hench would be the medium through which the scientific and the lay<lb/>
world alike could learn the story, correctly and impartially. I<lb/>
wanted to read his book while still in the land of the living. I<lb/>
am encouraged by Paul de Kruif, a Reed-Finlay advocate but decidedly<lb/>
pro-Carroll. He writes me that he will spend the winter in Havana<lb/>
and will pass on the merits of my &ldquo;Memoirs&rdquo;. If the good Lord spares<lb/>
me, I may be able to convert them into book size. Dr. Hench does<lb/>
not have an exalted opinion of the author of &ldquo;Microbe Hunters&rdquo;, I am<lb/>
sorry to state. Wishing you a Happy Birthday and with very kindest<lb/>
regards from Elida and myself to Mrs. Kean and your very good self,<lb/>
I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your obedient servant,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
