<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413094">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413094</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-09-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Aileen</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilber A.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-09-09">September 9, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413094</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean remembers a conversation with Gorgas, who believed that Reed had found a way of producing mild, non-fatal yellow fever. As such, Gorgas planned to start inducing experimental cases. Kean comments on the planned commemoration of Reed by the Fourth International Congress of Tropical Medicine and Malaria. He hopes that they will include a Cuban speaker for the event.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-09-09">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, September 9, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413094"/>
<opener>
1-<lb/>
Sep 9, 1947<lb/>
<dateline>
2804 N St. N. W. Washington 7 D. C.
<date value="1947-09-09">9/9/'47</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Colonel Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>Cornelia thinks you may be interested in<lb/>
a letter which came from Cuba today and in my<lb/>
reply to it- I have a very clear recollection of my<lb/>
talk with Gen. Gorgas in the summer of 1901 and his<lb/>
telling me that he believed that Reed had found a<lb/>
way of producing a mild non-fatal form of yellow<lb/>
fever and he was going to start (or had started) a series<lb/>
of experimental cases, and when he got 100 cases with-<lb/>
out a death he would have Aileen (his daughter) bitten<lb/>
and made immune- I have the record of his series of<lb/>
7 cases with names and dates somewhere with the<lb/>
three deaths, all of the deaths, I think being from one<lb/>
mosquito, who was evidently loaded for bears, as the old<lb/>
saying is- Just where the record is I dont know as I<lb/>
have not a set of files with a clever girl in charge<lb/>
as you have. I have however always at hand that bound<lb/>
volume on Yellow Fever (Senate Doc. no. 822) which I got to-<lb/>
gether and got the Surgeon General to have printed as a public<lb/>
document- In the back of it is Gorgas's Final Report to Gen-<lb/>
Wood being his last report as Chief Sanitary Officer of Havana-<lb/>
It is dated July 12 1902, more than 2 months after we left Cuba<lb/>
It reviews the history of the Sanitary Dept from its inception in 1899<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413095"/>
2-<lb/>
but does not mention the Las Animas Series of<lb/>
yellow fever experiments, which had such a sad termi<lb/>
nation. But I find in the Report of Dr. Carlos Finlay which<lb/>
precedes that of Gorgas on page 228 they are mentioned in<lb/>
a little table at the top of the page- I suppose the other two<lb/>
experimental cases in Oct. and Nov- are the <del>the</del> two cases<lb/>
of Carroll with filtered blood- But Finlay as you will<lb/>
see gives no details- The less said the better it may be agreed-<lb/>
I had a letter recently from Dr Wilbur A. Sawyer about the<lb/>
Fourth International Congress of Tropical Medicine and Mala-<lb/>
ria which will be held here May 10-18, 1948- He says<lb/>
--&ldquo;-it is planned to commemorate the demonstration by Walter<lb/>
Reed of the mosquito transmission of yellow fever and to celebrate<lb/>
his admission to the Hall of Fame&rdquo;- This will be at one Eve-<lb/>
ning meeting on Wed. May 12, '48- If you have not heard<lb/>
of it you will in due time, for you are on the program<lb/>
to make the chief address- All he wanted of me was to be a<lb/>
member of the committee which I of course will accept<lb/>
with pleasure- I wrote to him, if he was in favor of inter-<lb/>
national peace, to make a place in the program for<lb/>
some Cuban orator to tell of the contribution of Dr. Carlos Finlay,<lb/>
wont they blow up if Finlay is left out! Siler is elected<lb/>
Chairman of the Committee and we will agree that they<lb/>
have made a good start with his selection-</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
