<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413168">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 9, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413168</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-01-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Leon, Estela Agramonte Rodriguez</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Hagedorn, [s.n.[</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Haskins, Arthur</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Baldwin, General</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-01-09">January 9, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413168</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 9, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench informs Truby that he has assembled all the necessary data from the National Archives. He would appreciate any comments Truby has to make about these materials. Hench makes comments and raises questions about the information in the documents.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-01-09">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, January 9, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413168"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-01-09">January 9, 1948</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My Dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have finally assembled and expressed to you the collection of<lb/>
data I've long wanted you to see. Most of it is photostat and photographic<lb/>
copies of all sorts of data I unearthed from time to time in my visits to<lb/>
the National Archives. (These are my only copies, aside from the microfilm<lb/>
from which the prints were made).</p>
<p>Please look it all over at your leisure and <hi>don't let yourself<lb/>
get tired or disturbed</hi>. I would like you to return the Agramonte material,<lb/>
so I have it on or about February 1, as Mrs. Hench and I are going to Cuba<lb/>
and I want to review the Agramonte material before I go, and probably take<lb/>
some if it with me.</p>
<p>I leave here Saturday, January 24,for Augusta, Georgia (to visit<lb/>
the Oliver General Hospital, give some talks there, etc., at the request of<lb/>
the S. G. O.), then to Atlanta to give three talks January 27-29 at a Post-<lb/>
graduate Medical Assembly. Then home for a few days, until I leave to give<lb/>
a talk on Cout before the District of Columbia Medical Society, February 18.<lb/>
From Washington, we will go to Palm Beach for my first real post-war vaca-<lb/>
tion. Then to Cuba for a week about March 1. (Back to Washington in May,<lb/>
to Toronto in June and to Europe in October, so you see I have a very busy<lb/>
year!)</p>
<p>General Truby, as you look over these data, if you want to write<lb/>
<hi>anything</hi> please do so; write it on the back or clip a note to it by clip<lb/>
or scotch tape. <hi>But</hi>, if you wish to send any extensive comments, <hi>please<lb/>
don't</hi> trouble to do it by hand. Call in a Stenographer, dictate whatever<lb/>
you want and have her <hi>send me the bill</hi> - I <hi>insist</hi>. Always remember please<lb/>
that your help and comments are worth much more than I could possibly pay<lb/>
to any stenographer: But the data are for you to <hi>see</hi> and if you have no<lb/>
comments, that is fine too. By the way, all the data are <hi>carefully arranged<lb/>
in calendar sequence</hi>. If you can keep them that way, please do so. But<lb/>
don't hesitate to mix them up if you need to. I can later rearrange them.<lb/>
I think many of the memoranda will intrigue and surprise you. Much of the<lb/>
stuff isn't too useful or interesting, but much of it is helpful; some very<lb/>
important. I find it necessary to re-read much of it. Often, I miss<lb/>
completely the significance of something the first time I read it; a re-<lb/>
reading shows it to be very important-just a line, or a date, or a reference<lb/>
here and there provides a long-missing link. Therefore, if you want to<lb/>
keep most of this until my return from Cuba in mid March, <hi>do so</hi>.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06413169"/>
<p>General Albert E. Truby</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>January 9, 1948</p>
<p>You will need a magnifying glass to read much of the material. I<lb/>
believe you have one, I think I recall seeing you use one. If not, I'll send<lb/>
you a rather good large hand lens for your use. Let me know.</p>
<p>Please note that there is a <hi>letter and number</hi> on the back of most<lb/>
of the items. You can refer to these as codes if you wish.</p>
<p>Now let me make some comments about individual items.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. Hurd's letter of February 11, 1905 to Latimer (Kelly's Colleague)<lb/>
will interest you (Reed data). It contains the source of the &ldquo;gentlemen, I<lb/>
salute you&rdquo; legend, but Kelly didn't quote the letter correctly. This letter<lb/>
states that Reed told Hurd that Kissinger and Moran <hi>volunteered together</hi>. But<lb/>
if Hurd misquoted Reed on the &ldquo;salute matter,&rdquo; he may also have misquoted them<lb/>
on the joint-volunteering of K. and M.</item>
<item>2. Reed's letter to Carroll (February 16, 1901) which Carroll leaned<lb/>
Kelly and which Kelly copied, is amusing. Reed was upset that day! The letter<lb/>
dates Reed's return to the United States.</item>
<item>3. I enclose Agramonte's own &ldquo;personal report&rdquo; and the orders<lb/>
regarding his leave. September 24 - October 12, 1900. According to Carroll's<lb/>
letter to his wife (dated Sunday, September 23, 1900) Carroll stated that<lb/>
&ldquo;Agramonte left for New York yesterday with his wife&rdquo;, (presumably Saturday,<lb/>
September 22). Could Agramonte have left Havana on Saturday the 22nd even though<lb/>
his personal report dates his leave as from Monday the 24th? Note that S. O.<lb/>
164 is dated September 21.</item>
<item><p>4. Note Agramonte's letter to Mrs. Lazear, July 15, 1930. The<lb/>
letter is curious on several counts. There again, as he did in his Popular<lb/>
Science article (1915) (page 224) he implies, indeed he practically states,<lb/>
that he was in Havana if not actually at Lazear's bedside when he died on<lb/>
September 25, yet we know he wasn't even in Havana!</p>
<p>Equally curious is his error in paragraph 4 of this letter where he<lb/>
mentions the bronze busts in the little park facing the Sanitary Department.<lb/>
He states &ldquo;Reed and Carroll are also equally represented.&rdquo; This is quite wrong.<lb/>
I have photos of all these busts, (I showed you a photo). They are of Guiteras,<lb/>
Delgado, Lazear and Gorgas, two on either side of the monument to Finlay.<lb/>
And Agramonte certainly knew that Reed and Carroll were not represented, because<lb/>
(according to Miss Agramonte to me), it was only through Agramonte's inter-<lb/>
vention that even Lazier was included. He was included because he was the<lb/>
Martyr, but all other United States Commissioners were excluded.</p>
<p>The explanation probably is that when Agramonte wrote the letter<lb/>
July 15, 1930, he hadn't seen the busts for some time and had simply for-<lb/>
gotten who were represented (I don't recall what year the busts were erected,<lb/>
I have it written down somewhere).</p>
<p>The third notable feature of this letter is the evidence that<lb/>
Agramonte was at last (?) publicly showing a little jealousy or annoyance by<lb/>
criticizing openly the expressions, &ldquo;Reed Board&rdquo;, etc.</p></item>
<item>5. Agramonte's November, 1930 article is certainly misleading and<lb/>
not immodest! Note my marginal notes.</item>
<item>6. See Agramonte's letters of April 17, 1899 and of June 17, 1899<lb/>
to Sternberg. Agramonte was then only interested in the bacterial theory.</item>
<pb n="3" id="f06413170"/>
<item>General Albert E. Truby</item>
<item>-3-</item>
<item>January 9, 1948</item>
<item>7. See Memo of December 29, 1899, from Assistant S. G. to Agramonte.<lb/>
Why was Agramonte's contract almost annulled so often?</item>
<item>8. For several strong reasons, I believe the formation of the Y. F.<lb/>
Board was a sudden decision by Sternberg. Reed's letters to L. O. Howard<lb/>
indicated that Reed expected quite another trip. Also, Hagedorn in his Biography<lb/>
of Leonard Wood states (page 281, Vol. 1; Harper 1931) that Wood, worried about<lb/>
Y. F. in Havana, &ldquo;urged Sternberg to appoint a special Scientific Commission to<lb/>
study the problem of the origin of yellow fever&rdquo;. Hagedorn refers to a book by<lb/>
Eric Fisher Wood (Leonard Wood, Conservation of Americanism), publisher and date<lb/>
not given. See memorandum from S. G. to Agramonte May 14, 1900 (B 849-852<lb/>
marked on the back).</item>
<item><p><hi>Carroll Data</hi></p>
<p>9. Note the letter of August 16, 1906 to Carroll (from Kean ?),<lb/>
(B 1073-1082). Presumably, the S. G. considered Carroll more &ldquo;prominent and<lb/>
meritorious&rdquo; than Agramonte. See especially page 3 of Carroll's letter of August<lb/>
18, 1906 to the S. G. regarding Carroll's &ldquo;written evidence&rdquo; to show that<lb/>
Reed left Agramonte in ignorance by specific direction. Difficult to believe.<lb/>
Why would he? I've never seen the evidence. (Please return this one item also<lb/>
before February 1).</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Godfrey Data</hi></p>
<p>10. Note the interesting roster of Y. F. patients at Pinar Del Rio.<lb/>
I'm going to find out more about the prisoner, Arthur Hackins, who unwitt-<lb/>
ingly helped so much by dying. I'm curious to know what kind of a soldier he<lb/>
had been, why he was in prison, etc. Will write A. G. O. for data.</p></item>
<item>11. Note the S. G. O. (AGO record of Godfrey for 1900. On June 30,<lb/>
he was reprimanded by Stark. In entry of October 16, it states that on October<lb/>
25, 1900 Godfrey was commended by Gorgas. Was Godfrey a &ldquo;devil&rdquo; in August, a<lb/>
fine person in October 1900 and a hero in May, 1904 (<unclear>see</unclear> G. O. 7 Denver, Colo.,<lb/>
May 2, 1904)? Of course he could have been &ldquo;stupid&rdquo; one time (when he made a<lb/>
mistake) and later done good work for Gorgas, but the two periods seem to<lb/>
overlap.</item>
<item><p><hi>Gorgas Data</hi></p>
<p>12. See Gorgas to Assistant A G, August 29, 1900. Were the red<lb/>
flags over used? (A 43-44).</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Kean Data</hi></p>
<p>13. General Kean's paper (lecture) on &ldquo;Sanitary Work in Cuba -<lb/>
First Intervention&rdquo; is very interesting.</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Lazier Data</hi></p>
<p>14. Why did General Kean's wire of September 24, 1900 go direct to<lb/>
the S. G. and not &ldquo;through channels&rdquo;? (B-103). Perhaps Sternberg's wire to<lb/>
Kean (September 24, 1900 - B 1033) really comes ahead of B 103 which is Kean's<lb/>
direct answer to Sternberg. I think that is the explanation.</p></item>
<item><p><hi><del>Baldwin's</del></hi></p>
<p>15. Note how tardily Baldwin's wire to A. G.; Wash., was sent and<lb/>
received, September 26, 12:15 P.M.</p></item>
<pb n="4" id="f06413171"/>
<item>General Albert E. Truby</item>
<item>-4-</item>
<item>January 9, 1948</item>
<item><p><hi><del>Baldwin's</del></hi></p>
<p>16. Note Sternberg's letter, January 21, 1901 to Louderslager in<lb/>
which Sternberg credited Lazear's death to &ldquo;<hi><unclear>pa</unclear> experiment</hi>&rdquo;. Do you suppose<lb/>
by then, Sternberg had heard the &ldquo;secret dope&rdquo; from Reed?</p></item>
<item><p><hi>Reed Data</hi></p>
<p>17. See Sternberg's memorandum of May 23, 1900 to the A. G. creating<lb/>
the Y. F. Board. I wonder why the words, &ldquo;and especially yellow fever&rdquo; were<lb/>
&ldquo;stricken from the S O at the request of Mr. Jones, C. Clerk&rdquo;? (so as not to<lb/>
scare the home folks or to insult the Cubans?).</p></item>
<item>18. Note Sternberg's wire to Reed October 23, 1900. That is why<lb/>
Reed's Indianapolis paper (Preliminary Report) had practically no newspaper<lb/>
publicity, although other ordinary papers were well reported in the<lb/>
Indianapolis and other papers.</item>
<item><p><hi>Truby Data</hi></p>
<p>19. I did not look up your personal file. I merely noted these<lb/>
random special orders.</p></item>
<item><p>&ldquo;<hi>National Archives File</hi>&rdquo; (in <hi>calendar sequence</hi>)</p>
<p>20. You will find the &ldquo;Round Robin&rdquo; from Shafter and others which<lb/>
upset Alger so much, because it was made public in Cuba before Alger received<lb/>
it.</p></item>
<item>21. Note the argument (letters of June 10, 1900) (c 335-338), over<lb/>
the little railroad bridge to the &ldquo;Y F wards&rdquo;.</item>
<item>22. The Russell incident is curious (July 20, 1900 et Seq.)</item>
<item>23. Note Baldwin's letter of August 20, 1900 to A C; note regarding<lb/>
bridge across R.R. track (c 366-377).</item>
<item>24. The argument between Ludlow and Ward is interesting. Do you<lb/>
recall it? (October - November 1900).</item>
<item><p><hi>Miscellaneous File</hi></p>
<p>25. See Kean's letter of June 18, 1909 to Ellis stating that<lb/>
according to Reed, Kissinger was the <hi>first volunteer to be bitten</hi>. K <hi>was</hi> the<lb/>
&ldquo;first volunteer to be bitten&rdquo;, but was he the &ldquo;first volunteer&rdquo;? This<lb/>
doesn't settle it.</p></item>
<item>26. What did Mazurri do? See S. 0. 199, August 24, 1900. Time<lb/>
recently stated (when Mazurri died) that M was the doctor who took care of<lb/>
Reed's cases. Was he ever Ames' assistant?</item>
<item>27. Note especially Sternberg's (hard-to-find) letter of instructions<lb/>
to Reed, May 29, 1900 (B 890-891)</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06413172"/>
<item>General Albert E. Truby</item>
<item>-5-</item>
<item>January 9, 1948</item>
<item><p><hi>Medical Record of Camp Columbia Post Hospital</hi></p>
<p>28. I was very disappointed to find so little herein.</p></item>
</list></p>
<p>Well here they, General Truby. How I wish we could go over these<lb/>
things together.</p>
<p>Best to Mrs. Truby.</p>
<closer>
<signed>P. S. Hench</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
