<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06413053">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, May 21, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413053</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-05-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University</name>
<name type="place">Paris (France)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-05-21">May 21, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413053</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, May 21, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran wants Kean to explain to Nogueira that there shouldn't be any hostility between Cuba and the U.S. caused by distinguishing between Finlay &ldquo;discovering&rdquo; the mosquito theory and Reed &ldquo;demonstrating&rdquo; the theory. Kean also mentions his letter to Moran about Guiteras' speech given in Havana in 1900, which gives a proper analogy for the Finlay--Reed discovery.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-05-21">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, May 21, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413053"/>
<opener>
To Col. P. S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester Minn.<lb/>
2804 N STREET, N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-05-21">21 May '47</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Colonel</salute>
</opener>
<p>You must think that I am like<lb/>
the gophers which hibernate for the<lb/>
winter and do not wake up until<lb/>
hot s<del>a</del><add>u</add>mmer comes. Well it looks<lb/>
like that with me. I had a lunch engage<lb/>
ment with my cousin Prof(Ex). Julian<lb/>
Coolidge of Harvard, Master of Sowell House<lb/>
on April 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. I had a heart attack at<lb/>
lunch. I got home &amp; tumbled <add>into bed</add>. <unclear>It</unclear> wasn't so<lb/>
very bad, but the doctor was much exer-<lb/>
cised over it and not only kept me in<lb/>
bed for several days, but confined me<lb/>
to the second floor where is my bedroom<lb/>
&amp; the bathroom. He did not wish me<lb/>
to come down stairs and be climbing<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413054"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
2<lb/>
the long flight of stairs after breakfast<lb/>
for the call of nature. As regards<lb/>
urination I have long had a blue bottle<lb/>
with a large mouth, which I can use<lb/>
in my study, and empty in the kitchen<lb/>
sink next door. Well I felt quite helpless<lb/>
up there, with all my books and papers<lb/>
and letters down on the first floor.<lb/>
So my correspondence was a perfect<lb/>
mess when last Tuesday the doctor<lb/>
said that my heart was about as<lb/>
it was before and if I would be pru-<lb/>
dent he would discharge me as a<lb/>
patient. But he appointed Cornelia to<lb/>
be my Gromyko with a veto power.<lb/>
So I am not yet a free man. You<lb/>
see that an old retired lame duck<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06413055"/>
3<lb/>
like me has to do just one thing; to earn<lb/>
his &frac34; pay (no allowances, so it is really &frac12; pay<lb/>
like the English Army) and that one thing<lb/>
is to keep alive. So when my friends say<lb/>
&ldquo;Well good-by old man take good care<lb/>
of yourself&rdquo; I reply &ldquo;That is my only<lb/>
job in life - to live, and draw my pay,<lb/>
and distribute it to my dependents&rdquo;.<lb/>
Well I am now cleaning my desk and<lb/>
answering letters, and I cannot dash<lb/>
off letters as you can. If I turn my<lb/>
pen loose no one would ever read it<lb/>
and I would leave out words and<lb/>
misspell others, and my friends who<lb/>
are accustomed to typed letters would<lb/>
not bother to read them. So I write<lb/>
slowly and try to make my letters<lb/>
legible. Now see here are three pages and<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06413056"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
(4)<lb/>
all about myself!</p>
<p>I was immensely interested in your fine<lb/>
letter to Moran and to hear that he<lb/>
has written, or is writing, his autobiogra-<lb/>
phy. What you say about it is very<lb/>
clever and, I doubt not, very true that<lb/>
it will not conflict with yours. NONE<lb/>
will conflict with your <hi>Magnum Opus</hi><lb/>
and I am so pleased to have you<lb/>
speak of it as if you had put pen to<lb/>
paper on it. <hi>C'est la premiere pas qui<lb/>
coute</hi> - &ldquo;Well begun is half done&rdquo;.<lb/>
If I can hold the printed volume of it<lb/>
in my hand, I will be willing to say<lb/>
&ldquo;Now Lord let thy servant depart in peace&rdquo;.<lb/>
I had a nice note from Moran, being a<lb/>
letter of introduction of Dr. Pedro Nagu-<lb/>
-era, who brought it with him from Cuba.<lb/>
He had the Pan American where I think<lb/>
he was staying call me up to make an<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06413057"/>
5<lb/>
2804 N STREET, N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
an appointment, but Mrs. Kean who<lb/>
answered the phone replied that I<lb/>
was sick and not able to see him.<lb/>
So he mailed the letter to me, with a<lb/>
polite letter of regret. I have not writ-<lb/>
ten to Moran but will try to do so<lb/>
today. Moran wanted me to explain to<lb/>
him that I saw no reason for dispute<lb/>
between Cubans and US. Citizens as to<lb/>
the respective credit of Finlay and<lb/>
Reed: that I always spoke of Finlay as<lb/>
the <hi>Discoverer</hi> of mosquito transmission<lb/>
of Yellow Fever and Reed as the <hi>Demon-<lb/>
strator</hi>, who with his laboratory training at<lb/>
Johns Hopkins and his superior facilities<lb/>
was able to make Finlays' discovery at<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06413058"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
6<lb/>
(April 12, 1939. was the date of my letter)<lb/>
once accepted by the medical profession.</p>
<p>I wrote Moran once my account of the<lb/>
dinner given by the doctors of Havana<lb/>
to celebrate the triumphant demonstra-<lb/>
tion by Reed of Finlay's theory and<lb/>
the beautiful speech of Dr. Juan Gui-<lb/>
teras in which he compared Finlay's<lb/>
work to that of Manson with reference<lb/>
to the transmission of malaria and<lb/>
that of Reed to Ross's demonstration<lb/>
of the malarial agent in the anopheles mos-<lb/>
quito. This dinner was given on Dec. 22<lb/>
1900. Dr Finlay and Major Reed seemed<lb/>
quite satisfied with the point of view<lb/>
of Dr. Guiteras who made the principal<lb/>
address and was as I recollect the &lsquo;Master<lb/>
of the Feast&rsquo;. What was my amazement<lb/>
when I read in the biography of Dr Finlay<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06413059"/>
7<lb/>
2804 N STREET, N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
written in French by Dr. Francisco Dominiguez<lb/>
and printed in Paris, a quite full<lb/>
account of this dinner in which he says<lb/>
that <hi>he</hi> Dr. Dominguez got up the dinner<lb/>
at the request of the Military Governor, Gen.<lb/>
Leonard Wood! It is amusing that he does<lb/>
not mention Dr Guiteras's speech or my<lb/>
being there, altho. I was at that time the acting<lb/>
Chief Surgeon of Cuba and, as I recollect it,<lb/>
sat by Dr. Finlay. Also I do not recollect<lb/>
Dr Dominguez' being there. I think Moran<lb/>
wanted me to tell this story of my recollect<lb/>
of the dinner to Dr. Pedro Nogueira and<lb/>
I would have liked to do so. But Moran<lb/>
has my letter written April 12, 1939 that<lb/>
he can show Dr. Noguera if he wants to.<lb/>
But it reads like a different dinner from<lb/>
that which Dr Dominguez describes, and<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06413060"/>
8<lb/>
he would probably believe the fluent<lb/>
convincing French of Dr. Dominguez who<lb/>
was a member of the French Academy of<lb/>
Medicine. He almost convinced me that I<lb/>
had a pipe dream. He sent me his<lb/>
book in 1941 two years after I wrote to Moran<lb/>
I think you told me that you had the book,<lb/>
perhaps I gave it to you as I do not<lb/>
find it here in my den. I hope I did-<lb/>
Dr. D. is now dead, as are all the men<lb/>
who I recollect as being at that dinner:<lb/>
Reed &amp; his two assistants Finlay, Guetiras, Gorgas<lb/>
Gen. Wood and Dominguez whom I did not<lb/>
recall. Well this is a long letter and<lb/>
I must stop and get busy. Mrs Kean is<lb/>
sick in bed &amp; the Dr. thinks it is nerves &amp;<lb/>
worry and she must have a rest and stop<lb/>
worrying. If I had only a few drops<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f06413061"/>
9<lb/>
of 'that nepenthes which the wife of Thone<lb/>
in Egypt gave to Jove-born Helena&rdquo;<lb/>
but I fear it is not known to modern<lb/>
medicine. To go back to our question<lb/>
I fear our American medical writers are<lb/>
not free from blame. I have a book<lb/>
on Practice of Medicine by John H. Musser<lb/>
Professor of Internal Medicine at Tulane<lb/>
Univ in New Orleans <add>which</add> gives 36 lines to<lb/>
the History of Yellow Fever and <hi>does not men-<lb/>
tion Finlay</hi>, altho he mentions every one<lb/>
else. His book was printed in 1932 by Lea<lb/>
&amp; Febiger, Phila. My guess would be that he is<lb/>
a son of the Phila. Musser of a former generation</p>
<closer>
<salute>With cordial regards yours</salute>
<signed>J.R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
