<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413281">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Albert E. Truby, November 19, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413281</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Michie, Robert E. Lee</name>
<name type="person">Edmunds, Maj.</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-11-19">November 19, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413281</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Albert E. Truby, November 19, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean has attempted to identify the persons in the photographs from Truby, some of whom he describes. Kean discusses his large accumulation of personal papers and books, which will be deposited at the University of Virginia after his death. Kean describes his recent illness and its effects. He lists new members of the Walter Reed Memorial Association, and expresses his apprehension that Hench might not finish his yellow fever magnum opus.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-11-19">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Albert E. Truby, November 19, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413281"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2804 N STREET N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1948-11-19">Nov. 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> '48</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Truby</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your air mail letter of<lb/>
Oct. 17 came on the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and the pic-<lb/>
tures of Cuba came somewhat later-<lb/>
There seemed to be no special hurry<lb/>
about them, as Dr Hench was in Europe<lb/>
so I have let them lie around while<lb/>
I looked intermittently for a bundle<lb/>
of photos and papers concerning the<lb/>
7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> army Corps which I had stuck<lb/>
away some where- They would help<lb/>
out the identification of the members<lb/>
in the photo of Gen Fitzhugh Lee and his<lb/>
Staff- I have not yet been able to give<lb/>
the names of all, but think I could if I<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413282"/>
could find a photo like that<lb/>
which I think had the names on the<lb/>
back- But I have not yet found it.<lb/>
I have only one letter-filing case in<lb/>
my den and it will not hold a 1/3<lb/>
of the papers and letters which I have<lb/>
accumulated in my long and somewhat<lb/>
eventful career. The overflow are in<lb/>
cartons and bundles stuck in here and<lb/>
there in my small den I did have<lb/>
a chestful down stairs but that has<lb/>
been invaded and policed. I feel sure<lb/>
that Dr. Hench has every <add>thing</add> pertaining to<lb/>
Walter Reed &amp; Yellow Fever, and the rest<lb/>
await the inevitable day when my ashes<lb/>
will go to the Monticello Graveyard, and<lb/>
there will be a grand house cleaning-<lb/>
I think that Cornelia and my son<lb/>
Robert will send what looks of value<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06413283"/>
to the admirable Library at the Univ. of Va-<lb/>
which has been most friendly in offer-<lb/>
ing house room to my books and papers<lb/>
with the understanding, which I from time<lb/>
to time repeat, that they are requested to<lb/>
burn what they do not want.</p>
<p>Well to go back to the pictures, Cornelia<lb/>
said they had to go on to Dr. Hench as<lb/>
she was afraid something might happen<lb/>
to them, and she kindly offered to<lb/>
pack them up and ship them by express<lb/>
to Rochester Minn. if I would note on the<lb/>
separate envelope what I had to say-<lb/>
II stated that most of the faces were<lb/>
familiar but I could only attach the<lb/>
proper names to about half of them and<lb/>
made guesses of the rest, all but three-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06413284"/>
C2<lb/>
B5<lb/>
I had a good chuckle at your naming<lb/>
no 1. on the left as <hi>Kean</hi>: The face had a<lb/>
certain resemblance to me, but I never<lb/>
had that much stomach in my life, and<lb/>
besides, his legs were straight and I had<lb/>
a shortened left leg with a crooked knee<lb/>
since 1891- Besides I was not in the pic-<lb/>
ture, or on Gen. Lee's staff at that time.<lb/>
I looked up in my diary which sustained<lb/>
my memory, and gave me the dates-<lb/>
Lt, Col Louis M. Maus was the chief Surgeon<lb/>
and was there as big as life as no.3 I think-<lb/>
I have not the photo infront of me as it<lb/>
it packed and awaiting shipment by<lb/>
express- I came to Cuba in Dec. 1898 as<lb/>
Chief Surgeon of Gen. Keifer's 1<hi rend="superscript"><unclear>st</unclear></hi> Division<lb/>
VII A. C. But Maus was on the skids and<lb/>
was <del>mustered</del> relieved on Feb. 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 99. I succeeded<lb/>
him and became Chief Surgeon of the VII A. C.<lb/>
on 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb <unclear>'99</unclear> 2 or atmost 3 weeks after the photo. was<lb/>
taken-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06413285"/>
J. R. K. to A. E. T- sheet 2-</p>
<p>nov 19, 1948</p>
<p>5</p>
<p>2804 N STREET N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.</p>
<p>The date on the photo is Jan. 2/ the rest of<lb/>
the date being torn off, but I think it was<lb/>
twenty something- The figure 1. which you<lb/>
thought was me was a Vol. Med. Major<lb/>
named Fowler, from New York, who had<lb/>
come to Jacksonville and reported to Gen<lb/>
Lee- He was a good surgeon, and Gen Lee<lb/>
attacked him to the Staff, I suppose tempo-<lb/>
rarily, until a good vacancy presented<lb/>
itself for him- He was a Major &amp; <hi>Chief</hi><lb/>
Surgeon, and was not so easy to locate as<lb/>
the Chief Surgeons of Divisions were all of<lb/>
the Regular Med. Corps- (or Dept as it was<lb/>
then-) The Lt. Col on Gen. Lee's left was O. E.<lb/>
Wood Chief Commissary- You gave him some<lb/>
other name- He and his wife were in the<lb/>
mess with the Lees in 1900 in Marianao, but<lb/>
neither Gen Lee nor I had much use for him-<lb/>
When the staff attended one of the funerals of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06413286"/>
6<lb/>
a yellow fever victim, an officer, altho we<lb/>
were mounted, he could not attend for<lb/>
fear of catching it! Cornelia knew some<lb/>
of the staff- She came down as Miss <unclear>Knox</unclear><lb/>
to visit the Michies and Slocums who lived<lb/>
together in a fine house on the Calsada Real<lb/>
near the little plaza in front of the Toledo<lb/>
Casa where was Gen Lee's Hdqrs- I could<lb/>
not recognize <add>major</add> Edmonds who died of y. f.<lb/>
and from whom I think I got my case-<lb/>
But Major Michie and the Gen's two aides<lb/>
Lieuts Fitz Lee and <unclear>Sartoris</unclear>, and several<lb/>
others, Major Russell Harrison among them, I<lb/>
could identify readily- My memory for<lb/>
names has deteriorated since my 6 weeks<lb/>
illness at Walter Reed Hospital in the<lb/>
spring- I did not have a stroke, but had<lb/>
a congestion of the brain from suddenly<lb/>
increased blood pressure- After a week<lb/>
of treatment it came back practically to<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06413287"/>
normal but did some damage as I<lb/>
cannot remember names as well, even<lb/>
the names of familiar flowers- one day<lb/>
I can remember them and the next day<lb/>
I cannot- I had a postal from<lb/>
Dr. Hench this a. m. from Hamberg, Germany<lb/>
He said that Mrs Hench was going<lb/>
to Paris and then home- He has a<lb/>
job of inspections <add>in Germany</add> which will take<lb/>
him 2 to 3 weeks &amp; then he will return<lb/>
It was dated Nov. 14. so he will see<lb/>
starting home about Dec. 1<hi rend="superscript"><unclear>st</unclear></hi> I hope<lb/>
that he has had some rest while<lb/>
abroad- I am in constant fear that<lb/>
he will break down before he gets his<lb/>
<hi>magnum opus</hi> written- We had a<lb/>
good meeting of the Walter Reed memo<lb/>
<unclear>Assn</unclear>-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06413288"/>
C2<lb/>
B5<lb/>
last Monday- We elected Dr. <unclear>Soper</unclear> a<lb/>
member to replace Admiral Still who<lb/>
died last week, after a long illness-<lb/>
Dr. <unclear>Soper</unclear> is Director of the Pan Amer. San.<lb/>
Bureau and you will recall him as the<lb/>
Chairman who introduced the speakers<lb/>
at the meeting of May 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>- Col. Liles<lb/>
nominated him- Surg. Gen Bliss was<lb/>
also elected as an <hi>ex officio</hi>-member-increasing<lb/>
the number of members from 11 to 12-<lb/>
Gen. Ireland was not able to attend-<lb/>
I think now he cannot walk alone<lb/>
He has steel splints on both legs now.<lb/>
Our little part time maid is about<lb/>
to go so I must close, to get this<lb/>
in the mail- The bundle of pictures<lb/>
by express-<lb/>
went off an hour ago. Dr. Hench wanted<lb/>
them to got by registered mail, but<lb/>
that is very inconvenient for us-</p>
<p>Affectionate regards to your Bormie - &amp; your self</p>
<p>J. R. Kean</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
