<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413007">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, January 20, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413007</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-01-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lambert, Gustaf E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Carlisle Barracks (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Manila (Philippines)</name>
<name type="hospital">Camp Columbia Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Second Division Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-01-20">January 20, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413007</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, January 20, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench attempts to resolve the differences of memory between the yellow fever experiment survivors. The number of buildings in the yellow fever section is in question and the camp's exact location is unclear.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-01-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Gustaf E. Lambert, January 20, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413007"/>
<p>loaned<lb/>
1899 map<lb/>
1899 map - <unclear>survey 1901</unclear><lb/>
Yldefonso model - 4 photos<lb/>
1907 map<lb/>
Copy <unclear>sent to</unclear><lb/>
Kean &amp; Truby<lb/>
<date value="1947-01-20">January 20, 1947</date>
Mr. Gust Lambert<lb/>
8009 Avalon Avenue<lb/>
Chicago 19, Illinois<lb/>
My dear Mr. Lambert:</p>
<p>I wish to thank you very much indeed for your letter which I received<lb/>
January 9, 1947 with your comments and corrections of the interview that we<lb/>
had here June 21, 1946. I should have sent you long ago a copy of the interview<lb/>
to correct but was too busy to do so. I agree with you that some of the mistakes<lb/>
in the typed copy of our interview were clerical and did not represent exactly<lb/>
what you said. I am very glad to have the corrections. I appreciate it very<lb/>
much. The next time I send you a lot of questions I wish that you would hire<lb/>
someone to typewrite your answers and let me pay the expense--that would save<lb/>
you time and trouble, especially in view of your failing eyesight.</p>
<p>In your letter received January 9th you stated that I had not returned<lb/>
to you Andrus' letter to Lewis and Sheppard. That was an oversight on my part<lb/>
and I now return the letter to Lewis and one to Representative McLean. I think<lb/>
you must have meant that one as I have none to Senator Sheppard. I am absolutely<lb/>
sure of that as I have looked over everything I have.</p>
<p>Since receiving your corrections, I have spent a good deal of time<lb/>
trying to solve certain differences of opinion between you and others--chiefly<lb/>
of the number of little huts in the yellow fever section, who was in these huts,<lb/>
et cetera. I have written out quite a memorandum for General Truby as we have<lb/>
been discussing the same questions and I am enclosing a copy of part of that<lb/>
memorandum. My old maps of Camp Columbia, even the 1899 and 1900 maps, distinctly<lb/>
show eight little buildings just across the railroad track. Also the Yldefonso<lb/>
model of Camp Columbia, made in 1900 by one of the men at the Camp hospital<lb/>
and fastened securely to a wooden base and later exhibited in the Carlisle<lb/>
Barracks, this model also shows eight little buildings. If you will use a<lb/>
hand lens you will see that the little buildings in the model resemble very<lb/>
closely the buildings in the photograph which I found in the scrapbook of<lb/>
Mrs. Walter Reed. Also in reviewing some data which I got from the National<lb/>
Archives I came across the records of Camp Columbia Hospital, beginning when<lb/>
it was the Second Division Hospital, and the first entry indicates that there<lb/>
were in 1899 already constructed &ldquo;four little buildings in the yellow fever<lb/>
section&rdquo; and <del>there were under construction</del> also &ldquo;four little buildings in the<lb/>
small pox section.&rdquo; Since this is specifically mentioned and since the maps<lb/>
of 1899 and 1900, which I enclose, all contain eight buildings I must conclude<lb/>
that there actually were eight. It is possible that only four were used for<lb/>
wards and the other four were used for other purposes--or not used while you<lb/>
were there. Were the four yellow fever buildings sufficiently separated from<lb/>
the other four little buildings so that in discussing the matter you have dis-<lb/>
regarded them?</p>
<p>Another point--according to your description and diagram the four<lb/>
little buildings more or less faced each other; that is the first two buildings<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413008"/>
-2-<lb/>
across the railroad track faced west, the next two buildings faced east. You<lb/>
will see that they all face west in the Reed scrapbook photograph or in the<lb/>
Yldefonso model. I enclose pictures. The pictures of the Yldefonso model<lb/>
which I enclose were taken after the little buildings were taken off their<lb/>
permanent base and set up on the grounds of Carlisle Barracks but the relative<lb/>
position and direction of the buildings was not changed as I have photographs<lb/>
of the original model as was fastened down on the baseboard.</p>
<p>I would appreciate greatly your thoughtful review of the comments<lb/>
that I enclose.</p>
<p>In my previous letter I did not accept your statement that Ames<lb/>
became a major. I was told specifically that he was never commissioned in the<lb/>
regular army. That is true. But you also are correct. I have a copy of Ames'<lb/>
military record from the A. G. O. It states &ldquo;Ames' contract was annulled on<lb/>
his acceptance on April 26, 1901 of an appointment of Captain and Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon of Volunteers---. He was appointed Major and Surgeon of Volunteers<lb/>
January 6, 1902 and was ordered to Manila.&rdquo; You were right, therefore, in<lb/>
saying that he became a commissioned officer; however, this note to my mind<lb/>
definitely indicates why Ames was transferred from Columbia Barracks to Pirotechnia,<lb/>
not as punishment as you thought, but because, being commissioned, he was then<lb/>
given a more responsible and more military assignment.</p>
<p>I have further looked up the records which indicate that General Kean<lb/>
had nothing whatever to do with the transfer of yourself or Doctor Ames. When<lb/>
these transfers occurred Major Kean had ceased to be Chief Surgeon. General<lb/>
Lee's department was abolished about November 15, 1900 and <add><unclear>Kean</unclear></add> he was on duty on<lb/>
General Wood's Staff May, 1901. You must believe me when I say that he had<lb/>
nothing to do with the transfer of Ames or yourself.</p>
<p>I understood from you and from your correspondence with Doctor Brumby<lb/>
that special order No. 83 had just recently been discovered. As a matter of<lb/>
fact, in reviewing my file on Doctor Ames I find that Mrs. Ames has long had<lb/>
that special order No. 83. I have so much material that I can't keep it all<lb/>
in my head at one time but around 1940 Mrs. Ames loaned me some material and<lb/>
I find at that time she had special order No. 83.</p>
<p>I enclose various maps and photographs to show the indications that<lb/>
there were at first, between 1899 and 1902, eight little huts across the rail-<lb/>
road track. In the 1907 map (enclosed) only five are marked as being present.<lb/>
Please note that on the 1899 map the two western most little buildings are<lb/>
labeled &ldquo;kitchen.&rdquo; They may have been used for that purpose by the Second<lb/>
Division Hospital. Incidentally, will you please tell me from whence you got<lb/>
your food--the food for yourself and the food for your patients when they were<lb/>
convalescing? Was it cooked in the post hospital and brought to you or did<lb/>
you prepare it in one of the little buildings? Being under quarantine I don't<lb/>
imagine you went to a mess. I realize that during the first few days of your<lb/>
patients' illness they received practically no food, but later, while they were<lb/>
getting better--when their fever had disappeared but before they were ready<lb/>
for convalescent discharge, didn't they receive some food? If so, where was<lb/>
it prepared?</p>
<p>Very sincerely,<lb/>
P. S. Hench, M. D.<lb/>
PSH:alp<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06413009"/>
<hi>Lambert</hi><lb/>
1 <unclear>Thank</unclear> - <unclear>you gifts sent out</unclear> at my expense?<lb/>
2 Return Andrus letter to Senator <unclear>Jean</unclear> and <unclear>Congressman M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Lean<lb/>
now</unclear> from him to Gen Sheppard.<lb/>
3 <unclear>[?] corrected my</unclear> copies our interviews. <unclear>Delegated to</unclear> have the correction<lb/>
4) <unclear>Re</unclear> <del><unclear>halt sec</unclear></del> number huts - see maps &amp; <unclear>comments <add>Are you disregarding</add></unclear><lb/>
<add>&amp; other <unclear>nearly</unclear></add><lb/>
<add><unclear>not want</unclear> for <unclear>yf</unclear>?</add><lb/>
6) <unclear>Re</unclear> who was in huts see comments Was he on duty between __&amp;__.<lb/>
5) <unclear>Re direction</unclear> huts found (The drawings - <unclear></unclear>) see <unclear>Yldefonso</unclear> model<lb/>
<unclear>Justine to board<lb/>
when get it Kean of</unclear><lb/>
1900 &amp; Reed scrapbook photo<lb/>
7. <unclear>Correction on</unclear> Ames <unclear>as major. Reason</unclear> for his <unclear>transfer</unclear><lb/>
8. <unclear>Mrs Ames for long had so 83. comments</unclear> of Kean &amp; Truby<lb/>
9. <unclear>When you <add>&amp; Ames</add> transferred</unclear> Kean no longer Chief Surgeon <unclear>at for Bldg Cent<lb/>
K ceased to be Chief S, when Gen Kean self abolished about</unclear> Nov 15, 1900 &amp; was<lb/>
<unclear>was done torn on</unclear> staff Gen Ward.<lb/>
<unclear>on date or Gen Wards staff</unclear> May 1901<lb/>
1.<lb/>
add</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
