<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-02-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="hospital">University of Virginia Hospital, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-02-05">February 5, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413025</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean comments on an interview with Reed's children. He explains the reasons Reed obtained two medical degrees after his graduation from the University of Virginia.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-02-05">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, February 5, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413025"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2804 N St. n w<lb/>
Washington 7 D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1947-02-05">5 Feb.'47</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Col. Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your interview with Gen Lawrence Reed and<lb/>
Blossom came yesterday and I have read it<lb/>
carefully- There isnt much in that we didn't know<lb/>
before- I was glad to read it however-<lb/>
I have the following comments to make-<lb/>
The answers to Q20 and Q21 are quite imaginary and<lb/>
incorrect, as the matter of Reed's prospective promotion<lb/>
at the time of his death was I think never given out<lb/>
officially, but was well known and is clearly in my<lb/>
memory- I think you know by this time that I rarely<lb/>
speak positively unless I am sure of the facts-</p>
<p>I had just prepared the Surgeon General's data for the<lb/>
Annual Report of the Secy of War and I knew that<lb/>
the Secy had recommended to the President the pro-<lb/>
motion of Reed to be Colonel and Gorgas to be Lieut<lb/>
Colonel additional to the roster- I told this to Reed<lb/>
on his death bed and his reply was &ldquo;I do not care<lb/>
for that now&rdquo;- I told Dr. Kelly of this when he was writing<lb/>
the first Ed. of his Life of Reed, and he said very<lb/>
prettily that it was the reply of <unclear>Lancelot</unclear> in Tenny son<lb/>
&ldquo;Prize me no prizes for my prize is death&rdquo;-</p>
<p>The recommendation was in print at the time of Reeds<lb/>
death but no action was taken on it. It never went<lb/>
to a congressional committee and there was no post<lb/>
humous promotion- A little later Gorgas's chum a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413026"/>
2<lb/>
retired Naval Officer named Ross came to see me in the<lb/>
S. G. O. and proposed that as Reed was dead Gorgas<lb/>
should be proposed for the Colonelcy instead of the Lieut.<lb/>
<unclear>Colonelcy.</unclear> I said I will speak to the Surgeon General about<lb/>
it and see if he will recommend it- I did so and it seemed<lb/>
reasonable, and Gen. O'Reilly made the recommendation-<lb/>
The Secretary agreed and it was done- So Gorgas got<lb/>
the reward, as was the rule of the Fates that Reed should<lb/>
saw and Gorgas should reap the harvest-</p>
<p><hi>Q22</hi> why did Reed go after two medical degrees after his<lb/>
graduation at Univ. Va?</p>
<p>A. The course of instruction at the Univ. Va was at that<lb/>
time, and when I graduated there, purely from books<lb/>
and lectures- There was no clinical instruction and<lb/>
we usually went to New York or another big city to<lb/>
get that- It was easy to get his second degree while<lb/>
getting his hospital experience and probably was a<lb/>
help in getting clinical opportunities- Now there is<lb/>
a large Hospital at the Univ. Va and they do not have<lb/>
to go elsewhere to get clinical instruction-</p>
<p>Q41- Blossom is probably correct if she positively states<lb/>
that Reed's apartment was on the first floor- My recollection<lb/>
was that I went up stairs to his apartment but it<lb/>
may well be that I went down stairs- I would<lb/>
advise you to take her statement about that, for it was<lb/>
to me a matter that I did mechanically- It was after<lb/>
all only a few months that we were together there-</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely Yours</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
