<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06413268">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413268</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-09-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Bonnie</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sawyer, Wilbur A.</name>
<name type="person">Phalen, James M.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-09-00">September 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413268</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby thinks that it is crucial for Hench to get access to the Wood diary and the Lazear notebook, but encourages Hench to write his book even if he cannot see these items immediately. He also understands that Hench should not let the yellow fever project get in the way of his medical research.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-09-00">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, September 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413268"/>
<opener>
The Sept. number of the Military Surgeon has just<lb/>
arrived. The Editorial by Col Phalen is on Walter Reed<lb/>
&amp; the Hall of Fame.<lb/>
Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-09-00">Sept. &sol;48</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Colonel Hench:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your much appreciated letter<lb/>
of July 17. was here when Mrs Truby<lb/>
&amp; I returned home from the East. We<lb/>
were away 3 months and had a wonderful<lb/>
time. The trip did us both a lot of good<lb/>
and I was astonished at the things I<lb/>
could do without fatigue. Besides the<lb/>
highlights of our visit in Washington &amp;<lb/>
New York, we were presented with a<lb/>
new grandaughter in Maryland and I<lb/>
made a special trip to my old home in<lb/>
Western N.Y. The sad part of that visit was<lb/>
that only a few of my old friends are<lb/>
left and those that are <add>seem</add> crippled up just<lb/>
as I am. Human flesh just is not made<lb/>
to last forever!</p>
<p>Mrs Truby &amp; I enjoyed our dinner <del>together</del><add>with you</add> at<lb/>
The Barclay Hotel. Sorry we could not have<lb/>
had a longer visit with you there. The Hall<lb/>
of Fame exercises and the people I met there,<lb/>
including many old friends, was a most interesting<lb/>
experience.</p>
<p>The Reed exercises in Washington were most<lb/>
impressive and your illustrated lecture<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413269"/>
AC<lb/>
Tr<lb/>
2.<lb/>
most carefully prepared and delivered<lb/>
You have become an expert lecturer and teacher<lb/>
and likewise you have mastered the Y.F.<lb/>
Episode. <unclear><del>[unclear]</del></unclear> I could find practically<lb/>
nothing in the whole lecture that was <add>not</add> exactly<lb/>
as I have <add>tried to</add> picture<del>d</del> it. You have visualized<lb/>
the scene in Cuba extremely well. We may<lb/>
differ on some of the moot questions, but I hope<lb/>
that when you finally, get all the material such<lb/>
as Wood's diary, Carroll's papers etc. that you<lb/>
will find my memory of these things quite<lb/>
reliable. I doubt if Finlay's diary will be<lb/>
of much help unless it contains info. re Reed's visit.</p>
<p>I quite agree with you therefore that<lb/>
it is most important to get <hi>Wood's diary</hi> and<lb/>
the <hi>Lazear note book</hi> before you publish <del>the</del><lb/>
your book. However, if time permits <add>I think</add> you<lb/>
would do well to write your manuscript, leaving<lb/>
out certain parts that will need revision. You<lb/>
already know the facts about most of the story<lb/>
and they should be recorded before you forget them.<lb/>
It might also be of help to you to let Kean, Moran<lb/>
and me check over the preliminary draft<lb/>
and make comments. That would be a great<lb/>
treat to us even if it does not help you.</p>
<p>I have not seen any published reports<lb/>
of the Reed celebration and your lecture. It<lb/>
should have been fully covered in the Military<lb/>
Surgeon but was not. I received a photo of the<lb/>
group on the stage from Gen Sawyer (photo 1376-88)<lb/>
When your letter come I wrote for no 93 but by<lb/>
that time there were none left. Can't you get<lb/>
Gen Sawyer to have a full report of the Reed exercises<lb/>
published?</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06413270"/>
<p>3.</p>
<p>But I have digressed from the main point<lb/>
in your letter of the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Of course it is<lb/>
evident to all of us that you must not let<lb/>
your great hobby take you away from the<lb/>
extremely important work you are doing on<lb/>
chronic arthritis. It is interesting to know<lb/>
that you are following up such a promising<lb/>
lead on rheumatoid arthritis and I do hope<lb/>
you are destined to feel the thrills of victory<lb/>
just as you know Walter Reed felt in Dec. 1900<lb/>
when he wrote to Mrs Reed of his successful<lb/>
discovery. I realize how important your<lb/>
work is and anything that can present the suffering<lb/>
and debility caused by those terrible rheumatic<lb/>
diseases would I think be more important than<lb/>
the Y.F. discovery of Reed's. I am still reading<lb/>
your Rheumatism Review and have found much<lb/>
in it of interest to me. I shall pass it on<lb/>
to a young medical officer at the Letterman just<lb/>
as I do all publications on medical subjects.</p>
<p>I am still getting the &ldquo;Proceedings of the<lb/>
Staff meetings of the Mayo Clinic&rdquo; which you<lb/>
so kindly sent me some yrs. ago. Too many<lb/>
of them are of no interest to me, although I have<lb/>
found many things of great interest, <del>I am</del><lb/>
I think I should stop having them sent as<lb/>
someone else would get more use out of them.<lb/>
Many thanks to you for the interesting things<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06413271"/>
AC<lb/>
Tr<lb/>
4<lb/>
I have found in them. If your secretary<lb/>
would phone the proper office &amp; have my<lb/>
name removed <add>from the mailing list</add> I will be obliged.</p>
<p>This is the hurricane season in Cuba and<lb/>
I do hope that your small &ldquo;casa&rdquo; there has<lb/>
been properly protected as promised by<lb/>
various Cubans. Everything is manana<lb/>
to them and their promises rarely<lb/>
eventualize. I did enjoy meeting Dr. Nogueira<lb/>
and was so glad <add>to find</add>that I had obtained a<lb/>
very wrong impression of him from his first<lb/>
letters to me several yrs. ago. He is quite<lb/>
up and doing for a Cuban. I feel that he<lb/>
is very definitely wrong about the location<lb/>
of the Camp Columbia Cemetery however.</p>
<p>I was sorry that Moran was not present<lb/>
for the Reed celebration. I hope he is much<lb/>
improved by this time. Hanberry looked very<lb/>
well <add>and</add> was the big drawing card of the show.</p>
<p>He was one of the men I knew very well<lb/>
and <add>he</add> did good work as a soldier. I did<lb/>
not get much information from him for my book.</p>
<p>Col. &amp; Mrs La Garde enjoyed meeting you at<lb/>
the Reed's dinner and were greatly impressed<lb/>
by your lecture.</p>
<p>I have been real busy since my<lb/>
return and hence this belated reply to your<lb/>
good letter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With all good wishes for you &amp; Mrs Hench<lb/>
Very Sincerely yours</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
