<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413034">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413034</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-03-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-03-03">March 3, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413034</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby reviews yellow fever material. He is uncertain about the location of Reed's hospital room and is unsure how often he visited Reed in his final days. He refers Hench to Kean's diary. He identifies persons in the picture and encourages Hench to begin writing his book on Reed and yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-03-03">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, March 3, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413034"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, 18, Calif.<lb/>
<date value="1947-03-03">March 3, 1947</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Colonel Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Well, all of your wonderful pile of material was sent on<lb/>
March 1st by Express, together with my answers. The whole thing<lb/>
has been thoroughly enjoyed but it has been almost too much in a<lb/>
bunch for me to do good work and not get excited. Nothing really<lb/>
worried me except the huts. That is a mess and you saved the day<lb/>
by producing that really precious photograph of the huts. That, I<lb/>
think, really solves everything pretty well. Whoever took that<lb/>
picture must have done it in 1900, and because he took a special<lb/>
picture of 118 and 116, I think he knew that those had been the<lb/>
huts where <hi>Lazear</hi> and Carroll had been treated. I underscore<lb/>
Lazear as I really think he had the martyr in mind and so 118 was<lb/>
in the center of the field.</p>
<p>The only other thing of real importance is about Reed's<lb/>
early knowledge of Carter's paper and his interest in Finlay's theory.<lb/>
You have had Lazear in your mind as the leader in the mosquito work<lb/>
from the start but I have never agreed with you in that. I think my<lb/>
arguments are sound and I believe General Kean will agree. You may<lb/>
still find letters of Carter's or Reed's on that subject.</p>
<p>Many of the <del>e</del>questions you asked I have answered before but<lb/>
I think my answers will not be very different. The location of Reed's<lb/>
room in the hospital is an example. I have tried to get everything as<lb/>
near right as possible. While the general situation is quite clear<lb/>
about most things, details won't come to the surface. While Reed was<lb/>
sick, for instance, I may have been with him more than one night.<lb/>
I even may have been in his room the last night for a time, for I<lb/>
remember all the somberness of the occasion, the location of the bed<lb/>
and the window. However, I have nothing so good as Kean's diary to<lb/>
fall back on. Reed was surprised to see me at his bedside. That I<lb/>
know.</p>
<p>I have just received a letter from General Kean and it is<lb/>
the keenest and best letter he has written me in a couple of years.<lb/>
Evidently he is feeling fine and is very cheerful. He is &ldquo;saving a<lb/>
bottle of bottled-in-bond to drink to your health&rdquo; when I come to see<lb/>
him in May. He says that &ldquo;Dusty&rdquo; Siler is now coming along in fine<lb/>
style after a terrible siege. Good news.'</p>
<p>Before I forget, I want to thank you for the picture of<lb/>
Reed and his gang with the old ambulance at Camp Lazear. You know I<lb/>
think that the big fellow with a mustache between Kissinger and Cooke<lb/>
is <hi>Jernegan</hi>. The tall chap on the barrel next to Reed may be <hi>Springer</hi><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413035"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
and the tall young officer in the dinky cap may have been Kean's<lb/>
assistant, Contract Surgeon, Peter C. <hi>Field</hi>. The men in caps sitting<lb/>
on the ground are Evidintly the Spanish Volunteers, who were there<lb/>
at the close of the Camp. They are <hi>typical</hi> Spanish immigrants.<lb/>
The soldier at the right of Cooke looks like <hi>Olsen</hi>. All of those<lb/>
I have mentioned (except Dr. Field) were at the camp in January and<lb/>
February. This helps in identifying them.</p>
<p>Mrs. <unclear>Stark</unclear> might remember Jernegan- Show her that picture and see.</p>
<p>Because of the amount of work, I did not feel like asking<lb/>
for clerical help from the new C.O. at Letterman, so I did as you<lb/>
suggested. I could not work very long at one stretch. However, she<lb/>
- the steno - was very <hi>obliging and I paid her $20.</hi> I have written<lb/>
in many things that I found later. I really hunted for things that I<lb/>
knew were in that Sen. Doc. I always find something new in it. Wonder-<lb/>
ful book, full of mistakes, but it is grand. How about an index? I am<lb/>
too busy to do it!!</p>
<p>I called Mrs. Gilhus yesterday about those pictures. She<lb/>
has not been able to find them but will continue to search. I think<lb/>
they will turn up in time.</p>
<p>General Kean wrote that he thinks you have now gathered<lb/>
together all the known facts re the yellow fever story and should soon<lb/>
get to work on your magnum opus. I agree with him. He and I both<lb/>
would like to see it in print before the last note of taps fades away<lb/>
for us.</p>
<p>I am still planning to go to Washington about May 8th and<lb/>
want to stay a while with my daughter near Frederick, Md. Mrs. Truby<lb/>
and I want to be East for 2 or 3 months. I want to see you in Washington<lb/>
in June unless for some unexpected reason we should cancel our trip.</p>
<p>I liked your B<add>r</add>umby and Lambert letters but will return them<lb/>
later. Would like to know their answers first.</p>
<p>Wish you would let Kean read my typed answers. He may be<lb/>
able to add an idea here and there that would be of help.</p>
<p>I sent the papers by express as I think<lb/>
that is <unclear>sofar</unclear> and just as easy for me.</p>
<p>I will await your reaction to my effort<lb/>
with the hope that you won't feel that I<lb/>
am an obstinate old <unclear>crank</unclear>- I can't<lb/>
change my convictions-</p>
<p>With best wishes for you &amp; Mrs Hench from<lb/>
all the Trubys.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
