<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413082">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413082</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-07-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Jessie Daniel</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>9 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-07-24">July 24, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413082</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean discusses his case of yellow fever. He maintains that there is no proof Ames ever contracted yellow fever. He writes that Lazear conducted secret experiments, and discusses Moran's draft of his memoirs.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-07-24">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, July 24, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413082"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2804 N STREET, N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1947-07-24">24 July '47</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear Colonel Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>Yesterday I came across your very<lb/>
interesting letter of Feb, 19 with its equal-<lb/>
ly interesting inclosures, and read them<lb/>
over carefully- This much cluttered up<lb/>
old desk of mine is not an office of<lb/>
record and I have no copies of<lb/>
letters sent, so, tho. I remember read-<lb/>
ing you letter, I am not sure that I<lb/>
answered it- I have a small book<lb/>
in which I try to keep a record of letters<lb/>
received and sent, and I do not find<lb/>
any record of a letter to you, between Feb<lb/>
23 when it came and March 17 which<lb/>
may have been a delayed answer.<lb/>
Your letter contained photostat copies<lb/>
of the temperature chart and clinical<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413083"/>
2<lb/>
record by Lambert of my case of yellow<lb/>
fever- They let me go to my quarters<lb/>
on the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day which is in accordance<lb/>
with my recollection, for I remember<lb/>
that I was very anxious to get to my<lb/>
quarters where I could write to my<lb/>
wife and make an application for<lb/>
sick leave- I was feeling quite weak<lb/>
and &ldquo;rocky&rdquo; but was in a hurry to get<lb/>
to see her, as she was in the ninth month<lb/>
of pregnancy- In fact the baby, my son<lb/>
Robert, came on July 5- before I got to<lb/>
New York- She was with her parents in<lb/>
New Jersey- I was glad to note that<lb/>
there was nothing on the clinical history<lb/>
to indicate any excitement or carrying<lb/>
on such as Lambert has charged to me<lb/>
subsequently- I think that that, like Dr-<lb/>
Ames &ldquo;experimental attack&rdquo; of yellow fever<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06413084"/>
3<lb/>
was a subsequent secretion of what<lb/>
the french call an <hi>id&eacute;e fixe</hi> - an obsession.<lb/>
The letters of Dr. Berry are certainly<lb/>
curious- He seems to be perfectly sincere<lb/>
and honest but to have made no effort<lb/>
to find out the facts- There is no evi-<lb/>
dence that he ever read Reed's reports<lb/>
of the establishment of Camp Lazear<lb/>
and of the experimental cases- In Reeds<lb/>
Additional Note which is really the main<lb/>
Report of his Commission, he mentions<lb/>
carefully the immunes at the Camp and<lb/>
that Dr. Roger P. Ames, in charge, was<lb/>
an immune- In fact I never heard<lb/>
of Ames<unclear>'</unclear> attack of yellow fever until<lb/>
years after, when Gen. Ireland, the<lb/>
Surgeon General at the time, called me<lb/>
up on the prove and asked me if I have<lb/>
ever heard of a case of yellow fever<lb/>
that lasted only 5 days, I said no I had'nt-<lb/>
Well, he said, in &ldquo;a report of the Hospital<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06413085"/>
4<lb/>
at Columbia Bks. Ames is reported as having<lb/>
been sick with yellow fever but he was<lb/>
in hospital only 5 days-&rdquo; I laughed<lb/>
and said, Ames always claimed to be an<lb/>
immune and I never heard of his<lb/>
having yellow fever, but as he is an expert<lb/>
in that disease I guess they accepted<lb/>
his diagnosis- Neither Gen. Ireland nor<lb/>
I believe that he ever had yellow fever-<lb/>
I do not know the date of this attack of<lb/>
mild fever, It may have been while I was<lb/>
absent on sick leave- But it is certainly<lb/>
a great stretch of the imagination for Dr Berry<lb/>
to say in his letter to the Journal of the<lb/>
American Med Assn of Feb, 1 1907 &ldquo;Only<lb/>
three physicians Drs Lazear, Carroll<lb/>
<hi>and Ames</hi> allowed themselves to be<lb/>
bitten by infected mosquitoes etc.&rdquo;<lb/>
As you say Ames never stated positively<lb/>
that he was an experimental case for the<lb/>
records are against him, but the reply<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06413086"/>
5-<lb/>
2804 N STREET, N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
that Dr, Berry quotes Ames to have<lb/>
made in a letter to him is certainly<lb/>
a model of what the lawyers call<lb/>
the <hi>suggestio falsi</hi> - Mrs. Ames in her<lb/>
long talk with me when she was trying<lb/>
to have his name added to the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Roll of Honor, never made any<lb/>
such claim- It would have been a<lb/>
powerful argument, if she believed it-<lb/>
This that I have written is in response<lb/>
to your request for comment- If it<lb/>
has been made before, you will excuse<lb/>
it- What Ames meant by the &ldquo;unreported<lb/>
experimental cases&rdquo; I do not know- There<lb/>
were unreported experiments, made by<lb/>
putting infected mosquitoes on some of the<lb/>
young doctors at the Columbia Barracks Hospital<lb/>
<add>by Lazear,</add> but as this was done while Reed was away<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06413087"/>
6<lb/>
in the United States in August 1900 I<lb/>
think, and before the Carroll and Lazear<lb/>
cases occurred, and the knowledge that<lb/>
there was an interval of two weeks before<lb/>
the infected mosquitoes became infectious.<lb/>
They caused no illness, and were never counted.<lb/>
Lazear conducted these experiments in<lb/>
secret, for fear the Comd'g Officer might hear<lb/>
of this violation of the quarantine order-<lb/>
Dr. Pinto was one of these cases- None of these<lb/>
doctors after Lazear's death, came forward<lb/>
and offered to be bitten by a <hi>ripe</hi> mosquito.<lb/>
The last one of these secret experiments,<lb/>
and the only one which was <del>reported by<lb/>
Reed</del> successful, was that of Dean which<lb/>
was case no. 11 in Table III, the X Y of Reed's<lb/>
Preliminary Note (p. 62)- Carroll was no, 10 in<lb/>
that <del>report</del><add>Table III</add> and the others were the <unclear>youngsters</unclear><lb/>
about the hospital, who regarded it as a<lb/>
joke since none of them believed in the<lb/>
Finlay theory- So none of the first nine who<lb/>
did not volunteer with the knowledge that they<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06413088"/>
7<lb/>
were risking their lives, and who did not<lb/>
suffer an attack of y. f. were considered for<lb/>
the Roll of Honor- There was also no way<lb/>
of prooving their names, as Lazear and Reed<lb/>
were dead and Lazear's notebook from<lb/>
which Reed got his knowledge of them had<lb/>
disappeared - <add>before the Roll of Honor Act was passed</add> of course Ames could not<lb/>
have been one of these cases as he was<lb/>
known to be immune and was was selected<lb/>
by Reed to have charge of Camp Lazear<lb/>
largely because of that fact-</p>
<p>I have just yesterday received a letter<lb/>
from John Moran- He has sent me a copy<lb/>
of the first two or three sheets of his memoirs<lb/>
and has asked me to cross out anything<lb/>
with which I am not in accord-<lb/>
It does not tell anything about himself<lb/>
but is, almost from the beginning, a very<lb/>
aggressive attack on the Cubans and<lb/>
especially the Cuban Medical Profession<lb/>
for their failure to give proper credit for<lb/>
the demonstration of the Finlay theory to Reed<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06413089"/>
Ac<lb/>
K<lb/>
but to claim it all for Finlay- It is<lb/>
too partisan in tone to do any good<lb/>
and will just aggrevate the dispute- I<lb/>
think that the Americans are not without<lb/>
blame in this as Finlay is given little credit<lb/>
by doctors and newspaper men in the U. S.<lb/>
I will answer Moran's letter tomorrow and<lb/>
urge him to tell a little about himself and<lb/>
his early life and approach the Episode<lb/>
naturally and gradually and then to<lb/>
discuss it calmly and without <unclear>adjectives</unclear><lb/>
and partisanship- He might end by discuss-<lb/>
ing why it was if the whole merit was<lb/>
Finlay's that Finlay had by voice and pen<lb/>
stated his discovery to the doctors of Havana<lb/>
for 10 years and made not a convert except<lb/>
his disciple Delgado- Yet when Reed made<lb/>
his demonstation at Camp Lazear in a few months<lb/>
he converted them all and then the medical<lb/>
World- So we should consider this scientific<lb/>
question with scientific detachment and<lb/>
not with the partisan spirit of a political matter-</p>

<p>I think I have discussed the matter, without starting another<lb/>
sheet.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With cordial regards</salute>
<signed>J. R. Kean</signed>
<pb n="9" id="f06413090"/>
<seg>
P. S. I have written my reply<lb/>
on note paper and has sealed<lb/>
it in a small envelope when<lb/>
on glancing again at your letter<lb/>
I saw that Dr. Berrys letters<lb/>
were to be returned &ldquo;at my<lb/>
convenience&rdquo; I am afraid I have<lb/>
made a large use of that phrase!<lb/>
But better late than never-<lb/>
Your friend sincerely<lb/>
J. R. Kean<lb/>
I am using your fine large envelope-<lb/>
which is better than any which I have-<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
