<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06410001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 19, 1946</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06410001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1946-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Havard, H. O.</name>
<name type="person">Geddings Henry Downes</name>
<name type="person">McCaw, Walter D.</name>
<name type="person">Baldwin, T. A.</name>
<name type="person">Borden, William C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Blossom [Emilie M.]</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Army Medical Museum, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Marianao (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Washington Barracks Hospital, Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>17 pp.</extent>
<date value="1946-11-19">November 19, 1946</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06410001</idno>
<title>Interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 19, 1946</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench interviews Kean about the Yellow Fever Commission.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1946-11-19">
<head>Interview with Jefferson Randolph Kean, by Philip Showalter Hench, November 19, 1946</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06410001"/>
<opener>
INTERVIEW WITH GENERAL JEFFERSON R. KEAN<lb/>
<dateline>
AT 2804 N. ST. N.W., WASHINGTON, D.C.<lb/>
BY<lb/>
DR. P. S. HENCH<lb/>
<date value="1946-11-19">November 19, 1946</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f06410002"/>
<p>INTERVIEW WITH GENERAL JEFFERSON R. KEAN at 2804 N St. N.W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON, D. C.<lb/>
BY<lb/>
DR. P. S. HENCH, Nov. 19, 1946</p>
<p>(Note: In this manuscript, for the sake of brevity, General Kean's answers will<lb/>
be designated as &ldquo;K&rdquo;.)</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>#1a. General Truby asked me to find out when you wrote Chapter 2, Senate Document<lb/>
61, on yellow fever. He thought it was about 1904. Do you have any recollection?</item>
<item>K. I think it was about 1904.</item>
<item>#1b. When was Chapter 3 written?</item>
<item>K. At the top it says Dec. 5, 1906. Just below that it says August 30, 1906.</item>
<item>#1c. You wrote Chapter 3, didn't you? On page 23 is O'Reilly's name. When did you<lb/>
write it? August 30, 1906?</item>
<item>K. I wrote the part signed by Gen. O'Reilly. I must have written it in<lb/>
August, 1906.</item>
<item>#1d. Did you write Chapter 4?</item>
<item>K. Yes, I wrote it for Gen. Torney and it is dated April 29, 1910.</item>
<item>#2. Would you mind giving me a letter to the Guiteras family in Cuba, indicating<lb/>
my collaboration with you in the study of the work of Walter Reed, etc. that I might<lb/>
use next Spring when I visit Cuba and hope to meet the family of Dr. Guiteras?</item>
<item>K. I shall be glad to write you a letter.</item>
<item>#3. When did General Truby first tell you the story about Lazear's death?</item>
<item>K. Several years ago, when Gen. Truby was commanding officer at Walter<lb/>
Reed, he and I had had some discussions about Walter Reed and it was then that he told<lb/>
me his suspicions about the true nature of Lazear's death. This was just before Gen.<lb/>
Truby stated his wish to have the bust of Walter Reed moved from the National Museum<lb/>
to Walter Reed Hospital.</item>
<item>#3b. When was the marble bust made?</item>
<item>K. The original marble bust was made about 1904 or thereabouts and paid for<lb/>
by the Walter Reed Memorial Association. About 1926 the University of Virginia wanted<lb/>
a copy and we had a bronze replica made, the first one of which went to the University<lb/>
of Virginia. Another one was made for the surgeon General, who placed it in the Army<lb/>
Medical Museum. It was sometime between 1925 and 1935 that Gen. Truby told me.</item>
<item>#4. When was Washington Barracks Hospital abandoned as a hospital?</item>
<item>K. When Walter Reed Hospital was erected, about 1908 or 1910.</item>
<item>(Note: General and Mrs. Kean and I visited the old building this morning. It is<lb/>
now used as apartments for married non-commissioned officers. The upstairs corridor<lb/>
turns to the left and a hallway which originally turned right has now been blocked by<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06410003"/>
Kean interview<lb/>
#2<lb/>
a doorway. Apparently Major Reed died in what is now Apartment #5. or #6.--Dr. Hench)</item>
<item>Truby says - on 2nd floor.<lb/>
Kean says - 2nd floor on left side, next room to the front, not the<lb/>
front room-</item>
<item>#5. In our interview of May 11, 1946, you made the statement that Lazear had<lb/>
studied mosquitoes and their relationship to malaria in Italy. Agramonte makes this<lb/>
statement on the bottom of Page 25 of S.D. 61. Now, General Kean, the Lazear family<lb/>
has no recollection that Dr. Lazear ever studied any mosquito work in Italy on his<lb/>
visits to Italy. I have been over the family diaries, his mother's diary, etc. He<lb/>
went to Europe with his mother and traveled around. He studied in Edinburgh, but<lb/>
apparently when he was in Italy, he was sightseeing. So far as the diary of his mother<lb/>
shows, and so far as his family and his wife know, he never studied mosquito work in<lb/>
Italy. Do you have any information to the contrary?</item>
<item>K. No. Just where I got that idea, I do not now recall. He was an author-<lb/>
ity on mosquito work at Johns Hopkins and I had understood that he had obtained his<lb/>
experience in the mosquito work in malaria in Italy. There was a great deal of work<lb/>
done down there in the Campania. I have nothing to put against that, so you are<lb/>
probably right. He was an expert in examining blood, you know.</item>
<item>#6. How did you get from Quemados to Havana and vice versa?</item>
<item><p>K. We took a one track narrow gange railroad (the Marianao R.R.) into Havana.<lb/>
From General Lee's headquarters, we would take the Marianao train at the Quemados sta-<lb/>
tion near Camp Lazear. When I was later transferred to Gen. Wood's staff and was in<lb/>
my quarters it was nearer for me to take the train at the Buena Vista station. The<lb/>
railroad ended as shown by your map of Havana (August 1, 1899) at the Paso de Tacon.<lb/>
We would then take a coche (a little one horse buggy holding two people) and go down<lb/>
Calzada de la Reina, down across the Campo de Marte, turn left along the Prado to<lb/>
O'Reilly Street and down O'Reilly Street to the Governor General's Palace. When I<lb/>
took Reed in Gen. Lee's carriage down to see Gen. Wood, we drove along a new road<lb/>
north, parallel to the Almendares River, to its mouth where we crossed a bridge into<lb/>
<unclear>Venado</unclear>. That was a very pleasant and very direct route, going right through Vedado<lb/>
and going right to the palace. We didn't go through Havana, but took the avenue<lb/>
the whole way around along the sea front.</p>
<p>From Gen. Lee's headquarters, we drove down Calzada Real to Buena Vista.<lb/>
Then we would use what we called &ldquo;Gen. Lee's Road&rdquo; going straight north to the mouth<lb/>
of the Almandares, where we crossed over a new bridge which I believe was made by<lb/>
boats. Then we cut through Vedado to hit the sea drive. We followed the sea drive<lb/>
the whole way down to La Punta and came to the Plaza in front of the palace.</p></item>
<item>#6b. How often did the trains run?</item>
<item>K. I think about every hour.</item>
<item>#6c. How long did it take to go down town?</item>
<item>K. It didn't take so very long. Probably an hour.</item>
<item>#6d. How many passenger cars were there?</item>
<item>K. There were usually two, and a small steam engine. There was very little<lb/>
<unclear>freight</unclear>, but some provision for freight.</item>
<item>#6e. How were they lighted?</item>
<item>K. Probably by kerosene lamps but we didn't use the train much at night.<lb/>
Then we would get a private conveyance, usually a doherty wagon.</item>
<pb n="4" id="f06410004"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#3.</item>
<item>#6f. How long would it take you to drive to town in a doherty wagon?</item>
<item>K. It was about eight miles and it took about an hour to get to the city.<lb/>
As I recollect, it was a nice sunny day when I took Reed down.</item>
<item>#7. You and Gen. Truby have given me a lot of facts. I started to write them down.<lb/>
I still find many empty places because the facts are not clothed with detail. I should<lb/>
like to fill in one or two details and if you can tell me what <hi>actually</hi> hap<add>p</add>ened, that<lb/>
will be fine. If you can tell what probably happened, that will be all right too for<lb/>
my purpose. One of the high-lights of the story is of course the death of Dr. Lazear.<lb/>
I would like to know what <hi>probably</hi> happened the night of his death. Gen. Truby was<lb/>
called and signed the death certificate. Do you think he notified you that Dr. Lazear<lb/>
had died? That evening you sent a wire to the War Department. Will you please tell<lb/>
me what happened that night or what you think happened? I would like to cloak it with<lb/>
more detail. Can you reconstruct for me the probable events of that night? It happened<lb/>
about 8 o'clock in the evening and you sent a wire that night.</item>
<item>K. I had been away. I think I got back that morning and found that Dr.<lb/>
Lazear was very ill. He wasn't allowed to have any visitors. I didn't see him at<lb/>
any time after he became sick.</item>
<item>#7b. Did you have your own telegraph office or was it sent otherwise?</item>
<item>K. They had a government telegraph office at General Lee's headquarters<lb/>
where I lived. That was at Calzada Real. How we got her address in Boston, I do not<lb/>
know. That must have been given by somebody in Washington.</item>
<item>#7c. Didn't you tell me once that you had a hard time finding her?</item>
<item>K. No, I didn't. I don't know about this.</item>
<item>#7d. You say they had a government telegraph office in General Lee's headquarters<lb/>
on Real Street where you lived? How you got her address, you don't know, but probably<lb/>
from somebody in Washington.</item>
<item>K. Undoubtedly. It should have been sent through the <add>Chief</add> Surgeon's Office<lb/>
(Col. Havard, Chief Surgeon of the Department of Cuba). However, obviously this wasn't<lb/>
done as my name is signed to the wire. I assume that Truby telephoned me from the<lb/>
hospital and undoubtedly I was there that evening in my quarters.</item>
<item>#7e. What do you think happened? Would he have telephoned you directly?</item>
<item>K. He wouldn't have left it to some underling. I think Truby must have<lb/>
telephoned me the news directly to the headquarters. I should have sent the wire through<lb/>
channels, namely Col. Havard; however, apparently I sent it direct. Later the evening<lb/>
of Dr. Lazear's death, I wrote the following note in my diary: &ldquo;8 P.M., Sept. 25: Lazear has<lb/>
just died--a martyr to scientific research and to his profession.&rdquo;</item>
<item>#7f. The wire was sent by government telegraph from headquarters?</item>
<item>K. I am sure it was.</item>
<pb n="5" id="f06410005"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#4.</item>
<item>&ldquo;on the heights of Cabana&rdquo;<lb/>
(under <unclear>mo</unclear>)</item>
<item>#8. Will you show me on the map where the Spanish immigrants were?</item>
<item>K. Look<add>ing</add> at the map of 1899 showing the Department of Havana, taken from<lb/>
the annual report of the Commanding General, which you got at the N.Y. Public Library<lb/>
I believe it was on the heights just east and north of Morrow Castle and Cabana and<lb/>
just north of the little settlement called Casa Blanca. Probably 200 there per day (look up<lb/>
<unclear>around figures</unclear>) came to get good money for work in sugar fields</item>
<item>#9. Do you think Reed really believed that Lazear had been accidentally bitten?<lb/>
You later wrote: &ldquo;It has always puzzled me that <add><unclear>be</unclear></add> (<hi>Reed</hi>) should have apparently accepted<lb/>
it&rdquo; (meaning that idea). Was he really fooled or was he being diplomatic?</item>
<item>K. I don't know. We never discussed it. I always accepted it as a statement<lb/>
that was made and there was no reason why we shouldn't accept it.</item>
<item>#9b. In retrospect, in the light of what we now know, do you really think that<lb/>
Reed believed that story?</item>
<item>K. I doubt whether he did. He was a careful man who wouldn't dispute it<lb/>
unless he had evidence on the other side. Reed did accept Lazear's statement that<lb/>
he was infected by his own will but <hi>he got that from the diary</hi>. He and Truby evidently<lb/>
talked that over. Reed never talked that over with me.</item>
<item>#10. In your letter to me of Jan. 23, 1941 <add>p. 4</add>, you told me that you had given away<lb/>
to institutions and writers most of Reed's letters to you. To whom did you give them?</item>
<item>K. I never gave a collection to any one person but various ones to various<lb/>
individuals. Possibly one or two to the Librarian, University of Virginia (Mr. Harry<lb/>
Clemons). None to Hopkins, none to Wel<del>s</del><add>c</add>h Library.</item>
<item>#10b. How many do you think you gave away--a half dozen? Do you have any idea to<lb/>
whom else?</item>
<item>I gave one to my daughter,<lb/>
K. Possibly one or two to the Army Medical Museum. Mrs. Chason.<lb/>
Note: Mrs. Kean doesn't know either and doesn't think there were very many<lb/>
given away.</item>
<item>#11. Will you please comment on Lambert's interview?</item>
<item>K. It is like a pipedream. A great deal of it never happened at all. I<lb/>
think he has his dates all mixed up. I doubt very much that any of that about Andrus<lb/>
was true. Certainly I never heard any of it. It is entirely untrue about my behavior.<lb/>
I could have had female nurses if I had asked for them but I didn't like to have them<lb/>
when other men had been nursed by the hospital corps men, so I just took what came. I<lb/>
am sorry to say I can't remember who took care of me. Apparently during my illness<lb/>
I was somewhat stupid because I couldn't remember my conversation with Reed. Evidently<lb/>
he <add>(Lambert)</add> is a man who has thought of it until he has worked up a case in his own mind. He<lb/>
just takes this thing out of his own head. He states I ordered the men away from Col. Barracks.<lb/>
At that time I was with Gen. Wood. I would prefer to look over this more at my leisure<lb/>
and I will either write out my answers verifying the dates or will call Miss Schnurr.</item>
<item><unclear>di no<lb/>
moran</unclear></item>
<item>#12. In what building in Havana was the Pan-American Congress held in February, 1901,<lb/>
when Reed gave his second paper? You attended that conference.</item>
<item>K. I don't know. I was called away just before the meeting. I have no idea.</item>
<pb n="6" id="f06410006"/>
<item><unclear>C1</unclear><lb/>
B2</item>
<item>Lazear went alright. He wrote his mother about<lb/>
the trip. His letter is dated Aug. 5, 1900</item>
<pb n="7" id="f06410007"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#5.</item>
<item>#13. You told Major Reed the afternoon he was dying that the Secretary of War's<lb/>
recommendation that he become a Colonel and assistant Surgeon General had been approved.<lb/>
(See S.D. p20, <unclear>pa12 <del><unclear></unclear></del>3)</unclear>. Was that recommendation passed even though he died?</item>
<item>K. My recollection is that Congress did pass a bill making Reed a colonel<lb/>
and Gorgas a lieutenant colonel but Reed being dead, Gorgas was given the colonelcy.<lb/>
That is, because Reed was dead, no commission was actually made out. Therefore he was<lb/>
not actually commissioned a colonel posthumously.</item>
<item>#14. When I was visiting the Lazear family this July, I was allowed to go through<lb/>
Mrs. Lazear's little trunk of souvenirs of her husband. In there I found an order, order -<lb/>
ing Dr. Lazear to go to Pinar del Rio at the time of that epidemic. According to the<lb/>
record, Agramonte went there first, then sent for Reed and they found it was yellow fever.<lb/>
I have never seen anywhere that Lazear went down and yet I found the order ordering him<lb/>
there. Do you have any knowledge of that? Do you know whether he went?</item>
<item>K. I wasn't in Cuba at that time. I was in the U.S. but I don't believe he<lb/>
went. I never knew he had been ordered and I have never seen anything like that in the<lb/>
record. If it was decided that it wasn't necessary for Lazear to go, they would not have<lb/>
issued an order revoking the first order. They would merely have told him not to go.</item>
<item>#15. Please see S.D. page 59. Do you have any idea when Reed first became interested<lb/>
in Carter's work? Was it before he went down to Cuba or was it after he went down there<lb/>
and began to study the Finlay theory in Cuba? (See Keans answer #94 - May 25, 1946)</item>
<item>K. I think he had read Carter's paper before he came down there. He told me<lb/>
about it late in August or the first of September. Reed called my attention to Carter's<lb/>
work and said, &ldquo;What explains that difference? If a man comes into a town in Mississippi<lb/>
and gets yellow fever, no cases occur for three weeks. After that, anyone who goes there<lb/>
and talks to him gets it within a week. What makes the difference?&rdquo; (And he stuck out<lb/>
his long finger) Don't you see, that was due to a period of incubation in the carrier.<lb/>
He made that remark late in August or the first of September <add>1900</add> before Lazear started his<lb/>
experiments.</item>
<item>#15b. Do you think that he knew about Carter's article before he went to Cuba to<lb/>
form the yellow fever board?</item>
<item>K. Yes, I do. Not as something he had just seen.</item>
<item>#16. It is called the &ldquo;yellow fever board&rdquo;, but it was commissioned to study several<lb/>
conditions and the name &ldquo;yellow fever&rdquo; is not included in the order. Who decided to<lb/>
study yellow fever first--Reed or Sternberg?</item>
<item>K. I think it was Reed. That was the purpose of the board.</item>
<item>#16b. Was the rest camouflaged and if so, why?</item>
<item>K. I think they didn't want to offend Cuban sensibilities or frighten the<lb/>
American people whose relatives were there, by indicating that yellow fever was a menace<lb/>
they all had to look out for. It was a yellow fever board and everybody knew about it<lb/>
from the beginning.</item>
<item>#16c. Do you think that their naming the board as one for various infectious diseases<lb/>
and suggesting that they even study diseases of animals was mostly &ldquo;eye wash&rdquo;?</item>
<pb n="8" id="f06410008"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#6.</item>
<item>#16c. K. I believe it was largely &ldquo;eye wash&rdquo;. However, they may have decided<lb/>
to give Reed wide latitude in case he wanted to study anything else. Thus the orders<lb/>
were written, and if he had wanted to buy animals they would have come under the head<lb/>
of studying diseases of animals.</item>
<item>#17. Kissinger said to me he was one of the first nine cases but Reed never said<lb/>
so in any of his papers.</item>
<item>K. He (Kissinger) is entirely mistaken. I don't think that he was one of<lb/>
the first nine.</item>
<item>#17b. Why?</item>
<item>K. Because Reed never said he was.</item>
<item>#18. Look on S.D. page 65. The post mortem which Carroll attended was listed as<lb/>
a case of &ldquo;pernicious malarial fever&rdquo;, S.D. page 65. I <hi>think</hi> in one of your letters you<lb/>
and others have stated that it was a case of severe yellow fever. I would assume that<lb/>
Reed is correct and that it was a case of malaria and not of yellow fever. Do you have<lb/>
any further comments on that?</item>
<item>K. I think Reed's record here settles the matter that it was not yellow<lb/>
fever, that it was a case of malarial fever which had been suspected of being yellow<lb/>
fever. Note the next paragraph where it states that a fatal case of yellow fever had<lb/>
been autopsied in the same room the day before.</item>
<item>#19. S.D. page 71, para. 5, speaks about two Spanish immigrants who got sick at<lb/>
Camp Lazear and were expelled. Do you know what they were sick of and did you pay them<lb/>
some money anyhow?</item>
<item>K. We didn't pay them any prize money but they were getting the pay of day<lb/>
laborers. The paragraph tells what they had.</item>
<item>#20. Have you ever seen the full discussion of Reed's first paper in Indianapolis?</item>
<item>K. No. But I know that Wasden <add>wasdin</add> was at the meeting and later published a<lb/>
paper of his own, viciously attacking Reed.</item>
<item>#21. See S.D. p. 94, paragraph 2, and page 107, next to last paragraph. Who were<lb/>
&ldquo;both of the non-immune inmates&rdquo; mentioned in paragraph 2, and who were &ldquo;the two re-<lb/>
maining nurses&rdquo; mentioned in the same paragraph?</item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#22. S.D. page 101, last paragraph. Who failed to fulfill his promise?</item>
<item>K. Weatherwalks.</item>
<item>#23. page 110. Who were the &ldquo;five non-immunes who did not consent?&rdquo; Were they<lb/>
American soldiers or Spanish immigrants?</item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#24. Page 118. Who was the case bitten by the Pungens?</item>
<pb n="9" id="f06410009"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#7</item>
<item>#24. K. I think this was Neate. I know I paid him $100.00 for participating<lb/>
in that part of the experiments. You will probably find the date of the check in the<lb/>
old checkbook I gave you. You have told me about Springer having received the bit of<lb/>
a Pungens as you found in Reed's laboratory notebook. I knew nothing about that.<lb/>
I didn't pay Springer anything and I don't think you will find him listed in my<lb/>
checks.</item>
<item>#24b. Who was bitten by the daughter insects?</item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#25. Page 144. To what fort on the outskirts of Havana are they referring on<lb/>
page 144, where they found Stegomyia in the tin cans about the legs of a table in an<lb/>
officer's kitchen?</item>
<item>K. My recollection is that it was the Santa Clara Battery in Vedado, just<lb/>
on the outskirts of Havana.</item>
<item>#26. S. D. page 150. What was the Havana paper mentioned in the next to the last<lb/>
paragraph? (re &ldquo;sensational &amp; distorted statements following 3 deaths on <unclear>Guiteras'<lb/>
serves</unclear>)</item>
<item>K. I don't know. It might have been La Lucha or La Discussion. It was<lb/>
one of the two.</item>
<item>Incidentally, when we decided who should receive pensions and medals<lb/>
for the work in yellow fever, we paid no notice to the case of Guiteras because the<lb/>
matter had already been proven and these cases were made under the theory that it was<lb/>
a milder form of yellow fever than had been used in the experiments. Do you know that<lb/>
Guiteras' cases were all reported in full by Dr. Carlos Finlay in his reports?</item>
<item>#26b. When that series was published, why wasn't Gorgas' name on the paper? Only<lb/>
Guiteras' name was on it. (<unclear>Seen see Doc</unclear> p 29 par 9; page 30 par 6</item>
<item>K. Guiteras was the officer in charge of the yellow fever hospital there.<lb/>
It may be that he (Gorgas) was not officially in charge of anything there. He was<lb/>
largely there to supervise the mosquito prevention service and I think that is often<lb/>
spoken of as the Gorgas-Guiteras series. Gorgas instituted it. He said, &ldquo;Kean, I<lb/>
think that Reed has proved that you can transmit yellow fever by an infected mosquito<lb/>
but that doesn't prove that that is the only way or even the usual way.&rdquo; And he didn't<lb/>
believe that it was the usual way. You will notice that Gorgas never paid any atten-<lb/>
tion to those experiments of sleeping in infected bedding, and never mentioned them in<lb/>
his discussions at all. It was his idea that that was the way yellow fever was carried.<lb/>
I am sure that Gorgas instigated a series of cases. He told me, &ldquo;When we get a hundred<lb/>
cases of experimental yellow fever without a death I am going to put an infected mosquito<lb/>
on my daughter, Eillen.&rdquo; He thought Reed had discovered a method of producing mild yellow<lb/>
fever. About this time Carroll returned to do his work on filtered blood. He had a<lb/>
hard time getting infected serum. They wouldn't let him take blood from Guiteras' in-<lb/>
fected mosquito carriers. There was a certain amount of panic about it as these cases<lb/>
had been so severe and three died, and they were afraid of the effect on the American<lb/>
soldiers.</item>
<item>#27. Did the U.S. soldiers who received the experiments sign contracts with Reed<lb/>
like the ones that he signed with the Spaniards?</item>
<item>K. I think they signed some sort of an agreement that it was done with their<lb/>
consent. But I never saw them and it is just an impression of mine. I don't know whether<lb/>
they had a routine contract. They may have. had one.</item>
<pb n="10" id="f06410010"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#8.</item>
<item>#28. P. 183, paragraph 2, S<add>enate</add>. D<add>ocument</add>. When did Havard and associates publish the paper<lb/>
on fomites? What paper does he mean and who were Havard's associates?</item>
<item>K. I don't know what this means, probably nothing at all except that Havard<lb/>
had taken the position that fomites were not infectious and should not be disinfected.<lb/>
I don't hink Havard ever conducted any experiments but he had gone on record that fomites<lb/>
were not infectious, in April, 1901. Havard issued an order that the destruction or<lb/>
disinfection of clothing in yellow fever cases should cease (April 2, 1901).</item>
<item>#29, P. 197. <add>Sen Doc</add> Who was the &ldquo;well-known writer&rdquo; mentioned in S.D., p. 197, and the<lb/>
&ldquo;American physician&rdquo; mentioned on 215?</item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#30. How would Lazear when he was taken sick, have had an opportunity to talk to<lb/>
Carroll and tell him of the supposed Los Animas mosquito bite when Carroll himself was<lb/>
still sick. I can believe that Lazear called on Carroll every day when Carroll was sick<lb/>
but when Lazear got sick, he wouldn't call on anybody. How did Lazear get the opportunity<lb/>
of telling Carroll of the accidental mosquito bite?</item>
<item>K. I don't know anything about that.</item>
<item>#31. P. 232, (bottom) and top of p. 233. <add>Sen Doc</add> Did Major Gorgas <add>or <unclear>Finlay</unclear></add> write that or did you<lb/>
write it?</item>
<item>K. I did.</item>
<item>#32. Where was the temporary cemetery where Lazear was buried? On this map of the<lb/>
hospital grounds of Camp Columbia, Gen. Truby thought it was about 300 to 400 yards &ldquo;north&rdquo;<lb/>
of this stream. (dry bed)</item>
<item>K. I agree with Gen. Truby's remark to you. It was about 400 yards north<lb/>
of the dry bed of the stream between the Marianao Railroad and the Camino de la Playa.</item>
<item>#33. Why was Carroll called &ldquo;Sunny Jim&rdquo;? (@ to) <unclear>2</unclear> W. A Powell-&ldquo;because of a<lb/>
<unclear>tousonal ordety</unclear>&rdquo; - <unclear>Bard head</unclear></item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#34. About Wasden and Geddings--is Geddings alive? (Ravanel said "Wasden)<lb/>
(ended in a <unclear>Sanitorium</unclear>)</item>
<item>K. No. He died ten years ago at least. I don't know where. Geddings I<lb/>
thought was an intelligent man. He never cracked back at Reed's criticism, but Wasden<lb/>
did.</item>
<item><unclear>man McCord - new Sollen</unclear></item>
<item>#35. Are these two nurses whom Lambert mentioned still alive?</item>
<item>K. I don't know. They were against letting nurses being exposed to yellow<lb/>
fever, but I pointed out the necessity for some nurses to take care of officers' wives.</item>
<item>#36. Did or did not Lazear inoculate himself prior to the fatal inoculation?<lb/>
S.D., p. 10 says &ldquo;yes&rdquo; written by McCaw, but S.D. 16, para. 2, says &ldquo;no&rdquo;. See page 68<lb/>
where it says he was inoculated but not infected.</item>
<item>K. McCaw only knew what he learned from others, especially me. Obviously Lazear<lb/>
was inoculated but not infected, as it says on page 68, he was Case #6.</item>
<pb n="11" id="f06410011"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#9.</item>
<item>#37. Who wrote Chapter 6, S.D., page 4<del>9</del><add>48</add>?</item>
<item>K. I wrote it. It is modification of the reference given at the bottom<lb/>
of the page.</item>
<item>#38. P. 90. <add>Sen Doc</add> Where was this paper read by Reed? Where and what is the Med. and<lb/>
Chirurg. Faculty of the State of Maryland?</item>
<item>K. I don't know, but it was obviously an old organization as they were cele-<lb/>
brating their hundredth birthday in 1901.</item>
<item>#39. When Reed went down to Cuba and on his first visit home, he certainly must<lb/>
have had all of Finlay's papers translated, and certainly when he was writing his later<lb/>
papers, he would have had to have his Spanish papers translated. Do you know if he<lb/>
did have them translated or do you have his works?</item>
<item>K. I don't know from my own knowledge. It is quite possible that he did<lb/>
not have them all translated. The important ones had been published already in English<lb/>
and some were published in French. Reed knew French and Italian, at least he read them<lb/>
well, although he couldn't speak them.</item>
<item>#40. Who was your first wife? When were you married?</item>
<item>K. Louise Hurlbut Young. She was born in Connecticut of a New York family.<lb/>
We were married October 10, 1894. She died on December 13, 1915, at Fort Leavenworth,<lb/>
Kansas.</item>
<item>#40b. Was she in Cuba with you?</item>
<item>K. Yes, but I sent them home on May 1, 1900 so that they escaped the epi-<lb/>
demic. They (she and her two children) came back in October. They were there that<lb/>
winter.</item>
<item>#40c. Where did you live?</item>
<item>K. We lived at Camp Columbia for a while, then transferred to Gen. Wood's<lb/>
staff. We lived in rented houses. Gen. Wood said, &ldquo;Rather than renting a house, I<lb/>
am going to build a house for you.&rdquo;</item>
<item>#40d. When were you remarried?</item>
<item>K. March 23, 1919.</item>
<item>#40e. What was her maiden name?</item>
<item>K. Cornelia Knox, daughter of Col. Knox, U. S. Cavalry.</item>
<item>#41. Many times, in stories about the Spanish-American War, you read the statement<lb/>
that yellow fever killed more soldiers in the Spanish-American War than were killed by<lb/>
the enemy. Hagedorn says 200 a day were killed by yellow fever. In looking over reports<lb/>
of the Surgeon General and the War Department, I don't find figures that bear that out.<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="f06410012"/>
Kean interview<lb/>
#10.<lb/>
Do you agree?</item>
<item>K. I don't know of a case where 200 men died in a day.</item>
<item>#41b. Is it your opinion that yellow fever killed more soldiers than the enemy?</item>
<item>K. It is an undecided question. The Army that captured Santiago got sick--<lb/>
malaria, typhoid and yellow fever. How many deaths there were from each one is in a<lb/>
good deal of doubt. I think that probably in Santiago there were more deaths from yellow<lb/>
fever than from the Spaniards during the war. It is certainly doubtful. In other words,<lb/>
in some places in Cuba and at some times during the war, yellow fever killed more than<lb/>
the enemy, but the over-all figures probably do not indicate that yellow fever killed<lb/>
more than the enemy. I never looked up the figures, but you have to remember there were<lb/>
a number of cases that were very doubtful.</item>
<item>#42. How did you and Major Reed address each other?</item>
<item>K. I think we gave each other our military titles in addressing each other.<lb/>
At least I called him &ldquo;Major Reed&rdquo; but he mostly called me &ldquo;Doctor Kean&rdquo;. The envelopes<lb/>
of his letters to me I believe were all addressed to &ldquo;Doctor Kean.&rdquo; For doctors under the<lb/>
rank of &ldquo;Major&rdquo; one usually addressed them as &ldquo;Doctor&rdquo;. When one became &ldquo;Major&rdquo; or<lb/>
higher in rank, you usually used the military title. We would not use each other's<lb/>
first names. When we kept talking to each other, we probably called each other by our<lb/>
last names. We called the contract surgeons &ldquo;Dr.&rdquo; so-and-so. They had no actual<lb/>
military rank. They had a &ldquo;relative&rdquo; military rank.</item>
<item>#43. Will you tell me in confidence, without your being quoted, what kind of a man<lb/>
was Col. Baldwin?</item>
<item>K. He was a very mean man. They called him &ldquo;Old Muggione&rdquo;. They hated him in<lb/>
the regiments. (Muggione was a range of mountains in Arizona where he had been. We<lb/>
called him that because he talked a lot about it.)</item>
<item>#43b. In what way was he mean?</item>
<item>K. He would deny people things. The question of the location of my house, <add>for</add> example.<lb/>
<add>He located it</add> as far as possible from the railroad <add>station</add> to inconvenience me, because he resented very much<lb/>
that I went from his command to Gen. Wood's. There was an ambulance that came around to<lb/>
take the officers and wives to the hop. room. He issued an order that officers who were<lb/>
not under his command were not allowed to use that ambulance. I got an official copy<lb/>
of the order and sent it to Lt. McCoy. He showed it to Gen. Wood who wrote a letter to<lb/>
him and told him to revoke that order.</item>
<item>#43c. Did Baldwin interfere with Walter Reed's work or with the yellow fever work<lb/>
in any way?</item>
<item>K. He didn't know anything about it. Reed was very careful not to let him<lb/>
know. He wouldn't have hesitated to have ordered him off the post as he was admitting<lb/>
cases of experimental yellow fever inside the post which was quarantined.</item>
<item>#43d. Was Baldwin the commanding officer there all of the time this was going on?</item>
<item>K. Baldwin was commanding officer of Camp Columbia in 1900, 1901 until 1902,<lb/>
when we left Cuba. He didn't like medical men and he was jealous of anyone who was not<lb/>
under his command.</item>
<pb n="13" id="f06410013"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#11.</item>
<item>#43e. Was he commanding officer of the whole camp independent of the Seventh<lb/>
Cavalry or was he commanding officer by virtue of the fact that he was the highest<lb/>
ranking officer of any of the units of Camp Columbia?</item>
<item>K. Baldwin was commanding officer by virtue of being highest ranking officer<lb/>
of any of the units. He was a full colonel, head of the Seventh Cavalry.</item>
<item>#44. In one of my papers it says you lived at 1601 Nineteenth St. N.W., on the<lb/>
northeast corner of &ldquo;Q&rdquo; and 19th, when Walter Reed took sick. But your diary showed<lb/>
it was 1603, not the house on the corner.</item>
<item>K. I lived in 1603, in the house next to the corner, not the house on the<lb/>
corner.</item>
<item>#45. May I copy from your diary the remarks you made about Reed's illness and death?<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>K. Yes.</item>
<item>"Nov. 14, 1902: Reed has a well marked case of appendicitis. He began the<lb/>
day before yesterday (the 12th) but he has not stayed in bed.</item>
<item>"Nov. 15: Reed better this morning. Otherwise, Borden would have operated<lb/>
today. I dined last night (Friday) with Mrs. Reed, Gorgas having been invited and Reed<lb/>
being sick, I took his place.</item>
<item>"Nov. 17: Reed still sick and uncomfortable with his appendicitis, although<lb/>
pulse is normal and temperature not over 99.5. (General Kean made the remark that<lb/>
Borden was entirely deceived by this. Borden knew he had appendicitis but thought it<lb/>
was a growling appendicitis.)</item>
<item>"Noon, Nov. 17: Reed had an uncomfortable night with slight temperature and<lb/>
Borden operated on him this morning at 11:30. Appendix tightly adherent behind the<lb/>
caput coli and a small abscess behind them. Borden walled this off with gauze and thinks<lb/>
there was no infection in the bowels. He had to drain, however, and make a long incision.<lb/>
The cecum was dark and rigid and Borden fears a fecal fistula, and is rather despondent--<lb/>
unduly so, it seems to me. I cannot bear for a minute to think of the possibility of<lb/>
losing Reed. I went down with him to the (ambulance) and saw the operation. Dr. Neff and<lb/>
Gen. O'Reilly were also there and Reynolds and Truby. Ford and Connor assisted Borden.</item>
<item>"Nov. 18: Went to the hospital to see Reed today. He was suffering from<lb/>
nausea and thirst and was much distressed. I fear he is a very ill man, and I am very<lb/>
unhappy about him.</item>
<item>"Nov. 19: Saw Reed again this afternoon. He seems a shade better but is<lb/>
still very ill. Pulse 138, temperature 102, and very nervous.</item>
<item>"Friday afternoon, Nov. 21, when I went to see Reed, he was asleep. That<lb/>
night he had a turn for the worse and Saturday his condition was very bad. The pack was<lb/>
taken out of the wound by Borden Saturday morning. As he predicted, he found a fecal<lb/>
fistula. Borden did not let me see him Saturday morning when I went down there. I<lb/>
saw him when I took Blossom Reed down. By that time his condition was hopeless and at<lb/>
half past nine when I saw him, his legs and arms were cold and he was hopeless and at<lb/>
half past nine when I saw him, his legs and arms were cold and he was in the collapse<lb/>
of a general peritonitis. He knew me, however, and talked rationally. Blossom broke<lb/>
down as soon as she came into the room to see him and went directly out, nor could we<lb/>
get her to go back although he was anxious to see her. I excused her absence by saying<lb/>
that the odor of the fistula made her ill and he said, &ldquo;All right, take her home, Kean.<lb/>
She had better not stay here.&rdquo; So Louise and I took her home and she lost her last<lb/>
chance of seeing him, for he died at 2:05 A.M., Sunday morning, Nov. 23, 1902. I had<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06410014"/>
Kean interview<lb/>
#12.<lb/>
charge of all arrangements for the funeral, which was military, and took place at<lb/>
2 P.M., Tuesday, November 25. The pallbearers were Col. Calvin De Witt, Medical Dept.,<lb/>
U.S.A., Majors Louis A. LaGarde, William B. Davis, W. D. McCaw, J. R. Kean and William<lb/>
B. Banister.</item>
<item>"Members of the family in attendance were Mr. and Mrs. John N. Vaughan Norfolk, a<lb/>
kin of Mrs. Reed, Rev. James C. Reed, Danville, and Mrs. Vaughan's sister and her<lb/>
daughter.</item>
<item>"The funeral was from St. Thomas' Church and was very impressive. The students<lb/>
of the Army and of the Navy Medical Schools attended in a body in uniform. The professors<lb/>
and students of the Medical Department, Columbian College, also attended. (Now George<lb/>
Washington University?).</item>
<item>&ldquo;Prof. Wm. H. Welsh, Simon Flexner and Osler also attended and a number of general<lb/>
officers and other officers. He was buried at Arlington on the brow of a high hill<lb/>
overlooking the river and the city. He left much unfinished work and his loss is<lb/>
irreplacable to the corps. To me, his death is like the loss of a brother and takes<lb/>
away much of the pleasure of my tour in Washington.&rdquo; (End of quotation from diary)</item>
</list></item>
<item>#46. Let me show you the old Army photograph of Camp Lazear showing the tents,<lb/>
with Building No. 1 on the right and Building No. 2 on the left. Near Building No. 2<lb/>
in this photograph is a structure which nobody has been able to identify. Do you remember<lb/>
from your own knowledge what it was?</item>
<item>K. I don't know.</item>
<item>#46b. How often did you visit Camp Lazear?</item>
<item><p>K. I don't know. I visited there only a half dozen times only because of<lb/>
my interest in the camp. I went out there mostly while it was being made although I<lb/>
went out occasionally after it was in operation. I really had no business out there<lb/>
except of my interest. When Reed wanted to see me, he would come to see me at headquarters.<lb/>
Often, however, I would see the experimental cases after they had been moved from Camp<lb/>
Lazear to the yellow fever huts.</p>
<p>(Dr. Hench showed Gen. Kean a photograph of the remains of this unidentified<lb/>
structure as they were in 1940.)</p>
<p>(Note: Nobody has identified for me the structures immediately to the left of<lb/>
Building No. 1.--P.S. Hench.)</p></item>
<item>#47. The Army photographs of Camp Lazear, taken in the direction they were taken<lb/>
makes the camp look very flat. Actually there is quite a little slope to the land<lb/>
between Buildings No. 1 and No. 2, which Reed spoke of as &ldquo;a little valley&rdquo;. In the<lb/>
opposite direction from that in which the Army photographs were taken, the land is<lb/>
very rough and hilly. Do you remember of your known knowledge that the land was rough<lb/>
and hilly in the opposite direction?</item>
<item>K. My only recollection is that it was rolling.</item>
<item>#48. When I visited the Lazear family this July they gave me this photograph of<lb/>
Dr. Lazear taken in Havana, February, 1900. It shows him by a wall with bits of shrubbery.<lb/>
It looks like the veranda of a hotel. Can you identify it?</item>
<item>K. I don't recognize where that was. It looks as if it were down town be-<lb/>
cause of the high buildings across the street. It might be a summer garden. It might<lb/>
have been in Marianao but I don't recognize it.</item>
<item>#49. Accomplished.</item>
<pb n="15" id="f06410015"/>
<item>C1<lb/>
B20</item>
<item>Later. I now <unclear>rework</unclear> a note about Ames' illness<lb/>
written by Reed in the Gorgas Reed notebook.<lb/>
(N Y <unclear>acod</unclear> med). See his note p141 of the <unclear>notebook</unclear></item>
<pb n="16" id="f06410016"/>
<item>Kean interview<lb/>
#13.</item>
<item>#50. When I was here last, you gave me this typewritten copy of Dr. Finlay's<lb/>
article. In someone's handwriting on page 1 is given the date &ldquo;May 27, 1899&rdquo; and on<lb/>
the last page (9) of the manuscript is written in your handwriting &ldquo;Published in the<lb/>
N.Y. Record, May 27, 1899. Shown to Col. R. M. O'Reilly, Chief Surgeon, Division of<lb/>
Cuba, Dec. 1898 and to Dr. H. R. Carter of Marine Hospital Service.&rdquo; What is the<lb/>
significance of that? You showed it to Col. O'Reilly <add>and Dr. Carter</add> in 1898. Did you or Dr. Finlay<lb/>
show it to them?</item>
<item>K. The note means that I showed it to them, but the date &ldquo;Dec. 1898&rdquo; is<lb/>
an error. It should have been 1899 as neither O'Reilly nor Carter were in Cuba, and<lb/>
the paper wasn't published until May, 1899.</item>
<item>#50b. In other words, you were interested in the Finlay theory in December 1899<lb/>
sufficiently to show this manuscript to O'Reilly and Carter. Did Dr. Finlay give you<lb/>
that manuscript or is that a copy you had made?</item>
<item>K. I think that Dr. Finlay must have given me that. I had a very personal<lb/>
acquaintance with him. Some time after Reed's experiments were finished, Dr. Finlay<lb/>
loaned me his notebook with all of his experiments written up in it. Later I said<lb/>
to him, &ldquo;Dr. Finlay, I don't think that you transmitted yellow fever by the mosquito in<lb/>
any of these experiments. At least it is not shown according to the laws that were<lb/>
worked out by Lazear. Also your cases were not under quarantine.&rdquo; Dr. Finlay replied<lb/>
that he thought the limits of the incubation period were very arbitrary in Reed's cases<lb/>
and that it was much longer than that.</item>
<item>#51. What do you think of Ames' supposed case of yellow fever?</item>
<item>K. I think it was tommyrot. I think he was immune, and I don't think he<lb/>
had yellow fever. Because he was immune he never acquired it as long as we were there.<lb/>
He was only in the hospital for five days. I think that Ames just called it yellow<lb/>
fever. Stark <add>probably</add> said, &ldquo;You are the yellow fever expert.&rdquo; I think he wanted to get on<lb/>
the bandwagon. He thought it would be a fine thing on his record. I don't know why<lb/>
he should think so. Starked signed his yellow fever card and yellow fever diagnosis<lb/>
in the service record. Stark must have taken Ames' word for it. Ames was the yellow<lb/>
fever expert--Stark wasn't.</item>
<item>Note by Dr. Hench: I am not sure on what I am about to say but I believe that<lb/>
somewhere Reed accepted Ames' case as yellow fever.</item>
<item>K. I don't think Reed ever heard of it. I never heard of it until quite<lb/>
recently. I think Truby, however, heard about it. I never heard of it down there.<lb/>
He was certainly there at the time Lambert said he had yellow fever. He used to<lb/>
see Ames quite often.</item>
<item>#52. I read to Gen. Kean Dr. Lazear's letter to Mrs. Lazear, dated July 15, 1900<lb/>
in which Lazear describes Carroll. Gen. Kean said it was a very accurate description.<lb/>
I asked Gen. Kean if this description was not part of history and I said I would like<lb/>
to include it in my book. He had no objections.</item>
<item>#52b. I read to Gen. Kean Dr. Lazear's letter to Mrs. Lazear dated August<lb/>
23,1900 in which one sentence reads, &ldquo;I am more interested in this than in the yellow<lb/>
fever work. Reed and Carroll have been at that for a long time.&rdquo; I told Gen. Kean<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f06410017"/>
Kean interview<lb/>
#14.<lb/>
that my interpretation of this sentence was as follows:</item>
<item>I think Lazear was interested in mosquitos and malaria and obviously in<lb/>
mosquitos and yellow fever. What he meant here was that he was more interested in the<lb/>
mosquito studies in relation to malaria and yellow fever than he was in &ldquo;the yellow<lb/>
fever work&rdquo; that Reed and Carroll were doing at that time, namely, the bacteriological<lb/>
work. It did not mean that Lazear was not interested in yellow fever. His previous<lb/>
letters and the work he was doing on and before August 23, 1900 proves that. Later on<lb/>
where Lazear says, &ldquo;The malarial work, on the other hand, is my own&rdquo; to me means<lb/>
Lazear's study of mosquitos and malaria and the possible relationship also to yellow<lb/>
fever. That is my interpretation.</item>
<item>I asked General Kean how he interpreted this letter. <add>Keans answer:</add> &ldquo;Note he does not state anything<lb/>
about Finlay's work or the relation of the mosquito to yellow fever. Therefore, just<lb/>
what Lazear had in mind is not clear. However, we know that Lazear was not interested<lb/>
in the bacterial work which Dr. Reed felt had to be cleared away before they could go<lb/>
on with the mosquito work.&rdquo;</item>
<item>#52c. I read him the fragment of Dr. Lazear's letter to Mrs. Lazear dated Sept.<lb/>
8, 1900.</item>
<item>K. I think that is very important as far as it goes. It is very interesting.<lb/>
It indicates to me that Agramonte was <add>not</add> in on the secret of Lazear's work up to this date.</item>
</list></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
