<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06413259">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 17, 1948</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06413259</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1948-07-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, George</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1948-07-17">July 17, 1948</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06413259</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 17, 1948</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench explains why he has not had time to write the yellow fever story. He hints about a possible breakthrough in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1948-07-17">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, July 17, 1948</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06413259"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1948-07-17">July 17, 1948</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Thank you so much for returning the material which<lb/>
arrived in good shape. I felt sure that it would be of<lb/>
great interest to you and General Kean and revive many in-<lb/>
teresting memories. By separate post I am sending you our<lb/>
latest Rheumatism Review for your passing interest. You<lb/>
will of course not want to keep it but you might give it to<lb/>
some young doctor friend as the reprints are rather scarce<lb/>
but I wanted to have you see how I keep myself busy and<lb/>
why I don't get further along with the yellow fever story.<lb/>
I have felt a little bit the gentle pressure which you and<lb/>
General Kean have put upon me to finish the book. My only<lb/>
defense is as follows:</p>
<p>When I got into this thing, I first thought I was<lb/>
merely going to publish for them the little story of Moran<lb/>
and Kissinger. You know how involved I have become. I<lb/>
would be ashamed to have some of my colleagues in the Clinic,<lb/>
especially the Board of Governors, know how many hours I have<lb/>
spent on this hobby and I am afraid I would have to plead<lb/>
guilty to the charge that I have not always worked on it out<lb/>
of hours. I have spent many Clinic hours on it. Nevertheless,<lb/>
I have tried to maintain the fundamental principal that this<lb/>
yellow fever story was after all a hobby (my chief one) and it<lb/>
will be published. Nevertheless, my main contribution to<lb/>
human society and to my profession and to my own professional<lb/>
standing is first the daily job of making a living at the Clinic<lb/>
and secondly a continuing need to try to become the finest<lb/>
rheumatologist that I can become with the possible hope that I<lb/>
can make a real scientific contribution to the miserable vic-<lb/>
tims of chronic arthritis. Therefore, my second job after the<lb/>
primary one of making a living is in the field of clinical<lb/>
research over which I have spent long, long hours, not only<lb/>
during Clinic hours but over weekends and long into the night.<lb/>
I am not being immodest when I state that my own contribution<lb/>
describing and trying to reproduce certain phenomena which<lb/>
occur in rheumatoid arthritis have been considered by many the<lb/>
most promising and outstanding lead ever discovered for rheuma-<lb/>
toid arthritis. Just last week a visitor came from London to<lb/>
talk to me about it and slowly but surely we are making progress.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06413260"/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
July 17, 1948<lb/>
We are about to embark on the most promising leads we have ever had. This in-<lb/>
volves getting a special research chemist from Switzerland as we are working in<lb/>
a field of chemistry which is practically untouched, getting a new $1,000 apparatus<lb/>
and training a laboratory worker in special new methods. I simply cannot pause<lb/>
in this extremely important work. It would be folly for me to suggest that I may be<lb/>
successful but at least I must try and if we are successful our work will almost<lb/>
compare with that of our mutual hero, Walter Reed. Therefore, I have had to keep<lb/>
a proper prospective and even though I should love nothing better than to slow<lb/>
up and put aside all except the yellow fever work, my conscience will not permit.<lb/>
It has been even more painful to me than to you three very close and valuable<lb/>
friends of mine that I have not yet been able to prepare the manuscript, but such<lb/>
little matters as a four year service in the Army as well as lesser matters of<lb/>
new discoveries and my inability yet to tap two or three very important sources<lb/>
such as General Wood's diary and the Finlay Diary and the material that Carroll<lb/>
probably has, have lead me to keep trying to get this material before actually<lb/>
starting the manuscript. The last item I shall not wait for. The first item<lb/>
I hope to get in the near future; the second I think would be very useful but<lb/>
I will not necessarily wait.</p>
<p>Please, therefore, be patient and understanding. You may be surprised<lb/>
that I have taken this opportunity to speak so frankly. Your own little gentle<lb/>
hints have not precipitated the letter but the accumulation of perfectly proper hints<lb/>
of encouragement have brought forth this confession.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M. D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
cc: Moran<lb/>
Kean<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
