<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06507062">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, October 3, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06507062</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-10-03</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Tocantins, Leandro M.</name>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Treanor, Wally</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-10-03">October 3, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06507062</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, October 3, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby describes his physical condition and also states that Finlay deserves credit for all the help he gave to Reed. He encloses a letter from John Kelly.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-10-03">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, October 3, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06507062"/>
<opener>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<dateline><date value="1953-10-03">October 3, 1953</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Philip S. Hench<lb/>
Mayo Clinic<lb/>
Rochester, Minnesota<lb/>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I had intended writing you a long letter to be at your home upon<lb/>
your return from Europe. Conditions, however, seem to have made<lb/>
that impossible as I had a virus attack some months ago, and since<lb/>
that time, my right knee has gradually lost much of the progress<lb/>
it had made before. So, instead of getting better with exercise,<lb/>
it got worse. I gradually realized that something was wrong and<lb/>
so I took the matter up with the Chief of the PT Service and for<lb/>
the first time, I got action. A new doctor, Capt. Trainor, took<lb/>
me over and unfolded a lot of new and astounding ideas which I<lb/>
think will get us back on the right track. Trainor has only been<lb/>
here a few days and I think has recently been at the Mayo Clinic.<lb/>
(As soon as possible I will find out about him and advise you.)<lb/>
He has been so busy with me and other cases here that I have not<lb/>
had time to find out much about him, but I am most heartily pleased<lb/>
with the way he has taken hold of things, and for the first time,<lb/>
I feel I am in proper hands, with a man in charge who knows his<lb/>
stuff. I received their routine treatment here but evidently it<lb/>
was not suited to my case. I have no trouble to speak of except<lb/>
with my right knee in that I cannot flex it when walking. The<lb/>
condition was properly diagnosed after I was in the hospital a<lb/>
year and I suppose I have told you some time or other that the real<lb/>
trouble was that the quadricepts on that side was stronger than the<lb/>
hamstrings and other muscles which produced flexion. The result is<lb/>
that when I walk I not only strengthen the hamstrings and other<lb/>
muscles involved, but at the same time, the quadricepts gets stronger<lb/>
and stronger, and I failed to make the progress which I did at first.<lb/>
Really, am losing by the exercise. Now, we are endeavoring to cut<lb/>
out exercises which strengthen the quadricepts and have adopted<lb/>
a new method of exercising the other muscles I mentioned by utilizing<lb/>
the old principle of reflex action. For the hamstrings, for<lb/>
instance, they twist my right big toe and up comes my leg as if<lb/>
nothing were the matter with it by <hi>involuntary</hi> hamstring action. In<lb/>
that way, we exercise that group of muscles without much effort on<lb/>
my part. After doing that a few times, I can do it myself. That<lb/>
is an entirely new thing here, and I am the first one here to be<lb/>
treated in that way. After nearly two years at the Letterman, I<lb/>
have great hopes of getting real results, but so far I am not making<lb/>
any predictions except to let you know that I find Capt. Trainor a<lb/>
real live wire and he believes that the prospects in my case will<lb/>
be excellent. Now, I will be able to let you know more about this<lb/>
in the next month.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06507063"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>First of all, here are a few things which I have been wanting to<lb/>
write about, but I will only touch on them briefly. I was most<lb/>
appreciative of your telegram about the cost analysis I made of<lb/>
the yellow fever cases at old Camp Lazear, also the letter which<lb/>
repaid me for all efforts I have put out to do a good job. I<lb/>
also want to thank you and your secretary for mailing the article<lb/>
by Dr. Tocantins on &ldquo;Yellow Fever, Mosquitoes, and Carlos Finlay.&rdquo;<lb/>
I was quite pleased to see the illustrations, especially the 7-8<lb/>
foot wall of white limestone rock. I think it is beautiful.<lb/>
When will you be able to publish your little article about the<lb/>
dedication, last December? I also wish to tell you that I have<lb/>
heard from Father Kelly and will enclose a <xref id="t06507064">copy</xref> of his letter<lb/>
to me. When I wrote him I explained my physical difficulties and<lb/>
told him he could probably get a copy of my book from Dr. Nogueira.<lb/>
There he will find many references which explain my admiration for<lb/>
the very courteous old doctor who was so kind and helpful to me.<lb/>
I also told him that Dr. Finlay's deep interest and belief in his<lb/>
theory was responsible for his clinging so persistently to it<lb/>
throughout the years. Finlay should really get credit for the<lb/>
help that he gave Reed and others to prove it.</p>
<p>If Dr. Trainor's ideas come through as he expects, I shall be very<lb/>
glad to furnish you with short accounts about Reed and the other<lb/>
members of the Board. But I am in no condition to tackle that just<lb/>
yet. When I get so that I can keep on my feet without breaking my<lb/>
neck in the many falls which continue to bother me, I will soon be<lb/>
able, I think, to summarize all that I know about them.</p>
<p>I am still up in the air about the rent matter. Our landlord has<lb/>
not yet notified us of the increase but it will be very unreasonable<lb/>
I am sure.</p>
<p>I will now try to hurry this off and hope it gets to Rochester<lb/>
before you are ready to go to work on your stack of correspondence.<lb/>
When I hear from you I will probably know more about Dr. Trainor<lb/>
but the last few days have encouraged me still more and I am quite<lb/>
sure that he is already getting results in my case. I was just about<lb/>
ready to quit when this new development came.</p>
<p>I am sure you and your family had a most enjoyable and restful trip.<lb/>
Remember, it is time to take it easy. With best wishes to everyone,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>AET</signed>
Albert E. Truby<lb/>
<del>Brigadier General<lb/>
U. S. A., Retires Retired</del><lb/>
<hi>1 encl.</hi><lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
