<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06507009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 30, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06507009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-01-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Nogueira, Pedro</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Louise Adriana</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Governor's Island (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-01-30">January 30, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06507009</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 30, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby discusses the Camp Lazear National Monument and Nogueira's efforts in establishing the monument. Truby expresses his displeasure at the inaccuracies in an article about &ldquo;Finlay Field.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-01-30">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Philip Showalter Hench, January 30, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06507009"/>
<opener>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-01-30">January 30, 1953</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Dr. Hench:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I was very much impressed with your long letter describing the<lb/>
dedication of the &ldquo;Camp Lazear National Monument&rdquo; and the other<lb/>
functions of December 3 in Havana. I was impressed too with the<lb/>
fine layout of the little park, especially the beautiful white<lb/>
limestone wall with the medallions and placques. What a <hi>fine</hi><lb/>
little memorial it can become with a little attention by someone<lb/>
like Dr. Nogueira! What a wonderful job he really has done in<lb/>
laying the foundation of a fitting little shrine, such as you<lb/>
have visualized and which will be forthcoming if both countries<lb/>
cooperate. The thousands of visitors to Cuba during the winter<lb/>
season will want to see that historical place because everybody<lb/>
seems to be interested in our episode of yellow fever at Camp<lb/>
Lazear.</p>
<p>The floral tributes were wonderful and I was sorry that I did not<lb/>
inquire about them and manage to get the University of Pennsylvania<lb/>
in on it also with the University of Virginia and so many other<lb/>
institutions.</p>
<p>I was delighted to hear that &ldquo;Louiseta&rdquo; Wood was present and I<lb/>
like the way she seems to have stolen the show. She can do much<lb/>
to help you in your work down there as the Cuban people simply<lb/>
adored the General and his family, and evidently that feeling for<lb/>
the family still exists. I wonder if you happened to mention my<lb/>
name to her? I was the Surgeon at Governors Island, N. Y., while<lb/>
General Wood was in command and I was their family physician, but<lb/>
as everyone in the family was so strong and healthy, I had very<lb/>
few calls from them. However, &ldquo;Louiseta&rdquo;, as we all called her in<lb/>
those days was at one time quite sick with a respiratory infection.<lb/>
So I think she will probably remember me and my family. Her mother<lb/>
died just prior to the publication of my book which I very much<lb/>
wanted her to see. If I had an extra copy I would certainly send<lb/>
it to Miss Wood. I will keep my eyes open for one to send her.<lb/>
I think I was the first one to really point out how little the<lb/>
public really knew how important his help was to the success of<lb/>
Reed's work.</p>
<p>I have heard nothing from the Cubans re my medal but your statement<lb/>
makes it clear that it was actually awarded. I was hoping that<lb/>
they would notify me officially but as it did not come, I thought<lb/>
it wise to send Pedro copies of the four letter that I wrote to<lb/>
various Cuban officials and asked him to set me straight with them.<lb/>
Which letter was received by them I do not know. I expected to<lb/>
express my thanks upon some official notification from the Cuban<lb/>
Government. Of course, I want you to know how much I have<lb/>
appreciated all your efforts, for I feel that you and Dr. Nogueira<lb/>
had much to do with getting my name before the Cuban officials.<lb/>
Possibly my book helped, but I doubt if they had many copies.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06507010"/>
<p>Dr. Philip S. Hench &nbsp;&nbsp; - 2 - &nbsp;&nbsp; January 30, 1953</p>
<p>I am enclosing a copy of the remarks made in the Military Surgeon<lb/>
about the dedication of &ldquo;<hi>Finlay Field.</hi>&rdquo; It was such a short,<lb/>
inaccurate, and imcomplete account that I thought you ought to<lb/>
see it. Someone should see that the Medical officers of the<lb/>
services get a full account of the story by receiving a more<lb/>
factual and interesting account of this ceremony. Photos of<lb/>
the medallions and readable ones of the two placques should<lb/>
appear as illustrations.</p>
<p>I have been slow in writing you because of several reasons. First,<lb/>
I have to spend most of my time developing my muscles and this<lb/>
takes it out of me so much that I am quite used up by afternoon<lb/>
every day. The holidays and everything else have increased my<lb/>
correspondence so that I can hardly keep up with it. But, things<lb/>
are going well with me and I am really making progress. These<lb/>
lesions of nerve tissues make recovery very long since the accompany-<lb/>
ing atrophy of the muscles has to be redeveloped by real work. I<lb/>
have been extremely well in all other respects during this entire<lb/>
illness which is almost a year old. My family join me in very<lb/>
best wishes for you and yours. Congratulations on your fine<lb/>
results in Cuba.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Albert E. Truby</signed>
Albert E. Truby<lb/>
&sol; Enclosure<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I enjoyed and appreciated the many clippings you sent.<lb/>
Dont you want them back?<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
