<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06501101">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Gustaf E. Lambert, February 25, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06501101</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-02-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Lambert, Gustaf E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Morris, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, Albert S.</name>
<name type="person">Mazzuri, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Tulane University, New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Yellow Fever Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Havana Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-02-25">February 25, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06501101</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Gustaf E. Lambert, February 25, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby explains to Lambert the conditions for being placed on the Roll of Honor. Truby says that Ames does not meet these conditions, although he did take good care of the yellow fever volunteers.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-02-25">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Gustaf E. Lambert, February 25, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06501101"/>
<opener>
Copy for<lb/>
<hi>Dr Hench</hi><lb/>
<dateline>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<date value="1950-02-25">February 25, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Mr. Gus E. Lambert<lb/>
121 Morris Blvd.<lb/>
Birmingham, Alabama<lb/>
<salute>Dear Lambert:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your recent letter is here and because of the fact that you do not<lb/>
seem to have a clear understanding of my feelings of respect and<lb/>
admiration for our late friend and associate, Dr. Roger Post Ames,<lb/>
I will try to enlighten you although, if you will carefully read<lb/>
my book on the Yellow Fever Episode, you will find that I praised<lb/>
Ames and his professional work most highly. In fact, I think I<lb/>
said more about his fine achievements at Columbia Barracks, especial-<lb/>
ly in his treatment of yellow fever, than has ever been published<lb/>
elsewhere. Dr. Ames and I were very close friends, as you must<lb/>
know, and on that account alone I would do everything possible to<lb/>
honor his memory.</p>
<p>Congress very carefully drew up the provisions of the Roll of Honor<lb/>
Act, approved February 28, 1929, and the men that were to be so<lb/>
honored were selected and classified under two heads; first, the<lb/>
Board consisting of Reed, Carol, Agramonte, and Lazear; and second,<lb/>
all of the men who underwent at least one of the Board's tests at<lb/>
Camp Lazear. To make it ironclad, Congress even designated the<lb/>
actual names of the four members of the Board and the names of the<lb/>
men who took the test. This was evidently done so that the many<lb/>
officers and men at our hospital at Columbia Barracks in Cuba, who<lb/>
were also most helpful to the Board, could not be added to the list<lb/>
later and thereby lessen the great value of this precious medal to<lb/>
the real heroes. You know very well that since this Act was passed<lb/>
many bills have repeatedly been introduced into Congress to place<lb/>
other names on that list. None of them have been favorably consid-<lb/>
ered.</p>
<p>Dr. Hench advised you correctly that General Orders No. 83, dated<lb/>
Nov. 14, 1900, did not make Dr. Ames a member of that Board. That<lb/>
was a local order of our Department Commander, General Lee, which<lb/>
placed doctors and men from our hospital at Major Reed's disposal<lb/>
to help perform the routine duties at Camp Lazear. You will also<lb/>
notice that two enlisted men of our detachment, John S. Morris and<lb/>
John R. Kissinger, were also ordered to report to Major Reed for<lb/>
duty in that same order. They were not members of the Board however<lb/>
as that was created by orders from the War Department and to change<lb/>
the membership of the Board would require orders from that same<lb/>
source. Kissinger took the mosquito test and his name was included<lb/>
in the Act of Congress, mentioned above. Private Morris worked at<lb/>
the Camp but did not take any of the tests and was not a member of<lb/>
the Board so he is not included as one of the heroes. Dr. Ames was<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06501102"/>
Mr. Gus E. Lambert<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
probably needed by Major Reed at Camp Lazear for several reasons<lb/>
but one of the main ones, I am sure, was to have him present in<lb/>
Camp whenever any of the men who had been bitten by infected<lb/>
mosquitoes developed any symptoms that might turn out to be yellow<lb/>
fever. As Dr. Ames was to take care of Reed's cases at the yellow<lb/>
fever hospital, I feel sure that Ames indicated to Major Reed that<lb/>
it was most important that he should be at Camp Lazear part of the<lb/>
time every day in order to diagnose every <unclear>cases</unclear> at the earliest<lb/>
possible moment. This, of course was one of the most important<lb/>
things in the treatment which brought such great success to Ames.<lb/>
General Order No. 83 was probably considered necessary since Dr. Ames<lb/>
had to do part-time duty in two places and under two commanders. At<lb/>
the yellow fever hospital, Stark was in command while Camp Lazear<lb/>
was commanded by Reed. The duties of Dr. Ames, however, were strict-<lb/>
ly professional in both places and strictly in accordance with his<lb/>
contract with the Government -- i.e., to treat the sick, and because<lb/>
of his extensive experience with yellow fever, to assist in every<lb/>
way possible in the care of such cases. He did that work in a<lb/>
highly efficient manner.</p>
<p>The Act of Congress honored the members of the Board for &ldquo; the<lb/>
brilliant character of this scientific achievement&rdquo; and also honored<lb/>
the men who underwent the <hi>hazardous tests</hi> at Camp Lazear. Dr. Ames<lb/>
belonged to neither of these groups, therefore was not qualified to<lb/>
receive the medal under the terms of the Act.</p>
<p>The conclusion I drew of this matter as published in my book, &ldquo;The<lb/>
Yellow Fever Episode&rdquo;, are on pages 191 and 192. That can not be<lb/>
changed.</p>
<p>The very fine precepts of Masonry which you mention could in no way<lb/>
be violated when a commissioned officer obeys his oath of office and<lb/>
supports the laws and regulations on such matters as this. Further-<lb/>
more, I do not agree with you that Dr. Ames was deliberately harmed<lb/>
in any way by the Congressional Act. In fact, his achievements in<lb/>
caring for the sick of that Board have brought him most signal honors<lb/>
as a doctor.</p>
<p>In view of the lack of a substantial marking at the grave of our<lb/>
lamented friend and other matters you mentioned, why not get some of<lb/>
his old friends in New Orleans and other places to make an effort<lb/>
to bring this neglect to the attention of the medical profession in<lb/>
New Orleans and to the public in general? In this connection, I<lb/>
received a letter from Dr. W. M. Brumby of Houston, Texas about a<lb/>
year ago:</p>
<p>"I am writing an account of my contacts with my close friend<lb/>
since boyhood, a classmate at Tulane University, Roger Post Ames<lb/>
to place in the Medical Library at Tulane.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I have read with interest your &lsquo;Memoir of Walter Reed&rsquo; and,<lb/>
because they run a close parallel with facts I have at hand,<lb/>
collected over the past fifty years, I should like to use, and<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06501103"/>
Mr. Gus E. Lambert<lb/>
- 3 -<lb/>
credit to you some passages from your work that give mention of<lb/>
Dr. Ames.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I am sure that Dr. Brumby would join heartily with anyone who proposed<lb/>
a memorial to Ames at Tulane University similar to that which honored<lb/>
Lazear at Washington and Jefferson University. You will remember that<lb/>
Dr. Hench delivered the address a few years ago and paid a very fine<lb/>
tribute to Lazear's memory when a new building was dedicated to him at<lb/>
that school.</p>
<p>Certainly, Tulane University can well be proud of the fine profession-<lb/>
al attainments of their former student, Dr. Ames.</p>
<p>As I left Columbia Barracks November 30, 1900, I have no personal<lb/>
knowledge of the work you said that Ames and others did in placing<lb/>
infected mosquitoes on volunteers. My information about that is<lb/>
entirely hearsay.</p>
<p>In regard to Dr. Mazzuri, I am glad that you have finally found out<lb/>
who assisted Ames at the yellow fever hospital during the last few<lb/>
cases from Camp Lazear. Heretofore, you insisted that it was Dr. Pinto<lb/>
who treated the cases when Dr. Ames was not present and Andrus was<lb/>
having so much trouble. I did not know Mazzuri. He came to Columbia<lb/>
Barracks after I left.</p>
<p>Thank you for the pictures you sent. I was quite interested in them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>sig A. E. Truby</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
