<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06501067">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, November 29, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06501067</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-11-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena A.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-11-29">November 29, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06501067</idno>
<title>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, November 29, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tate believes that neither Lambert nor Ames belongs on the Yellow Fever Honor Roll. However, Tate believes that Lambert was courageous and Ames was a good doctor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-11-29">
<head>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, November 29, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06501067"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley 3 California<lb/>
<date value="1949-11-29">November 29, 1949</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I greatly appreciated your kind letter of<lb/>
October 25th. Your mention of Colonel (then Captain) Stark,<lb/>
Doctor Ames and others, brings me into a reminiscent mood.--<lb/>
I feel the spell upon me--and so should I meander on without<lb/>
regard to your reading time, please forgive me. Anyhow it does<lb/>
not obligate you to reply to my wanderings.--I will be amply<lb/>
be repaid should you derive a little interest or amusement in<lb/>
the reading.</p>
<p>Yes, I am still interested in the old days at Col-<lb/>
umbia Barracks (and at Pinar del Rio also). Of course I have<lb/>
been through many experiences since then--things that really<lb/>
affected my life more, but yet my mind often goes back to the<lb/>
old days in Cuba.--Something in the Cuban atmosphere--or, per-<lb/>
haps because I was young, that those old scenes are etched up-<lb/>
on my mind.</p>
<p>I suppose you have been all over the world, and in<lb/>
a big war since then, but I'll wager Cuba still stands out in<lb/>
your mind, too, with memories you won't forget.</p>
<p>I have often wondered what became of Capt. Stark.<lb/>
I remember he was quite strict. For instance, if at an opera-<lb/>
tion he suddenly asked some Corpsman who had been admitted,<lb/>
(after orders to bathe, change to whites, etc.) some simple<lb/>
anatomical question relating to the operation, and the man<lb/>
could not answer correctly, he could never get in on another<lb/>
operation. As Gray's Anatomy was my bible at that time, I was<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06501068"/>
(2)<lb/>
fortunate enough to attend many, and it was always highly in-<lb/>
teresting to watch him work.</p>
<p>He had an idea that the men did not like him. But he did<lb/>
not know that although the men realized he was strict, that<lb/>
they knew he was always fair. So, when he left for Washington<lb/>
the last time, practically broken down from so many operations<lb/>
he performed, the men presented him with a beautiful dress-<lb/>
sword, he could not control his tears at the surprise.</p>
<p>I remember once he cut out a growth on the inside of<lb/>
my right eyelid. He knew I liked an occasional drink, so said,<lb/>
&ldquo;Tate, I can't give you any anesthetic for this, so it is going<lb/>
to hurt, so if you keep that eye steadily to the right, I'll<lb/>
prescribe a drink for you when I get through.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'd rather have it now.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, hold tight to the Nurse's hand and look steadily<lb/>
at her, and don't move that eye to the left.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I did so, but it was rather difficult to appreciate<lb/>
female pulchritude when that scalpel got going! But he saw<lb/>
to it that I got the drink in the pharmacy. That is one side<lb/>
of Capt. Stark many did not know of--he had humor.</p>
<p>Then I remember he had his baby boy circumcised. He had<lb/>
another doctor do it. But he wouldn't even go inside--Paced<lb/>
up and down beside the operating room door like an expectant<lb/>
father! And he was sure angry when they turned me down on that<lb/>
Steward promotion after I had passed highest, as he was the<lb/>
one who suggested that I take it. It was a tough exam, too.<lb/>
Doctor Amador said to me after the oral examination, &ldquo;Tate,<lb/>
they became so interested trying to stick you, that they<lb/>
asked you questions even I couldn't have answered!&rdquo; Well, I<lb/>
performed full Sterard's work all after that at Ft. Bayard, and<lb/>
received extra-duty pay, but I was disappointed, too. I had big<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06501069"/>
(3)<lb/>
ideas of what I was going to do in the Medical Corps. But that<lb/>
is all long ago and far away!</p>
<p>I wrote to Wyeth, Inc. telling them that while I<lb/>
represented no hospital or library, that I had seen all the<lb/>
people in the picture, &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever&rdquo; at the<lb/>
time depicted, and asked if they would allow me to buy a<lb/>
large copy of it. They sent me a very nice letter and one of<lb/>
the large pictures, 18" x 20" which I intend to get suitably<lb/>
framed. I would not have known of these large pictures if you<lb/>
had not so thoughtfully sent me the smaller one.</p>
<p>Lambert should realize that the established require-<lb/>
ments for mention on the Honor Roll cannot be broken. But I<lb/>
guess he has become a sort fanatic on the subject of Doctor<lb/>
Ames not receiving full credit, and inc<del>u</del><add>i</add>dentally himself. I<lb/>
understand how he thinks.--He of course, took more chances of<lb/>
Yellow Fever before they discovered the mosquito was the car-<lb/>
rier, than anyone there, and it probably hurts him to see men<lb/>
like Doctor Cooke and Cor<add>p</add>sman England, for instance, get credit<lb/>
for # taking a chance that he took every day for months as a<lb/>
simple duty. Well, he is a discouraged old man with a phobia<lb/>
that I fear will never be satisfied. What I give him credit<lb/>
for is sticking on that disagreeable job alone for so long.<lb/>
I think he had lost any fear of the disease, as some few of us<lb/>
did. I know that in Pinar we had far more Yellow Fever in the<lb/>
two years I was there than they had at Quemados, although for<lb/>
a long time we didn't know it. We also had plenty of dysentery,<lb/>
typhoid, malaria and some small-pox.--Yellow Fever to us was<lb/>
just one more disease. Perhaps that's why Jernegan and Olson<lb/>
were not afraid of it. After some of us had handled so many<lb/>
cases at post-mortems held by Capt. Godfrey at Pinar, showing<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06501070"/>
(4)<lb/>
us it was Pernicious Malaria instead of Yellow Fever, and later<lb/>
we found those cases were the latter disease, we concluded,<lb/>
&ldquo;Well, if I haven't got Yellow Jack after going through all<lb/>
this, I'll never get it!&rdquo; --All we nonchalantly slapped mos-<lb/>
quitoes away, never dreaming that they were the buzzing death-<lb/>
carriers!</p>
<p>I can understand, too, how Lambert feels about Doctor<lb/>
Ames. I, too, have never forgotten that other doctors and nurses<lb/>
had fever patients and lost most of them, prior to the experi-<lb/>
ments. And other doctors and nurses lost cases in Havana after<lb/>
the experiment. Doctor Ames lost only one, I believe. The people<lb/>
of his community should erect a monument to him.</p>
<p>They say that old men always think that the age they<lb/>
were young in was the best in every way. Well, I don't, there<lb/>
are many things far better in every way than they were fifty<lb/>
years ago, and many things of fifty years ago I'd hate to see<lb/>
come back. But there's one thing I would like to see back, or<lb/>
the spirit of it. --A Government that would go over and block-<lb/>
ade that Communist government coast of China--as would have<lb/>
been done long ago if we had the people of fifty years ago!<lb/>
Looks like we will never learn.</p>
<p>Going back to Lambert being so sore about not getting the<lb/>
credit he thinks he deserved--Its remarkable how many people<lb/>
tried to get some glory out of that experiment. I read in Dr.<lb/>
Kelly's book on life of Major Reed some extracts written by<lb/>
Mrs. Warner, that surely stretched things. But several years<lb/>
ago I read a newspaper interview in which she claimed credit<lb/>
for all kinds of things which simply were not so. Said she<lb/>
nursed all the experimental cases! That she, on account of<lb/>
work was made &ldquo;Executive Nurse&rdquo; of Col. Bks. Hospl., and<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06501071"/>
(5)<lb/>
many other incredible statements. Now I don't think anyone<lb/>
there was better acquainted with Lena than I was. We were very<lb/>
good friends. I used to go over the the Receiveing Ward on<lb/>
many evenings and we leaned against the railing outside the<lb/>
ward and talked. I liked her very much and I know she was a<lb/>
competant trained nurse. So I was greatly astonished at these<lb/>
later statements she made for publication. She was never<lb/>
&ldquo;Executive Nurse&rdquo; there, but was in charge of the Receiving<lb/>
Ward for a long time before I left.</p>
<p>November 5th--I dated this letter Nov. 29th and then put it<lb/>
aside, concluding not to bother you with it. But I was uptown<lb/>
today trying to get a copy of your book, so thought I'd tell<lb/>
you about that, and then decided I'd send you this whole long<lb/>
epistle and let you cuss!</p>
<p>There are several real large book stotes here, (Berkeley<lb/>
being a literary minded city) but I could not find a copy of<lb/>
your book anywhere. But I left an order with the largest firm<lb/>
to advt' in their journal and try to get it for me. I was<lb/>
astonished at the size of that store. They told me that they<lb/>
send out thousands of educational and technical books weekly<lb/>
all over the world, especially to the P. I. where all books<lb/>
were burned by the Japs, and thousands to Japan, Arabia and<lb/>
Iran.</p>
<p>With very best wishes for you in every way, and<lb/>
apologies for this crazy letter,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially &amp; Sincerely Yours,</salute>
<signed>Paul L. Tate</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
