<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06507060">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, August 23, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06507060</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-08-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-08-23">August 23, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06507060</idno>
<title>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, August 23, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tate recollects his impressions about the members of the Yellow Fever Board. He encourages Truby to share his memories of Reed with Hench.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-08-23">
<head>Letter from Paul L. Tate to Albert E. Truby, August 23, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06507060"/>
<opener>
Mailed Aug. 23, '53<lb/>
Copy<lb/>
<dateline>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley, 3 California<lb/>
<date value="1953-08-23">August 23, 1953</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am returning with this doctor Hench's letter to you of<lb/>
August 12th which you favored me with. Will write you as<lb/>
requested regarding my knowledge of Major Reed and his<lb/>
Board, which, naturally, is very little and will not be<lb/>
of any benefit to you or Doctor Hench.</p>
<p>I know nothing about the members of the Board from a per-<lb/>
sonal standpoint. I very seldom saw Agramonte. The only<lb/>
time I saw him closely was when he came to Pinar del Rio<lb/>
to investigate the cause of the many deaths there. I went<lb/>
through the wards with him and Capt. Godfrey, (whose clerk<lb/>
I was). I still remember the curious, <unclear>quissical</unclear> way he<lb/>
glanced at Godfrey as he examined some of the patients and<lb/>
their bed charts. I remember this more than I do his appear-<lb/>
ance except that he was tall and handsome. I think Major<lb/>
Reed came a few days later, as I remember him being there.</p>
<p>As I did not arrive at Columbia Barracks until Sept. 9th,<lb/>
1900, and Lazear became ill Sept. 16th, I knew nothing of<lb/>
him except hearsay.</p>
<p>My only remembrance of Carroll is of an English heavy-face<lb/>
type. Mess-room gossip was that he got his medical educa-<lb/>
tion the hard way and was always willing to take mosquito<lb/>
tests, so we were for him.</p>
<p>So the above don't mean anything, and I regret it, especi-<lb/>
ally in view of the fact that in those days I took precise<lb/>
notice of everyone I met--a habit instilled by newspaper<lb/>
work. A few years after those events I could have given a<lb/>
graphic discription of everyone there, but the changes and<lb/>
events of fifty years have erased it all from my memory,<lb/>
and I just cant stretch it as &ldquo;old soldiers&rdquo; often do!</p>
<p>I saw Major Reed numerous times outdoors, in the Hospital<lb/>
office of Capt. Stark and once at a post-mortem. All that<lb/>
I remember of his physical appearance is that he was fairly<lb/>
tall and slender. It seems to me his hair was slightly red-<lb/>
dis brown or sandy. (This is not a statement, merely an<lb/>
impression.) I got no impression of sternness from him--<lb/>
He seemed more preoccupied and earnest in expression.</p>
<p>Doctor Hench says he does not know how much of personality<lb/>
should go into his book. He is distressed that he has not<lb/>
an actual knowledge of Reed and his colleagues. I think I<lb/>
understand his feeling. His last paragraph tells what he<lb/>
wishes. He would like to write intimately but never having<lb/>
known these men, he can write only through the eyes and<lb/>
minds of others. . And there are no others except your-<lb/>
self who knew Reed with any degree of personal friendship.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06507061"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p>It is of no avail to him to read that a man was dignified,<lb/>
disciplined, stern, etc. That would apply to very many<lb/>
older Army officers. Its a type, not a personality. By the<lb/>
way, if you will excuse the digression, I don't like that<lb/>
word, &ldquo;dignified.&rdquo; Of all the known traits it is the most<lb/>
easily counterfeited by those who rate pomposity as dignity.<lb/>
My impression of Reed, superficial though it may be, was<lb/>
one of Intellectual earnestness.</p>
<p>But, in your outstanding book on this subject one can find<lb/>
more discriptions of Major Reed, from an intimate source<lb/>
than I think has been published anywhere else, and Doctor<lb/>
Hench should be able to derive much from that. But I think<lb/>
he wants to be in your place and thoughts in some of the<lb/>
conversations you had with Reed that are merely hinted at<lb/>
in your book, so that he can see Reed as you, a bright, in-<lb/>
tellectual, fine young officer, doctor saw him and thought<lb/>
of him.</p>
<p>He thinks, as I do, that you were offered the place on the<lb/>
Board vacated by Lazear's death. He knows that the letter<lb/>
Reed sent you--The first written account of the first case<lb/>
of experimental Y. F. would not have been sent to anyone<lb/>
but to one he thought much of. That he was probably instru-<lb/>
mentalin your being dispatched to Rowell Barracks when they<lb/>
became suspicious of Y. F. there and where his son was ser-<lb/>
ving.</p>
<p>He knows from all this that you knew Reed better that any<lb/>
one else alive and he wants to live with Major Reed vicar-<lb/>
iously through you. So I think that what you write him on<lb/>
your association with Major Reed and the others and what<lb/>
you actually thought of them will be of the greatest im-<lb/>
portance in writing a factual book of this kind. In fact,<lb/>
it won't be complete without your contribution.</p>
<p>Well, this is a very lengthy reply to you questions, but<lb/>
you well know what a garrulous old man I am at a typewriter!<lb/>
You have never told me how you are getting along now with<lb/>
your walking. Very well, I sincerely hope. I feel that you<lb/>
can conquor anything in that line. Fact is you are a great<lb/>
source of inspiration to me. I'm a regular coward, and when<lb/>
some unusual ache or pain develops I get scared stiff! Then<lb/>
I think of what you have been through and conquored and it<lb/>
braces me up.</p>
<p>With very best wishes to you and family from my wife and<lb/>
self,</p>
<closer>
<salute>As always<del>s</del> sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Paul L. Tate</signed>
(lencl)<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
