<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06501074">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 12, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06501074</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-12-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hench, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Fowler,George</name>
<name type="person">Maus, Louis M.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Stitt, Edward R.</name>
<name type="person">Grosvenor, Gilbert</name>
<name type="person">Keiffer, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Rochester (Minn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-12-12">December 12, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06501074</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 12, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean corrects a case of mistaken identity in a photograph Hench had sent to him, and provides details about his assignments in Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-12-12">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Philip Showalter Hench, December 12, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06501074"/>
<opener>
2804 N STREET N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1949-12-12">12 Dec, '49</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My Dear Col. Hench</salute>
</opener>
<p>I think you wrote that you<lb/>
would be back from Europe on<lb/>
Dec. 17, so it is about time for me<lb/>
to get off a letter to meet you at<lb/>
Rochester and welcome you home.<lb/>
I hope the divertion of the trip has<lb/>
given you a good rest. If I could<lb/>
judge from the pictures of you in<lb/>
the Norse papers that you sent me<lb/>
I would say that you had renewed<lb/>
your youth like the eagle. They gave<lb/>
you a really boyish look. I suppose<lb/>
they were Norse, or some Skandinavian<lb/>
language. Certainly out of my repertoire<lb/>
which is limited to English French and a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06501075"/>
a little Spanish. You will find where<lb/>
you get around to it, which will I am<lb/>
sure not been until after Christmas<lb/>
(Mrs Hench and the children will see to<lb/>
that), the huge package of Spanish War<lb/>
photographs which came in due time<lb/>
from Truby. I got them off by express<lb/>
about a month ago with Cornelia's<lb/>
valient assistance, and with comments<lb/>
written on the back of one-that of Gen.<lb/>
Fitzhugh Lee and his staff. It is about<lb/>
the only one which I think is worth copy-<lb/>
ing. Truby found two of those of La Punta<lb/>
of interest also as he was stationed there<lb/>
when he first arrived in Cuba. Truby sup-<lb/>
posed very naturally that I was in the group<lb/>
of the VII Corps staff and named the officer<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06501076"/>
on the left end of the line as Kean.<lb/>
He was a nice looking fellow but as<lb/>
I wrote Truby he had more stomach<lb/>
and straighter legs than I. My broken<lb/>
and shortened left leg dated from 1891.<lb/>
He was a volunteer Medical Officer whose<lb/>
name was Fowler I think. He was attach-<lb/>
ed to the staff as a surgical expert<lb/>
who knew how to perform appendec-<lb/>
tory. A rare accomplishment in those<lb/>
days! I was not at that time on Gen.<lb/>
Lee's staff but was Chief Surgeon of<lb/>
the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Division with which I came to<lb/>
Cuba. But Gen Lee had his eye on<lb/>
me and soon after the taking of that<lb/>
photograph Col Maus was relieved as<lb/>
Chief Surgeon and went back to the U. S.<lb/>
and I took his place and was promoted<lb/>
to Lt. Col. of Volunteers. My rank in the<lb/>
regular Army was Captain. I think I<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06501077"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
4<lb/>
became Ch. Surgeon VII Army Corps on<lb/>
March 6, 1899 but did not have that<lb/>
honor long as the Corps was mustered out<lb/>
and its constituent units sent home.<lb/>
But Gen. Lee held on to me and I became<lb/>
as you know his Chief Surgeon of Western<lb/>
Cuba. When he went home after a year or<lb/>
more I went to Gen Woods Staff but<lb/>
always as a Major, first of Volunteers and<lb/>
then in 1901 in the regular service.<lb/>
I had a letter from Truby yesterday<lb/>
about the pictures which I will<lb/>
inclose. Dont return it.</p>
<p>We missed you at the annual meeting<lb/>
of the Reed Memorial Assec. Admer<lb/>
Stitt, who had been ill a long time,<lb/>
died some days before the meeting and<lb/>
it looked as if we would not have a<lb/>
quorum. But Dr. Gilbert Grovener came<lb/>
in which made 6 and then we took<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06501078"/>
5<lb/>
2804 N STREET N. W.<lb/>
WASHINGTON 7, D. C.<lb/>
comment on, they came to me from Truby<lb/>
a couple of weeks ago. I agreed with him<lb/>
that they were of no special interest or<lb/>
importance to the Walter Reed and Yellow<lb/>
Fever Episode, but had a certain historical<lb/>
interest in connection with the VII Army<lb/>
Corps. We both tried to identify the mem-<lb/>
bers of Gen. Fitzhugh's staff in the photo-<lb/>
graph. Fortunately there was a date<lb/>
on it tho. torn off in part. It was Jan. 2<lb/>
which was clearly, I think in late Jan '99<lb/>
Truby identified as me, the man on the left<lb/>
who had a certain facial resemblance to me<lb/>
but his stomach was bigger than mine ever was<lb/>
and his legs were straight, whereas <add>one of</add> mine was<lb/>
always crooked since my fracture of the thigh<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06501079"/>
6<lb/>
split into the Knee, in 1891. Most of the faces<lb/>
were familiar to me, but I have not been<lb/>
able to recall all the names. My memory,<lb/>
which was never good for names has been<lb/>
notably weakened by my illness last spring.<lb/>
I pointed out in a letter to Truby that I was<lb/>
not at that time a member of Gen. Lee's<lb/>
Staff. Col. Louis M. Maus, Med. Dept. was<lb/>
the Chief Surgeon and is there prominently.<lb/>
He was relieved as Ch. Surgeon and or-<lb/>
dered to the U.S. a few weeks after that<lb/>
picture was taken, and I succeeded him<lb/>
as Chief Surgeon. I came to Cuba as Chief<lb/>
Surgeon 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Division VII Corps, under a dear<lb/>
old man*<add>Brig. Gen. Keiffer of Ohio.</add>, who had been a Brig. Gen. US Army<lb/>
in the Civil War and later was in Congress,<lb/>
and because speaker of the H.R. I became<lb/>
Chief Surgeon of the Corps a few weeks<lb/>
after that photograph was taken.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06501080"/>
<p>7-</p>
<p>I have some where a bundle of papers and<lb/>
photos of the VII Army Corps, but I have<lb/>
no systemac files and no clerk to help<lb/>
me, and so have not been able to put<lb/>
my hand on this bundle. If and when<lb/>
I find it I will be able to get most, if<lb/>
not all the names. Most of them were<lb/>
Volunteer Officers who went home<lb/>
when the Corps was mustered out and<lb/>
dropped out of army life. Cornelia was<lb/>
afraid that some of the pictures would<lb/>
be misplaced, so she undertook the job<lb/>
of packing up and sending off the<lb/>
big bundle of photographs to your ad-<lb/>
dress in Rochester. We sent it by express<lb/>
rather than by registered mail, for it<lb/>
is much more convenient - for express<lb/>
the man comes on phone call and takes<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06501081"/>
AC<lb/>
K<lb/>
8<lb/>
it and the bill is sent later. Whereas<lb/>
to mail any thing, one has to <hi>tote</hi> it<lb/>
to the Post Office and stand in line,<lb/>
and deliver it, which for us old<lb/>
people is quite an undertaking.</p>
<p>I suppose that after you get home<lb/>
and look over your big pile of<lb/>
mail, you will begin to wonder what<lb/>
the two hurricanes which swept over<lb/>
Western Cuba have done to your little<lb/>
<del>little</del> house no 1 at Camp Lazear.<lb/>
I hope it is <del>are</del> still there.<lb/>
We hope that Mrs Hench enjoyed<lb/>
her trip to Europe, and on her<lb/>
return found the Children all<lb/>
flourishing. With all good wishes</p>
<closer>
<salute>I am sincerely yours</salute>
<signed>J.R.Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
