<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06504038">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Albert E. Truby to Mary Standlee, May 26, 1951 [Enclosed in 06504036]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Truby, Albert E.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06504038</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-05-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Standlee, Mary </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Hemmeter, John</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wasdin, Eugene</name>
<name type="person">Geddings, Henry Downes</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-05-26">May 26, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06504038</idno>
<title>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Mary Standlee, May 26, 1951 [Enclosed in 06504036]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Truby reviews Chapter 3 of Standlee's manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-05-26">
<head>Letter from Albert E. Truby to Mary Standlee, May 26, 1951 [Enclosed in <xref id="t06504126">06504036</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06504038"/>
<opener>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco 18, California<lb/>
<dateline><date value="1951-05-26">May 26, 1951</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Mrs. Mary W. Standlee<lb/>
The Library<lb/>
Walter Reed Army Hospital<lb/>
The Army Medical Center<lb/>
Washington 12, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Mrs. Standlee:</salute>
</opener>
<p>In reviewing your manuscript, Chapter 3, I find that I will have to write it all<lb/>
out in long hand and then later have it typed.</p>
<p>To save myself work, I am referring to my book, &ldquo;Memoirs of Walter Reed - The<lb/>
Yellow Fever Episode&rdquo;, with the page numbers in brackets and I think you will<lb/>
find it easy from the references to my book to understand where things fit i<del>t</del><add>n</add>.</p>
<p><hi>Your Page 37</hi>-</p>
<p>First paragraph &ldquo;By early spring of 1900...&rdquo; should be <hi>1899</hi>. See my book,<lb/>
page 40, note 4, April 29, 1899. Reed and Carroll were already convinced that<lb/>
Sanarelli's organism was not the cause of yellow fever. Dr. Hammeter's refer-<lb/>
ence, No. 8, probably came from Reed and Carroll's article in the Medical News<lb/>
of April 29. (Note 4). Additional work on blood cultures from new cases of<lb/>
yellow fever were necessary to compa<del>t</del><add>r</add>e with Wasdin and Geddings' work on<lb/>
similar cases of yellow fever. (Pg. 87.)</p>
<p><hi>Page 38</hi>-</p>
<p>Last paragraph. The outbreak of yellow fever at Mariano (Pg. 78) was<lb/>
purely incidental and had no bearing on the orders for the Reed Board. The<lb/>
first case of yellow fever there occurred on May 19 and the orders for the<lb/>
Board were issued May 23rd from Washington so that the epidemic had just started.<lb/>
During March and April, 1900, Reed lived with us at the Hospital, Columbia Bks.<lb/>
Then he went direct to Washington and I am sure he requested orders to continue<lb/>
work on the etiology of yellow fever. (Pg. 76.)</p>
<p><hi>Page 38-</hi></p>
<p>Dr. Welch was probably consulted about Dr. Lazear's qualifications for<lb/>
Reed had become well acquainted with him and his work in the laboratory at<lb/>
Columbia Bks. during March and April. (See last paragraph, Pg. 75; also Page 76.)<lb/>
As Reed had already concluded that our Hospital was the place to study yellow<lb/>
fever and that Lazear would be helpful to him in his laboratory work, I am sure<lb/>
that my observations are more nearly correct than those of writers who are only<lb/>
guessing. There is no factual confirmation of the Reed-Welch discussion as far<lb/>
as I know.</p>
<p><hi>Page 39</hi>-</p>
<p>Re your Note 13b, I have never seen or heard of any verbal or written<lb/>
discussions between Dr. Welch and Gen. Sternberg about the Reed Board. Neither<lb/>
of these distinguished men could give Reed much information on entomology,<lb/>
especially on mosquito work, but Reed had already made contact with Dr. L. O.<lb/>
Howard, the entomologist of the Department of Agriculture in Washington.<lb/>
(Pgs. 141-143 and 194-195.)</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06504039"/>
<p>- 2 -<lb/>
Mrs. Mary W. Standlee.</p>
<p><hi>Page 39</hi>-</p>
<p>Lazear reported for duty at the Columbia Barracks Hospital as the result of<lb/>
my request that a bacteriologist be assigned to duty in our laboratory. (Pgs. 60-<lb/>
61.) Lazear had, I think, requested duty as a Contract Surgeon in some Army<lb/>
laboratory and when his application arrived in the SGO, Mr. Jones, the Chief<lb/>
Clerk, probably had him sent to Cuba to meet our request. This lest sentence<lb/>
is not factual but my memory indicates that Lazear gave me that information.<lb/>
There is nothing that I know of indicating that Dr. Welch had anything to do<lb/>
with the assignment of Lazear as described above.</p>
<p>Lazear and Reed first met in March, 1900 at the Hospital, Columbia Bks., Cuba.<lb/>
(Pg. 75) Reed therefore wanted him on the Yellow Fever Board and also wanted<lb/>
Agramonte who was an immune. (Pg. 76) Reed and Carroll returned to Cuba,<lb/>
June 25, 1900. (Pg. 77) I think the words <hi>very positive</hi> should be substituted<lb/>
for &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo;.</p>
<p><hi>Page 39</hi>-</p>
<p>Instead of &ldquo;Dr. Reed had to return....&rdquo; I would change that sentence to<lb/>
read, as follows: &ldquo;Major Reed was ordered...&rdquo;. In those days, many people in<lb/>
the Service did not like to give doctors their military title but it was always<lb/>
used in military orders. While Dr. Carroll was the senior Board member present<lb/>
during Reed's absence, both he and Lazear had their work prescribed for them by<lb/>
Maj. Reed and there was practically no administrative work required. Sgt. Neate<lb/>
was really the man who had cultures and mosquitoes to look after and he got his<lb/>
instructions on cultures from Carroll. Lazear had already taught him how to<lb/>
breed, feed, and care for mosquitoes and they all worked in harmony doing their<lb/>
special duties. Carroll was completely wrapped up with his intestinal flora job<lb/>
and I never saw him do anything else until after he recovered from yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>Page 39</hi>-</p>
<p>As the experiments had scarcely begun when Reed was as Pinar del Rio, I<lb/>
doubt if he thought of <hi>fomites</hi> at all. It was Gorgas who continued to disinfect<lb/>
homes in Havana after the Board's reports were published. (Pgs. 184-185.)</p>
<p>&ldquo;Urged by the younger members of the Board&rdquo;. No doubt Lazear did urge Reed to<lb/>
begin testing Finlay's theory, but Carroll and Agramonte probably did not.<lb/>
Lazear was not an entomologist but was much interested and had done much work<lb/>
in studying mosquitoes. Reed felt that the Board's work in studying Sanarelli's<lb/>
theory, as Wasdin and Geddings had done on fresh cases of yellow fever, must be<lb/>
completed first. (See Pg. 87.) Then they could take up the mosquito theory.<lb/>
However, he and Lazear did start the breeding of mosquitoes and I saw then at<lb/>
&cross; <hi>this work</hi> about the middle of July, 1900. (Pgs. 90-93 and 103-104.) Work on<lb/>
the Sanarelli theory was then concluded and Reed left for Washington on August 2<lb/>
to finish the typhoid fever report and Lazear was given the go-ahead signal with<lb/>
infected mosquitoes. (Pgs. 101-104.)</p>
<p><hi>Page 40</hi>-</p>
<p>Lazear was not immune. If Hammeter credits Dr. Welch as saying that Carroll<lb/>
was &ldquo;the real hero&rdquo;, I think he meant that because he was the first case of<lb/>
experimental yellow fever, and not the &ldquo;accurate and flawless leader in the work&rdquo;.<lb/>
Hammeter's statement should not be accepted as a fact unless it can be shown when,<lb/>
<add>See p 233 Sen. Doc. last par. Kean wrote this himself<lb/>
and it shows that Finlay was visited early after arrival<lb/>
of Reed in Cuba on June 25, 1900<lb/></add>
<pb n="3" id="f06504040"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
Mrs. Mary W. Standlee<lb/>
where, and to whom it was made. I think Dr. Welch's letter to the Secretary of<lb/>
War should be copied in full in your story to counteract anything so completely<lb/>
false. I know - for I was there; and further, my book tells why Carroll was<lb/>
unable to be of any help to Reed or Lazear during his illness and long convalescence.<lb/>
For the Welch statement, see Senate Document 822, 1911, Page 20. Right here,<lb/>
you should also quote Gen. Leonard Wood's statement in full. (Also in Senate<lb/>
Document 822, 1911, Page 20.)</p>
<p>I am much perturbed by your failure to bring out the splendid things said about<lb/>
Reed, especially in that wonderful book, Senate Document 822, 1911, prepared<lb/>
by Gen. Kean. He wrote most of the text not long after the work in Cuba so that<lb/>
is reliable. Why not give both sides of the controversy?</p>
<p>I also wish to state that since about 1938, Gen. Kean, Dr. Hench and I have been<lb/>
constantly working on this yellow fever episode and trying to help Dr. Hench in<lb/>
getting factual data on things in my book which were based on my memory and those<lb/>
of doctors and enlisted men who were in Cuba with me. So far I think that<lb/>
nothing of importance has been found wrong. I suggest that you follow<lb/>
Dr. Hench's advice carefully. Hammeter was no authority on the subject and<lb/>
I expect that there are others in Washington who are in the same category.<lb/>
Much of your story about the work done fifty years ago is from the memory of<lb/>
<add>not</add><lb/>
people who were <add>not</add> in Cuba and therefore it is hearsay. In this yellow fever<lb/>
episode, we must be factual and demand facts before we print them.</p>
<p>Unless you can finally summarize all the conflicting statements and give Reed<lb/>
the credit of being the master mind in the Board's work, as shown by the<lb/>
statements of the Secretary of War, Dr. Welch, General Leonard Wood, Gens.<lb/>
Sternberg, McCaw, Kean and others in Senate Document 822, 1911, I would not<lb/>
like to see this Chapter published in connection with a history of the<lb/>
Walter Reed Army Hospital - the great memorial to Walter Reed.</p>
<p>Professor Welch was a good friend of mine and when he came to see Gen. Ireland,<lb/>
which was often, he had to pass through my office (SGO Executive Officer) and<lb/>
often, especially when the Surgeon General was away, he talked with me about<lb/>
Reed's work and my experiences in Cuba. He was truly a great medical man and<lb/>
when he stated &ldquo;I am in a position to know that the credit for the original<lb/>
ideas embodied in this work (yellow fever experiments) belongs wholly to<lb/>
Maj. Reed&rdquo;, it seems to me Dr. Hammeter's statement unsupported by documentary<lb/>
facts re the statement has no place in your history; likewise, when Gen. Leonard<lb/>
Wood, who, as Governor General of Cuba, gave Reed so much time and assistance<lb/>
says: &ldquo;His work was the originating, directing, and controlling mind in this<lb/>
work, and the others were assistants only&rdquo;. I was there and I know these<lb/>
statements are true.</p>
<p>AET</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>I wrote the above in longhand two days ago but had to stop as I was completely<lb/>
worn out by my efforts to hurry up as you requested. I tried to save myself<lb/>
by giving page references from my book and leaving the writing for you. However,<lb/>
I exploded as you see for on this subject I get too excited and upset for my own<lb/>
good. I have left things just as they were for, on my doctor's advice, it is<lb/>
time to stop all work of this kind for some time. On his advice and also on<lb/>
Mrs. Truby's insistence, I am therefore compelled, but with sincere regret, to<lb/>
return your manuscript without further review by me. Of course you will be<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="f06504041"/>
- 4 -<lb/>
Mrs. Mary W. Standlee.<lb/>
shocked by this turn of events but it can't be helped.<lb/>
<add>Don't blame yourself,<lb/>
it could not have been<lb/>
prevented.</add><lb/>
<hi>AET</hi></p>
<p>I have been most interested in Gen. Love's comments and of all the retired<lb/>
officers of the Corps in Washington, you can not, I think, find a more<lb/>
competent and honest advisor on this yellow fever episode.</p>
<p>The Senate Document 822, 1911 has long been &ldquo;my bible&rdquo; in this work. It was<lb/>
thrown together hurriedly by our lamented friend, Gen. Kean, so there were<lb/>
many errors but by correspondence I know the correct answer to most of them.<lb/>
I hope you will refer to it more frequently.</p>
<p>One last suggestion which you may not like. Why try to solve these controversies<lb/>
in your story when we know that Dr. Hench has made and continues to make the<lb/>
most factual and complete investigation on the whole subject, and that he will<lb/>
publish it as soon as he possibly can? <add>No one can or even will try to do<lb/>
what he has done on this subject. His will be the last word</add></p>
<p>If at any time there is any question that I can answer, don't hesitate to call<lb/>
on me. However, I must not undertake any long and tedious work.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Sig AET</signed>
<seg>
P.S. Yours of the 22nd just came and I think that fills the bill splendidly.<lb/>
I have made a few changes in pencil on it (mms) which you can change if it is<lb/>
OK. <add>with you</add><lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
