<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06501106">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, February 4, 1950</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Lambert, Gustaf E.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06501106</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1950-02-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Mazzuri, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Martinez, Jose</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Warner, Lena</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Collins Park, Miami (Fla.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Yellow Fever Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Havana Hospital (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Post Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1950-02-04">February 4, 1950</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06501106</idno>
<title>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, February 4, 1950</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Lambert promotes the work that Ames did in caring for yellow fever patients during the experiments. He thinks Ames did not get the recognition due him. He also points out that he, Lambert, was the only one who volunteered to care for patients.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1950-02-04">
<head>Letter from Gustaf E. Lambert to Albert E. Truby, February 4, 1950</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06501106"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
121 Morris Blvd.<lb/>
Birmingham, Alabama<lb/>
<date value="1950-02-04">February 4, 1950</date>
</dateline>
Gen. Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, Calif.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It took me a long time to get the name of the man who was supposed to take<lb/>
care of work while Dr. Ames was sick. I attended V.F.W. convention at<lb/>
Miami, then went over to Havana. On my way back I visited Hanberry who<lb/>
gave me the clipping which I had photographed. Hundreds of thousands<lb/>
might have read the article and though Mazzuri a wonderful man. Dr.<lb/>
Hench told me that General Order 83 did not make Dr. Ames a member of the<lb/>
Board in place of Dr. Lazear, but only the physician. Could it have been<lb/>
necessary for Maj. Reed to ask for Dr. Ames's service when he had already<lb/>
had charge of yellow fever hospital during the epidemic? Even treated two<lb/>
members of the Board and the first authentic case &ldquo;Dean!&rdquo; Was it not<lb/>
rather for the part each one played in making the experiment a success that<lb/>
honors were bestowed? If membership in the Board was all that was needed<lb/>
in order to be honored, then I can honestly say Agramonti got his medal<lb/>
easy! I know there are hospitals, university buildings, statues, and<lb/>
monuments and other things erected to honor men who took part in the work,<lb/>
but for Dr. Ames not as much as a little stone to mark his last resting<lb/>
place. I have visited at his grave in one of the cemeteries in New Orleans.<lb/>
If Maj. Reed did not ask for Dr. Ames to be a member of the Board I can't<lb/>
see why he went out to Camp Lazear. His work as a physician was at the<lb/>
hospital.</p>
<p>Has a physician the right to innoculate a man with disease just for the fun<lb/>
of seeing if he can cure him later on? Dr. Ames did so. I helped when<lb/>
Jernegan received innoculation from Martinez and, General, you would surely<lb/>
have thought attending physicians under your command had lost their minds<lb/>
if you had found them feeding mosquitos on their patients just for a<lb/>
pastime<unclear>,</unclear> Dr<unclear>.</unclear> Ames was the only one that fed mosquitos down in our hospital.<lb/>
After Dr. Carroll tried to feed on the first Spaniard and was kicked in the<lb/>
belly by the man, he never tried again. If Dr. Ames had been unlucky in<lb/>
his treatment like the doctors at Pinar Del Rio where they had several<lb/>
deaths and diagnosed these cases as <unclear>pernicious malaria</unclear> (you will recall<lb/>
that happened about three weeks before we started the Yellow Fever Hospital<lb/>
at Quemados) or as told in the book &ldquo;Major Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo; by<lb/>
Dr. Kelly. It is stated by Nurse Werner that Maj. Gorgas lost <hi>only five</hi><lb/>
cases the week she was there (Page 236) or as the bad luck they again had<lb/>
at Las Animas in August, when the world's greatest expert (?) Guiteras took<lb/>
part. I am certain that none would have offered themselves as guinea pigs<lb/>
if Dr. Ames had lost only two or three during the summer, even though $200<lb/>
was a big sum of money in those days!</p>
<p>General, you told me in one of your letters you were a Mason. If so, I know<lb/>
you have sworn not to let a wrong be done to a man if you could prevent<lb/>
it. I can't help thinking that a wrong was done to Brother Ames. Neither<lb/>
can I help thinking that only a word from you could correct that injustice.<lb/>
I will always believe that Dr. Ames's unusual ability of quick diagnosis<lb/>
and treatment made the experiment possible.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very respectfully yours,</salute>
<signed>Gust E. Lambert</signed>
(Continued)<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06501107"/>
-2-<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. I enclose some pictures I took while in Havana Hospital with grounds<lb/>
where Columbia Hospital used to be, Monument of Dr. <unclear>Finley</unclear> standing as<lb/>
near as I could figure out where Dr. Lazear's <unclear>laboratory</unclear> used to stand<lb/>
and statue of Dr. <unclear>Finley</unclear> in Collins Park, Miami, Florida.<lb/>
General Order 83 was not found with Dr. Ames's service record but in<lb/>
Day Book from General Lee's Headquarters found in the archives.<lb/>
For myself - I know Major Reed would not have innoculated anyone with<lb/>
yellow fever except if he knew there was someone to care for the patient.<lb/>
I was the only one to volunteer.<lb/>
No need to return.<lb/>
Lambert<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
