<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06509001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Lecture: Sanitary Work in Cuba, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [May 2, 1910]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06509001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1910-05-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Havard, Valery</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Black, William M.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Barton, Clara</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>22 pp.</extent>
<date value="1910-05-02">May 2, 1910</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06509001</idno>
<title>Lecture: Sanitary Work in Cuba, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [May 2, 1910]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Kean] gives a brief summary of conditions in Cuba before the arrival of the Yellow Fever Board. He provides an account of the activities of the Board, which ultimately shows the mosquito as the bearer of yellow fever. Included are notes by Truby.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1910-05-02">
<head>Lecture: Sanitary Work in Cuba, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [May 2, 1910]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06509001"/>
<p>I have never seen or heard<lb/>
of this splendid paper by Kean.</p>
<p>I have underlined a few<lb/>
places in pencil. &ldquo;Lazear wrote&rdquo;<lb/>
p. 7 (Agramonte says we wrote.)</p>
<p>I think K was wrong, in his<lb/>
surmise that Lazear did not tell<lb/>
xy of the possible danger of an<lb/>
infected mosquito bite. So I question<lb/>
that on p 7. Otherwise his story<lb/>
is just about the best account<lb/>
of things that I know of. It<lb/>
would have helped me a lot<lb/>
if I had had it when I<lb/>
started out to tell my story.</p>
<p><hi>AEt</hi></p>
<pb n="2" id="f06509002"/>
<p>Kean </p>
<p><hi>Sanitary Work in Cuba</hi>.<lb/>
First Introduction</p>
<p>Before the outbreak of the Spanish War the Army was as placid and pacific an<lb/>
institution as the sun looked down upon in his diurnal journey. Lookping back from<lb/>
the strenuousness of the succeeding decade we can truly say in the words of the<lb/>
Psalmist that &ldquo;its ways were ways of pleasantness and all its paths were peace&rdquo;.<lb/>
The Medical Department shared in the I nocuous desuetude of this idylic existence<lb/>
and was a very subordinate factor of military life. I cannot recall in the 14 years<lb/>
of my service previous to 1898 any mention of the Medical Department in the Reports<lb/>
of the Secretary of War or the speeches or messages of the President or in any im-<lb/>
portant publication. Since the beginning of the new era our Corps and its works are<lb/>
much in the public eye and are frequently in evidence in the utterances and writings<lb/>
of the President and the Secretary of War. Our <hi>status</hi> has greatly changed and grown<lb/>
in importance. Without disparagement to the excellent work which has been done by<lb/>
the Medical Corps in Porto Rico the Philippines the Isthmus of Panama and elsewhere<lb/>
it is not too much to say that this change is due in great part to the sanitary re-<lb/>
generation of Cuba and primarily to the extinction of yellow fever in the Island.</p>
<p>It seems not unreasonable therefore that the President of this School should<lb/>
desire that <del>this the largest class in its history</del><add>the medical officers just intering the service</add> should have some familiarity with<lb/>
the details of that glorious work, and should demand them of one who was on the<lb/>
ground and in intimate association with the principal performers. <del>My only regret<lb/>
is that I have not the practice and facility in speaking to which you are accustomed<lb/>
in the learned professors who usually occupy this platform which would enable me to<lb/>
give to the story the interest which it deserves.</del></p>
<p><del>I think that it is safe to assume that you are all familiar with the classical<lb/>
experiments of the Reed Commission and with the general results of the application<lb/>
of the mosquito theory by Gorgas, so I will not go into these, but will if you will<lb/>
pardon a rather personal and remniscent narrative, give you a brief account of con-<lb/>
ditions in Cuba before these experiments</del> <add>same unpublished details with regard to them</add> <del>and then a few points in practical sanitary</del><lb/>
<add>Lecture given before Army Med<lb/>
School May 2 1910 and May 22 1912</add></p>
<pb n="3" id="f06509003"/>
<p>It is safe to assume that you all have a general familiarity with<lb/>
the classical experiments of the Reed Commission, but I think for members<lb/>
of the Medical Corps of the Army a somewhat more intimate and accurate<lb/>
knowledge should be expected and I have arranged to have placed in your<lb/>
hands for the future personal use of each a copy of the Compilation <add>made by Capt <unclear>Sen</unclear> of the S.G.O. and</add> print-<lb/>
ed by Congress <add>at the request of the S. G.</add> which includes all of Reeds own reports of his work in<lb/>
Cuba, together with articles throwing light upon other parts of this great<lb/>
work by Carroll, Gorgas, Finlay and Havard. The memorand<add>a</add>ums in the 3rd<lb/>
and 4th chapters were prepared by me and include I believe the names of<lb/>
all individuals who took part, either as conductors or as the subjects of<lb/>
these experiments. As the story is told fully and in official form in<lb/>
this valuable publication, I will not go into details which are <del>told in it</del><add>narrated <unclear>there</unclear></add><lb/>
but<add>,</add> if you will pardon a rather personal and reminiscent narrative, I will<lb/>
give you a brief account of conditions in Cuba before the arrival of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Board and some unpublished details with regard to their work.</p>
<p>When Santiago was captured by our troops it presented all the horrors<lb/>
of a besieged city. Bodies of men and animals, dead of wounds or<lb/>
disease were scattered through the streets <add>and houses</add> and as all sanitary services<lb/>
had been abandoned during the siege the accumulation of filth made the<lb/>
condition of affairs intolerable. General Leonard Wood was placed<lb/>
in command of the city and the conquered territory and the energy and<lb/>
thoroughness with which he brought the city into a good sanitary condition<lb/>
and organized a government attracted wide-spread attention and laid the<lb/>
foundation of his future career. Colonel Valery Havard was appointed<lb/>
<del>as</del> chief surgeon on August 7, 1898 and continued as chief surgeon of the<lb/>
department of Santiago until his transfer in 1900 to Havana where he<lb/>
occupied a like position for the division of Cuba.</p>
<p>2</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06509004"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>I accompanied the 7th Army Corps to Cuba, being Chief Surgeon, 1st Division<lb/>
and landed in Havana Dec. 28, 1898, just in time to be with my Division Commander<lb/>
Gen. Keifer (<del>now</del><add>lately</add> a representative in Congress from Ohio) at the imposing ceremonies<lb/>
incident to the transfer of the Sovereignty over Cuba from Spain to the United States.<lb/>
Sitting on our horses on the Prado we saw the red and yellow flag hauled down from<lb/>
the flagstaff of the Morro where it has floated for nearly four centuries <add>(</add>with one<lb/>
brief interruption,<add>)</add> and saw its place taken by the Stars and Stripes. Three years<lb/>
and five months later I saw the American flag give place on the same staff to the<lb/>
Cuban.</p>
<p>Cuba was for the purposes of government a military division divided in 1898<lb/>
into seven military departments corresponding in limits to the six provinces and the<lb/>
city of Havana. The number of departments was reduced after Gen. Leonard Wood was<lb/>
transferred from Santiago to Havana as the successor to Gen. Brooke and after a couple<lb/>
of years Cuba was made one single Department.</p>
<p>The whole country outside of the cities was laid waste and the latter were fill<del>ing</del><add>ed</add><lb/>
with starving reconcentrados, who had to be furnished food and tools and work animals<lb/>
in order to be established in their desolate homes in the country. The cities were<lb/>
in a state of indiscribable filth and neglect and in every tained breeze we feared to<lb/>
inhale the mysterious infection of the dreaded yellow fever. There was no central<lb/>
sanitary organization but each of the even Chief Surgeons went bravely to work to<lb/>
solve his own problems without other expert assistance than the oc<add>c</add>a<del>s</del>sional advice of<lb/>
the Chief Surgeon of the Division whose supervision was however confined largely to<lb/>
the military administration. This lack of bureaucratic organization lasted through-<lb/>
out the period of the first intervention, and it is highly creditable to the medical<lb/>
officers and others concerned in the sanitary work of the military government that<lb/>
such good results were attained under so loose a system.</p>
<p>In Havana where were the greatest problems, Major Gorgas was Chief Surgeon, but<lb/>
3</p>
<pb n="5" id="f06509005"/>
<p>Within a few months after the establishment of American control<lb/>
Havana and the other principal cities of Cuba were clean, the streets<lb/>
were being repaired, and garbage regularly removed. This service was in<lb/>
Havana under an officer of the Engineer Department, Col. Wm. M. Black, and<lb/>
was admirably organized, the relation of the Sanitary Department to it being<lb/>
inspectorial only. The placing of houses and private premises in a<lb/>
sanitary condition was in charge of the Sanitary Department and was like-<lb/>
wise carried on with great energy. The first cleaning up was done by<lb/>
the sanitary gangs and householders were thereafter required to maintain<lb/>
a proper state of cleanliness. The organization of the other and more<lb/>
technical functions of a Sanitary Department such as the collection of<lb/>
vital statistics, the reporting and investigation of contagious diseases,<lb/>
the establishment of laboratories, the enforcement of vaccination, etc.,<lb/>
took a longer time.</p>
<pb n="6" id="f06509006"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>during the first year, he was not permitted to have any thing to do with the sanitary<lb/>
administration of the City which was under a volunteer surgeon better known for per-<lb/>
sonal energy than for scientific attainment. When some comment was made to the<lb/>
General who was Governor of the city<add>,</add> a distinguished officer of Engineers, as to the<lb/>
peculiarity of this arrangement he was said to have replied &ldquo;Oh in that matter I pre-<lb/>
fer to furnish my own brains&rdquo; When in Dec. 1899 he offered me the position of Chief<lb/>
Sanitary Officer of Havana I was compelled to think the compliment a somewhat dubious<lb/>
one. Early in 1900 however both this General and his energetic sanitary officer de-<lb/>
parted for the Philippines. The city of Havana was added to the Department of Gen.<lb/>
Fitzhugh Lee on whose staff I was serving as Chief Surgeon and Major Gorgas became<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer of the city reporting directly to Gen. Wood who <add>had</add> came into su-<lb/>
preme command of the Island.</p>
<p>The work of the Sanitary Department <add>in Havana</add> consisted in house-to-house inspections of<lb/>
dwelling houses, shops, factories, stables, &amp;c., with the enforcement of sanitary con-<lb/>
ditions - the disinfections of cases of infectious disease including very extensive<lb/>
disinfections of houses, clothing, &amp;c., for yellow fever, the regulation of the markets<lb/>
and the collection of vital statistics. <add><del>Within a few months</del> after the establishment<lb/>
<del>American control the city was</del> clean <del>and garbage</del> regularly removed. The <unclear>organi-<lb/>
tion</unclear> of the other function of a sanitary department took longer.</add></p>
<p>I was doing work of the same sort in the garrisoned towns of the Province of<lb/>
Havana and Pinar del Rio and had in addition the care of the orphan asylums which had<lb/>
been established by Miss Clara Barton, President at that time of the American Red<lb/>
Cross Society. This benevolent lady after renting the houses, employing teachers<lb/>
and servants and collecting all that she could of the abundant crop of orphans left<lb/>
by the victims of the reconcentration calmly sailed away to the United States without<lb/>
provision for house-rents, services, or food, leaving the military Governor to hold<lb/>
the bag. This Gen. Brooke promptly passed on to Gen. Lee and he in turn to his chief<lb/>
surgeon. Thus I acquired 16 orphan asylums in one day. There were moreover public<lb/>
hospitals in all the larger towns crowded with unhappy creatures perishing in filth<lb/>
and neglect from every variety of disease. These had all been brought into order<lb/>
4<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f06509007"/>
4<lb/>
and fairly good administration by April 1900. <add>Col. E. St. John Guble F. A is <unclear>entitle</unclear><lb/>
to the credit of first bringing order &amp; good administration into the institutions<lb/>
under the Dept. of Charities. I succeeded him as Supt. of beneficincia in Gen. Woods Staff in April 1901.</add></p>
<p>Early in May <del>of</del><add>1900</add> Gen. Wood came out on a visit to Gen. <add>Fitz</add> Lee at Marianao<lb/>
the town which was the Headquarters of the latter and near the post of Columbia Bar-<lb/>
racks where were 1200 American Soldiers<add>,</add> and <add>he</add> remarked that it was cleaner than any New<lb/>
England Village. The inhabitants endured our scrubbings and sweepings and disinfec-<lb/>
tions with patient good humor accompanied by many shrugs, and the only Kick which I<lb/>
recall was against the use of carbolic acid to disinfect cesspools because they said<lb/>
it gave a bad taste to the water in the wells! We had all accepted the doctrine<lb/>
that yellow fever was a filth disease and great was our consternation to find that<lb/>
summer that cleanliness was no protection, and the disease which we all so frankly<lb/>
dreaded went through Havana <add>and</add> Marianao, like a fire. In Marianao we finally only<lb/>
checked it by forceably expelling from town all non-immunes and putting them in Camp.</p>
<p>It was in the midst of this epidemic on June 25th that Major Reed and Dr. Carroll<lb/>
came to Cuba and organized the Yellow Fever Board, Drs. Lazear and Agramonte being<lb/>
already there. I was at the time sick with the disease and Reed came the day he<lb/>
landed out to the hospital at Columbia Barracks to see me. I believe that I was the<lb/>
first yellow fever patient which he had ever seen for tho he had been in Havana for<lb/>
three weeks in March. <add>to investigate the use of electrozine as a disinfectant</add> there was then very little fever in the city. The Board spent<lb/>
the month of July in searching for the bacillus icteroides of Sanarelli both in the<lb/>
blood and excretions of the sick and in the organs of the dead and was able to show<lb/>
in 18 cases that it was not present, thus giving a final quietus to Sanarelli's<lb/>
claims.</p>
<p>Reed and Agramonte had however in July investigated a sharp epidemic among the<lb/>
American troops at Pinar del Rio and were particularly struck with the fact that a<lb/>
prisoner in the guard house had been attacked altho he could not have been in any<lb/>
infected locality and Dr. Agramonte says that the possibility of mosquito infection<lb/>
was discussed with reference to this case and it was determined to try it. <add>Carter's -<lb/>
observation.</add></p>
<p>Dr. Carroll has stated that the final decision to make experiments on human<lb/>
5<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="f06509008"/>
5<lb/>
beings was made the night before Reed returned on August 1st to Washington to com-<lb/>
plete <add>the</add> publication of the great Report on Typhoid Fever in the Volunteer Camps by<lb/>
Reed. Vaughan and Shakespeare. <add>(work on)</add>The Board had before this talked on the subject with<lb/>
Dr. Carlos J. Finlay. of Havana, who had maintained in numerous publications since<lb/>
1881 the mosquito transmission of yellow fever and had made between that date and<lb/>
Reed's first report no less than 103 experiments on human beings to demonstrate his<lb/>
theory.-<del>yet latho he had selected the right species of mosquito as the carrier he<lb/>
did not succeed in producing the disease in a single case. The shortest interval.</del><lb/>
</p>
<p>It is very interesting to study these cases which were recorded in a careful<lb/>
and scientific manner, for they show the extraordinary difficulties which the be-<lb/>
ginners in this field had to encounter, and illustrate the admirable acumen with<lb/>
which Reed drew his conclusions. Dr. Finlay reports 16 cases out of 103 as success-<lb/>
ful but in order to do so he had to extend the incubation period to 25 days, altho.<lb/>
In none of Reed's or Guiteras cases was the incubation period longer than 6 days.<lb/>
Also it is my understanding that many of these cases were exposed to other sources<lb/>
of infection. Rejecting the cases in which the incubation period was more than 6<lb/>
days we have left four in none of which was there albuminuria and only one of which<lb/>
presented the clinical symptoms of yellow fever. In none of these cases was the<lb/>
mosquito infected by a case in the first three days of the disease and in none of<lb/>
them had a longer period than 6 days elapsed since the mosquito had bitten the<lb/>
infecting case and so was not ripe.</p>
<p>Applying our present knowledge that cases of yellow fever can only infect mos-<lb/>
quitos in the first three days of the disease and secondly that a period of twelve<lb/>
days must then pass before the mosquito becomes ripe and able to convey the infection.<lb/>
we find that none of Dr. Finlay's cases fulfilled both of these conditions, and so<lb/>
in 20 years of work <add>we</add> can safely say that he did not produce a single case of experi-<lb/>
mental yellow fever. And yet with what Gorgas called &ldquo;splendid scientific clairvoy-<lb/>
ance&rdquo; he held to his theory with unshaken tenacity.</p>
<p>6</p>
<pb n="9" id="f06509009"/>
<p>6</p>
<p>It was between these two stools of the short infecting stage in the human patient<lb/>
and the long incubation stage in the mosquito that Lazear fell in his first 9 experi-<lb/>
ments all of which were failures, much to the discouragement of the Board. In the<lb/>
two other cases of this series those of Carroll and X.Y. the mosquito had become ripe<lb/>
and he promptly got results. The case X. <del>X</del><add>Y</add>. was bitten on August 31st the day that Dr.<lb/>
Carroll was taken sick but before his sickness was recognized, and I think that it<lb/>
deserves some mention on account of the immense importance of it.</p>
<p>Dr. Carroll who was at that time somewhat skeptical in the matter of mosquito<lb/>
transmission had vitiated the value of his attack as a scientific experiment by going<lb/>
into the infected zone and even to the yellow fever hospital after he was bitten and<lb/>
during the period of incubation, and so it was on this case X.Y. that Reed rested the<lb/>
burden of his proof in his Preliminary Note. It was <add>the</add> X.Y. case which convinced him.<lb/>
AEJ</p>
<p>Reed was you remember in Washington in August and September and <hi>Lazear wrote</hi> to<lb/>
him the account of these two cases. I happened to be in the city of Matanzas on Oct.<lb/>
3rd when the transport came into that port with Reed on board and I went out to see him.<lb/>
It was there that I heard for the first time the true story of X.Y. which had been kept<lb/>
by Lazear a close secret. He wrote it to Reed but it is my impression that he told no<lb/>
one <add>at Camp. Columbia and J. altho. Ch. Surgeon of the Dept. and living only half an<lb/>
mile from the hospital knew nothing of the facts in the case.</add></p>
<p>The story is this:- On the morning of Aug. 31st Lazear took seven mosquitos in-<lb/>
cluding four that had bitten yellow fever patients, one of them being the insect which<lb/>
had bitten Carroll 4 days <add>b</add>efore, into a ward of the hospital at Columbia Barracks and<lb/>
said &ldquo;Who will feed my mosquitos&rdquo;. A good natured cavalryman, <add><unclear>suffering or</unclear></add> offered to do so.<lb/>
AET</p>
<p>Whether he was told that the <hi>mosquitos had bitten yellow fever patients I do not know</hi> ?<lb/>
but as these mosquitos had uniformly failed so far to cause infection the matter was<lb/>
probably not regarded as very risky by Lazear and it is my impression that he did not<lb/>
mention it. Next day the soldier was returned to duty and on Sept. 5th came back to<lb/>
Hospital with yellow fever. Columbia barracks was at that time under strict quarrantine<lb/>
which it was proved the soldier had observed so he had not been otherwise exposed and<lb/>
7<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06509010"/>
7<lb/>
the case was clear.</p>
<p>But the dread of yellow fever was so great and the orders of the military author-<lb/>
ities so strict on the subject of exposure that it is probable that if the commanding<lb/>
officer had found out that a purposely infected soldier had been let loose in the<lb/>
midst of his 1200 non-immune men there would have been a great row and probably some<lb/>
court-martials. So the man's name was concealed and Reed in writing his preliminary<lb/>
note did not admit that he was a soldier. I laughed much at his efforts to conceal<lb/>
this fact and told him that if he suppressed too many details the scientists would not<lb/>
believe him while if he told them the military authorities would get him.</p>
<p>A year later when Carroll infected two soldiers Privates Hamann and Covington of<lb/>
the Coast Artillery with filtered blood their commanding officer started out to make<lb/>
trouble about it. But the victory had been won. Havana was free from yellow fever<lb/>
and every one was happy and proud of this great triumph of our Corps. Besides it was<lb/>
well known that the great authority of General Wood was behind these experiments. So<lb/>
the communications of this officer were quietly pigeon-holed. But it would have<lb/>
probably been far different in 1900.</p>
<p>It is however desirable now that this probably unconscious volunteer should have<lb/>
his name added to the roll of honor and so <del>a few days since</del><add>in 1910</add> I collected all the data<lb/>
concerning him and had no difficulty in identifying his name on the Report of Sick and<lb/>
Wounded of Columbia Barracks for Sept. 1900, as that of Pvt. William H. Dean, Troop B.<lb/>
7th Cavalry, born in Ohio, aged 27 years.</p>
<p>I hope that the day is not far off when Congress will erect a statute to Walter<lb/>
Reed in this city and that its pedestal will bear on three sides the portraits in<lb/>
base-relief of Carroll, Lazear and Agremonte, while the fourth should contain the names<lb/>
of those who submitted to these famous experiments. In this list the name of William<lb/>
H. Dean should come next below that of Carroll.</p>
<p>8</p>
<pb n="11" id="f06509011"/>
<p>8</p>
<p>To return to Dr. Finlay: He was able to indicate to Reed the actual variety of<lb/>
mosquito which was the transmitter of the disease and to present him with its eggs<lb/>
for breeding purposes. This suggestion must have been of much assistance to Reed's<lb/>
Board for if they had begun with any other variety the technical difficulties of<lb/>
breeding and handling the insects would have been far greater and the patience of the<lb/>
Board might not have like that of Dr. Finlay stood the test of a long series of<lb/>
failures. The stegomyia is a domesticated and tractible insect which breeds well<lb/>
in captivity and is perfectly willing to bite any fist which is thrust into its jar.<lb/>
In fact it can be carried in the pocket in a test tube plugged with cotton, and if<lb/>
the plug is withdrawn and the mouth of the tube placed upon the patient's skin it<lb/>
will promptly descend and bite. The common brown culex pungens cannot be got to<lb/>
bite in this way, and in an experiment of Reed's with pungens he could only get them<lb/>
to bite by placing them inside the mosquito bar of the patient. When he went to<lb/>
collect them in the morning he found that the Spanish patient had taken his revenge<lb/>
on them by killing them all. I think this ended the experiments with pungens</p>
<p>A couple of yeras ago I had occasion to ask Dr. Guiteras to make some experiments<lb/>
to determine if mosquitos could get through wire gauze 16 meshes to the inch. He re-<lb/>
ported that stegomyia could not, and I then suggested that he repeat the experiment<lb/>
with pungens and anopheles when he protested humorously against having to work with<lb/>
such wild creatures which insisted on dying and did not have the charming docility<lb/>
of stegomyia.</p>
<p>But the preservation of even this gentle insect had its difficulties, one of<lb/>
which was their liability to be devoured by a tiny red ant which was omnipresent<lb/>
in Cuba. I remember one big jar of infected mosquitos nearly ripe at Camp Lazear<lb/>
which were all devoured in one night in spite of jars of water under the legs of the<lb/>
table on which it sat. It was found that the cord of the window shade had been<lb/>
allowed to touch the table and had thus made a suspension bridge over which the ants<lb/>
had made their foray.</p>
<p>9</p>
<pb n="12" id="f06509012"/>
<p>9<lb/>
10</p>
<p>To Reed's mind the case of Dean reenforced by that of Carroll established the<lb/>
theory and his quick mind saw in a flash the vast importance of it. After the fate<lb/>
of Lazear and the experience of Carroll he hardly expected that new volunteers would<lb/>
be forthcoming. So in a visit to me at Gen. Lee's headquarters on Oct. 12th he told<lb/>
me that he was going to Havana next morning to ask General Wood's permission to go<lb/>
back to the United States, announce the discovery at the approaching meeting of the<lb/>
American Public Health Association and consult Gen. Sternberg on what should be the<lb/>
next step.</p>
<p>I told him I would drive him down in <del>the</del> General' <del>a</del><add>Lee's</add> carriage, and after we started<lb/>
unfolded to him a scheme which had occurred to me. This was that as all Spaniards<lb/>
when they came to Cuba landed with the expectation of getting yellow fever, it would<lb/>
not be difficult with the help of money to persuade them to have their attack by<lb/>
experimental inoculation. So Reed was to ask Gen. Wood for the money, and the quar-<lb/>
antine camps at <hi>Triscornia</hi> where Spanish immigrants were at that time detained for<lb/>
their own protection until they should get employment, was to furnish the Spaniards.<lb/>
<hi>AEJ</hi></p>
<p>I shall never forget the faces of the two men <add>as</add> we stood in a window of the Palace<lb/>
at Havana looking out on the Plaza de Armas, and Reed with that lucidity and force of<lb/>
speech which was characteristic of him told his story while Gen. Wood listened grave<lb/>
impassive but alert. The two men knew each other well for Wood had taken a special<lb/>
course at this school under Reed only three years before when a Captain in the Medical<lb/>
Corps and assistant to the attending surgeon in this city. When Reed finished he<lb/>
looked at Gen. Wood a moment and then asked if the General would give him <del>the money</del><add>#10000</add> to<lb/>
employ Spaniards and continue the experiments. Instantly came the reply &ldquo;I will give you<lb/>
<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear> thousand dollars</del><add>the money</add> and if that is not enough I will give you $100,000 more. I have<lb/>
today given a large sum for the secret service and this is certainly vastly of greater<lb/>
importance to Cuba than the catching of a few rogues&rdquo;. <add>Take no men who are not<lb/>
sound in mind &amp; body and of legal age by the Spanish law</add></p>
<p>We then went to lunch and I drank to a good voyage and to the great fame which<lb/>
would surely come to him. In less than three weeks he was <add>b</add>ack again and the money<lb/>
was placed by Gen. Wood's order to my credit <add>for disbursement</add> and we began to build the experiment<add>al</add></p>
<pb n="13" id="f06509013"/>
<p><hi rend="superscript">2</hi> But at first he did not expect much of it &amp; confesses in an report;</p>
<p>&ldquo;I had very little hope of accomplishing much; it seemed to me that even<lb/>
if the mosquito did convey yellow fever, he could not be gotten rid of, and,<lb/>
apparently, from all past experience, the mosquito was not the only way, or<lb/>
even the principal way, of conveying the disease. But as he evidently could<lb/>
convey the disease, it was our duty to take precautions in this direction. . . .<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06509014"/>
10<lb/>
station at Camp Lazear. From this point on I imagine the story is familiar to you all.</p>
<p>The conversion of Gorgas to the new theory was complete by the first of February<lb/>
1901, and during that month he began to make practical application of it<unclear>.</unclear> In his &cross;<lb/>
sanitary report for the month of February which is dated March 6th he says:<lb/>
&ldquo;During February 1900 we had 17 cases of yellow fever, in Feb. of 1901 we had 8<lb/>
new cases. As the number of non-immunes was very much larger in Feb. of this<lb/>
than in that of last year I think the showing is encouraging. Besides disinfecting the<lb/>
houses with formaline and other disinfectants we <del>could</del> screen the rooms occupied by<lb/>
a yellow fever patient as soon as his case is reported and kill all the mosquitos in<lb/>
the building with fumes of pyrethrum powder, at the same time covering with kerosene<lb/>
oil all places where mosquitos can breed about the building. We also kill the mosquitos<lb/>
in all the adjoining buildings in the same way. With these measures and the steps we<lb/>
are taking to kill the mosquitos in the suburbs I hope to markedly decrease the yellow<lb/>
fever in the coming summer.</p>
<p>The history of yellow fever in Havana shows that in Jan. Feb. and March there is<lb/>
a gradual decrease<add>,</add> these cases being the a<del>l</del><add>f</add>termath of the preceding year, and after the<lb/>
first of April it begins to slowly increase again and so it was the custom of sanitarian<lb/>
to count the epidemic year for yellow fever to begin April 1st. It was then a very<lb/>
favorable time for Gorgas to begin his campaign when the number of mosquitos was at<lb/>
the minimum - and also the number of cases.</p>
<p>The method of work and the difficulties encountered are very well told in a report<lb/>
dated Dec. 29, 1901, of the work done by the Stegomyia Brigade during the 8 months<lb/>
since its organization - for very soon it was found necessary to divide the mosquito<lb/>
work into that of the Anopheles Brigade which operated in the suburbs and the Stegomyia<lb/>
Brigade which made house and back yard inspections. These separate organizations still<lb/>
operate in Havana. It may be of interest to know that Mr. Joseph A. Le Prince who<lb/>
wrote this report <del>when</del><add>is</add> with Col. Gorgas in Panama and is in charge of the mosquito<lb/>
work there today. (See Rep. p. 101, Vol. IV, 1901).</p>
<p>11</p>
<pb n="15" id="f06509015"/>
<p>11</p>
<p>La Prince said</p>
<p>I have the honor to present herewith a brief report on the difficul-<lb/>
ties encountered, results obtained, and methods followed in reducing the<lb/>
number of mosquitoes in the City of Havana and its suburbs during the past<lb/>
eight months.</p>
<p>Previous to April, 1901, our Sanitary Inspectors made reports of those<lb/>
houses where larvae were found and such houses were subsequently visited<lb/>
and the deposits of water containing larvae were treated with petroleum.<lb/>
It soon became evident, however, that so many breeding places existed in<lb/>
the vicinity of the houses that it was found necessary to establish a spe-<lb/>
cial brigade to go over the City from house to house. The stegomyia bri-<lb/>
gade was started in April and was gradually enlarged to forty men.</p>
<p>As many parts of this city are without water supply the people store<lb/>
water in barrels, &ldquo;tinajones&rdquo;, cans, etc., etc., and it is in deposits of<lb/>
this character that the greater number of Stegomyia larvae are found. It<lb/>
might be mentioned also that even in the houses where city water is obtain-<lb/>
able water was kept stored in deposits.</p>
<p>Rain water being soft is kept in large quantities for washing pur-<lb/>
poses. Considering all these matters, it is not surprising to find that<lb/>
when we began our mosquito destruction work there was an average of one<lb/>
deposit of water containing larvae for every house in the City.</p>
<p>Mosquitoes were also breeding in many ditches and puddles and also<lb/>
in many wells, cisterns, tanks, &ldquo;Fosas Mouras&rdquo; and cess-pools, so it was<lb/>
quite natural that the number of mosquitoes in Havana should have been<lb/>
very large during past years.</p>
<p>Soon after the Stegomyia Brigade started we oiled all deposits of<lb/>
water which were being used and requested the people to keep petroleum<lb/>
on the surface of the water and draw water from the base of each vessel<lb/>
by means of a tap. This method, although it killed the larvae, was found<lb/>
to be impractical because a large number of people seemed afraid that the<lb/>
12<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="f06509016"/>
12.<lb/>
oil was poisonous and in many cases people skimmed the oil off and each<lb/>
heavy rain removed all the petroleum and spoiled our work.</p>
<p>Another plan had to be adopted. It was decided that two boards a<lb/>
foot wide and two feet long could be put together rapidly and nailed<lb/>
over each barrel, etc. In the center of the lid so made, a square hole<lb/>
8&Prime; &times; 8&Prime; was cut and over it was nailed a piece of wire gauze; such a lid<lb/>
was then ready to nail on the deposit and in a moment a hole could be<lb/>
made below to draw water from. Lids of this form were made in large num-<lb/>
bers and were nailed over the Darrels belonging to the people in desti-<lb/>
tute circumstances. Also on May 25th the following order was issued and<lb/>
delivered at 26,000 houses:</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS DEPARTMENT OF CUBA.<lb/>
Office of Chief Sanitary Officer of Havana,</p>
<p>Notice to Tenants and Property Owners.</p>
<p>It is known that the yellow fever mosquito (Stegomyia) prefers to lay<lb/>
its eggs in clear and quiet waters, and in order to destroy this mosquito,<lb/>
the Sanitary Department has issued the following order:</p>
<p>The covers of all wells, cisterns, tanks or any other vessel that may<lb/>
at any time contain water shall be tightly covered in such a manner that<lb/>
they shall be mosquito proof. All small entrance or cracks shall be prop-<lb/>
erly covered or have wire gauze nailed over them. All cisterns and wells<lb/>
shall be supplied with pumps. All wells and cisterns not in use shall<lb/>
have their covers nailed down or shall be sealed.</p>
<p>Wherever barrels are used to contain water, they shall be supplied<lb/>
with a clost fitting cover and in the center of each such cover shall be<lb/>
left an opening about 6 inches square. This opening shall be covered with<lb/>
a piece of fine mosquito proof wire netting and will serve as entrance for<lb/>
water to be kept in the barrel. At the bottom of the barrel a tap shall<lb/>
be placed.</p>
<p>Hereafter no person shall be allowed to have barrels or other vessels<lb/>
containing water which are not mosquito proof.</p>
<p>The above order having been made a law, must be obeyed and any person<lb/>
violating the same will be held responsible.</p>
<p>Respectfully,<lb/>
(Signed) W. C. Gorgas,<lb/>
Major and Surgeon, U.S. Army,<lb/>
Chief Sanitary Officer.</p>
<p>Immediately following the distribution of this law the Brigadee were<lb/>
ordered to break all non-mosquito-proof barrels containing water. Our<lb/>
13<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="f06509017"/>
13.<lb/>
Stegomyia Brigade is composed of several divisions and each such divisions<lb/>
contains one foreman and two laborers who carry petroleum. The foreman en-<lb/>
ters a house, examines all parts of the yard, sees that the laborer who is<lb/>
with him puts the correct quantity of oil in each drain, fosa moura, sewer<lb/>
basin, pozo negro, etc., etc. He next goes up onto the balconies and roofs<lb/>
of the houses to see if any deposits of water exist there. This work is<lb/>
all absolutely necessary for there are many ignorant persons who persist in<lb/>
breeding mosquitoes. In fact, as a rule little sympathy and still less<lb/>
assistance is given to the mosquito work by the public in general. In<lb/>
some sections of the City until lately, as soon as one of our divisions<lb/>
appeared the tenants would lock up their deposits of water containing lar-<lb/>
vae in the rooms until the Brigades had passed. In order to remove such<lb/>
difficulties a list of names of all people who have deposits of water at<lb/>
present has been made, and inspections of these are being made at irregu-<lb/>
lar intervals and the owners are being fined when larvae are found on their<lb/>
premises. This method of procedure is producing excellent results. In the<lb/>
daily routine each foreman enters in his books a report of each deposit of<lb/>
water in non-mosquito-proof condition with the name of the owner thereof.<lb/>
By this means we obtain each week lists of all wells, cisterns, tanks, etc.,<lb/>
and orders are sent at once notifying owners to make same mosquito-proof.<lb/>
It has been found practical by this means and by the enforcement of the<lb/>
order previously mentioned to have all deposits of water made and kept<lb/>
mosquito proof, and a glance at the summary attached to this report will<lb/>
show what has been done. It has not been found practical to get assist-<lb/>
ance from house tenants and so they have been forced rather than persuaded<lb/>
to obey the orders of this Department. Eternal vigilance is necessary, for<lb/>
at one time we left one section of the city without inspection for a period<lb/>
14<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="f06509018"/>
14.<lb/>
of five weeks to see whether the house tenants were sufficiently interest-<lb/>
ed at present to keep their premises free from mosquitoes. It is sufficient<lb/>
to state that many new deposits of water with larvae were found and also that<lb/>
in nearly every case where we had helped people by covering their deposits<lb/>
said covers had been torn off or destroyed.</p>
<p>In November a notice was published in the papers that thereafter all<lb/>
persons having receptacles with water which is found to contain larvae, will<lb/>
be fined $10.00 U.S. currency for every violation of said law.</p>
<p>From the difficulties we have encountered it might be supposed that<lb/>
there has not been a large decrease in the number of mosquitoes in this<lb/>
City. This is not the case. In fact, we have been exceptionally success-<lb/>
ful in our work and we hear good reports from all parts. Today, there are<lb/>
many parts of this city where a hundred houses may be inspected one after<lb/>
another without encountering any mosquito larvae. When you consider that<lb/>
the average used to be one deposit per house exclusive of wells, cisterns,<lb/>
tanks, etc., and also the fact that there are very few people who try to<lb/>
assist us, then it is certainly gratifying to know that so much good work<lb/>
has been accomplished. Mosquitoes were very numerous in Havana last sum-<lb/>
mer and it was necessary to sleep under a mosquito bar every night. Our<lb/>
soldiers at the Punta used to burn smudge every night to drive the mosqui-<lb/>
toes out. This year these same men do not even use mosquito bars. We are<lb/>
receiving similar reports from different parts of the city. When a suspect<lb/>
case of yellow fever has occurred in this city the house of the patient and<lb/>
the adjacent houses are fumigated to kill any infected Stegomyia present,<lb/>
and all dead mosquitoes found are burned. It has been noticed that the num-<lb/>
ber of dead mosquitoes found after fumigating is decreasing and also that<lb/>
of those found the percentage of Stegomyia mosquitoes has decreased largely.<lb/>
15<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="f06509019"/>
15.<lb/>
This will have an effect in reducing the possibility of yellow fever<lb/>
patients being bitten. In our inspections I have found that the largest<lb/>
quantity of Stegomyia larvae are found in house yards in vessels contain-<lb/>
ing clear and still water. Even though water in pools contaminated with<lb/>
sewage were close at hand containing (culex pungens) larvae the Stegomyia<lb/>
seems to prefer the clearer water. There seems to be a popular impres-<lb/>
sion that mosquitoes will not breed in moving water, but in Havana we<lb/>
find them breeding in ditches and creeks which have considerable current<lb/>
and also in the troughs where animals drink. In several cases tanks have<lb/>
been found where water was running in at one end and out at the other and<lb/>
many larvae were found to be present. Such tanks have been ordered to be<lb/>
completely emptied twice a week or owner to be fined when larvae were found.<lb/>
Even the tubs into which blacksmiths put red hot irons daily were found<lb/>
to contain many larvae.</p>
<p>In this connection it may be of interest<lb/>
to know that I have known them to be found<lb/>
breeding in lye hoppers and in the<lb/>
the alkaline water which has received<lb/>
the calcium carbide of acetylene <unclear>apporalu</unclear></p>
<p>16.</p>
<pb n="20" id="f06509020"/>
<p>In Havna, Cuba, <del>this disease</del><add>small pox</add> was likewise always present prior to<lb/>
the American occupation and in the eight years preceding 1899 it caused<lb/>
3123 deaths. In that year a general vaccination of the population occur-<lb/>
red and there were four deaths, while the total deaths for the succeeding<lb/>
seven years has been three.</p>
<pb n="21" id="f06509021"/>
<p>16</p>
<p>The result of this work is well shown by the chart on the black board- <add>See Comp. Y.F.,<lb/>
pp. 172 - 173</add></p>
<p>
<table rows="19" cols="4">
<row><cell cols="1-4">1901.</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell>cases</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>deaths</cell></row>
<row><cell>April</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>May</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>June</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>July</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>August</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>September</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>October</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>November</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>:</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>December</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>:</cell><cell>0</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>Death rate Havana av 50 years<lb/>
prior to 1900 - 40.<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> 1901 - 1910 20.</p>
<p>and by comparisons with the preceding<lb/>
year when a total of 1300 cases with<lb/>
296 deaths was reported, while for 1901<lb/>
there were 63 cases and 5 deaths.</p>
<p>The three last cases in Havana were taken<lb/>
sick in September but are carried as<lb/>
October cases. After this there were<lb/>
no more cases in Havana, for 4 years and<lb/>
the disease disappeared from all Cuba at<lb/>
the same time - for nowhere else did there<lb/>
seem to be a sufficient supply of non-<lb/>
immunes to support a continuing infection.<lb/>
It was quite different as we shall see, when<lb/>
<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> I came to fight the disease five years <add>later.</add></p>
<p>Gorgas' Report for the year 1901, ends with the following paragraph which <del>is a</del><add>has the</add><lb/>
<unclear>to</unclear> of subdued exultation of a nunc dimittis:</p>
<p>&ldquo;This is probably the last annual report that will be made by a United States Army<lb/>
officer as Health Officer of Havana, to his Military superior, the Governor of the Island<lb/>
I hope that I may be excused if I point out some of the sanitary differences between<lb/>
&ldquo;the then&rdquo; and &ldquo;the now&rdquo;.</p>
<p>The Army took charge of the Health Department of Havana when deaths were occurring<lb/>
at the rate of 21,252 per year. It gives it up with deaths occurring at the rate of<lb/>
5,720 per year. It took charge with smallpox endemic for years. It gives it up with not<lb/>
a single case having occurred in the city for over eighteen months. It took charge with<lb/>
yellow fever endemic for two centuries, the relentless foe of every foreigner who came<lb/>
within Havana's borders,-which he could not escape, and from whose attack he well knew<lb/>
that every fourth man must die. It found Havana feared as a thing unclean by all her</p>
<p>17</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
