<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06507021">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06507021</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-02-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-02-20">February 20, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06507021</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench inquires if it would be possible to determine the cost to the U.S. Army of the entire Yellow Fever Commission, beyond the regular pay of those involved.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-02-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, February 20, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06507021"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-02-20">February 20, 1953</date>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>My over-riding interest in my yellow fever hobby keeps me thinking about it<lb/>
even in the midst of a life very preoccupied with cortisone and related<lb/>
matters and I constantly keep pegging away at loose ends to my story. One<lb/>
of the things I have wanted to sit down and figure out is the cost to the<lb/>
U. S. Army of the entire Yellow Fever Board expenses beyond that of the<lb/>
regular pay of those concerned. This should not be too hard and one could<lb/>
present the conclusion purely for what it is, an intelligent estimate.</p>
<p>I have never had time to do this, or at least to finish it, and wondered if<lb/>
you would be in the mood to do it for me, completely at your leisure. I would<lb/>
not want you to take this seriously enough so that it would worry you or tire<lb/>
you. I should prefer to suggest it as a pleasant little game.</p>
<p>The first sum of course would be the $10,000 which General Wood gave Reed.<lb/>
This could be broken down to see roughly how much went for the building of<lb/>
the little shacks, the rental of the Finca San Jose and the allotments to<lb/>
the volunteers. We know exactly how many volunteers there were, which ones<lb/>
got yellow fever (at a larger sum), which ones were inoculated but did not<lb/>
get yellow fever (Did they get the same amount? At the moment I have for-<lb/>
gotten.). We know the size of the building. We know the lumber was Ameri-<lb/>
can wood, some of which was &ldquo;wasted&rdquo; as it is still there. We could even<lb/>
figure out roughly the number of cubic feet of wood used in the buildings.<lb/>
I have an architect friend who could do that easily.</p>
<p>We know the number of trips that Reed made away from Havana to present his<lb/>
papers (only one from Havana and back for the first paper). We know that<lb/>
three of the board went to Pinar del Rio. We know the exact dates and<lb/>
duration of their visits there. Their railroad fare would be the only extra<lb/>
to the government. One could make an intelligent guess as to the cost of<lb/>
the laboratory supplies which were expended and not returned to the Army.<lb/>
Do you know whether General Wood ever gave Reed any more than the original<lb/>
$10,000?</p>
<p>Would you be inclined to peck away at this little problem? I should like to<lb/>
put the estimate in my book in the form of a table and of course say that<lb/>
General Truby has estimated that the conquest of yellow fever cost about<lb/>
so many dollars, perhaps one of the greatest and most profitable invest-<lb/>
ments of all time.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06507022"/>
<p>General Albert E. Truby</p>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>February 20, 1953</p>
<p>Also, I find a curious blank spot in my notes and I don't believe your<lb/>
book answers them. I don't think I have any figure on Walter Reed's height,<lb/>
approximate weight, color of hair and eyes nor the same information for the<lb/>
other members of the board. Would you make a guess on these things? That<lb/>
would be most helpful. I have meant to ask the Reed family about this but<lb/>
never remember it when I am with them.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
