<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06504025">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Cornelia Knox Kean to Mary Standlee, May 4, 1951 [Enclosed in 06504022]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Cornelia Knox</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06504025</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1951-05-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Standlee, Mary </term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Hume, Edgar Erskine</name>
<name type="person">Barton, Clara</name>
<name type="person">McCaw, Walter D.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Mason, Charles F.</name>
<name type="person">Birmingham, Henry P.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>7 pp.</extent>
<date value="1951-05-04">May 4, 1951</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06504025</idno>
<title>Letter from Cornelia Knox Kean to Mary Standlee, May 4, 1951 [Enclosed in 06504022]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean harshly criticizes Standlee's manuscript and states the reasons for her opinions. She includes a detailed list of corrections for the Standlee manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1951-05-04">
<head>Letter from Cornelia Knox Kean to Mary Standlee, May 4, 1951 [Enclosed in <xref id="t06504022">06504022</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06504025"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1951-05-04">4 May 1951</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Mrs. Standlee:</salute>
</opener>
<p>You have asked me to criticize your manuscript. It<lb/>
is a difficult task for me, as I am not capable of doing<lb/>
justice to the subject. I can only give you my point of view.</p>
<p>I was born in the Army many years ago. When my father<lb/>
was ordered to Washington Dr. O'Reilly was the attending<lb/>
Surgeon. There never was a nobler man, with a tender<lb/>
sympathy for all mankind. In those days he made his<lb/>
calls in a buggy, with a colored driver. I was a<lb/>
child, and every morning I would stand on the corner of<lb/>
21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> and J streets to watch for him. He would lean out<lb/>
the side of his buggy and give me his beautiful smile,<lb/>
which made me happy. So you can see how I loved<lb/>
him, and revered his memory.</p>
<p>In the old Army I think the Medical Officers were<lb/>
judged, as were all men, by their character and ability. Of<lb/>
course each branch had the pride of its own service and<lb/>
esprit de corps.</p>
<p>The Spanish War was the end of an era. I never saw<lb/>
Walter Reed, but I know how he was honored by Harvard<lb/>
University, which was not the Army. General Kean loved<lb/>
Cuba and his Cuban friends, so I know he would have been<lb/>
unhappy to read <hi>page 36</hi>. He always gave Finlay the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06504026"/>
Mrs. Standlee<lb/>
2<lb/>
gave Finlay the credit for the theory, and Reed the credit<lb/>
for having demonstrated the theory. And General Kean always<lb/>
worked for a friendly feeling between the Cubans and ourselves.<lb/>
He and Dr. Finlay were friends. As I said to you the day<lb/>
you were here, I hoped you would do, as I feel deeply, that<lb/>
you would take Dr. Hench's work on Walter Reed and Yellow<lb/>
Fever as Gospel, for that is the way General Kean felt.</p>
<p>You are a friend and admirer of General Kean's. I<lb/>
like your term &ldquo;judicial&rdquo; for him. But on <hi>page 58</hi> you<lb/>
use &ldquo;suave and adroit&rdquo; as if the term astute politician<lb/>
is meant. General Kean always worked for his country and<lb/>
for the Medical Corps and the welfare of the Army. Certainly,<lb/>
not for himself. He always gave all that he had to<lb/>
those who sought him - of his learning, his generous cre-<lb/>
ative gifts, and his sympathetic and constructive mind.<lb/>
Always and Inspiration - even now - to those who knew<lb/>
him and loved him. I like General Hume's ap-<lb/>
preciation of General Kean, P. 237 of his History of the<lb/>
Military Surgeon. Also I like the citation which<lb/>
he received with the Gorgas medal.</p>
<p>I know there are those at Walter Reed who never<lb/>
heard of Walter Reed except as the name of a Hospital, who<lb/>
never heard of General Ireland, who never heard of<lb/>
General Kean - Such is fame.</p>
<p>For your story why perpetuate the old jealousies and bitternesses?<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06504027"/>
3<lb/>
Mrs. Standlee<lb/>
To me Walter Reed Hospital is the most blessed place<lb/>
on earth. There is glory enough for all who have ever<lb/>
served it, with the tender care of human beings in distress.<lb/>
The only place I know where money has no value. I would<lb/>
like your story to be a tribute to Humanity, our<lb/>
Country and our Medical Corps. This is the prayer<lb/>
of an old Army woman born and bred, and I hope died,<lb/>
at Walter Reed.</p>
<p>When you asked me to criticize your story, you told me<lb/>
you would not be offended at anything I might say.<lb/>
I have taken you at your word. If I can be of help<lb/>
to you along the lines of my own convictions, I<lb/>
would be glad to do so.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
<signed>Cornelia Kean</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1951-05-04">
<head>Notes from Cornelia Knox Kean to Mary Standlee, May 4, 1951 [Enclosed in 06504022]</head>
<pb n="4" id="f06504028"/>
<p>P<lb/>
1</p>
<p>6 Clara Barton}<lb/>
31 " " }<lb/>
Have you historical facts on this subject?<lb/>
(<hi>C. Kean</hi>)</p>
<p>26 (26) In 1881 courtly, contentious Dr. Carlos Finlay<lb/>
of Havana delivered a scientific paper before the Royal<lb/>
Academy of Havana on the Mosquito Hypothetically considered<lb/>
as the agent of Transmission of Yellow Fever. Few if<lb/>
any of Dr. Finlay's contemporaries gave his theories<lb/>
the consideration they deserved. And such is the re-<lb/>
sistance to new ideas, if not self-propounded, that in<lb/>
time the stubborn doctor was considered senile or<lb/>
visionary or both.</p>
<p>47 Apart from the spectacular control of epidemics, which<lb/>
followed the work of the Yellow Fever Board, these factors<lb/>
assisted in immortalizing Walter Reed. Unlike the<lb/>
combat services, the Medical Dept. then had few put-<lb/>
licized heroes, and Dr. Reed's untimely death, at the peak of<lb/>
his career, provided a Martyred hero for immediate adoption,<lb/>
solving the epidemiology of Yellow Fever was indisputably a<lb/>
major medical accomplishment, although it was by no means a single-<lb/>
handed effort, a credit to one man alone. Yet as chairman<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="f06504029"/>
P<lb/>
2<lb/>
of the board, he received more recognition than his collaborators.<lb/>
Thirdly and perhaps most important, his friends kept the altar<lb/>
candles a light to his memory for half a century.</p>
<p>47 ... (52<hi rend="superscript">A</hi>) although Kean, McCaw, and Ireland came in time to<lb/>
resent the favors and publicity which followed Gorgas<lb/>
(52<hi rend="superscript">G</hi>) Gorgas likewise memorialized Walter Reed</p>
<p>48 ... (57) Defensively his friends became Sentinels to his memory.</p>
<p>48(<hi rend="superscript">G</hi>) ... In 1906 during the height of the controversy, Dr. Howard<lb/>
(58) Kelly, with Major Kean's untiring assistance, produced a<lb/>
Touching biography. With love and forsight zeal and<lb/>
perseverance, they success fully canonized him for he<lb/>
&ldquo;being dead it (was) an obligation of his friends to see<lb/>
that his scientific achievements (were) not forgotten.&rdquo;</p>
<p>55(15) Interview with Gen. Kean</p>
<p>Dr. Borden ... been known as the physician to Presidents.<lb/>
Others hinted that he was politically successful because he had<lb/>
known Cleveland and that having once X-rayed Teddy Roosevelt's<lb/>
knee he had obtained the listening ear of politicians.</p>
<p>57(25) Surgeon General Robert maitland O'Reilly was not a<lb/>
spectacular successor to the professionally outstanding<lb/>
General Sternberg, but he was a conservative and agreeable<lb/>
man who endorsed sound policies. Any lack of aggressiveness was<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06504030"/>
P<lb/>
3<lb/>
57 was offset by his pleasant dignified manner and his<lb/>
quiet plodding along a course founded by the Dodge Com-<lb/>
missions recommendations and the enthusiasm of his young<lb/>
satellites for administrative innovations. Field medical<lb/>
officers were conscious of their lack of prestige with line<lb/>
officers, with whom seniority, rank and responsibility were<lb/>
nearly synonomous terms, and they were determined to over-<lb/>
come the military handicap which doctors, as technicians,<lb/>
met constantly in the highly organized caste system<lb/>
fastered by the Army ((25) Kean April 17, 1950)</p>
<p>58 While General O'Reilly made an excellent impression on<lb/>
Congressional Committees, he would not personally lobby far special<lb/>
(26) interest programs, and so he detailed energetic young doctors<lb/>
to key office positions and held them responsible for the of-<lb/>
fice management. The resourceful and aggressive Dr. Borden<lb/>
was offered the influential position of executive officer,<lb/>
but as his primary interest lay in the professional field<lb/>
he declined, saying he preferred being the &ldquo;power behind<lb/>
the throne&rdquo;, although Borden had a personal career plan</p>
<p>(27) Toward which he worked, there were a good many would be<lb/>
powers in those days, and he soon found that he had a<lb/>
friendly rival in his alternate, Dr. Jefferson Randolph Kean,<lb/>
who was appointed executive officer and became one of<lb/>
General O'Reilly's principal advisers.</p>
<p>The two young doctors were opposite in type, temperament<lb/>
and interests. The suave and adroit Kean.</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06504031"/>
<p>
P<lb/>
58<lb/>
was already well known as a practical sanitarian and <lb/>
"trouble shooter" for the Department, but at this time<lb/> 
he was intensely interested in establishing a personnel<lb/>
section in General O'Reilly's office, supervised by a doctor<lb/>
rather than the autocratic civilian Chief Clerk.  Further,<lb/>
he disapproved of the allegedly patronage ridden system<lb/>
of the National Guard and milita appointments and<lb/>
favored formation of an Officer's Reserve Corps which <lb/>
would guarantee a roster of professional men not only<lb/>
familiar with military medical problems (28) but quickly<lb/>
available in time of war.</p>
<p>A great deal of Kean's recent service had been in the<lb/>
tropics, and he had come to believe that the medical officer<lb/>
made a better sho of authority in effecting sanitary reforms<lb/>
when addressed by a military title, for &ldquo;doctor&rdquo; was a self-<lb/>
limiting term which restricted the holder to an ad-<lb/>
visory (29) or service role.  Kean agreed heartily with <lb/>
Theodore Roosevelt's opinion that medical officers must<lb/>
"supplement in (their) calling the work of surgeon<lb/>
(30) with the work of the administrator." It was during <lb/>
this period, therefore, that medical officers began <lb/>
abandoning their professional title, adopting, almost<lb/>
to the point of a fetish, the the military form of address.<lb/>
</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06504031"/>
<p>P<lb/>
5</p>
<p>86 (73) I think the families of Ireland, Birmingham and Kean<lb/>
here among those immunized for typhoid fever. (C. Kean)</p>
<p>113 Colonel Charles E. Mason succeeded Major Ashburn as<lb/>
commander at Walter Reed on October 6, 1916. Author of a<lb/>
handbook which the Military Surgeon called the medical<lb/>
Soldier's &ldquo;Bible&rdquo;, he had long been interested in sanitary<lb/>
tactics. Quiet, refined, scholarly and cultured.<lb/>
Like Colonel Richards he was small of Stature. In<lb/>
spite of his charming manners and the reputation of having<lb/>
twice married beautiful women, by the time he became<lb/>
the eighth Commander of Walter Reed a haunting, brooding<lb/>
look of suffering had settled like a shadow on his face.<lb/>
It was a time for action rather than for meditation, and<lb/>
the tenure at Walter Reed may have been trying for the<lb/>
some what melancholy officer whose record as man-<lb/>
ager of the Ancon Hospital, Canal Zone, showed that he<lb/>
had a flair for husbanding federal money.</p>
<p>I do not like - Gen. Kean was a friend of Col. Mason and of<lb/>
his lonely wife. I think it poor taste to mention the<lb/>
wives in a Military History, and Colonel Mason was a<lb/>
sick man<lb/>
C. Kean</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
