<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06507035">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, April 20, 1953</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06507035</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1953-04-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Truby, Albert E.</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Fernandez, Nicanor</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Tate, Paul L.</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1953-04-20">April 20, 1953</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06507035</idno>
<title>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, April 20, 1953</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Hench will send Truby copies of the checks in Kean's checking account, as well as the checkbook itself, so that Truby can estimate Camp Lazear's expenses.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1953-04-20">
<head>Letter from Philip Showalter Hench to Albert E. Truby, April 20, 1953</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06507035"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1953-04-20">April 20, 1953</date>
</dateline>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
145 Laurel Street<lb/>
San Francisco, California<lb/>
<salute>My dear General Truby:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I am still head over heels with my long and very difficult paper, working far<lb/>
into the night. However my secretary has kindly made for us a typewritten<lb/>
record of all the checks in Major Kean's checking account. I think these will<lb/>
be very useful to you as they will tell you something about what the money was<lb/>
spent for and so on. I am sending you herewith three copies of the account,<lb/>
thinking you might want to have some correspondence with someone and perhaps<lb/>
actually show the account. If you want more, we can easily make another ozalid<lb/>
copy.</p>
<p>You will note that we have copied the items as Major Kean wrote them, even<lb/>
though we know some of the spellings are wrong. For example, check No. 25,<lb/>
was for Niconar Fernandez, which Major Kean spelled <hi>Nicomar</hi>. Check No. 26<lb/>
should have been for John R. Kissinger instead of John J., etc. In other words,<lb/>
this represents as faithful a record of the actual check stubs as we could make<lb/>
it, interpreting his handwriting.</p>
<p>Because there is nothing like actually seeing the check book, I am taking a chance<lb/>
on the U. S. mails and sending you the actual check book by separate registered<lb/>
mail. I am sure that nothing will happen to it in your careful hands and I<lb/>
would appreciate it if you would return it to me eventually also by registered<lb/>
mail.</p>
<p>In your recent letter you seem to have that that maybe Reed received $40,000<lb/>
from General wood. I am writing this without reference to my yellow fever data<lb/>
but off-hand I thought he only received $10,000. Wasn't that amount mentioned<lb/>
in General Kean's description of his visit to General Wood with Major Reed - the<lb/>
description given in Kean's address at the dedication of Reed's birthplace, but<lb/>
you may be correct in this amount. I have never come across any accounting made<lb/>
by Reed himself for any more money and wondered whether $10,000 had been promised<lb/>
but actually only $6,635.50 was used as per the enclosed account. I haven't<lb/>
checked to see whether the payments to all of the volunteers are accounted for<lb/>
here and it may well be that Reed had a separate account; however I doubt it as<lb/>
Kean's seems to begin with the opening of the camp and ends after the camp was<lb/>
finally given up.</p>
<p>It was my impression from Johnny Moran that the Reed buildings were constructed<lb/>
by soldiers in the Engineering Corps from Camp Columbia and this may well be so<lb/>
as at least one of the buildings was ready for occupancy late in November and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06507036"/>
General Albert E. Truby<lb/>
- 2 -<lb/>
April 20, 1953<lb/>
if it was built by civilians paid for by the army, we don't have the account or,<lb/>
if it was built by soldiers, we have no record. In any event, notice the checks<lb/>
for carpentry service in December.</p>
<p>Some of the most costs for the camp seem extremely low. I don't know whether they<lb/>
represent extra meat or the rest being gotten from the Quartermaster Corps or<lb/>
whether all of the camp expenses are listed here. I would certainly suspect<lb/>
that the grocery items here listed were extras and did not represent the entire<lb/>
grocery expense for the camp personnel, but of that you will know more.</p>
<p>Do you have any idea what the small checks on January 3 to various volunteers<lb/>
were for - checks for $22 and $24 or less? Do you suppose it was like that for<lb/>
<unclear>Gust</unclear> Lambert, Check No. 30, for extra services as laborers or were they per-<lb/>
haps paid for clerical services, although Moran seems to have been the one who<lb/>
got that pay.</p>
<p>Check No. 70 is interesting and inexplicable to me.</p>
<p>The deposit of September 9 of $100 I understand. Reed and others had intended<lb/>
to release the camp earlier and then in one of Reed's letters which I have, he<lb/>
wrote, I think from Washington, to Wood or perhaps to Kean (I have the letter<lb/>
at home) and asked him to continue the rent of the camp through the summer with<lb/>
the possibility that they might use it again. Therefore Major Kean had to get<lb/>
another $100 of which he spent $60.</p>
<p>Should you wish to send the extra copy to Mr. Hanberry, he might be able to<lb/>
help and I don't know whether or not Mr. Tate would be able to help.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>P. S. Hench, M.D.</signed>
PSH:alc<lb/>
Enclosures<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
