<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06501033">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from Paul L. Tate to [Philip Showalter Hench], September 25, 1949</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Tate, Paul L.</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06501033</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1949-09-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Hench, Philip Showalter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Amador, R. A.</name>
<name type="person">Godfrey, Guy Charles Moore</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Columbia Barracks Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1949-09-25">September 25, 1949</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06501033</idno>
<title>Letter from Paul L. Tate to [Philip Showalter Hench], September 25, 1949</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tate informs [Hench] that he was the medical records clerk at Columbia Barracks during the yellow fever experiments. He claims that Ames was the real hero and yet became the forgotten man because he was simply a contract doctor.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1949-09-25">
<head>Letter from Paul L. Tate to [Philip Showalter Hench], September 25, 1949</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06501033"/>
<opener>
<unclear>and JF</unclear><lb/>
Truby <unclear></unclear><lb/>
<unclear>"</unclear><lb/>
<dateline>
1530 Tyler Street<lb/>
Berkeley 3 California<lb/>
<date value="1949-09-25">September 25, 1949</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have heard that you intend publishing a book<lb/>
dealing with the Yellow Fever experiments in Cuba in 1900-<lb/>
'01. It intrigues me to think that people are still writing<lb/>
of that medical discovery of nearly half a century ago.</p>
<p>Of course it was a tremendous event.--The dramatic<lb/>
solving of a great medical problem, resulting in saving unold<lb/>
lives, and time and money by eliminating quarrantine, etc.<lb/>
But one would think that interest would have waned after so<lb/>
long a time and so much written about it.</p>
<p>I think I have read all the books published on<lb/>
this subject, and saw the play &ldquo;Yellow Jack,&rdquo; and heard sev-<lb/>
eral radio versions. I found that all but one were written<lb/>
by people who were not there. I especially had to laugh at<lb/>
the dramatic version.--Tiled bath room and fancy fixtures!<lb/>
They should have seen the stark sord<del>i</del>ness of the real place!</p>
<p>The only factual account is by Gen Truby. He was<lb/>
then a Lieutenant, Army Medical Corps and was in charge of<lb/>
Columbia Barracks Hospital during part of the time the ex-<lb/>
periments were going on, during the temporary absence of<lb/>
Captain Stark. I served under both.</p>
<p>But even his account was second-hand, as he had<lb/>
nothing to do with the experiments other than to detach the<lb/>
Hospital Corpsmen used in the experiment. Besides he was even<lb/>
then obsessed with the Regular Army atmosphere and this in-<lb/>
creased with years of service and promotion. It was closer<lb/>
to facts than any other book, but yet was more a biography<lb/>
of Truby than a history of the experiment.--Lots of credit<lb/>
given to Regular Army Quartermasters, etc. who did nothing<lb/>
but their duty, but little of the scientific medical aspects<lb/>
that I heard talked about between Reed, Guerteris, Carroll,<lb/>
Lazier, Amador, Ames, and other men working with and on the<lb/>
Board.</p>
<p>No, the inside story of that experiment has not<lb/>
yet been written. Part of it died with Lazier, and the <hi>one</hi><lb/>
man that could have told it <hi>all</hi>, Doctor Roger Post Ames, is<lb/>
dead.</p>
<p>These books interest me because I had a &ldquo;ringside<lb/>
seat&rdquo; during all of it. I was at Pinar del Rio, Cuba in the<lb/>
Hospital Corps when we were so swamped with deaths from ##</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06501034"/>
<p>(2)</p>
<p>Yellow Fever, which Capt. Godfrey (Reg. Army Doctor) per-<lb/>
sistently diagnosed as Pernicious Malaria, that Gen. Gorgas<lb/>
<hi>sent Dr. Amador</hi> down there to investigate. One doctor there<lb/>
told me it was Yellow Fever. But he could not do anything<lb/>
about it because he was only a Contract Doctor. (Not a Reg-<lb/>
ular)</p>
<p>The post was abandoned and I came to Columbia Bks.<lb/>
just before the experiments started there, and was medical<lb/>
record clerk until end of the experiments in 1901. I was as<lb/>
nearly personally acquainted with every member of the Board<lb/>
and other doctors as an enlisted man could be with officers.<lb/>
I was studying for promotion and many of them helped me along.<lb/>
In course of my duties I saw some of them every day and, of<lb/>
course heard much talk about the cases. <hi>I knew personally</hi><lb/>
every Hospital Corpsman who took the test (12 of them, of<lb/>
<hi>whom 5 had come with me from P delR.) and talked with them<lb/>
all before and after the tests.</hi></p>
<p>I would not detract one bota from the heroism of any<lb/>
one of these men, but in stories I have read, some are rated<lb/>
higher than others, and generally the rating was wrong.-The<lb/>
writer was not there, so did not know. In fact, Gen. Truby in<lb/>
his book, left out one man entirely--Clyde West, Hosp. Corps)</p>
<p>But there would have been no successful experiment if<lb/>
it had not been for Doctor Ames. He was the one man who did<lb/>
more for the success of the experiment than any other. This<lb/>
is my belief, and it would have been known as a fact if Major<lb/>
Reed had lived longer. (Major Reed was a doctor first, an<lb/>
army officer second). But where are you going to find any<lb/>
of this for your book? Like all the other futile writers you<lb/>
look through War Dept. records and orders or what some Army<lb/>
doctor wrote. But you won't find the real facts, for Doctor<lb/>
Ames was a Contract Doctor--not a Regular Army Officer!</p>
<p>Very, very fortunately for his Fever patients, (all of<lb/>
whom he saved in the experiments and over 50 others) he cared<lb/>
more for the science of medicine than he did for the Brass<lb/>
of the Army. And that was unfortunate for him, for he was the<lb/>
real hero of it all and yet became the forgotten man.</p>
<p>Don't think I'm prejudiced against the Army.--I am an<lb/>
old Regular Army Man and proud of it. But I think the prac-<lb/>
tice of medicine <add><unclear>is</unclear></add> one of the greatest professions in the world,<lb/>
and I hate to see a man who thinks a little rank and brass<lb/>
tinsel can add anything to that profession.</p>
<p>I corresponded with Dr. Ame's nurse, Gus. Lambert, who<lb/>
handled all the experimental cases, and I think he is still<lb/>
in Chicago. And, believe me, he was in my opinion some hero<lb/>
himself. He did not have to stick in that horrible place<lb/>
and alone nurse all those cases (over 8 months). He could<lb/>
have refused. But I guess he would not let Doctor Ames down.<lb/>
He was a great Swede I knew him well while there. If you<lb/>
you want some real information, look him up in Chicago di-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06501035"/>
(3)<lb/>
directory. He really knows more about some phases of that<lb/>
event than anyone alive.--He should for he saw the really<lb/>
main part of it from the inside out!</p>
<p>I suppose your book will be like the rest of them,<lb/>
but I would sure like to read it. I will enclose postal<lb/>
addressed. Will you kindly name the publishers and date<lb/>
so I can obtain a copy. Really that is why I wrote this<lb/>
long crazy letter. Merely intended asking you name of the<lb/>
publisher, and now look what I've inflicted on you! Its<lb/>
unforgivable from a perfect stranger, but I hope you will<lb/>
overlook it. Wishing you great success.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially &amp; Sincerely Yours,</salute>
<signed>Paul L. Tate</signed>
see my letter<lb/>
?<lb/>
<unclear>questionaire</unclear><lb/>
of Jul - 54<lb/>
to him<lb/>
question #95<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
