<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t06510001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Report: I Become a Guinea Pig, by John H. Andrus, [19--]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06510001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>19**-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Lewis, Nellie</name>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>17 pp.</extent>
<date value="19**-00-00">[19--]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">06510001</idno>
<title>Report: I Become a Guinea Pig, by John H. Andrus, [19--]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Andrus describes the work of the Yellow Fever Board and his role as a volunteer. He provides exacting lists of his fellow volunteers and their cases of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="19**-00-00">
<head>Report: I Become a Guinea Pig, by John H. Andrus, [19--]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06510001"/>
<opener>
&ldquo;<hi>I B e c o m e  a  G u i n e a  P i g</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
An episode from<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>B i g  M o m e n t s<lb/>
in a<lb/>
Little L i f e</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
By John H. Andrus.<lb/>
See p. 9.<lb/>
A E T<lb/>
9.<lb/>
</opener>
<pb n="2" id="f06510002"/>
<p><hi>I B e c o m e  a  G u i n e a  P i g</hi></p>
<p>By John H. Andrus</p>
<p>The doctor scrubbed a spot on my arm with a piece of<lb/>
alcohol-saturated cotton, inserted a hypodermic needle,<lb/>
slowly pressed the plunger and I was richer by one cu-<lb/>
bic centimeter of blood, taken but a moment before from<lb/>
a vein of a fellow-soldier, Wallace Forbes. At that<lb/>
time his temperature was 102.6&deg; F. and he was at the<lb/>
height of a pronounced case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>Forbes had been innoculated with the disease by the<lb/>
injection of one-half cubic centimeter of blood from a<lb/>
&ldquo;natural&rdquo; case that had proven fatal.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;shot&rdquo; was given me at 12:15 p. m., Jan. 25, 1901.<lb/>
At that time the same amount of Forbes' blood was injec-<lb/>
ted into four volunteers who had recovered from yellow<lb/>
fever given them by the bite of infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>After my innoculation I stepped into an ambulance and<lb/>
was driven to Camp Lazear to await developments. There<lb/>
could be but one outcome. I knew that, from the instant<lb/>
that needle pierced my skin, no power on earth could pre-<lb/>
vent my getting yellow fever.</p>
<p>Six days later, (Jan. 31, 1901), Major Walter Reed,<lb/>
in a letter to the Surgeon-General of the Army, George M.<lb/>
Sternberg, wrote of my case: &ldquo;Although our immune (Mos-<lb/>
quito-made) cases, four in number, have shown no sympt-<lb/>
oms whatever, I am very unease about the non-immune sol-<lb/>
dier who got the same amount of blood at the same time.<lb/>
He seems to have acquired a very serious infection, his<lb/>
temperature running along the 104&deg; line now for three<lb/>
days...Should he die I shall regret that I ever under-<lb/>
took this work. The responsibility for the life of a<lb/>
human being weighs upon me very heavily just <unclear>at<del>x</del>present</unclear>,<lb/>
and I am dreadfully melancholic. Everything is being<lb/>
done for him that we know how to do.&rdquo; (Extract from<lb/>
page 227 of the biography of General Sternberg.)</p>
<p>In those days yellow fever had not found a place among<lb/>
the unpleasant things that could be forgotten. On the<lb/>
contrary, it was so well up on the list of great scourges<lb/>
that foreign countries - or sections of our own country<lb/>
where it was known to be epidemic - were rigidly quaran-<lb/>
tined.</p>
<p>1</p>
<p>9.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f06510003"/>
<p>Tropical Diseases - with special emphasis on yellow fever.<lb/>
This Board met at Columbia Barracks, Cuba, in May, 1900.<lb/>
It was composed of Major Walter Reed and Acting Assistant<lb/>
Surgeons (Contract Doctors) JamesvCarroll, Jesse W. Lazear<lb/>
and Aristides Agramonte.</p>
<p>After the Board had proven several theories groundless,<lb/>
Major Reed decided to investigate a theory originally ad-<lb/>
vanced by Dr. Carlos J. Finlay, of Havana, in 1881, that<lb/>
yellow <unclear>fever<del>b</del>is</unclear> transmitted by mosquito-bite. This<lb/>
theory had never been accepted by the medical profession<lb/>
and, in spite of more than 100 experiments on human beings,<lb/>
between 1881 and 1895, Dr. Finlay had been unable to<lb/>
demonstrate it.</p>
<p>It was thought necessary to use human beings as sub-<lb/>
jects in the experiments as it was not known at that time<lb/>
that there are one or two species of monkeys that can be<lb/>
given the disease. Major Reed and Doctors Carroll and<lb/>
Lazear agreed to submit themselves for innoculation.<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte, the Cuban member of the Board, having had<lb/>
the disease, was immune.</p>
<p>While Major Reed was temporarily absent on official<lb/>
business, Dr. Carroll was innoculated by an infected mos-<lb/>
quito, August 27, 1900, and had a severe attack of yellow<lb/>
fever. While this was the first successful innoculation,<lb/>
it was not accepted as conclusive as Dr. Carroll had been<lb/>
within the epidemic some several times during the period<lb/>
of incubation.</p>
<p>The second case was referred to in official records as<lb/>
&ldquo;X. Y.&rdquo; for the reason that his innoculation was without<lb/>
military authorization. This was Private William H.<lb/>
Dean, Troop &ldquo;B&rdquo;, Seventh Cavalry. He was bitten by the<lb/>
same mosquito that had innoculated Dr. Carroll, four days<lb/>
before, and by three other mosquitoes. He had a very<lb/>
mild attack.</p>
<p>Dr. Jesse W. Lazear watched a mosquito feed on his<lb/>
hand in Los Animas - the yellow fever hospital in Havana -<lb/>
on September 13, 1900. He died of yellow fever Septem-<lb/>
ber 25, 1900, a martyr to science.</p>
<p>Encouraged by these successes with the &ldquo;mosquito<lb/>
theory&rdquo;, the Board decided to prosecute that phase of the<lb/>
investigation with added vigor and, at the same time,<lb/>
to investigate an entirely different theory.</p>
<p>2</p>
<p>9.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06510004"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>military authorization. This was Private William H. Dean,<lb/>
Troop &ldquo;B&rdquo;, Seventh Cavalry. He was bitten by the same <unclear>mos-<lb/>
quitg</unclear> <unclear>that<del></del>had</unclear> innoculated Dr. Carroll, four days before, and<lb/>
by three other mosquitoes. He had a very mild attack.</p>
<p><hi>A Martyr to Science</hi>:</p>
<p>The case of Dr. Lazear was the single tragedy to mar the<lb/>
work of the Board. It sacrificed the life of a young scien-<lb/>
tist on the threshold of what promised to be a brilliant ca-<lb/>
reer. Educationally, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear was the product of<lb/>
Washington and Jefferson, Johns Hopkins and Columbia Univer-<lb/>
sities, Bellevue Hospital and the Pasteur Institute. He had<lb/>
studied bacteriology and entomology in the United States and<lb/> Europe.</p>
<p>A paper read by Major Reed before a meeting of the American<lb/>
Public Health Association, at Indianapolis, Oct. 22 - 26, 1900,<lb/>
said: &ldquo;Dr. Lazear, while on a visit to Los Animas Hospital,<lb/>
Sept. 13, 1900, and while collecting blood from yellow<lb/>
fever patients for study, was bitten by a Culex mosquito...<lb/>
As Dr. Lazear had been previously bitten by a contaminated<lb/>
insect without after effects, he deliberately allowed this<lb/>
particular mosquito, which had settled on the back of his<lb/>
hand, to remain until it had satisfied its hunger. On<lb/>
the evening of Sept. 18, five days after the bite, Dr.<lb/>
Lazear complained of feeling &lsquo;out of sorts&rsquo;, and had a<lb/>
chill at 8 p. m... The subsequent history of this case was<lb/>
one of progressive and fatal yellow fever, the death of<lb/>
our much lamented colleague having occurred on the even-<lb/>
ing of Sept. 25, 1900.&rdquo;</p>
<p>9.</p>
<p>3</p>
<pb n="5" id="f06510005"/>
<p>General Albert E. Truby was a lieutenant and the Post Sur-<lb/>
geon at Columbia Barracks when the Major and his Board were<lb/>
there. There was very evident mutual esteem and respect be-<lb/>
tween the distinguished scientist and the young officer.</p>
<p>In his forthcoming autobiography General Truby - after<lb/>
pointing out that Major Reed was in the United States at the<lb/>
time of Dr. Lazear's tragic death will continue: &ldquo;... In La-<lb/>
zear's notebook .. the data on Carroll and Dean and those<lb/>
who did not get yellow fever were clear, but Reed was<lb/>
much troubled as to what to say of Lazear's case. I have<lb/>
a distinct recollection that there were some notations in<lb/>
Lazear's notebook which Reed thought were entries about<lb/>
mosquitoes which Lazear had applied to himself. Reed<lb/>
confided his suspicion to Kean and to me, possibly also<lb/>
to Carroll and Agramonte. Reed believed that when<lb/>
Lazear was taken sick he worried lest his life insurance<lb/>
become forfeited if it became known that he had deliber-<lb/>
ately infected himself with a fatal disease. Was this<lb/>
the reason for Lazear's incomplete entries about himself<lb/>
in his notebook? Did he withold facts to protect his<lb/>
dear ones at this critical moment? Was this why he told<lb/>
Gorgas and Carroll the story about <add>his</add> having been bitten by<lb/>
a mosquito at Los Animas Hospital? Reed believed that<lb/>
it was. A competent scientific investigator who had al-<lb/>
ready produced two cases of yellow fever, Lazear certainly<lb/>
would not knowingly let a mongrel mosquito bite him at a<lb/>
yellow fever hospital, especially when he now knew the<lb/>
danger. He was after information of tremendous importance<lb/>
and the only way to get it was to be bitten by one of his<lb/>
9.<lb/>
4<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f06510006"/>
own mosquitoes hatched and infected under his own super-<lb/>
vision. But there was no way for Reed to prove this view<lb/>
and so ... Reed finally decided to let it appear that he<lb/>
was accidentally infected while in the performance of his<lb/>
duties as a member of the Board, a possibility of course.<lb/>
But all of us were convinced that Lazear had placed the<lb/>
mosquito on his arm just as he did on Carroll in accor-<lb/>
dance <unclear>with<del>b</del>the</unclear> agreement of the non-immune members of the<lb/>
Board.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A tablet to Dr. Lazear's memory, in the amphitheater of<lb/>
Johns Hopkins Hospital bears this inscription, written by for-<lb/>
mer President Eliot, of Harvard:</p>
<p>&ldquo;With more courage than the devotion of a soldier,<lb/>
he risked and lost his life to show how a fearful pesti-<lb/>
lence is communicated and how its ravages may be pre-<lb/>
vented&rdquo;.</p>
<p>9.</p>
<p>5</p>
<pb n="7" id="f06510007"/>
<p><hi>Fomite Theory Exploded</hi>:</p>
<p>Up to that time it was the opinion, among the medical<lb/>
profession as well as the laity, that yellow fever was<lb/>
transmitted by fomites. This belief was so firmly im-<lb/>
planted that it was the custom to thoroughly disinfect<lb/>
clothing and bedding from sections where yellow fever<lb/>
prevailed whether it had been contaminated by contact<lb/>
with yellow fever patients or not.</p>
<p>Major Reed had to be shown. There was erected, at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, a one-room frame building 14 x 20 feet.<lb/>
It was poorly ventilated and wood shutters excluded<lb/>
germ-killing sunlight.</p>
<p>Three groups of men, in turn, occupied this building.<lb/>
Each night they unpacked three large boxes filled with<lb/>
sheets, pillow-slips and blankets purposely soiled -<lb/>
from contact with yellow fever cases - with black vomit<lb/>
and other highly disagreeable matter. A new supply of<lb/>
contaminated bedding was used for each group. Their<lb/>
beds were made with this soiled bedding and the rest<lb/>
was thoroughly shaken and distributed around the room.<lb/>
Each morning the boxes were repacked. The men occu-<lb/>
pied a near-by tent during the day. At the conclusion<lb/>
of their ordeal each group was quarantined for five days<lb/>
and returned to duty none the worse for their experience.</p>
<p>The men who underwent the fomite experiments:<lb/>
V<lb/>
<table rows="3" cols="2">
<row>
<cell>Dr. Robert P. Cook)<lb/>
Levi E. Folk *(<lb/>
Warren G. Jernegan*)</cell><cell>From Nov. 30 to Dec. 19, 1900.<lb/>
20 days.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>James L. Hanberry *)<lb/>
Edward Wetherwalks*)</cell><cell>From Dec. 21, 1900<lb/>
to Jan. 10, 1901. - 21 days.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>James Hildebrand *)<lb/>
Thomas M. England *)</cell><cell>From Jan. 11<lb/>
to Jan. 31, 1901. - 20 days.</cell></row></table></p>
<p>(* indicates member of Hospital Corps detachment.)</p>
<p><hi>e</hi></p>
<p><hi>Innoculation by Mosquito-bite</hi>:</p>
<p>Having proved that the disease could NOT be transmit-<lb/>
ted by fomites, the Board proved that it COULD be caused,<lb/>
at will, by the bite of a species of mosquito twelve<lb/>
days after one had fed on a yellow fever sufferer and,<lb/>
from then on, as long as the mosquito lived. This spec-<lb/>
ies was first called Culex Fasciatus, then Stegomyia<lb/>
Fasciatus and, finally, Aedes Egypti.</p>
<p>9.</p>
<p>6</p>
<pb n="8" id="f06510008"/>
<p>It required a great many experimental innoculations -<lb/>
each on a human being - to ascertain that there must be<lb/>
a twelve-day incubation period before an infected mos-<lb/>
quito can transmit the disease. That Major Reed per-<lb/>
sisted, after many disheartening failures, is indicative<lb/>
of his patience, thoroughness and determination. .It is<lb/>
highly probable that Dr. Finlay did not discover that a<lb/>
twelve-day waiting period is necessary and that may<lb/>
account for his inability to demonstrate his theory in<lb/>
spite of more than 100 experiments.</p>
<p>In Major Reed's work, eight American volunteers were<lb/>
given yellow fever by mosquito-bite. While some of the<lb/>
earlier innoculations were negative, and several innocula-<lb/>
tions necessary to produce the disease, all of the last<lb/>
series produced yellow fever with certainty.</p>
<p><hi>Infection by Blood-Innoculation</hi>:</p>
<p>The reason for innoculation by the injection of infec-<lb/>
ted blood is difficult for a layman to understand.<lb/>
These experiments were useful in establishing that yellow<lb/>
fever is transmitted NATURALLY by no means other than<lb/>
mosquito-bite.</p>
<p>They showed that the specific agent which caused the<lb/>
disease is present in the blood, at least during the<lb/>
first, second and third days of the attack. That the<lb/>
blood which caused the disease did not contain bacteria<lb/>
which would grow in any of the usual laboratory media.<lb/>
That its passage through an intermediate host (a mos-<lb/>
quito), although this seems to be nature's method, is<lb/>
not necessary to the life-cycle of the virus.</p>
<p>Blood-innoculation showed that the disease is caused<lb/>
by a virus in that it cannot be seen in a microscope or<lb/>
grown as a culture. This was proven by innoculating<lb/>
some of the non-immune volunteers with serum filtered<lb/>
through a bacteria-proof filter. (A Berkefeld filter<lb/>
of unglazed porcelain.)</p>
<p>The special reason for my innoculation will appear<lb/>
later.</p>
<p><hi>I go to Columbia Barracks and Get a Job</hi>:</p>
<p>When the Post at Guanajay was about to be abandoned,<lb/>
because of a yellow fever epidemic, I applied for assign-<lb/>
ment to China or the Philippines with the next detach-<lb/>
ment of troops leaving Cuba for either place.</p>
<p>9.</p>
<p>7.</p>
<pb n="9" id="f06510009"/>
<p>The answer had been to send me to the probable &ldquo;take<lb/>
off place&rdquo;, Columbia Barracks.</p>
<p>Then, early in October, 1900, I was detailed for duty<lb/>
with the Board. When Major Reed and Dr. Carroll came<lb/>
to Cuba, from the Army Medical <del>College</del><add>School</add>, in Washington,<lb/>
<del>that</del>they brought with them a hospital steward and a private<lb/>
of the Hospital Corps. When the enlistment of the pri-<lb/>
vate expired he did not re-enlist and the Post Surgeon,<lb/>
Lieutenant Albert E. Truby, recommended me to Major Reed<lb/>
for the job.</p>
<p>Major Reed and Dr. Carroll were bacteriologists.<lb/>
They set up a laboratory in the shanty that, when the<lb/>
post hospital was in tents, had been the operating room.<lb/>
Both spent a great deal of time at their microscopes in<lb/>
a vain effort to find the micro-organism responsible<lb/>
for yellow fever.</p>
<p><hi>My Cuban Farm</hi>:</p>
<p>Most of my work was in this laboratory where, under<lb/>
direction of Hospital Steward Neats, I had hundreds of<lb/>
captive mosquitoes. Many of these had been matured<lb/>
from pupae or larvae which I had obtained from recept-<lb/>
acles containing stagnant water. Also, it was my job<lb/>
to &ldquo;raise&rdquo; mosquitoes from eggs. As a female mosquito<lb/>
cannot deposit her eggs until she has had a meal of<lb/>
blood, I had allowed a great many mosquitoes to feed on<lb/>
my hands and wrists.</p>
<p>Both Major Reed and Dr. Carroll, as they were busy<lb/>
at their microscopes and I with my &ldquo;pets&rdquo;, talked of<lb/>
plans for the work of the Board and of progress being<lb/>
made, paying no more attention to me than to the furn-<lb/>
iture.</p>
<p>I</p>
<p>I heard them discuss the fear that their &ldquo;good luck&rdquo;,<lb/>
in having had no deaths among the experimental cases,<lb/>
might end and that a single death would &ldquo;scare off&rdquo;<lb/>
additional volunteers and halt the work.</p>
<p>Both expressed gratitude at their good fortune in<lb/>
having the services of the yellow fever specialist, Dr.<lb/>
Roger Post Ames. They attributed much of their good<lb/>
luck to his fidelity and skill. On one occasion Major<lb/>
Reed tolf Dr. Carroll that Dr. Ames' male nurse, Gustav<lb/>
Lambert, wanted to volunteer for innoculation. Both<lb/>
agreed that Lambert was too valuable, assisting Dr. Ames,<lb/>
to risk breaking up the combination. I mention this<lb/>
9.<lb/>
8<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="f06510010"/>
because I have always felt that, while others have been<lb/>
honored, these two have been unjustly left out.</p>
<p>Another subject I heard discussed related to Lieut.<lb/>
Albert E. Truby. After Dr. Lazear's death, Major Reed<lb/>
planned to ask the Surgeon General to appoint Lieut.<lb/>
Truby to fill the vacancy on the Board. The Major had<lb/>
discussed this with the Lieutenant and both had agreed<lb/>
to submit themselves for innoculation. The Department<lb/>
Chief Surgeon, Major Kean, objected to the appointment<lb/>
on the ground that Lieut Truby was badly needed by him.<lb/>
The Major was disappointed and did not ask for the ap-<lb/>
pointment of anyone else.</p>
<p><hi>I Hear a Discussion</hi>:</p>
<p>On the morning of January 24, 1901, when Major Reed<lb/>
and Dr. Carroll appeared at the laboratory, they contin-<lb/>
ued a discussion that had evidently been going on for<lb/>
some time. It appeared that a patient with experimen-<lb/>
tal yellow fever (Forbes) had reached the stage where<lb/>
his blood should be taken to innoculate the next sub-<lb/>
ject and that the man who had volunteered had backed out.</p>
<p>Major Reed insisted that he was going to have himself<lb/>
innoculated. Dr. Carroll was pleading with him to<lb/>
change his mind, pointing out that the Major's age was<lb/>
against him and that a recent illness had left him in no<lb/>
condition to fight yellow fever. The Major said that<lb/>
if Dr. Finlay's latest theory was correct he would be in<lb/>
no danger.</p>
<p>I got only a vague idea of what the new theory was at<lb/>
that time but, later, fould this explanation: In the<lb/>
New York Medical Record of May 27, 1900, Dr. Finlay mod-<lb/>
ified his original theory &ldquo;to include the important cir-<lb/>
cumstance that the faculty of transmitting the yel-<lb/>
low fever germ need not be limited to the parent<lb/>
insect, directly contaminated by stinging a yellow<lb/>
fever patient (or perhaps by contact with or feed-<lb/>
ing upon his discharges), but may be likewise<lb/>
inherited by the next generation of mosquitoes<lb/>
issued from the contaminated parent.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Major Reed pointed out that he had allowed several<lb/>
such &ldquo;next generation&rdquo; mosquitoes to feed on his hands.<lb/>
(The hemoglobin of the blood seems necessary for the<lb/>
maturation of the ovume of the female mosquito and she<lb/>
will not deposit her eggs until she has had a meal of<lb/>
blood.)</p>
<p>9</p>
<p>9.</p>
<pb n="11" id="f06510011"/>
<p>We had fed our blood to a great many mosquitoes hatch-<lb/>
ed from eggs deposited by infected mosquitoes to deter-<lb/>
mine whether they, in turn, would deposit eggs; whether<lb/>
eggs they did deposit would hatch and whether the new<lb/>
generation was normal. (Innoculation with yellow fever<lb/>
seemed to have no effect on the insect.)</p>
<p>The Major said that if Dr. Finlay's new theory was<lb/>
correct he would have contracted yellow fever. On the<lb/>
other hand, if he was innoculated with blood and got the<lb/>
disease, it would indicate that he was not a natural<lb/>
immune and that the modified theory was erroneous. He<lb/>
admitted, when pinned down by Dr. Carroll, that he did<lb/>
not think there was anything in it.</p>
<p>They continued to discuss the Major's proposed innoc-<lb/>
ulation, intermittently, until he left the laboratory in<lb/>
something of a temper with the declaration that he would<lb/>
be innoculated &ldquo;tomorrow&rdquo; and there was no use discus-<lb/>
sing it farther.</p>
<p><hi>I Become a Guinea Pig</hi>:</p>
<p>Next morning Dr. Carroll was first to reach the lab-<lb/>
oratory. I asked him if I would not do as well as the<lb/>
Major for the innoculation. He said &ldquo;no&rdquo; with apparent<lb/>
regret, pointed out that the Major was determoned to use<lb/>
this as a means of testing Dr. Finlay's modified theory<lb/>
and briefly outlined the new idea. I told him I had<lb/>
fed more mosquitoes hatched from the eggs of infected<lb/>
insects than the Major had and my statement was confirm-<lb/>
ed by Steward Neate.</p>
<p>When the Major arrived Dr. Carroll sent me on an<lb/>
errand. When I returned the Major asked me if I real-<lb/>
ized what I was letting myself in for. I told him I<lb/>
had nursed yellow fever at Guanajay Barracks and had<lb/>
seen men die with it. He asked me why I was doing it<lb/>
and seemed satisfied with my answer.</p>
<p>I do not know what I told him but one thing is cer-<lb/>
tain, I did not tell him - or even intimate - that I<lb/>
had volunteered with the idea of &ldquo;saving&rdquo; the Major.<lb/>
I didn't even think of it in that light. From what I<lb/>
had heard Major Reed and Dr. Carroll say, I knew some-<lb/>
thing of what proof of the &ldquo;mosquito theory&rdquo; would mean<lb/>
to humanity. I knew that Major Reed was the main<lb/>
spring that made the work of the Board tick and that if<lb/>
he was sick of yellow fever and had a slow recovery - as<lb/>
Dr. Carroll had - the work would all but stop.</p>
<p>10</p>
<pb n="12" id="f06510012"/>
<p>Then, too, there is something in my makeup that has<lb/>
always made me willing to &ldquo;die for dear old Siwash&rdquo; -<lb/>
any old Siwash in which I was very interested.</p>
<p>And here, as said in the movies, is where we came in.</p>
<p>I was in an ambulance on my way to Camp Lazear - re-<lb/>
member? There I was assigned to a small tent and at<lb/>
liberty to go where I pleased, within the camp, while<lb/>
the &ldquo;bugs&rdquo; with which I had been innoculated set up<lb/>
housekeeping and raised families in my blood stream.</p>
<p>One of the first things I did was to write home.<lb/>
I told my Mother I had been detailed to accompany a troop<lb/>
of the Seventh Cavalry on a practice march into the in-<lb/>
terior of the Island and would not be able to write again<lb/>
for two or three weeks. My conscience bothered me about<lb/>
this. I wanted to leave things so that the folks at<lb/>
home would not worry when they did not hear from me for<lb/>
a while and that was the most reasonable explanation that<lb/>
occured to me. I did not like the idea of lieing in my<lb/>
letter for I realized that it might be the last letter<lb/>
I would ever write home.</p>
<p>Time passed slowly. I knew, from what I had heard<lb/>
about previous innoculations, that there was a wide varia-<lb/>
tion in the time between innoculation and the chill that<lb/>
heralds the disease. I don't think I worried much - cer-<lb/>
tainly not enough to interfere with my appetite. I had<lb/>
a bad quarter-hour, however, when I heard that Dr. Ames<lb/>
was sick and, himself, in the hospital. He had doctored<lb/>
all of the experimental yellow fever cases and had not<lb/>
lost one.</p>
<p>What happened next is best told by the official report<lb/>
of my case as printed in Senate Documents, Volume 61,<lb/>
of 1911:</p>
<p>***Case IV. - J. H. A., American, non-immune, aged 22,<lb/>
with his full consent, received subcutaneously, at 12:15<lb/>
p. m., January 25, 1901, 1 cc of blood taken from the<lb/>
median-cephalic vein of Case III, just 27 1/2 hours after<lb/>
the commencement of the latter's attack of yellow fever<lb/>
(Temperature 102.6&deg; F.) The subject remained in his<lb/>
usual condition during January 26 and 27, except that on<lb/>
the afternoon of the last mentioned date he complained of<lb/>
occipital headache. This was present on the following<lb/>
morning, January 28; otherwise he felt well. His tem-<lb/>
perature at noon was 98.6&deg; F., and his pulse 68.<lb/>
Occipital headache continued. He partook of dinner with<lb/>
fair appetite<lb/>
11<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f06510013"/>
&ldquo;He was not seen again until 3 p.m. In the meantime,<lb/>
at 1:15 p. m., the subject states that, while alone in<lb/>
his tent, he began to feel cold and that this was fol-<lb/>
lowed by a decided chill with increase of headache.<lb/>
He noted the hour in writing at the time. At 3 p. m.<lb/>
his temperature was 103.6&deg; F., and his pulse 120.<lb/>
His eyes were intensely congested and the face deeply<lb/>
suffused. (The official report does not say so, but<lb/>
here is where I took a two-mule power ambulance<lb/>
to the yellow fever hospital. I remember start-<lb/>
ing but do not remember getting there.)<lb/>
&ldquo;The patient was very restless and complained bitterly<lb/>
of occipital headache and <hi>backache</hi>. Photophobia was<lb/>
very marked. He vomited several times in the next<lb/>
two hours. Skin hot and dry. The height of the pri-<lb/>
mary paroxyam was reached at 3:30 p. m. at which hour<lb/>
the temperature was 104.2&deg; F., <del><unclear></unclear></del><lb/>
and the pulse 120. The subsequence was one of severe<lb/>
yellow fever. There was no remission of the fever un-<lb/>
til the fourth day, when the temperature fell to 101.2&deg;<lb/>
F. Now, for the first time, the patient ceased to<lb/>
complain of occipital headache and backache. Albumin<lb/>
appeared at the end of 18 1/2 hours. * * A few hyaline<lb/>
casts were also present at this time. The specimen of<lb/>
urine passed at 6:40 a.m., January 30, contained albumin<lb/>
one-twentieth by volume, and many fine and coarse, gran-<lb/>
ular, bile-tinted casts. Ocular jaundice appeared on<lb/>
the third day. The skin of the face and the anterior<lb/>
part of the neck and thorax was tinted on the fourth day.<lb/>
This rapidly became intensified and general. The secon-<lb/>
dary fever lasted about 50 hours, the temperature falling<lb/>
to 97.2&deg; F. at 12 o'clock (midnight) of the fifth day.<lb/>
Marked fluctuations of temperature continued until the<lb/>
eleventh day of the illness. Recovery was slow and much<lb/>
delayed by the development of a carbuncle on the left<lb/>
sacral region. A trace of albumin was still present on<lb/>
March first, 32 days after the attack begun. (Chart IV)&rdquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>In this report, Major Reed emphasized occipital head-<lb/>
ache. What he lightly dismisses as &ldquo;backache&rdquo; lingers<lb/>
in my memory as intense and unremitting pain. I shall<lb/>
refer to it again later.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;carbuncle&rdquo; referred to provided opportunity for<lb/>
Dr. Ames and Lambert to demonstrate why Major Reed regar-<lb/>
ded their fidelity and abilities so highly. When my<lb/>
carbuncle developed, the doctor who was pinch hitting for<lb/>
Dr. Ames did nothing to relieve me. This worried Lam-<lb/>
bert and he went to the post hospital and, after waiting<lb/>
12<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="f06510014"/>
until Dr. Ames' nurse - Miss Nellie Lewis - had left his<lb/>
room, he told Dr. Ames about me. Dr. Ames had Lambert<lb/>
and another Corps man carry him, on his bed, to my bed-<lb/>
side where he opened my carbuncle. When Lambert return-<lb/>
ed Dr. Ames to his room, Miss Lewis had summoned the Post<lb/>
Surgeon, Captain Stark, and the latter threatened to have<lb/>
Lambert court-martialed. Dr. Ames told Captain Stark<lb/>
that Lambert was only carrying out his (Ames') orders.</p>
<p>out</p>
<p>My enlistment expired April 24, 1902 and I left the<lb/>
Army. Then my yellow fever experience was no more than<lb/>
an interesting memory until late in 1929 when a friend<lb/>
wrote asking whether I knew there was a bill affecting<lb/>
me in congress.</p>
<p>On getting a copy of the bill, I found that it pro-<lb/>
vided an annuity of $1500. for life, a gold medal and<lb/>
inclusion on an honor roll to be published annually in<lb/>
the Official Army Register. (The names which appear<lb/>
on the honor roll will be given later.) Unfortunately,<lb/>
my name was in the bill as &ldquo;James A. Andrus&rdquo;. The bill<lb/>
was approved by President Hoover Feb. 28, 1929. Then<lb/>
it was necessary for Congressman Wolverton to put through<lb/>
a special bill to correct my name.</p>
<p>That &ldquo;Backacke.&rdquo;</p>
<p>For quite a number of years there has been something<lb/>
wrong with my spine. It was thought <add>by my doctors</add> to be arthritis.<lb/>
From 1918 until 1932 I wore a steel, spinal brace.<lb/>
March first, 1932, I could no longer walk and had to go<lb/>
to bed. From May 13 until Oct. 6, 1932, I was at<lb/>
Walter Reed Hospital, Washington, where my trouble was<lb/>
diagnosed as &ldquo;syringo-myelia&rdquo; and I was told I could<lb/>
never walk again. As this is written (October, 1940,)<lb/>
I am still bedfast.</p>
<p>I do not know whether my condition is due to my hav-<lb/>
ing had yellow fever or not. The doctors at Walter<lb/>
Reed Hospital were unable to pin it on tuberculosis,<lb/>
syphlis, or any one of several other possible causes.</p>
<p>I cannot forget the intense back-pains incident to my<lb/>
attack of yellow fever. Then, too, another of the vol-<lb/>
unteers, John R. Kissinger, was bedfast with spinal<lb/>
trouble several years although he has since recovered.<lb/>
Senate report 210, on Senate bill 6272, passed Feb. 15,<lb/>
1910, said, in part, * * &ldquo;he is unable to furnish direct<lb/>
testimony tracing his present grevious condition<lb/>
back to yellow fever in the Army, although there<lb/>
is but little doubt that the relation of cause and<lb/>
effect exists. Since his discharge he has never<lb/>
13<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="f06510015"/>
SP-11<lb/>
been in good health, which he at first attributed<lb/>
to slow recovery from that disease, thinking that<lb/>
with the passing of time his constitution would<lb/>
enable him to throw it off. He continued to fail,<lb/>
however, and is now a helpless paralytic.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I would rather think my condition is due to my humble<lb/>
part in the work of Major Reed and his Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board than from some mysterious and unaccountable cause.</p>
<p>On those occasions when I am tempted to rail at the<lb/>
fate that had kept me in bed so long, without hope of<lb/>
ever being able to resume a normal way of life, I like<lb/>
to think that I may have contributed, in some measure,<lb/>
to such results as these:</p>
<p>At the time Major Reed's Board was experimenting,<lb/>
Major W. C. Gorgas was Chief Sanitary Officer on the<lb/>
staff of General Leonard Wood. He is said to have had<lb/>
some doubt about the &ldquo;mosquito theory&rdquo; at first. He<lb/>
followed every development, however, and, when he con-<lb/>
cluded that the &ldquo;theory&rdquo; was sound, he exterminated mos-<lb/>
quitoes with the speed and thoroughness that marked his<lb/>
work, later, as Chief Sanitary Officer on the construct-<lb/>
ion of the Panama Canal. You may judge what the ver-<lb/>
dict of &ldquo;guilty&rdquo; against the mosquito meant, in the<lb/>
fight against yellow fever, by what it accomplished in<lb/>
Havana alone. From 1880 to 1899 there were an average<lb/>
of 483.7 deaths per year in Havana. In 1900 - before<lb/>
the &ldquo;theory&rdquo; was accepted and the campaign of mosquito-<lb/>
extermination launched - there were 1240 cases, in<lb/>
Havana, with 302 deaths. In 1901 - when the war on<lb/>
mosquitoes was only started - there were 30 cases and<lb/>
but 6 deaths. The monthly record follows:</p>
<p>
<table rows="5" cols="15">
<row> <cell>Year</cell><cell></cell><cell>Jan</cell><cell>Feb</cell><cell>Mar</cell><cell>Apr</cell><cell>May</cell><cell>Jun</cell><cell>Jul</cell><cell>Aug</cell><cell>Sep</cell><cell>Oct</cell><cell>Nov</cell><cell>Dec</cell><cell>Total</cell></row>
<row> <cell>1900</cell><cell>Cases</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>96</cell><cell>219</cell><cell>269</cell><cell>308</cell><cell>214</cell><cell>62</cell><cell>1240</cell></row>
<row> <cell></cell><cell>Deaths</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>49</cell><cell>52</cell><cell>74</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>302</cell></row>
<row> <cell>1901</cell><cell>Cases</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>30</cell></row>
<row> <cell></cell><cell>Deaths</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>6</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>In 1901 mosquito-extermination was the only unusual<lb/>
method employed. Results show, rather conclusively,<lb/>
that it is the only method needed. Since 1901 yellow<lb/>
fever has been unknown in Havana except a few cases<lb/>
brought into the City from outside infection.</p>
<p>In all parts of the world, due to the findings of<lb/>
the Yellow Fever Board, under Major Walter Reed, yellow<lb/>
fever has been stamped out by wiping out mosquitoes.</p>
<p>14</p>
<pb n="16" id="f06510016"/>
<p><unclear>19</unclear></p>
<p><hi>Another of my Gloom Chasers</hi>:</p>
<p>General Leonard Wood was Governor-General of Cuba at<lb/>
the time Major Reed's Board was working there.<lb/>
The General was a physician before he was a soldier.<lb/>
He fully understood what the Major was trying to do.<lb/>
He authorized the innoculation of soldiers who volun-<lb/>
teered and, otherwise, lent every encouragement.</p>
<p>At a memorial meeting of scientific men, in Washing-<lb/>
ton, shortly after Major Reed's death, General Wood said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know of no other man on this side of the world<lb/>
who has done so much for humanity as Dr. Reed.<lb/>
His discovery resulted in saving more lives annually<lb/>
than were lost in the Cuban war, and saves the com-<lb/>
mercial interests of the world a greater financial<lb/>
loss each year than the cost of the Cuban war.<lb/>
He came to Cuba at a time when one-third of the of-<lb/>
ficers of my staff died of yellow fever, and we<lb/>
were discouraged at the failure of our efforts to<lb/>
control the disease. In the months when the dis-<lb/>
ease was ordinarily worst the disease was checked<lb/>
and driven from Havana. That was the first time<lb/>
in nearly 200 years that the city had been rid of it.<lb/>
The value of his discovery can not be appreciated by<lb/>
persons who are not familiar with the conditions of<lb/>
tropical countries. Hereafter it will never be<lb/>
possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that<lb/>
quarantine will exist from the mouth of the <unclear>Potomac</unclear><lb/>
to the mouth of the Rio Grande. Future generations<lb/>
will appreciate fully the value of Dr. Reed's ser-<lb/>
vices. His was the originating, directing and con-<lb/>
trolling mind in this work and the others were<lb/>
assistants only.&rdquo;</p>
<p>15</p>
<pb n="17" id="f06510017"/>
<p>. . . . . . . . . <hi>R O L L  O F  H O N O R</hi> . . . . . . . . .</p>
<p>An act of Congress, approved Feb. 28, 1929, provides that:<lb/>
&ldquo;..in special recognition of the high public service rendered<lb/>
and disabilities contracted in the interest of humanity and<lb/>
science as voluntary subjects for experimentation during the<lb/>
yellow fever investigations in Cuba, the Secretary of War be<lb/>
directed to publish annually in the Army Register a roll of<lb/>
honor on which shall be carried the following names:&rdquo;</p>
<p>
<list type="simple">
<head><hi>M E M B E R S  O F  T H E  B O A R D</hi></head>
<item>MAJOR WALTER REED - Chairman of the Board</item>
<item>Dr. JAMES CARROLL - Had experimental yellow fever</item>
<item>Dr. JESSE W. LAZEAR - Died of yellow fever</item>
<item>Dr. ARISTIDES AGRAMONTE -</item>
</list></p>
<p><hi>VOLUNTEERS INNOCULATED WITH YELLOW FEVER</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="8">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Name of Volunteer</cell><cell>Mosquito<lb/>
Innocu-<lb/>
ulation</cell><cell>Blood<lb/>
Innoc-<lb/>
ulation</cell><cell>Fomite<lb/>
Exper-<lb/>
iment</cell><cell>Date<lb/>
Taken<lb/>
Sick</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>William H. Dean (XY)</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>9- 6-1900</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>John R. Kissinger *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>12- 8-1900</cell><cell>1</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>John J. Moran</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>12-25-1900</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Warren G. Jernegan *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>Negative</cell><cell>x</cell><cell>o</cell><cell>1-8-1901</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>3</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>William Olsen *</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>1-11-1901</cell><cell>3</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>4</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Levi E. Folk *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>o</cell><cell>1-23-1901</cell><cell>4</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>5</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>Wallace Forbes *</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>1-24-1901</cell><cell>5</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>6</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>John H. Andrus *</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>1-28-1901</cell><cell>6</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>7</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>Clyde L. West *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2- 3-1901</cell><cell>7</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>8</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>James L. Hanberry *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>o</cell><cell>2- 9-1901</cell><cell>8</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>9</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>Charles G. Sonntag *</cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2-10-1901</cell><cell>9</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>12</cell><cell>Paul Hamann</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>10-19-1901</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>13</cell><cell>A. W. Covington</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>10-19-1901</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>14</cell><cell>John R. Bullard</cell><cell></cell><cell>x</cell><cell></cell><cell>10-23-1901</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p><unclear>Dunolley F F</unclear></p>
<p><hi>VOLUNTEERS EXPOSED TO FOMITES</hi></p>
<p>
<table rows="7" cols="4">
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>Dr. Robert P. Cook</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell>Warren G. Jernegan *</cell><cell>From Nov. 30, to Dec. 19, 1900<lb/>
-20 days</cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>6</cell><cell>Levi E. Folk</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>James L. Hanberry *</cell><cell>From Dec. 21, 1900,<lb/>
to Jan. 31, 1901 - 21 days</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>10</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>Edward Wetherwalks *</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>11</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>James Hildebrand *</cell><cell>From Jan. 11,<lb/>
to Jan. 31, 1901 - 20 days</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>12</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>Thomas M. England *</cell><cell></cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>After submitting to the fomite experiment without getting the<lb/>
disease, Jernegan (4) was twice innoculated by mosquitoes but<lb/>
escaped infection; then innoculated by blood; the only volun-<lb/>
teer to take all 3 experiments. Folk (6) and Hanberry (10)<lb/>
were innoculated by mosquitoes. Wetherwalks (16), infected<lb/>
by 12 mosquitoes, was not ill. Hildebrand (17) was refused<lb/>
mosquito innoculation because of his age. Dr. Cook (15) and<lb/>
<hi>England (18) were not innoculated - did not have yellow fever</hi>.<lb/>
Names are from the official roll. Arrangement is author's.<lb/>
* - Indicates member of Hospital Corps detachment.</p>
<p>16</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
