<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="t06512041">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memoir: L. S. Reed, by T. McN. Simpson, [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Simpson, T. McN.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06512041</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Reed, Thomas Walk</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Pharaba W.</name>
<name type="person">Keesee, Gervas M.</name>
<name type="person">Crowder, Thomas A.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Mary</name>
<name type="person">Blincoe, Laura Reed</name>
<name type="person">Reed, James C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Christopher</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Annie</name>
<name type="person">Cannon, James, Jr.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Gayle, R.F.</name>
<name type="person">Compton, R.A.</name>
<name type="person">Grant, W.E.</name>
<name type="place">Durant's Neck (Perquimans County, N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Farmville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Currituck Mission (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Princess Anne County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Nottoway County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Gates (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Murfreesboro (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Prince Edward County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Bedford County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Brunswick County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Norfolk (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Amherst (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Henrico County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Cumberland County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Danville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Petersburg (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Harrisonburg (Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">06512041</idno>
<title>Memoir: L. S. Reed, by T. McN. Simpson, [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Simpson summarizes the life of Lemuel S. Reed, as he knew him through religious work, and gives an account of his death and funeral. Simpson conducted the funeral service.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Memoir: L. S. Reed, by T. McN. Simpson, [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06512041"/>
<p>from Mr R M White<lb/>
Washington St Meth Ch<lb/>
Petersburg, Va</p>
<p><hi>MEMOIR</hi></p>
<p>REV. L. S. REED<lb/>
by<lb/>
T. McN. Simpson</p>
<p>Rev. Lemuel Sutton Reed was one of North Carolina's sterling sons,<lb/>
and one of nature's noblemen. To me, he was a father in Israel, and a<lb/>
friend indeed. Upon his knees, in the little country school of their<lb/>
neighborhood, my mother learned her A B C's; and upon his counsel and<lb/>
support, I took my first steps in the itinerant ministry. He presided<lb/>
at the Quarterly Conference that licensed me to preach, and recommended<lb/>
me to the Annual Conference; he gave me work on his district, encour-<lb/>
aged my discontinuance to pursue a course at Randolph-Macon College,<lb/>
received me again into his district, and continued to the hour of his<lb/>
death my faithful friend and affectionate adviser. Upon his newly<lb/>
made grave I would place today the sweetest flower in the garden of<lb/>
my heart; and to his memory, I would give the tenderest tribute of<lb/>
my love.</p>
<p>Brother Reed was born in Durant's Neck, Perquimans County, N.C.,<lb/>
May 5th, 1819, and died in Farmville, Prince Edward Co. Va. December 18th,<lb/>
1897. Between those dates, embracing nearly four-score years, he<lb/>
fought the good fight of faith, and he kept the faith. His early years<lb/>
were largely spent in school work, first as a pupil, then as a teacher;<lb/>
but his advantages were limited to the facilities of his own and an<lb/>
adjoining county, and he never had the privilege of a college course.<lb/>
He was, however, a thoughtful observer and a careful student of men<lb/>
and books; and being naturally well endowed, mentally, morally and<lb/>
physically, he acquired a competent furnishing, and he showed himself<lb/>
a workman that needed not to be ashamed. Having been religiously<lb/>
trained by his parents, Thomas Walke and Elizabeth Reed, he publicly<lb/>
professed saving faith in Christ August 13, 1838, at Oak Grove Church,<lb/>
in his native county, under the ministry of the Rev. Gervas M. Keesee,<lb/>
and joined the Methodist Episcopal Church. On Oct. 16, 1846, under a<lb/>
conviction of a divine call to the work, he applied for and obtained<lb/>
license to preach from the Quarterly Conference of the Pasquotank<lb/>
Cirvuit, to which he had moved after his marriage in 1839; and in<lb/>
Nov. 1848, at the session of his Annual Conference in Elizabeth City, N.C.,<lb/>
he applied for admission on trial, into the traveling connection; but<lb/>
being pale and thin from recent sickness, and being opposed by a lead-<lb/>
ing member on the ground that he would soon be in his grave, and his<lb/>
dependent family a care upon the Church, he was rejected. Disappointed,<lb/>
but not disheartened, he accepted his defeat as a providential indication<lb/>
that his call was simply to the local ranks, and he set himself anew to<lb/>
the tasks of the school room. His Presiding Elder, however, Rev. Thos.<lb/>
A Crowder, dissatisfied with the unfavorable action of the Conference,<lb/>
advised a renewal of his application; and being improved in health, he<lb/>
stoos again at the door of his Conference in Nov. 1849, at Petersburg, Va.<lb/>
was admitted without a dissenting vote. His former opponent giving him<lb/>
his support, and continuing ever his steadfast friend. In 1851 he was<lb/>
ordained a deacon by Bishop Andrew, and in 1853, an elder by Bishop Paine.<lb/>
Through fifty-one years he bore the title and adorned the office of a<lb/>
Methodist preacher; and for more than forty of these he went in and out<lb/>
among us an active, effective itinerant, observing the injunction:<lb/>
Watch thou in all things; endure afflictions; do the work of an evan-<lb/>
gelist; make full proof of thy ministry. &ldquo;Every part of our territory has<lb/>
praise for him in its gates; and every kind of our regular work -<lb/>
missions, circuits, districts - bear witness to his faithful, practical<lb/>
hand.</p>
<pb n="2" id="f06512042"/>
<p>- 2 -</p>
<p>Currituck Mission, Gloucester, Princess Anne, Gates, N.C. Murfrees-<lb/>
boro, N.C., Prince Edward (twice), Bedford, Nottoway, Brunswick, East<lb/>
Rockingham of the Baltimore Conference - where he spent the year 1870<lb/>
to be near an aged relative - Amherst, Henrico, and Cumberland Circuits,<lb/>
and Charlottesville, Murfreesboro, Norfolk, Danville Farmville and<lb/>
Petersburg Districts were the fields of his labors, the scenes of his<lb/>
toils and triumphs. Three times he was elected by his brethren as a<lb/>
delegate, and once as an alternate, to the General Conference of his<lb/>
Church, and he represented them through the sessions of 1866, 1874,<lb/>
and 1878, and during a part of the session of 1886, when Dr. Bennett<lb/>
became too feeble to attend. He was married twice - first to<lb/>
Miss Pharaba White, of Pasquotank Co. N.C., Feb. - 1839, then on<lb/>
Dec. 11, 1866 to Mrs. Mary C. Kyle, of Harrisonburg, Va., who survives<lb/>
him. Both were helpmeets indeed, and blessed the hearts and brightened<lb/>
the home to which they gave themselves. Six children live and &ldquo;rise<lb/>
up to call him blessed&rdquo; - Mrs. J. W. Blincoe, Ashland, Va., Rev. J. C.<lb/>
Reed, Virginia Conference, Judge Christopher Reed, St. Louis, Mo.,<lb/>
Mt. Thomas Reed, Kansas, Dr. Walter Reed, Georgetown, D.C., and<lb/>
Mrs. D. T. Elam, Farmville, Va. (the only child by his second marriage,<lb/>
and the one at whose home he breathed his last. The domestic relations<lb/>
of Bro. Reed were most charmingly tender and sweet. He was revered as<lb/>
the worthy head of his family, and enjoyed as the cordial companion of<lb/>
its members. His children were the pride and joy of his heart, and he<lb/>
was their friend and associate. Few men have succeeded better in com-<lb/>
manding their households after them, and few have left more creditable<lb/>
representatives of their names. His home was ever the sphere of<lb/>
bright and happy fellowship, and the scene of generous and unaffected<lb/>
hospitality. His door never closed against &ldquo;an angel unawares&rdquo;, and his<lb/>
beds and his board were never more enjoyed than when shared by his<lb/>
friends. His conversation was free and easy and instructive. He never<lb/>
lowered the standard of true ministerial dignity; yet he never re-<lb/>
dtrained nor repressed &ldquo;the feast of reason and flow of soul.&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;His speech was always with grace, seasoned with salt.&rdquo; In the councils<lb/>
of his church and the advisory boards of his community he was esteemed<lb/>
for his strong common sense, and for his fine practical wisdom. He was<lb/>
gifted with unusual powers of penetration and discrimination, and his<lb/>
knowledge of men and measures was exceedingly accurate. Bishops availed<lb/>
themselves of his counsels and young men sought and followed his advice.</p>
<p>In manner Bro. Reed was frank, candid, transparent. You knew where<lb/>
he stood on all important questions, and which side he espoused in all<lb/>
serious controversies. He made no concealments, practiced no diplomacy,<lb/>
but exercised himself to have a conscience void of offense. His convic-<lb/>
tions were always positive and his methods straightforward; but his<lb/>
spirit was kind and considerate. He was a scion of English stock, and<lb/>
his build and his bearing were those of the sturdy Briton.</p>
<p>In the pulpit he was grave, deliberate and impressive. His sermons<lb/>
gave evidence of patient study and careful preparation. He avoided all<lb/>
ostentation and devoted himself to a plain exposition of the Word, and a<lb/>
practical application of the truth. souls were nourished by his ministry,<lb/>
consciences were quickened, sinners were saved and saints built up in<lb/>
their most holy faith.</p>
<p>At the session of his Conference in Danville, Va., November 1893,<lb/>
he felt that perhaps the time had come for him to lay down the work of<lb/>
a regular itinerant preacher, and to seek the relation of a superannuate.<lb/>
But he was reluctant to give up his &ldquo;loved employ,&rdquo; and enter a relation<lb/>
in which he had been restless in 1891; after consultation, however,<lb/>
with his son in the conference, he asked to be retired, and he never<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="f06512043"/>
- 3 -<lb/>
had the privilege of assembling again with the brethren that he had<lb/>
loved so long and served with so faithfully. His Conference was to him<lb/>
as the apple of his eye. As the time for its annual session drew near,<lb/>
he would catch the spirit of its sacred reunions, as the war-horse sniffs<lb/>
the battle afar off, and he would plan and prepare to attend, with the<lb/>
enthusiasm of a school boy anticipating a return to his home. It was<lb/>
positively pathetic at times to see his strong, hopeful spirit attempt<lb/>
to assert itself over his weak and diseased body, and determine to drag<lb/>
its weary weight, at any cost, to the place of his brethren's assembling.<lb/>
But, as the date arrived, and he saw and felt that he could not go, he<lb/>
would meekly and uncomplainingly submit, and say: &ldquo;Tell the brethren I<lb/>
would be with them if I could. My heart is with them, but I am too<lb/>
feeble to leave home.&rdquo; As the last session of our Conference approached,<lb/>
he charged me with a message of love to the brethren, and said: &ldquo;You can<lb/>
say that though I am a great sufferer, I am happy in the love of God, and<lb/>
in the sense of his favor.&rdquo; Often, as his paroxysms of pain would subside,<lb/>
he would quote: &ldquo;I reckon that the sufferings of this present time are not<lb/>
worthy to be compared with the glory that shall be revealed in us;&rdquo; and he<lb/>
would rest in hope. The walk that he had through the valley of the<lb/>
shadow of death was a long and weary one. Shortly after his superannuation<lb/>
he began to break down in health, showing signs of a serious heart dis-<lb/>
turbance. But his robust frame and vigorous constitution enabled him to<lb/>
keep at bay the last enemy through many months, and to take some part in<lb/>
the Church services at which he worshiped. He was the steadfast friend<lb/>
and hearty supporter of the pastor, and he never allowed his seat in the<lb/>
sanctuary to be vacant if he was able to fill it. <unclear>Frewuently</unclear>, in feeble-<lb/>
ness extreme, he was at the place of prayer, and his means were as gen-<lb/>
erously offered as himself for the kingdom and the glory of Christ.<lb/>
A more liberal, regular and conscientious contributor to the Church, we<lb/>
had not among us, and no more fair, and just and high-toned man. He was<lb/>
the very soul of honor, and his name was a synonym for integrity and<lb/>
uprightness, fair dealing and manly bearing. His word was as good as<lb/>
his bond. Soon after the close of our last Conference session, he began<lb/>
to decline very rapidly - more rapidly than some of us knew; but he was<lb/>
not unaware of his progress, and he carefully set his house in order,<lb/>
giving direction concerning the smallest details of his affairs; then<lb/>
calmly and confidently awaited the issue, knowing that his calling and<lb/>
election had been made sure, and &ldquo;that if our earthly house of this<lb/>
tabernacle were dissolved, we have a building od God, an house not made<lb/>
with hands, eternal in the heavens.&rdquo; On Friday, the day before his de-<lb/>
parture, he asked two or three times if he were not dying; being assured<lb/>
that he was not, he said the end was not far off; and on Saturday morn-<lb/>
ing, Dec. 18, 1897, as the morning light was breaking, and the dawn of a<lb/>
new day was driving back the darkness of the night, his released spirit<lb/>
caught the wings of the morning of eternal day, and his shadowed eyes<lb/>
opened to the beauties and glories of a never darkening world. All his<lb/>
children, except those in distant states, and all the members of his<lb/>
household, and his pastor, were with him as he desired that they should be,<lb/>
when he left the circle of earthly friends and loved ones, to join the<lb/>
company of those who had gone before. On Monday afternoon, Dec. 20, 1897,<lb/>
at the Methodist Church in Farmville, Va. the solemn service for the dead<lb/>
was conducted by the writer, assisted by Revs. Jas. Cannon, Jr., R.F. Gayle,<lb/>
R. A. Compton and W. E. Grant. Each of whom paid touching tribute to his<lb/>
memory and all that was mortal of Rev. L. S. Reed was laid to rest in the<lb/>
quiet cemetery of the town.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
