<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY f06512013 SYSTEM "f06512013.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="t06512012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Notes by [Philip Showalter Hench], [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Hench, Philip Showalter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>06512012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Lambert, Gustaf E.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Neate, John S.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Cartwright, George</name>
<name type="person">Peterson, Matthew</name>
<name type="person">Brooks, E. C.</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">06512012</idno>
<title>Notes by [Philip Showalter Hench], [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Hench] outlines details of the yellow fever investigation, including a diagram of the Board's laboratory at Columbia Barracks.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Notes by [Philip Showalter Hench], [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="f06512012"/>
<p>#1.</p>
<p>Page 42:</p>
<p>Arailroad cut about ten feet deep passed through the southwestern part<lb/>
of the hospital grounds. It was a one track line running between Quemados and La<lb/>
Playa, a small fishing village on the shores of the Gulf. The grounds on the far<lb/>
side of the cut were barren with no habitations nearby. It was therefore an ideal<lb/>
site for an isolation camp. The Second Division Hospital had used it for that pur-<lb/>
pose and had left a few small, wooden shacks, (Nos. 115-118 inclusive) in such bad<lb/>
repair that during 1899 we preferred to use tents for the few cases requiring iso-<lb/>
lation. One case of yellow fever was isolated and treated there in July 1899.<lb/>
During the epidemic of yellow fever at Quemados in 1900, the shacks were repaired<lb/>
and the isolation camp became the Columbia Barracks yellow fever hospital. The small<lb/>
buildings were then referred to by many as the yellow fever &ldquo;<hi>wards</hi>&rdquo;. Dr. Ames had<lb/>
charge under the direction of the post surgeon. Major Kean, Dr. Carroll, Dr. Lazear<lb/>
and Private Dean were a few of the cases treated there. Dr. Lazear died there.<lb/>
The two buildings 117 and 118, were 10&times;16&prime; and each provided accommodations for<lb/>
from three to five patients. The smaller buildings, 115 and 116, were 7&times;9&prime; in size<lb/>
and provided for one or two beds. No. 114 was still smaller and was used by Dr.<lb/>
Ames as an office. The other small buildings shown on the map were for storage and<lb/>
toilets. Much of the information in this paragraph was given me by Gust E. Lambert<lb/>
who served at the hospital under Dr. Ames.</p>
<p>Pages 56-58:</p>
<p>The prediction that this was to be a &ldquo;yellow fever year&rdquo; was soon confirmed.<lb/>
The clean and beautiful village of Quemados on the border of the hospital grounds<lb/>
was one of the first places to be attacked. On May 19th, yellow fever appeared at<lb/>
No. 20 General Lee Street, only a few hundred yards from the hospital. It spread<lb/>
rapidly to other houses on the same street and then to houses on the nearby inter-<lb/>
secting street, Calzada Real. Most of the residents on these streets were non-<lb/>
immune Americans serving on General Lee's staff. Some were married civilian em-<lb/>
ployees from Columbia Barracks who could not get quarters at the post. From May 16th<lb/>
to June 30th, there were thirty-two cases with eight deaths. Three of these cases<lb/>
developed in soldiers from Columbia Barracks who were working in the infected district.<lb/>
These three men were treated in the post yellow fever hospital and all recovered.<lb/>
No secondary cases in the post resulted as there were very few Culex Fasciatus mos-<lb/>
quitoes since werwere provided at that time with a good piped water supply and a<lb/>
<hi>new sewer system</hi> which removed waste water and provided good drainage. During the<lb/>
next few weeks, eighteen additional cases with four deaths resulted. Seven of these<lb/>
with one death were among soldiers from Columbia Barracks. The infection of these<lb/>
cases was again definitely traced to Quemados where the soldiers worked; and again<lb/>
no secondary cases resulted at the post, as all fever cases were promptly isolated<lb/>
and treated in the hospital. Major Edmunds of General Lee's staff died. Major<lb/>
J. R. Kean, our Chief Surgeon, recovered as did one or two other officers who had<lb/>
quarters in the infected zone.</p>
<p>The Post hospital was called upon for male and female nurses to assist<lb/>
in the care of the Quemados cases in their homes. Several of them contracted the<lb/>
disease, one female nurse and one male nurse dying. Dr. Ames also helped in the<lb/>
treatment of some of the cases which were treated in their homes.</p>
<p>At this time, it was decided to repair the small wooden shacks in the<lb/>
hospital isolation camp which was described in the previous chapter. A foot bridge<lb/>
was built over the railroad cut, as the activities increased. Sick soldiers and<lb/>
civilian employees from the Quemados epidemic were then brought there for treatment.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f06512013"/>
#2.<lb/>
Major Kean was admitted on June 21st and was seen there by Walter Reed on June 25th,<lb/>
the day of his arrival in Cuba. Later some of the cases from General Wood's staff<lb/>
and the three experimental cases (Carroll, &ldquo;XY&rdquo; and Lazear) were all treated there.</p>
<p>All of the experimental cases from Camp Lazear were likewise admitted and<lb/>
treated in these wards. None of them died. Ames saw to it that these men were placed<lb/>
under treatment upon the appearance of the first symptoms and then, even before a<lb/>
positive diagnosis could be made, had them transferred to these &ldquo;wards&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Pages 66-68:</p>
<p>When the Second Division Hospital departed in the Spring of 1899, they<lb/>
left a small wooden building which was used by them (and later by us) as an operating<lb/>
room. The dimensions of this building were approximately 16&times;20&prime;. A new operating<lb/>
pavilion and new ward buildings were ready for occupancy early in 1900. The old<lb/>
operating building then became available for treating pus cases and for venereal<lb/>
work. When Reed came, it was converted into a laboratory for the use of the Board.<lb/>
It was in this building that Reed, Carroll and Lazear did all of their work. The<lb/>
mosquitoes used in their early experiments were hatched there from eggs presented by<lb/>
Dr. Finlay early in July when the members of the Board saw him at his home. The<lb/>
plan of the interior of this laboratory was given me by Mr. J. H. Andrus, who was on<lb/>
duty at the laboratory in 1900 under the direction of Major Reed.</p>
<p>The Board's laboratory, Columbia Barracks, 1900:-</p>
<p><figure entity="f06512013"></figure></p>
<pb n="3" id="f06512014"/>
<p>#3.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>A. Major Reed's microscope on a long, high table in front of a large window<lb/>
furnishing a north light.</item>
<item>B. Dr. Carroll's microscope.</item>
<item>C. Steward Neate's quarters.</item>
<item>D. Table with large glass jars containing mosquitoes.</item>
<item>E. Table holding more jars, microtome and other equipment.</item>
<item>F. Shelves in small room, hundreds of cultures in test tubes, incubator.</item>
<item>G. Shelves and counter containing supplies. Also two monkeys in cages.<lb/>
One monkey died of pneumonia. Species unknown to me.</item>
<item>H. General storage and shelves for mosquito jars.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Pages 91-92:</p>
<p>This is probably what happened: Lazear was still on duty as a member of<lb/>
the hospital staff. He visited all the wards in his capacity of bacteriologist. In<lb/>
going through this ward, he found a soldier who would soon be returned to duty<lb/>
and considered him an ideal young subject who could not have been exposed to yellow<lb/>
fever. He then probably explained his work and obtained the soldier's consent to<lb/>
be bitten. Lazear may have asked several patients before getting any volunteers.</p>
<p>It will be noted that the real name of this soldier was not published in<lb/>
the Preliminary Note. Reed, who was of course thoroughly familiar with military<lb/>
procedure in such cases, realized that a slip had been made in not obtaining the<lb/>
Post Commander's consent before experimenting on enlisted men of his command. This<lb/>
had not been done and Reed decided to indicate the case as &ldquo;XY&rdquo; in the report and<lb/>
explain matters when he had more time ...</p>
<p>Note from Truby to Pinto, page 91:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I think you know more than anyone else re this subject and I would like your views<lb/>
on Dean, when and where Lazear put the mosquitoes on him, etc. As I remember it you<lb/>
were the Ward Surgeon. Dean was in the Venereal Ward I think with an epididymitis<lb/>
and was ready for duty when Lazear saw him.</p>
<p>Note from Pinto to Truby, page 91:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Dean was in the hospital for a venereal bubo and as I remember it was<lb/>
hospitalized for about 10 days. A few days later he was readmitted and a diagnosis<lb/>
of yellow fever was made. I commented on the strangeness of the case at dinner and<lb/>
after dinner the same day Lazear came to my quarters and we discussed the case in<lb/>
full and I assured him there was no doubt in the diagnosis for I had already sent<lb/>
Dean to the yellow fever hospital. Lazear said, &ldquo;Are you dead sure that that is<lb/>
yellow fever. One of my &ldquo;mosquitoes bit him when he was in the hospital before.&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;Say nothing about&rdquo; it.</p>
<p>Note from Truby to Pinto, page 95:</p>
<p>Pinto: &ldquo;Did he tell you? Reed thought a<unclear>&rdquo;</unclear> lot of you and may have taken you<lb/>
in his confidence. If so I want to add your name.<unclear><add>&rdquo;</add></unclear></p>
<p>Note from Pinto to Truby, page 95:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The fantastic story that Lazear allowed a mongrel mosquitoes to bit him at<lb/>
Los Anamis Hospital was pure moonshine. Reed discussed it with me after his return<lb/>
to Cuba. We two as well as Ames were certain he was hiding something regarding in-<lb/>
fection. He already had two cases and in his own mind while not probly sufficient<lb/>
evidence to convince the world was certain that the mosquitoe was the intermediate<lb/>
host.&rdquo;</p>
<pb n="4" id="f06512015"/>
<p>#5.</p>
<p>Plaza on which was located the Governor General's Palace. In this same building<lb/>
were located the offices of Chief Paymaster and Chief Commissary. In a vacant<lb/>
room on the second floor of this building we organized a small mess, where we<lb/>
served our luncheons. There were eight people who were members of this mess,<lb/>
including my principal assistant, Major George Cartwright; Major Matt Peterson,<lb/>
Chief Commissary Officer; Mrs. Peterson, his wife; Captain Page, an aide-de-camp<lb/>
to the Commanding General; Colonel Dodge, the Chief Paymaster; Lieutenants Hanna<lb/>
and E. C. Brooks, aides-de-camp to the Commanding General, General Wood.</p>
<p>&ldquo; - The earliest deaths from yellow fever during this epidemic occurred outside<lb/>
the limits of Havana, at Pinar del Rio and Marianao. The first of this group at<lb/>
mess to go down with yellow fever was Major George Cartwright, my principal assistant,<lb/>
who died of the disease. Sitting at his left was Major Peterson, who went down<lb/>
with the disease and died. On the next day, as I followed this funeral to the last<lb/>
resting place, a carriage ahead of me turned out and I paused long enough to<lb/>
speak with the occupant, Captain Page, who informed me that he was so ill he could<lb/>
not proceed. I told him I would go on to the funeral and as soon as I got back would<lb/>
get in touch with him. Page occupied quarters at the top story of Segundo Cabo.<lb/>
When I returned to my office I found him there, unable to climb the stairs to his<lb/>
quarters and with help I assisted him to his room at the top of the building. Within<lb/>
48 hours he died of yellow fever. The next to be stricken with the disease was<lb/>
Colonel Dodge, Chief Paymaster of the Department. Fortunately he recovered and<lb/>
later became Paymaster General of the Army. The next place at the table was vacant<lb/>
as Lieutenant Hanna had taken a leave of absence, returned to the United States.<lb/>
That left Captain E. C. Brooks and me looking across the corner of the table at<lb/>
one another.</p>
<p>At the advise of the surgeons, we had been in the habit of serving a<lb/>
small quantity of red wine at luncheon. Some one of the group, at the early incep-<lb/>
tion of the epidemic, had proposed the old English toast: &lsquo;To those who are gone<lb/>
already and here's to the next to go.&rsquo; This toast was drunk daily until Brooks and <add>I</add><lb/>
were left looking across the corner of the table at one another. Then, when he poured<lb/>
out a glass of wine and pushed the decanter to me, he lifted his glass and gave the<lb/>
toast. I remember saying: &lsquo;Brooks, I won't drink that toast to myself. You had<lb/>
yellow fever in Santiago and are immune and won't have it again. Besides that,<lb/>
you are a teetotaler and don't drink. So I'll drink my wine, but not the toast.&rsquo;<lb/>
He laughed and neither he nor I was stricken with the disease.</p>
<p>During the same period, one after the other, I placed five men in charge<lb/>
of Major Cartwright's papers which I was anxious should be closed up as promptly<lb/>
as possible, especially in view of the conditions that existed. In order to make<lb/>
sure that they would be promptly closed and worked upon continuously, I set aside<lb/>
a small room back of my own office and I assi<add>g</add>ned a clerk to this special duty. The<lb/>
first that I placed in charge was Mr. Ferguson, a civilian clerk, supposed to be<lb/>
immune, having passed through more than one epidemic in New Orleans. Within 24<lb/>
hours after he took charge of the papers, he came to me and said he was too ill to<lb/>
go on. The next day he was dead of yellow fever. One after the other, five men<lb/>
working on these papers went down with yellow fever. The fifth man went down but<lb/>
fortunately recovered and finished the papers.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
