<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t14304001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George M. Sternberg to the Secretary of War, March 25, 1898</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>14304001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1898-03-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Chaille, Stanford L.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Isle of Pines (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Matanzas (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>13 pp.</extent>
<date value="1898-03-25">March 25, 1898</date>
<idno rend="suppress">14304001</idno>
<title>Letter from George M. Sternberg to the Secretary of War, March 25, 1898</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Sternberg reports on the prevalence of yellow fever in Cuba. He relates the history of yellow fever epidemics, and provides statistics on yellow fever throughout Cuba.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1898-03-25">
<head>Letter from George M. Sternberg to the Secretary of War, March 25, 1898</head>
<pb n="1" id="f14304001"/>
<opener>
Copy<lb/>
FROM GEN. J. R. KEAN<lb/>
<dateline>
WAR DEPARTMENT,<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
WASHINGTON, <date value="1898-05-25">March 25, 1898.</date>
</dateline>
To the Honorable<lb/>
THE SECRETARY OF WAR,<lb/>
<salute>Sir-,</salute>
</opener>
<p>In view of the possibility of war with Spain and of military opera-<lb/>
tions in Cuba, I have the honor to invite attention to the following facts<lb/>
relating to the prevalence of yellow fever in that island The data given<lb/>
are taken principally from the report of the Havana Yellow Fever Commission<lb/>
of 1879, of which Prof. Stanford L. Chaille, M. D. of New Orleans, was<lb/>
chairman and I was a member:</p>
<p>TEMPERATURE.</p>
<p>This is conceded to be the climatic element of greatest importance<lb/>
and the &ldquo;annual mean&rdquo; to be the chief factor Throughout the West Indies<lb/>
the mean annual temperature, near the sea, is from 78&deg; to 80&deg;, the mean<lb/>
daily range is only about 6&deg;, and the extreme annual range does not usually<lb/>
exceed 20&deg;. At Havana the mean annual temperature varies in different<lb/>
years from 77&deg; to 79&deg;; the mean temperature of the hottest months, July<lb/>
and August varies from 82&deg; to 85&deg;: and of the coldest months, December<lb/>
and January, from 70&deg; to 76deg; The minimum temperature is very rarely as<lb/>
low as 50&deg;, and the maximum as rarely exceeds 100&deg;; in fact, the thermom-<lb/>
eter, in the shade, seldom rises above 94&deg; There are no records nor any<lb/>
tradition of frost having ever occurred except on December 24 and 25, 1858<lb/>
File,<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f14304002"/>
2<lb/>
it is alleged that even in the sparsely inhabited mountains in the east of<lb/>
Cuba, where the Tarquino peak reaches an altitude of about 8,000 feet, frost<lb/>
rarely occurs, and snow never.</p>
<p>RAINFALL AND HUMIDITY.</p>
<p>During the sixteen years, 1859-'74, the average number of rainy days<lb/>
at Havana was 113; the minimum number, 97 days, occurred in 1869, and the<lb/>
maximum number, 141 days, occured in 1862 The average amount of rain<lb/>
for the sixteen years was 49 inches, the minimum was 42.5 in 1861, and the<lb/>
maximum was 70 inches in 1857. The maximum amount of rain falling in any<lb/>
one day was 8 1/4 inches on April 7, 1869. The so-called rainy season is from<lb/>
May to September, inclusive, but especially during August and September The<lb/>
rain then descends with such rapidity that it runs off in torrents; but as<lb/>
is seen, the usual belief that the annual rainfall is excessive is erroneous<lb/>
The annual mean relative humidity varies in different years from about 73 to<lb/>
74.5, and that of the different months of the year from 66 to 79; the minimum<lb/>
occurring in any day of the year may be as low as 34, and the maximum as high<lb/>
as 96. Evaporation is extremely rapid.</p>
<p>PREVALENCE OF YELLOW FEVER AT PORTS OF ENTRY.</p>
<p>1. <hi>Havana</hi>. -- Annual prevalence since 1761, the chief center of infec-<lb/>
tion, and most dangerous to the shipping.</p>
<p>2. <hi>Metanzas</hi>. -- Annual prevalence certainly since 1828, and probably<lb/>
much longer; an important center of infection, but less dangerous to ship-<lb/>
ping than Havana.</p>
<p>3. <hi>Cardenas</hi>. -- Annual prevalence certainly since 1836, and it was not<lb/>
founded until 1828. It is an important center of infection, but not spec-<lb/>
ially dangerous to shipping, because of the distance vessels anchor <unclear>fr</unclear><lb/>
shore.</p>
<pb n="3" id="f14304003"/>
<p>3</p>
<p>4. <hi>Cienfuegos</hi>. -- Annual prevalence since at least 1839, and it was<lb/>
not founded until 1819-1825. It is a dangerous center of infection, but<lb/>
like Matanzas, has a very large harbor, and is less dangerous than Havana<lb/>
to the shipping.</p>
<p>5. <hi>Sagua</hi>. -- Some cases of yellow fever occur annually, but vessels<lb/>
are very rarely infected, as these anchor several miles distant from the<lb/>
coast, and Sagua is 10 miles inland.</p>
<p>6. <hi>Baracca</hi>. -- Yellow fever occurs occasionally as an epidemic, but<lb/>
not annually as an epidemic.</p>
<p>7. <hi>Ceibarien</hi>. -- Cases of yellow fever occur frequently, but not every<lb/>
year. Very little dangerous to vessels, as these anchor many miles distant</p>
<p>8. <hi>Trinidad</hi>. -- Annual prevalence certainly since 1838, and probably<lb/>
longer. The harbor is not believed to be specially dangerous to vessels</p>
<p>9. <hi>Cuba</hi>. -- Annual prevalence certainly since 1851, and probably very<lb/>
much longer It is a noted center of infection, and its small harbor is<lb/>
very dangerous to the shipping. This, next to Havana, is probably the most<lb/>
dangerous place to shipping in the whole island.</p>
<p>10. <hi>Manzanillo</hi>. -- Annual prevalence. It is in constant communication<lb/>
with Cuba, Trinidad and Cienfuegos. As vessels anchor in the open sea, sev-<lb/>
eral miles from shore, they probably suffer little.</p>
<p>11. <hi>Nuevitas</hi>. -- Annual prevalence. Vessels anchor a mile or more dis-<lb/>
tant, and are in little danger.</p>
<p>12. <hi>Guantanamo</hi>. -- Annual prevalence. The town is about seven miles<lb/>
from the harbor, and vessels are probably little exposed to infection</p>
<p>13. <hi>Gibara</hi>. -- Cases of yellow fever do not occur every year. Vessels<lb/>
anchor distant from the shore, and are in little danger.</p>
<pb n="4" id="f14304004"/>
<p>4</p>
<p>14. <hi>Zeza</hi>. -- Cases of yellow fever do not occur every year Vessels<lb/>
are probably in very little danger.</p>
<p>15 <hi>Santa Cruz</hi>. -- Cases of yellow fever occur in the majority of, but<lb/>
not in all, years Vessels anchor far from shore, and are in little danger.</p>
<p>SEAPORTS WHICH ARE NOT PORTS OF ENTRY</p>
<p>16. <hi>Babia Senda</hi> -- Yellow fever is not endemic, is even said to be<lb/>
&ldquo;unknown&rdquo;, and to present no cases &ldquo;either indigenous or imported&rdquo;</p>
<p>17. <hi>Satabano</hi>. -- Very few cases occur.</p>
<p>18. <hi>Cabanas</hi>. -- Cases occur very rarely, and the diseases is not endemic</p>
<p>19. <hi>Isle of Pines</hi>. -- Cases very seldom occur, and it is as <unclear>remarkably</unclear><lb/>
free as is Bahia Honda from the disease.</p>
<p>20. <hi>Mariel</hi> -- Yellow fever is not endemic here.</p>
<p>21. <hi>Puerto Padre</hi> -- The disease is not endemic.</p>
<p>INLAND TOWNS.</p>
<p>22. <hi>Bayazo</hi>. -- Occasionally epidemic, but not annually endemic.</p>
<p>23. <hi>Bejucal</hi> suffers little with yellow fever.</p>
<p>24. <hi>Ciego de Avila</hi> -- Not endemic.</p>
<p>25 <hi>Cobre</hi> -- Yellow fever is not endemic.</p>
<p>26. <hi>Colon</hi> -- Yellow fever is not endemic.</p>
<p>27. <hi>Guanabacca</hi> -- Cases occur annually.</p>
<p>28. <hi>Guanajay</hi> -- Cases occur in the majority of years.</p>
<p>29. <hi>Guines</hi> -- Yellow fever is not endemic.</p>
<p>30. <hi>Holguin</hi> -- Several epidemics since 1851, but cases do not occur every year.</p>
<p>31. <hi>Jaruco</hi>. -- Endemic.</p>
<pb n="5" id="f14304005"/>
<p>5</p>
<p>32. <hi>Marianao</hi> -- Endemic.</p>
<p>33. <hi>Mayari</hi> -- Not endemic.</p>
<p>34. <hi>Palma Soriano.</hi> -- Not endemic.</p>
<p>35. <hi>Pinar del Rio</hi> -- Not endemic</p>
<p>36. <hi>Puerto Principe</hi> -- Endemic.</p>
<p>37. <hi>Remedios</hi> -- Endemic</p>
<p>38. <hi>San Antonio</hi> -- Endemic.</p>
<p>39. <hi>Sancti Spiritus</hi> -- Endemic</p>
<p>40. <hi>San Jose de las Lajas</hi> -- Endemic.</p>
<p>41. <hi>Santa Clara</hi> -- Cases occur in the majority of years.</p>
<p>42. <hi>Santiago</hi> -- Endemic</p>
<p>43. <hi>Victoria de las Tunas</hi> -- Cases occur in the majority of years</p>
<p>The above forty-three places are all those from which trustworthy in-<lb/>
formation was secured, and it appears that of 21 seaports, yellow fever<lb/>
occurs annually in 10 of them and does not occur annually in the remain-<lb/>
ing 11; while of 22 inland towns, the disease occurs every year in 9 of<lb/>
them, and not every year in the remaining 13. A larger proportion of the<lb/>
seaports exceed the inland towns in the extent of their commerce with per-<lb/>
manently infected centers, and in the number of immigrants, so that the<lb/>
above list tends very strongly to prove that seaports in Cuba are no more<lb/>
liable to yellow fever, solely because located on the sea, than are inland<lb/>
towns. Yet the contrary has long been taught.</p>
<p>The Isle of Pines, Bahia Honda, Cabanas, Mariel, Zaza, and other preemi-<lb/>
nently maritime places in Cuba suffer little, if at all, with yellow fever.</p>
<p>1648. &ldquo;In this year there occurred in Havana, and in the fleet of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="f14304006"/>
6<lb/>
Don Juan Pujados, a great '<hi>pest of putrid fevers</hi>' which remained in the<lb/>
port almost all the summer. A third part of the garrison and a larger<lb/>
part of the crews and passengers in the vessels died.&rdquo; -- (Pezuela, v.<lb/>
3, p. 23.)</p>
<p>1849. &ldquo;In the spring of 1849 an unknown and horrible epidemic,<lb/>
imported from the continent of America, caused consternation in Cuba.<lb/>
The 'Unpublished History of the Island' says: 'A third part of its pop-<lb/>
ulation was devoured, from May to October, by a species of putrid fever,<lb/>
which carried off those attacked in three days. In the capital (Havana),<lb/>
where the Governor, Villalva, came near dying, there died, at short inter-<lb/>
vals, the counselor of the Governor, Francisco de Molina, and the lawyers<lb/>
Pedro Pedroso, Fernando de Tobar, and Pablo de Olivares, who successively<lb/>
replaced each other. By this can be judged the ravages which the <hi>conta-<lb/>
gion</hi> must have inflicted on other classes and towns. In that of Santiago<lb/>
(de Cuba) it increased during the following summer, so that the people fled<lb/>
for safety to the country.&rdquo; -- (Pezuela, v. 5, p. 182).</p>
<p>1658-'54 &ldquo;The epidemic was renewed with equal fury during this<lb/>
time, in spite of precautions taken to prevent communication between the<lb/>
towns, which were, however, better protected by their distance from each<lb/>
other, and by the bad roads, than by these precautions.&rdquo; (Ib., v. 3. p. 182)</p>
<p>1854-'55 &ldquo;This was an epoch of rivalry and disasters In the<lb/>
capital the pest continued to carry away its victims, without regard to<lb/>
rivalries and passions.&rdquo; -- (Ib., v. 3, p. 183.)</p>
<p>When it is considered that in the early history of yellow fever it<lb/>
was most frequently designated &ldquo;the pest&rdquo;, that the above scanty records<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="f14304007"/>
7<lb/>
indicate some of the characteristics of the disease while omitting any<lb/>
contra indications, and that historical records prove the existence of<lb/>
the disease during some of the years, 1648-1654, in Barbadoes, Guadeloupe,<lb/>
Martinique, St. Christophe, and probably in San Domingo, &ldquo;the cradle of<lb/>
yellow fever&rdquo;, it is difficult to disbelieve that yellow fever did visit<lb/>
Cuba, as an epidemic, during the above recorded years. This probability<lb/>
renders still more remarkable the fact that, after 1654, no other histori-<lb/>
cal indications of yellow fever visitations to Havana are to be found until<lb/>
1761, more than one hundred years.&rdquo; On the contrary, there are repeated<lb/>
records of the great salubrity of the climate and the absence of epidemic<lb/>
diseases.&rdquo;</p>
<p>1781. &ldquo;Although Havana is situated on the northern boundary of the<lb/>
Torrid Zone, it was very justly considered one of the most healthy locali-<lb/>
ties on the island before its invasion, in a <hi>permanent manner</hi>, by the vomito<lb/>
negro (yellow fever), imported from Vera Cruz in the summer of 1761.&rdquo; --<lb/>
(Pezuela, v. 3, p. 18)</p>
<p>&ldquo;In May, there came from Vera Cruz, with materials and some prisoners<lb/>
destined for the works on the exterior fortifications of Havana, the men-of-<lb/>
war Heina and America, which communicated to the neighborhood the epidemic<lb/>
known by the name of the 'vomito negro'. At the end of the following June<lb/>
there were stationed in this port nine men-of-war, dispatched from Cadiz,<lb/>
and sent to the chief of the squadron, Don Gutierre de Hevia; they brought<lb/>
a re-enforcement of 2,000 men. To the epidemic, more than 3,000 perso<lb/>
succumbed on this, <hi>the first appearance</hi> of the vomito; from May to October<lb/>
occurred the greater number of victims in the garrison and in the squadron&rdquo;<lb/>
-- (Pezuela, v. 3, p. 27.)</p>
<pb n="8" id="f14304008"/>
<p>8</p>
<p>1765. &ldquo;On June 30 the Conde de Riola was relieved by Field Marshall<lb/>
Don Diego Menrique, who died with vomito July 13.&rdquo; -- (Pezuela, v.3, p.51.)</p>
<p>1779. In July and August there arrived from Spain, because of its<lb/>
war with Great Britain. &ldquo;an aray of 3,500 men, who were immediately decima-<lb/>
ted by the vomito.&rdquo; -- (Ib., v. 3, p. 52.)</p>
<p>1780. On the 3rd to 5th August a large squadron brought an aray of<lb/>
8,000 men. &ldquo;In the two following months they suffered a loss of about<lb/>
2,000 men with the vomito&rdquo; (Ib., v. 3, p. 52); and Surgeon Romay reports,<lb/>
&ldquo;the same epidemic was renewed in 1780, there being in this city an arma-<lb/>
ment and numerous garrisons on account of the war with Great Britain.&rdquo;</p>
<p>1794. &ldquo;On the 9th of June the squadron of Aristizabal returned to<lb/>
repair damages at this port, where had arrived from Cadiz, as re-enforce-<lb/>
ments, four ships, with the chief of squadron, Don Jose Ulloa. The vomito<lb/>
appeared so severely this summer that, solely of the garrison and of the<lb/>
squadron, more than 1,800 victims were taken, one of these being Ulloa.<lb/>
It was indispensable to resort to a general levy to replace the losses on<lb/>
the vessels.&rdquo; -- (Pezuela, v. 3, p. 53.)</p>
<p>The statistics published in this report to the United States National<lb/>
Board of Health date back to 1851, and conclusively prove the annual preva-<lb/>
lence of yellow fever from that date to the present time, not only in Ha-<lb/>
vana, but also in numerous other places in Cuba</p>
<p>So far as Havana is concerned, the statistics, published herewith<lb/>
together with the official manuscript reports of the military hospitals<lb/>
in Havana, and of the Cuban superior board of health, prove such more than<lb/>
the annual prevalence of yellow fever; for they prove that, during the 408<lb/>
months, from January, 1856, to January, 1880, there was but one single month,<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="f14304009"/>
9<lb/>
viz., December, 1888, exempt from an officially reported case of the disease.<lb/>
Now, the combined reports referred to begin only with 1868, and they refer<lb/>
from 1858 to 1869 solely to the military and civil hospitals, exclusive of<lb/>
the very numerous cases of yellow fever in the preponderating civil popula-<lb/>
tion not treated in the hospitals; hence, the facts stated justify the conclu-<lb/>
sion that yellow fever has prevailed in Havana <hi>monthly</hi>, not only for the past<lb/>
twenty-four years, but also, in all probability, for many years anterior to 1858.</p>
<p>ANNUAL DEATHS FROM YELLOW FEVER IN HAVANA, 1870, '79.<lb/>
<table rows="12" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>Year.</cell><cell>Military and civil population.</cell><cell>Civil population.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1870 . . . . .</cell><cell>685</cell><cell>277</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1871 . . . . .</cell><cell>991</cell><cell>796</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1872 . . . . </cell><cell>515</cell><cell>372</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1873 . . . </cell><cell>1,244</cell><cell>1,019</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1874 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,435</cell><cell>1,256</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1875 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,001</cell><cell>94</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1876 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,612</cell><cell>904</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1877 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,374</cell><cell>587</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1878 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,559</cell><cell>738</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1879 . . . . .</cell><cell>1,444</cell><cell>737</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Totals . .</cell><cell>11,837</cell><cell>8,780</cell></row>
</table></p>
<pb n="10" id="f14304010"/>
<p>10</p>
<p>CASES AND DEATHS OF YELLOW FEVER IN THE SPANISH NAVY.<lb/>
<table rows="12" cols="3">
<row>
<cell>Year.</cell><cell>Cases.</cell><cell>Deaths.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1870 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>1,094</cell><cell>231</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1871 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>105</cell><cell>41</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1872 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>192</cell><cell>37</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1873 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>133</cell><cell>33</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1874 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>325</cell><cell>129</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1875 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>831</cell><cell>203</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1876 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>324</cell><cell>75</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1877 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>429</cell><cell>158</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1878 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>526</cell><cell>183</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>First six months 1879 . . . . . .</cell><cell>305</cell><cell>90</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>Total . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell>4,084</cell><cell>1,158</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>ISLE OF PINES.</p>
<p>This island appertains to the province of Havana It is about 90<lb/>
miles from the city, and 54 from Batabano, whence a steamer runs once or<lb/>
twice a week. It contains about 540 square miles, a mountain range with<lb/>
a peak 1,650 feet high, and &ldquo;the most wonderful mineral springs in the<lb/>
world,&rdquo; as is alleged. It has two villages on the north coast, which con-<lb/>
tained in 1882 a population of 1,293 out of a total population on the island<lb/>
of 2,082. The population of the island in 1877 is reported to have been 1,693</p>
<pb n="11" id="f14304011"/>
<p>11</p>
<p>Panuela reported in 1854 that &ldquo;cases of yellow fever, of small pox,<lb/>
and of cholera have not been seen at the Isle of Pines.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The military hospital statistics. Table No. 46, embrace the 28 years,<lb/>
1854-1878, and show a remarkable freedom from yellow fever. There were no<lb/>
cases until 1855, and then only two cases: only in 1856, 1859, and 1864 were<lb/>
the cases at all numerous; and during the recent 13 years, 1856-1878, there<lb/>
had not been one case The records of the military hospitals at Cuba show<lb/>
no exemption comparable to this at any other place except at Bahia Honda.</p>
<p>YELLOW FEVER CASES AND DEATHS IN THE CIVIL POPULATION OF MATANZAS FROM JULY,<lb/>
1857, TO AUGUST, 1879, AS RECORDED BY THE BOARD OF HEALTH.</p>
<p>
<table rows="15" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Years.</cell><cell>Cases.</cell><cell>Deaths.</cell><cell>Remarks.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1857, six months of ........</cell><cell>436</cell><cell><unclear>132</unclear></cell><cell>Only for July to Dec., 1857.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1858 ......................</cell><cell><unclear>546</unclear></cell><cell><unclear>843</unclear></cell><cell>Of these, 142 cases and 53<lb/>
deaths in January.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1859 .......................</cell><cell>34</cell><cell><unclear></unclear></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1860 ......................</cell><cell>192</cell><cell><unclear></unclear></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1861 ......................</cell><cell>813</cell><cell>30</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1862 ......................</cell><cell>262</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>Of these, 77 cases and 18<lb/>
deaths in January, Feb-<lb/>
ruary and March.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1863, nine months of .......</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>No records for June, Sept-<lb/>
ember, October</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1864 ......................</cell><cell>766</cell><cell>160</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1865 ......................</cell><cell><unclear></unclear></cell><cell>91</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1860, no months of, recorded .</cell><cell>.</cell><cell>.</cell><cell>No cases in military hospital.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1867 ......................</cell><cell>202</cell><cell>36</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1868 ........................</cell><cell><unclear>88</unclear></cell><cell>7</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1869, four months of .......</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>For March, April, May, June, only</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1870, eight months of .......</cell><cell>13</cell>
<cell>7</cell><cell>No records for January, Febru-<lb/>
ary, March and September</cell></row>
</table></p>
<p>No records.</p>
<pb n="12" id="f14304012"/>
<p>12</p>
<p>
<table rows="10" cols="4">
<row>
<cell>Years.</cell><cell>Cases.</cell><cell>Deaths.</cell><cell>Remarks.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1871 ......................</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1872 ......................</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>1</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1873 ......................</cell><cell>329</cell><cell>52</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1874 .......................</cell><cell><unclear>239</unclear></cell><cell>47</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1875 ......................</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>8</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1876 ......................</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>In addition, 313 cases of<lb/>
soldiers.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1877 ....................</cell><cell>86</cell><cell>21</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1878 ....................</cell><cell>201</cell><cell>97</cell><cell>In addition, 299 cases of<lb/>
soldiers.</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>1879, first seven months of</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>27</cell></row>
</table></p>
<closer>
<salute>Respectfully submitted:</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Geo. M. Sternberg,<lb/>
Surgeon General, U. S. Army.<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="f14304013"/>
S. G. O<lb/>
Washington D.C.<lb/>
March 25, 98<lb/>
Sternberg, Geo. M.<lb/>
Surgeon General<lb/>
Yellow Fever<lb/>
in Cuba-</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
