<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' []>

<TEI.2 id="t14303001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Letter from George M. Sternberg to Walter Reed, January 19, 1894</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author>Sternberg, George Miller</author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>14303001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1894-01-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term type="recipient">Reed, Walter</term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1894-01-19">January 19, 1894</date>
<idno rend="suppress">14303001</idno>
<title>Letter from George M. Sternberg to Walter Reed, January 19, 1894</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Sternberg discusses his theory of yellow fever and the necessary preventative measures to combat the spread of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1894-01-19">
<head>Letter from George M. Sternberg to Walter Reed, January 19, 1894</head>
<pb n="1" id="f14303001"/>
<opener>
Subject<lb/>
202<lb/>
FC<lb/>
<dateline>
War Department<lb/>
SURGEON GENERAL'S OFFICE,<lb/>
Washington, <date value="1894-11-19">January 19, 1894.</date>
</dateline>
<salute>My Dear Doctor:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of the 15th is at hand. What you say is en-<lb/>
tirely correct. Yellow Fever is non-contagious in the same sense<lb/>
that Cholera and Typhoid Fever are non-contagious. That is, under<lb/>
ordinary conditions the patient does not directly communicate the<lb/>
disease to others associated with him. But, like Typhoid Fever<lb/>
and Cholera, there is something given off from the bodies of Yellow<lb/>
Fever patients which, under favorable local and meteorological con-<lb/>
ditions, may multiply outside of the body and give rise to an ex-<lb/>
tended epidemic. And it seems to me extremely probable that, as<lb/>
in Typhoid Fever and in Cholera, this &ldquo;something&rdquo; is a living germ<lb/>
which is present in the discharges from the bowels of infected in-<lb/>
dividuals; and that when such infectious discharges are thrown out<lb/>
upon the ground or in shallow privy vaults, etc., especially in the<lb/>
presence of organic material of animal origin and in a tropical cli-<lb/>
mate, the living germ is capable of rapid multiplication. This being<lb/>
the case the same precautions must be taken with reference to the ex-<lb/>
clusion of Yellow Fever patients, and their isolation if they are<lb/>
landed upon our shores, as are necessary in the case of the strictly<lb/>
contagious diseases, such as Small-Pox. If our exposed seaports<lb/>
were in such a sanitary condition that the hypothetical germ con-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="f14303002"/>
203<lb/>
tained in the alvine discharges of the sick could not find a<lb/>
nidus for its multiplication outside of the body of an infected<lb/>
individual there would be no danger of an extension of the dis-<lb/>
ease. Or, if we could be absolutely sure that the discharges<lb/>
were thoroughly disinfected from the moment that the germ of<lb/>
the disease was present in them, we might dispense with isola-<lb/>
tion of the patient. But it is evident that the only reliable<lb/>
means of disinfecting the excreta is to have complete control of<lb/>
the sick or of those recently arrived from infected localities,<lb/>
who may possibly carry the germ in the contents of the bowels in<lb/>
advance of an attack, or even in the case of individuals when no<lb/>
attack is likely to be developed.</p>
<p>Taking this view of the case, the preventive measures to<lb/>
be used against Yellow Fever are similar to those to be used against<lb/>
Cholera, and include exclusion by quarantine regulations, isolation<lb/>
of cases landed upon our shores, disinfection of excreta, and cloth-<lb/>
ing which may possibly be soiled by the alvine discharges of the<lb/>
sick, together with municipal sanitation, and in time of epidemic<lb/>
the removal of all unprotected persons from infected areas.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Geo. M. Sternberg</signed>
Dr. Joseph Y. Porter,<lb/>
Key West, Florida.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>

