<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="C0128018">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Notes on anti-malarial measures for Camp Lee, by W. F. Draper and Henry Rose Carter, November, 1917</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
<author>Draper, W. F.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0128018</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability> 
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1917-11-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name>
 </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Haush, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Messer, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1917-11-00">November, 1917</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0128018</idno>
<title>Notes on anti-malarial measures for Camp Lee, by W. F. Draper and Henry Rose Carter, November, 1917</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The document describes ways to prevent malaria at Camp Lee, and includes handwritten notes.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1917-11-00">
<head>Notes on anti-malarial measures for Camp Lee, by W. F. Draper and Henry Rose Carter, November, 1917</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0128018"/>
<p>FIELD NOTES ON ANTI-MALARIAL MEASURES NECESSARY IN EXTRA CANTON-<lb/>
MENT ZONE WITHIN ONE MILE OF CAMP LEE.  RESULT OF SURVEY<lb/>
MADE BY P.A. SURGEON W.F. DRAPER<lb/>
AND MAJOR HENRY P. CARTER<lb/>
M.C., U.S.A.</p>
<p>November 1917.</p>
<p><lb/>
<hi rend="underline">Ettricks</hi>.</p>
<p>West of the Battersea mill 500 feet ditch 2 feet wide<lb/>
one foot deep.</p>
<p>From Old Mill toward river 300 feet ditch 3 feet <lb/>
wide one foot deep.</p>
<p>East of Mill 100 feet ditch 2 feet wide one foot<lb/>
deep.  Also clean present ditches and remove debris.</p>
<p>Small ponds and puddles in this area should be oiled<lb/>
at intervals during summer.  Estimated cost of oiling for<lb/>
summer, $10.00<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">Colonial Heights</hi>.</p>
<p>In wet meadow from river up hill, 600 feet ditch <lb/>
3 feet wide, also 400 feet ditch as side ditches.</p>
<p>From Hillside Spring, Colonial Heights, towards<lb/>
bridge to river 600 feet ditch, 3 feet wide, 1 &frac12; feet deep.</p>
<p>West from old stone house towards railroad tressle<lb/>
1,000 feet of cleaning of ditch already dug.</p>
<p>Survey low area on east side Richmond Turnpike<lb/>
opposite Aqueduct Spring to see if there are areas need-<lb/>
ing draining.  Open road drain on upper side of road.<lb/>
Also clean this.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">Prince George County</hi>.</p>
<p>Petersburg, Camp Lee, Highway fill gravel pit<lb/>
south side of road just before reaching concrete road.<lb/>
Estimated cost $10.00.</p>
<p>Clean spring branch at beginning of concrete road<lb/>
from N. &amp; W. track south 400 to 500 yards.</p>
<p>Ditch and clean meadow triangle between concrete<lb/>
road and street car tracks south side of road.  Will<lb/>
require 300 feet ditch 2 feet wide 1 foot deep.</p>
<p>Two thousand feet ditch 2 feet wide, 1 foot deep<lb/>
in Perkinson's meadow extending from spring towards<lb/>
Petersburg.  This must be staked by engineer.  Also<lb/>
4,000 feet 2 feet ditch, 1 foot deep extending from<lb/>
spring through pasture.  Must clean and open up several<lb/>
thousand feet old channel.</p>
<p>Oil marsh on north side of road 300 yards west of <lb/>
Lakemont.  This will take 1 barrel of oil every six weeks.</p>
<p>Fill in small pool on south side of railroad<lb/>
opposite marsh.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fC0128019"/>
<p>Field Notes</p>
<p>Camp Lee</p>
<p>1. Pool, Southside Electric R. R., 1,000&prime;, Petersburg side<lb/>
of Lakemont Park. Moderate sized pool, breeding anopheles freely, also<lb/>
culex. This close to camp is made by electric railroad's fill. <del>Drain</del><lb/>
<del>or fill</del> <hi rend="underline"><add><hi rend="italics">Drain a fill</hi></add></hi>.</p>
<p>2. Opposite this, between E. R. R. and N. &amp; W. R. R., is a pool<lb/>
and marsh large. An ideal <hi rend="underline">A</hi>. place; breeding A moderately, <hi>C</hi> freely.<lb/>
Also pool across R. R. <del>(inside)</del> <add><hi rend="italics">(N. Side) also breeding.</hi></add></p>
<p>3. Ditch, S. side N. &amp; W. breeding <hi>A</hi>. So is one on N. side,<lb/>
slightly. This is at 2 mile post, N. &amp; W. R</p>
<p>Both (2) and (3) can be drained to creek, <hi rend="italics">B</hi>oth caused by<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">N. &amp; W. R. R.</hi></p>
<p>4. Two small pools at Lakemont Park, southside of E. R. R.,<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">A</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C</hi>.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain or fill.</hi></p>
<p>5. North of R. R. beyond a cross road, a large swamp, phy-<lb/>
sically well suited for <hi rend="underline">A</hi>. <hi rend="underline">A</hi> in moderate number <add>(</add>and <hi rend="underline">C</hi> same<add>)</add> found.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain into Skipwith</hi> Creek.</p>
<p>6. Ditch S. side N. &amp; W. R. R. opposite this place <hi rend="underline">A</hi> freely.<lb/>
Ditch north side, <hi rend="underline">A</hi> moderately.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain as</hi> (5).</p>
<p>7. Ditch Ditch cut to drain N. &amp; W. right of way, running towards<lb/>
the church at Roseland Park and not far from it. Is full of water and<lb/>
breeding <hi rend="underline">C</hi>. Many Aedes sylvestres in woods adjacent. This ditch is<lb/>
blocked and the right of way which it should drain, <add>(</add>mainly to the north<lb/>
of the railroad,<add>)</add> is breeding <hi rend="underline">A</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C</hi> freely.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Remove</hi> obstructions and grade ditch so as to flow <del>&amp;</del> <add><hi rend="italics">drain R. of way</hi></add></p>
<pb n="3" id="fC0128020"/>
<p>-2-<lb/>
8. Down concrete road, one-fourth of a mile and off on road<lb/>
to southeast, many roadside pools, some permanent. <hi rend="underline">C</hi> freely, <hi rend="underline">A</hi> moder-<lb/>
ately. Not of much importance, too far from camp for their size.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Fill</hi> <add> <hi rend="italics">if anything is judged needed</hi></add></p>
<p>9. Afternoon. Out Middle Road from church across Bailey's<lb/>
Creek, then road east of south. Well at old saw-mill, <add><hi rend="italics">too deep to <unclear>dip</unclear> (Culex?)</hi></add></p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Fill with</hi> saw-dust. <add><hi rend="italics">of little importance</hi></add></p>
<p>10. Hence, a half mile to court House Road and half mile east<lb/>
on Court House Road to first road leading north, and a half mile on this<lb/>
road is a pond, blocked by a road, 150&prime; &times; 25&prime;, breeding <hi rend="underline">A</hi> profusely--<lb/>
20 at some dips, all sizes.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain across</hi> road. This will be easy.</p>
<p>Small branch enters this last pond and runs 800&prime; to con-<lb/>
nect almost at right angles with what seems to be the ditch from the pond<lb/>
(examined on 13th) on Court House Road, northeast of infantry barracks.<lb/>
This pool is shown on plot given Dr. Hill<del>s</del>man, <unclear><add><hi rend="italics">for being within camp.</hi></add></unclear></p>
<p>11. Returned by this same road from Middle to Court House Road,<lb/>
and 600&prime; from the latter, on the west side of this road, a pond 100&prime; &times;<lb/>
15&prime;, breeding <hi rend="underline">A</hi> and <hi rend="underline">C</hi> both in fair numbers. Pond blocked by road.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain</hi> at the cross roads, which is easy.</p>
<p>July 16.</p>
<p>Middle section of Harrison's Creek in the woods above<lb/>
Lakemont. Good deep banks and free flow. No side swamps up to where<lb/>
pipe line crosses. 600&prime; higher up is an under-bluff marsh, small and<lb/>
very shady, runs almost up to the old dam, not much importance unless<lb/>
cleared. If cleared, to be drained, <add><unclear><hi rend="italics">Culex moderate number -</hi></unclear></add></p>
<p>Above this are a number of side marshes up to the forks<lb/>
of the creek, all negative and not well suited for <hi rend="underline">A</hi> at present, in dense<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fC0128021"/>
-3-<lb/>
growth and far from blood supply. Doubtless breed <hi rend="underline">C</hi>, some of which are<lb/>
taken. Easy to drain if required. First branch on the right negative.<lb/>
First branch on the left, negative.</p>
<p><add><hi rend="italics">Remark</hi></add> It is to be noted that the heavy rains of yesterday and last<lb/>
night flooded everything, <del>XXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXXX</del> washed<lb/>
out the side pools and left them with so much water that many places<lb/>
suitable for breeding and which, doubtless, had been breeding, do not<lb/>
show larvae now.</p>
<p>Norfolk &amp; Western grading camp, near the head of Harrison Creek<lb/>
(Dark Swamp Run)<del>.</del><add>, <hi rend="italics">at spring</hi></add></p>
<p>12. Breeding <hi rend="underline">A</hi> freely and <hi rend="underline">C</hi> profusely in a wide marsh on the<lb/>
left bank of this run, from the spring down to the road crossing, 600&prime;.<lb/>
A bad place for breeding but quite far--&frac34; of a mile from the camp grounds<lb/>
and further from the buildings.</p>
<p>A stream comes in from the right at the road crossing <add><unclear><hi rend="italics">negative.</hi></unclear></add></p>
<p>Drain the marsh and clear the bed of the stream all the<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">way down</hi>.</p>
<p>Branch coming in on the right above the mule stable, nega-<lb/>
tive.</p>
<p>So is branch coming in from the right below the crossing,<lb/>
although there is a pool-<add>(</add>marl pit?<add>)</add> -- <del>xxxxx</del>near Mr. Haush's house, full of<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">C</hi>.</p>
<p>Some under-cliff marshes on the left side below the road<lb/>
crossing--of small importance, breeding <hi rend="underline">C</hi> only at present, and quite<lb/>
distant from the camp.</p>
<p>Obstructions should be removed from the bed of Harrison<lb/>
Creek the whole way down. This is a small job and, with a very little<lb/>
draining of side marshes, would, I believe, be sufficient. It is doubtful<lb/>
if this creek is the source of any considerable number of <hi rend="underline">A</hi>.</p>
<pb n="5" id="fC0128022"/>
<p>-4-<lb/>
Afternoon.</p>
<p>Miss Webb's Spring<unclear>,--</unclear>Monument, Pa., Regiment.</p>
<p>Just above road crossing, <hi rend="underline">A</hi> found--road dam as usual.</p>
<p>13. Valley of stream seems clear of breeding places until about<lb/>
100&prime; below the spring. Here, there is a false channel in pools and a<lb/>
long seepage area, which is permanent, under the bluff. <unclear><hi rend="underline">C</hi><del>2</del>breeding</unclear> pro-<lb/>
fusely in the latter. No <hi rend="underline">A</hi>. (In thick brush).</p>
<p>This creek was entered at several (5) places, and its val-<lb/>
ley was very dense and rough, but except at this place, no water outside<lb/>
the creek bed was found. Such may exist however, but it was not possible<lb/>
with the time at our disposal to explore the creek at all places. We<lb/>
followed it to its junction with the main creek.</p>
<p>Remove obstructions from the creek bed, which is fairly<lb/>
deep, and drain any side-pools or under-bluff marsh which may require it.<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">There are believed to be but few</hi>.</p>
<p>This is the right hand fork of Harrison Creek, the other<lb/>
one having been visited this morning (Dark Swamp Run).</p>
<p>14. About 300&prime; north of east <unclear>axex</unclear> of Webb Spring is another<lb/>
spring by two poplars. Below this a marshy place, breeding <hi rend="underline">A</hi> profusely.</p>
<p><hi rend="underline">Drain</hi>.</p>
<p>Blackwater Creek and its branches was visited and crossed<lb/>
in a number of places from July 13-17. It is in flood and its valley<lb/>
and that of its affluents, being very flat and the banks shallow, the<lb/>
streams were all well out of bank--some 200&prime; to 300<add>&prime;</add><del>s</del> wide. No examina-<lb/>
tion was then possible.</p>
<p>There is no reason to change the plan for the canaliza-<lb/>
tion of this stream, agreed on with Mr. Messer before the camp was<lb/>
established. It will probably yield a fair number of pestiferous mos-<lb/>
quitoes and some <hi rend="underline">A</hi> unless much pains is taken. It is not believed to<lb/>
be a bad place for <hi rend="underline">A</hi>, <del>XXXXXXXXXXXXXXX</del> but this judjment is<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fC0128023"/>
-5-<lb/>
based on its physical characteristics. No sufficient biological exam-<lb/>
ination was possible. The valley is densely wooded.</p>
<p>15. There is an area below the signal tower of the N. &amp; W.<lb/>
R. R., partly caused by its barrow pit, breeding anopheles quite freely,<lb/>
and which should breed freely later when there is less rain. This area<lb/>
is on both sides of the track. On the north side extends down to the<lb/>
bridge over the creek--a branch of Blackwater--and on the south side,<lb/>
a short distance on both sides of the creek. This about a half mile from<lb/>
the camp, further from the barracks. It can be easily drained into the<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">creek. In spite of</hi> its distance, I think this should be done.</p>
<p>July 17.</p>
<p>On Blackwater Creek and Branches, all of it within the<lb/>
reservation.</p>
<p>Creek in flood and close examination impossible. <hi rend="underline">A</hi> in swampy<lb/>
areas in fields near old saw-mill, a half mile southeast of Major Cole's<lb/>
house--in fair number--woods negative.</p>
<p><unclear><add><hi rend="underline"><hi rend="italics">main these arising</hi></hi></add></unclear></p>
<p>This examination was made in wet, the latter part in very wet,<lb/>
weather. Naturally, then, a number of places breeding in ordinary<lb/>
weather would have been washed out and found negative in this survey; al-<lb/>
so, on account of the flooding of pools, larvae were harder to find than<lb/>
would have been the case normally. A survey in normal weather, then,<lb/>
would have shown more breeding places and more breeding in such places<lb/>
than is here indicated.</p>
<p><hi>H.R. Carter</hi></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
