<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="C0302041">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article: Spirochetosis observed on the Upper Ivory Coast and clinically similar to yellow fever, by [s.n.] Stevenel, September 7, 1923 [Enclosed in C0302040]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Stevenel, [s.n.]</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0302041</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-09-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Balfour, Andrew</name>
<name type="place">Ivory Coast</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-09-07">September 7, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0302041</idno>
<title>Article: Spirochetosis observed on the Upper Ivory Coast and clinically similar to yellow fever, by [s.n.] Stevenel, September 7, 1923 [Enclosed in C0302040]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Stevenel's article describes case histories and blood examinations that confirm outbreaks of endemic spirochetosis, concluding this could be the cause of outbreaks of disease similar to yellow fever in the Ivory Coast area.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-09-07">
<head>Article: Spirochetosis observed on the Upper Ivory Coast and clinically similar to yellow fever, by [s.n.] Stevenel, September 7, 1923 [Enclosed in <xref id="C0302040">C0302040</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0302041"/>
<p>9-7-1923.</p>
<p>VS</p>
<p><hi>Spirochetosis observed on the Upper Ivory Coast and clinically similar<lb/>
to yellow fever</hi>. St&eacute;venel, Bulletin de la Soci&eacute;t&eacute; de Pathologie Exotique,<lb/>
v. 16, No.4, p.238.</p>
<p>A young European woman who was merely passing through the Lower<lb/>
Coast fell ill on September 4 with violent fever, lumbar pains, severe<lb/>
headache, and with bilious vomit on the 6th and 7th. The vomit and the<lb/>
feces turned black on the 8th; there was slight genital hemorrhage and<lb/>
epistaxis, and the patient died on the 9th. The urine had never been<lb/>
blood-tinged, and the patient had taken quinine regularly as a preventive.<lb/>
She was extremely icteric when she died.</p>
<p>A later inquiry revealed that a number of laborers had died<lb/>
after only a few days of fever, and often with black vomit ane epistaxis.<lb/>
There were about twenty such deaths. Stegomyia could not be found in the<lb/>
region at the time. These cases were not personally observed by the writer<lb/>
nor was he able to make a microscopic examination of the blood.</p>
<p>On December 4 another young European woman who had only been a<lb/>
few days on the Ivory Coast fell suddenly ill with severe headache, lumbar<lb/>
pains and facial congestion. The temperature rose very high, and she had<lb/>
epigastric and abdominal pains the same evening, but no vomit. The last-<lb/>
named appeared the next day, the temperature rose to 41.3, and the pulse<lb/>
fell to <unclear>60</unclear>. Black vomit and slight genital hemorrhage appeared on the 6th.<lb/>
A day later the temperature fell and there was slight icterus. Complete<lb/>
recovery.</p>
<p>The writer had made a microscopic examination of the blood of<lb/>
this patient on December 5, and had found that it contained a small number<lb/>
of spirochetes, about 20 in the field of vision. These spirochetes had a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0302042"/>
-2-<lb/>
length of about 1 1&sol;2 red corpuscle diameters, were formed of three<lb/>
to five spirals, were usually pointed at both ends, and were stained<lb/>
a deep blue-violet by permanganate-eosin. The Spirochaeta dentium,<lb/>
stained in the same way, absorbed less color and remained blue, with<lb/>
hardly any violet tint.</p>
<p>On the 5th, 1 cc. of blood was injected subcutaneously into<lb/>
a wild mouse, but it developed no abnormal signs and no spirochetes<lb/>
in the blood. Some of the patient's urine, which was at first very<lb/>
albuminous, was similarly injected into a guinea pig, with no results.</p>
<p>It was found that there was a slight epidemic of 15 cases<lb/>
in a locality a short distance away. The illness had begun in each<lb/>
case with sudden fever, violent headache, rachialgia, gastric and<lb/>
abdominal pains, with a fleeting icterus on the fourth day. Three<lb/>
patients had died and one of these had had black vomit. None of the<lb/>
convalescents had spirochetes, but all of them were ill more than<lb/>
four days when examined.</p>
<p>In still another case a little white boy of 7 was brought<lb/>
to the writer, as he had been ill for a week. According to his mother,<lb/>
his face had been red, he cried continually without cause, and he<lb/>
vomited a great deal. This had continued for a few days, and then<lb/>
he had been jaundiced for three days. An examination of the blood<lb/>
revealed only 7 spirochetes in all, similar to those found in the<lb/>
previous patient. A few days later he had completely regained his<lb/>
normal color, appetite and habits. On December 20 there were no<lb/>
spirochetes left in the blood. Injection of his urine into guinea pigs<lb/>
had no effect on them. Unfortunately there were no more quinea pigs<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0302043"/>
-3-<lb/>
available into which to inject his blood, so that there is a gap in<lb/>
the examination. The blood smears all contained a large proportion<lb/>
of mononuclear leucocytes, and eosinophiles were found in most cases.<lb/>
Some Stegomyia were found after protracted search in the location in-<lb/>
habited by the boy, but they are extremely rare in that region. The<lb/>
writer was then transferred and was unable to go on with his research.</p>
<p>The following conclusions may be drawn from these undortunately<lb/>
incompletely findings:</p>
<p>1( There evidently exists an endemic spirochetosis on the<lb/>
Upper Ivory Coast.</p>
<p>2) This is probably not Weil's disease, as the urine of the<lb/>
patients had no pathogenic effect on guinea pigs.</p>
<p>3) The disease cannot be relapsing fever, as the blood of<lb/>
the patients contained eosinophiles, as that disease is very deadly,<lb/>
and as no relapses were observed.</p>
<p>4) This spiro<add>_</add>chetosis is similar to the that of the Lepto-<lb/>
spira icteroides of Noguchi, but the extreme rarity or complete absence<lb/>
of Stegomyia in this region does not permit one to attribute to this<lb/>
insect alone the role of vector.</p>
<p>5) These researches must be methodically renewed withs<lb/>
sufficient microbiological material, for this endemic disease is<lb/>
perhaps the cause of the yellow-fever-like outbursts that appear from<lb/>
time to time on the Coast.</p>
<p>**********</p>
<p>Andrew Balfour, abstracting this article in the &ldquo;Trans-<lb/>
actions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene,&rdquo; v.17,<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fC0302044"/>
-4-<lb/>
nos. 1 and 2, p.86, 1923, introduces it by saying,</p>
<p>&ldquo;In view of the interesting communications which have<lb/>
recently been published by French observers in West Africa on the<lb/>
discovery of Spirochaetes in the centrifuged blood of blackwater<lb/>
fever patients, and more especially as regards the occurrence of<lb/>
what would appear to be a new form of human spirochaetal infection in<lb/>
which the virus is transmitted seemingly by bedbugs, attention may<lb/>
be drawn to a paper by St&eacute;venel.&rdquo;</p>
<p>There is so mention of bedbugs in St&eacute;venel's own article.</p>
<p>**********</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
