<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="C0302010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Kenneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0302010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability> 
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-30</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Maxcy, Kenneth F.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name>
 </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Cacinim, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Sella, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Bass, C. C.</name>
<name type="person">Taylor, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">McDonald, Angus</name>
<name type="person">Von Ezdorf, Rudolph H.</name>
<name type="person">Mayne, Bruce</name>
<name type="person">Pearl, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Fricks, Lunsford D.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Swellengrebel, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Schuffner, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Veldee, M. V.</name>
<name type="place">Badin (N.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Montgomery (Ala.)</name>
<name type="place">India</name>
<name type="place">Yazoo (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Scott (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">England</name>
<name type="place">Louisiana</name>
<name type="place">Mississippi</name>
<name type="place">Batavia</name>
<name type="place">Missouri</name>
<name type="place">Arkansas</name>
<name type="hospital">Badin Hospital, Badin (N.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-30">August 30, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0302010</idno>
<title>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Kenneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter responds to questions from Maxcy regarding the blood index of malaria and problems with blood examination tests based on data from various scientists addressing these issues.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1923-08-30">
<head>Letter from Henry Rose Carter to Kanneth F. Maxcy, August 30, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0302010"/>
<opener>
(Copy)<lb/>
PERSONAL<lb/>
&sol;L C<lb/>
<dateline>
Badin Hospital,<lb/>
Badin, N.C.<lb/>
<date value="1923-08-30">August 30, 1923.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr Kenneth F. Maxcy,<lb/>
U.S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Care of State Health Officer,<lb/>
Montgomery, Ala.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Maxcy:</salute>
</opener>
<p>About the problem in relation to the blood index<lb/>
of malaria about which you asked, I had purposed to wait until I<lb/>
got back home, where I have access to notes etc., but as I am still<lb/>
in bed I will outline it to you as well as I can without notes<lb/>
and send you a supplementary letter when I get to Washington,<lb/>
which I think will be shortly.</p>
<p>The problem was:</p>
<p>(1) To determine what proportion of infections would<lb/>
be missed by a blood examination (thick film) by a careful and<lb/>
trained man on a single examination.</p>
<p>(2) What proportion of cases found positive by such<lb/>
examination in the late fall would be found negative (presumably,<lb/>
but not necessarily, cured spontaneously) in the spring or<lb/>
summer under the ordinary conditions of life in the country on<lb/>
plantations in the south. The &ldquo;ordinary conditions of life&rdquo;<lb/>
do not imply the exclusion of quinine or its efficient use --<lb/>
simply people living as they habitually live during the fall,<lb/>
winter and spring.</p>
<p>Let me take the second problem first:</p>
<p>The desirability of its solution -- or rather the<lb/>
solution of the inverse problem: the proportion of relapses<lb/>
(parasitic or symptomatic) is stressed by Ross in his &ldquo;Prevention of<lb/>
Malaria&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A good deal of work on it has been done by the Italians,-<lb/>
especially by Cacini and by Sella. Ross himself gives data on<lb/>
this problem from India and Bass has data on it in his work on the<lb/>
Yazoo, where, however -- judging partly by the statistics of Taylor<lb/>
in Arkansas and my own single observation at Wilson, - his proportion<lb/>
of relapses is too high. My recollection is that he found from a<lb/>
little over 50% to about 69% relapses among the people who had<lb/>
malaria in 1918: but you have access to his papers.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fC0302011"/>
<p>-2-<lb/>
This problem was taken up tentatively by us in 1914.<lb/>
It was planned to take a careful blood index of a badly infected<lb/>
community <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the date at which infection could be contracted,<lb/>
taking the names of all persons. To take the same index by the<lb/>
same man -- or one equally careful and skillful -- in the early<lb/>
Spring <hi rend="underline">before</hi> malaria could be contracted. A comparison of these<lb/>
would give us data upon the subject. For instance, if 20% of all<lb/>
those that were positive in the fall showed negative in the spring<lb/>
and continued to show negative until well into the malaria season,<lb/>
it would be evidence -- although not quite proof -- that that<lb/>
proportion, under the conditions that existed, had freed themselves<lb/>
from infection. I say &ldquo;not quite proof&rdquo; because for proof<lb/>
these people should be kept not exposed to malaria infection and<lb/>
watched a long time. On the other hand, if 20% of those found<lb/>
negative in the fall were found positive in the early spring before<lb/>
it was possible to contract malaria, it would be proof (not merely<lb/>
evidence) that 20% at least of infections had been missed on our<lb/>
suppossedly careful examination. I say &ldquo;at least&rdquo; because it is<lb/>
obvious that if a careful examination in the late fall missed<lb/>
finding some infections a similar careful examination in the early<lb/>
spring might do the same and 20% would not represent all the<lb/>
infections beyond those found in the fall that existed. This<lb/>
difficulty could be met, however, by keeping our men who were<lb/>
negative in the fall out of contact with infected Anopheles<lb/>
for a considerable time until we could be certain by further<lb/>
examinations that no parasites could be found in their blood.</p>
<p>For the early spring chances of exposure to infected Anopheles<lb/>
we must take into consideration the hibernated females which --<lb/>
in any district we have examined in the United States -- are indeed<lb/>
come through the winter uninfected, but which, if they enter houses,<lb/>
(as quads do) can readily become infected from carriers, in whom,<lb/>
of course, the parasite does winter and, it being warm in the house,<lb/>
at the end of 20 or 30 days infect other men.</p>
<p>This matter has never been worked out in America but frankly<lb/>
I am inclined to think that a considerable number of the early<lb/>
spring cases are infections by these hibernated females becoming<lb/>
thus infected in houses and staying in houses or maybe warm stables<lb/>
long enough to become <hi rend="underline">infective</hi>. This, of course, could happen before<lb/>
the flight of the earliest spring brood who have no houses to warm up in.</p>
<p>Angus MacDonald has laid some stress on this in the early spring<lb/>
post-bellum malaria in England.</p>
<p>Dr. von Ezdorf took a blood index (thick film) at Scott, Miss.<lb/>
in the fall of 1915. At my instance, Mayne took a similar index<lb/>
there in February 1915 in conjunction with his great work on the<lb/>
hibernation of the parasite in the mosquito. As I remember the<lb/>
figures ----(my memory is quite reliable, but I will send the exact<lb/>
data when I get home) --- von Ezdorf out of 1666 people found a<lb/>
positive blood index of 41.11%. Mayne on 1164 specimens found an<lb/>
index of 39.9% (or 39.5%). Both were careful men: both used the<lb/>
same method in getting the specimens and in examining them: both<lb/>
took a sufficient number of specimens to eliminate accidental errors<lb/>
of observation: both found approximately the same proportion of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0302012"/>
-3-<lb/>
of positives. If then there was no chance of new infections<lb/>
in the interval between these indices one must take one horn or<lb/>
the other of this dilemma.</p>
<p>(a) either <unclear>the</unclear> men that were positive in the fall were<lb/>
positive in the spring and those that were negative in the fall<lb/>
were negative in the spring or</p>
<p>(b) that equal numbers changed from negative to positive<lb/>
and from positive to negative.</p>
<p>In only a small number -- 103 is my recollection --<lb/>
were specimens taken from the same men whose names were recorded<lb/>
by von Ezdorf as positive --- he kept no record of his negative<lb/>
cases. Of these 103, 55, as I remember, Mayne found negative<lb/>
(53%). Now 103 is not enough to make a percentage on, but<lb/>
if this proportion held true of other positives turning to<lb/>
negatives we will have to accept (b) as our explanation of the<lb/>
result of these observations.</p>
<p>Mayne's index was certainly made before the spring<lb/>
flight of Anopheles. His own dissections of wild Anopheles satisfy<lb/>
me that it was made before the hibernated ones became infective.<lb/>
I am not, however, certain that von Ezdorf's index was taken after<lb/>
all reasonable probability of infection was passed. (I will send<lb/>
you the dates when I get home).</p>
<p>I made several attempts with Mayne at the rural units<lb/>
of the penitentiaries of Louisiana and Mississippi to repeat this<lb/>
experiment, recording the names, and had the dates which would<lb/>
be beyond dispute, yet the positive data was so small that, while<lb/>
I have it, it is not enough to draw conclusions from.</p>
<p>I did send to the Central Office, however, -- in 1917<lb/>
as I recollect -- a rather long-winded equation by which --<lb/>
(admitting certain postulates, which I confess are only approximately<lb/>
correct) -- one can, from a few satisfactory observations of this<lb/>
kind, determine the proportions of infections that are missed at a<lb/>
careful examination by the method used and therefore the factor<lb/>
by which this positive finding must be multiplied to get approximately<lb/>
a true infection rate from such a blood index. It is rather an<lb/>
intricate equation, but not especially so. Certainly not any more<lb/>
so than the one Ross gives for the increase and diminution of<lb/>
malaria with the increase and diminution of the number of Anopheles<lb/>
present. At any rate, it is not in the same class with Pearl's<lb/>
(Lottka's) transcendental equation developing Ross', which while I could<lb/>
followI I would never reccomend to any friend as light reading.</p>
<p>I think I have a copy of it at home. Whether it is<lb/>
worth undertaking, even incidentally, any observation of this sort,<lb/>
naturally the central Office must be the judge. It is at least<lb/>
a question and depends upon what other work you are doing, but it<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">is</hi> connate to the work that you and others have been doing the last<lb/>
two seasons in the malaria index and is the problem you referred to.</p>
<pb n="4" id="fC0302013"/>
<p>-4-<lb/>
I will ask you then to please send this letter to<lb/>
Dr. Fricks. I would send a copy, as is my usual custom,<lb/>
but the typewriter (the machine,-not Laura) is old and out of<lb/>
order and refuses to copy. Indeed, I expect you will find<lb/>
some script in this letter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly your friend,</salute>
<signed>H.R. Carter</signed>
<seg>
P.S. I have 2 records about the Scott observations - in a<lb/>
note book - but I will go back to the original sources<lb/>
and send them to you when I get back to Washington.<lb/>
Also will give you the title and Journal containing a<lb/>
beautiful article on the relation of the blood index to<lb/>
the splenic index in Batavia, by, as I recollect, the two<lb/>
Swellengrebles ans Sch&uuml;ffne<unclear>r</unclear>,-which you can get from the<lb/>
Bureau. This in re Veldee's recent paper of splenic index<lb/>
in Missouri.<lb/>
H.R.C.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
