<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>
<TEI.2 id="C0302037">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report by Lucian C. Smith, August 28, 1923 [Enclosed in C0302036]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Smith, Lucian C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0302037</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-08-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Mabry, W. L.</name>
<name type="place">Tampico (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">San Jeronimo (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Cierra Azul</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-08-28">August 28, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0302037</idno>
<title>Report by Lucian C. Smith, August 28, 1923 [Enclosed in C0302036]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Smith's report details the medical examination of a suspected case of yellow fever and concludes that it was not yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-08-28">
<head>Report by Lucian C. Smith, August 28, 1923 [Enclosed in <xref id="C0302036">C0302036</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0302037"/>
<p>COPY</p>
<p>Tampico, Mexico<lb/>
August 28, 1923.</p>
<p>Notes on case held under observation for yellow fever by<lb/>
Dr. W. L. Mabry, of the Huesteca Company, at San Jeronimo. The patient<lb/>
was visited and examined by me in consultation with Dr. Mabry in a small<lb/>
isolation ward, designated as the Pest House, in connection with the<lb/>
camp hospital, about 10 o'clock the evening of August 27.</p>
<p>Name: Unknown. For the time the patient was carried on the<lb/>
hospital records by number only. She appeared to have no relatives or<lb/>
particular friends in the native village across the river from the oil<lb/>
camp where she was discovered critically ill, and from which place she<lb/>
was removed to the hospital at the direction of Dr. Mabry, the evening<lb/>
of August 25.</p>
<p>Age: Apparently about 28.</p>
<p>Nativity: Native Mexican woman of Indian type, but place of<lb/>
birth and previous residence undetermined. The Doctor was informed<lb/>
that the woman had been living in the native village close to the camp<lb/>
about three weeks, having come there from Cierra Azul, where she had<lb/>
been living prior to that for two months.</p>
<p>Previous history: Very little definite information had been<lb/>
obtained as to her previous history. Social condition, unmarried. She<lb/>
was said to have had children and to have been living irregularly in the<lb/>
native village. When Dr. Mabry first saw her she made some statement to<lb/>
the effect that she had been beaten and kicked in the abdomen by some<lb/>
man with whom she had been living in irregular relations. Later, the<lb/>
doctor said, she denied that story. She told the nurse that she had<lb/>
several attacks of abdominal pain with vomiting of blood in the past<lb/>
three years. She gave an account of having had an attack of peritonites,<lb/>
three months ago, that is, according to the symptoms she described. Dr.<lb/>
Mabry first saw the woman in a cantina in the village the evening of the<lb/>
24th.</p>
<p>No history of initial chill elicited.</p>
<p>Present Illness: When the case first came under the observation<lb/>
of Dr. Mabry the woman had attracted the attention of neighbors on account<lb/>
of vomiting blood. The history of the duration of the attack varied from<lb/>
a few hours to several days. When the Doctor first saw her she was having<lb/>
frequent paroxysms of vomiting. Some of the material ejected was dark red,<lb/>
conforming to the type of &ldquo;coffee-ground&rdquo; vomitus. At intervals consider-<lb/>
able quantities of bright red blood came up, apparently unmixed with gas-<lb/>
tric secretions. Dr. Mabry thought that within 20 minutes she had dis-<lb/>
gorged over a pint of bloody material. The hemorrhage at that time seemed<lb/>
to threaten her life immediately. Temperature at 6 P.M. that day 99.8<lb/>
Pulse 123. The principal complaint of the patient was of severe pain in<lb/>
the epigastric region, located with maximum intensity in the &ldquo;pit of the<lb/>
stomach&rdquo;; together with cramps in the calves and arms. The next evening<lb/>
the patient was brought over to the Pest House and placed under a mosquito<lb/>
bar with quarantine regulations. The temperature remained about the same.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0302038"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
Pulse rate 111. After being placed in the Pest House the vomiting<lb/>
subsided. The patient had not complained of nausea or vomiting after<lb/>
the evening of the 25th. The temperature was slightly lower, 99.2,<lb/>
on Sunday morning (the 26th) Pulse rate 107. Continued to complain<lb/>
of pain in the stomach and pain cramp in the thighs and arms. The<lb/>
morning temperature Monday, the 27th, was normal. Pulse 103. Evening<lb/>
temperature 38, pulse 113. The Doctor had been informed of the appear-<lb/>
ance of blood in the stools early in her illness, but there was no blood<lb/>
in the stools after she came under the observation of Dr. Mabry.</p>
<p>Physical Examination. General appearance: Fairly well nour-<lb/>
ished and moderately well developed young woman of Indian type. She<lb/>
did not look critically ill on inspection. However, when attempts were<lb/>
made to question her she appeared mentally clouded, answering incoher-<lb/>
ently or irrelevantly. When asked if she was suffering pain she in-<lb/>
variably placed her hand over the epigastric region. On inspection under<lb/>
electric flash light it was not possible to discover any ichteroid tinge.<lb/>
Dr. Mabry said that her conjunctivae had been slightly yellow the first<lb/>
and the second day she was under his observation. The tongue was broad,<lb/>
unindented by teeth marks, covered with a slight, whitish coat. The tip<lb/>
and edges were not marked red. There was no marked tremor observed upon<lb/>
protrusion. The gums were not bleeding. No oosing was observed. To<lb/>
the finger they did not feel spongy. Dr. Mabry said that the appearance<lb/>
of the tongue had remained about the same.</p>
<p>The heart and lungs appeared negative. The abdomen was negative<lb/>
to inspection. On palpation over the stomach pain was elicited by slight<lb/>
pressure. The spleen could not be palpated by this examiner (L.C.Smith)<lb/>
but Dr. Mabry said that the spleen had been palpable. At that time he<lb/>
said he could feel the edge of the organ under his fingers on deep pal-<lb/>
pation with the patient turned on the right side. The liver did not<lb/>
appear definitely enlarged on physical examination. It appeared ample<lb/>
within normal limits. Dr. Mabry was satisfied that he had detected ten-<lb/>
derness and increased tensio in the region of the gall bladder. This was<lb/>
not evident to this examiner. Dr. Mabry reported marked abdominal tym-<lb/>
panitis, with slight distention, at first.Further physical examination<lb/>
was generally negative.</p>
<p>The examination of the urine-August 27-showed a heavy trace of<lb/>
albumen. Specific gravity 1033. Not reported for casts. Gross appear-<lb/>
ance of urine decidedly high colored, &ldquo;febrile&rdquo; type. Scanty in quantity.</p>
<p>The treatment has been wholly symptomatic.</p>
<p>Conclusion: In the opinion of this examiner this is not a<lb/>
case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>------------------------------</p>
<p>Lucian C. Smith.</p>
<p>Cop.A V G.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
