<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0316001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Laura Armistead Carter, July 13, 1927</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Frost, Wade Hampton</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0316001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-07-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Carter, Laura Armistead</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Smiley, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-07-13">July 13, 1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0316001</idno>
<title>Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Laura Armistead Carter, July 13, 1927</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Frost describes the pace of his editing work on Henry Rose Carter's manuscript of the History of Yellow Fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1927-07-13">
<head>Letter from Wade Hampton Frost to Laura Armistead Carter, July 13, 1927</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0316001"/>
<opener>
Frost - <hi>re</hi> <add>Book</add> text for<lb/>
Section III: Part 2<lb/>
THE JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY<lb/>
SCHOOL OF HYGIENE AND PUBLIC HEALTH<lb/>
615 NORTH WOLFE STREET<lb/>
DEPARTMENT OF EPIDEMIOLOGY<lb/>
BALTIMORE, MD.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1927-07-13">July 13, 1927.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Miss Laura A. Carter,<lb/>
Dunlora, Box 453,<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Miss Laura:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Mrs. Smiley is getting along excellently with<lb/>
the manuscript, having now finished the copying of<lb/>
sections I and II, and part I of section III. In<lb/>
addition to that she and I together have checked<lb/>
your index of bibliographic references in section<add>s</add> I<lb/>
and II and believe that as an index this is now com-<lb/>
plete, though of course a good many of the references<lb/>
remain to be filled in in proper form and verified.</p>
<p>With reference to section III, part II, we<lb/>
are in some doubt as to what text to use for making<lb/>
the copy. I find in the files two texts, namely:</p>
<p>(1) <del>a</del><add>A</add> loose, that is, unbound manuscript of<lb/>
your own typing<add>,</add> with amendments in your father's<lb/>
handwriting and with notes which you have transcribed <add>&amp;</add><lb/>
inserted here and there, either by pinning on slips<lb/>
or by pasting them in. This, I presume, is <del>a</del><add>the</add> copy<lb/>
which you intended <del>thus</del> to use<add>,</add> and my only doubt<lb/>
arises from the fact that it was tied up in a bundle<lb/>
with a similar manuscript of section III, part I,<lb/>
on which there was your notation not to use this<lb/>
manuscript but another more completely revised one<lb/>
which we have found <add>(for part 1)</add></p>
<p>(2) the bound copy made in the offices of<lb/>
the International Health Board. This<add>,</add> so far as I<lb/>
have checked it<add>,</add> seems to be identical with your<lb/>
own copy and to have had incorporated in it all the<lb/>
revisions which are indicated in your copy.</p>
<p>I assume that in making our copy, we should<lb/>
use the one which I have indicated under (1) above<lb/>
and am writing to you merely to confirm this.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fC0316002"/>
<p>Miss Carter<lb/>
-2-</p>
<p>As Mrs. Smiley will be able to complete<lb/>
the copying well before the end of the month I think<lb/>
it may be advantageous for her thereafter to make an<lb/>
index of references and allusions for section III<lb/>
similar to what you have already made for section I<lb/>
and II. I think something of this kind<add>,</add> bringing<lb/>
together in one place all the references to and quo-<lb/>
tations from each authority<add>,</add> will be necessary<add>;</add> and<lb/>
with the guidance afforded by your index of the<lb/>
other sections I think that Mrs. Smiley can make this<lb/>
index quite satisfactorily.</p>
<p>As regards sections I and II<add>,</add> which I have<lb/>
already been over carefully<add>,</add> I find that they need<lb/>
almost no editorial revision - at least in my judgment -<lb/>
and that practically nothing remains to be done on them<lb/>
except to identify and verify the bibliographic<lb/>
references. This will be somewhat laborious but<lb/>
for the most part I think it will not be very difficult<lb/>
if one works in a more complete library than we have<lb/>
here.</p>
<p>As regards verification of all the citations<lb/>
and quotations in section III where the references are<lb/>
mostly to old works, this can be done only by some<lb/>
one like yourself who is thoroughly familiar with<lb/>
the languages in which they are written. I do not<lb/>
know<add>,</add> in fact, that a check of all the quotations is<lb/>
really necessary<add>,</add> because I think it is evident from<lb/>
the way in which the quotations are given that your<lb/>
father copied them verbatim as he read the texts<lb/>
and that they were certainly done with great care<lb/>
so that there is hardly any chance for an error<lb/>
except a typographical one or a slip of the pen which<lb/>
one ought to be able to identify from the text. I<lb/>
think it is certain that in making these quotations<lb/>
your father took full notes<add>,</add> copying from the texts<add>,</add><lb/>
and if these notes can eventually be found, they<lb/>
may be of considerable help.</p>
<p>Since I have been checking over the manuscript<lb/>
I have appreciated more fully than I had heretofore,<lb/>
the extent and the difficulties of the work that you<lb/>
have already done in putting in the notes and in<lb/>
making such careful cross references as you have</p>
<p>Please let me know at your convenience about<lb/>
the copy to be used for section III, part II. For<lb/>
the rest there is nothing in this letter that re-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0316003"/>
Miss Carter<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
quires any answer and certainly nothing for you<lb/>
to trouble yourself about. Everything goes well and<lb/>
I am confident that after you come back<add>,</add> after a good<lb/>
rest<add>,</add> you will find no great difficulty in finishing<lb/>
up what remains to be done<add>,</add> which is not a great deal.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With best regards,<lb/>
Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>W. H. F.</signed>
WHF:F<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
