<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0312017">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Hugh S. Cumming, October 15, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0312017</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-10-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Cumming, Hugh S.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ravenel, Mazyck P.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, William S.</name>
<name type="person">Parker, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Byam, Eber C.</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-10-15">October 15, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0312017</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Hugh S. Cumming, October 15, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter refutes Ravenel's suggestion that Henry Rose Carter did not influence Reed's decision to investigate the theory of mosquito transmission of yellow fever and encloses documents to support this position.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-10-15">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Hugh S. Cumming, October 15, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0312017"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1925-10-15">October 15, 1925.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Surgeon General H. S. Cumming,<lb/>
U. S. Public Health Service,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Cumming:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of October 14, 1925, enclosing that of Dr. Mazyck<lb/>
Ravenel, has just reached me.</p>
<p>I am enclosing herewith <xref id="C0312020">enclosure 1</xref></p>
<p>1: A carbon of a <xref id="C0312021">letter</xref> of Walter Reed to Father (original<lb/>
in my possession) in which he states that Father's work &ldquo;did more to<lb/>
impress&rdquo; him &ldquo;with the importance of an intermediate host than every-<lb/>
thing else put to-gether&rdquo;.</p>
<p>2: <xref id="C0306001">Transcription</xref>, from stenographic notes taken at the time, of<lb/>
<add>part of</add> a talk Father had with Thayer and Parker one Sunday afternoon in July<lb/>
1924, just before we left for the Jamaica Conference.</p>
<p>As you know Father was very loath to talk of the influence of<lb/>
his work in determining the direction of the experiments of the Reed<lb/>
Board. Indeed, I tried vainly sever<add>a</add>l times to get him to dictate or<lb/>
write out in detail the happenings in Cuba, but he replied that &ldquo;the<lb/>
only allowable ambition for a man was the ambition of <hi>achievement</hi>&rdquo; and<lb/>
that it didn't matter who got the credit so long as the work was done.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0312018"/>
done.<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
He further told me that he was rather glad that he would probably die be-<lb/>
fore he got to the Section of his History of Yellow Fever dealing with the<lb/>
discovery of the method of transmission of yellow fever as if he did so<lb/>
he would have to claim credit for &ldquo;determining the direction of Reed's work&rdquo;<lb/>
<del>for while</del><add><del>Since</del> for although</add> Reed himself, both in personal letters and in some of his earlier<lb/>
(&ldquo;preliminary&rdquo;) announcements freely and whole-heartedly admitted this, yet<lb/>
it <del>is</del><add>was</add> one thing to have the value of one's work admitted by the fellow<lb/>
scientist to whom it had shown the way and another to claim that credit for<lb/>
oneself--even when possessing, as <add>I consider</add> we do, data to prove <add>it.</add></p>
<p>It was just by good luck then that one Sunday afternoon, shortly<lb/>
before we left for Jamaica last year, <del>that</del> Dr. Thayer and Dr. Parker (both<lb/>
old and trusted friends) spent most of the afternoon with him and, in the<lb/>
enthusiasm engendered by a long talk between the three on yellow fever, he<lb/>
gave the details herein enclosed. As soon as he started, I slipped quietly<lb/>
behind the head of his bed (where he couldn't see what I was doing!) and,<lb/>
with an understanding glance at the other two, opened my stenographic note<lb/>
book and began to record the conversation. Not, of course, with any idea<lb/>
of publication, but because I wanted the exact data for &ldquo;the family ar-<lb/>
chives.&rdquo; There are gaps, as I had to get up to answer the telephone etc.<lb/>
once or twice and, of course, he kept on talking. Indeed, had he known<lb/>
what I was doing he would have stopped his narrative--or have stopped me!</p>
<p>I am sure Dr. Thayer will gladly vouch for the accuracy of the<lb/>
statements in Enclosure B, <add>of this letter</add> although, of course, he couldn't swear to the<lb/>
identical words of the parts in quotation marks. I can assure you, however,<lb/>
that they are as Father spoke them.</p>
<p>3: No one was more keenly desireous that Finlay be accorded <add>the</add> honor<lb/>
justly due him than Father. He both loved and revered the Great Cuban--<lb/>
&ldquo;<hi>nomen clarum et venerabile</hi>!&rdquo; as he nearly always added <del>after</del><add>when</add> mentioning<lb/>
hi<del>s</del><add>m</add> <del>name</del>. Indeed, when Father was asked to write the Section on Yellow Fever<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0312019"/>
Fever<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
in The Practice of Medicine in the Tropics (Oxford Press:London, 1922) he<lb/>
made it an absolute condition of so doing that they should waive <add>their</add> request<lb/>
that no historical data be incorporated in the article in order that he be<lb/>
allowed to pay proper tribute to Finlay. This, Colonel Byam agreed to, and<lb/>
I am enclosing a copy of the <xref id="C0312022">paragraphs</xref> (from the 1922 edition) treating of<lb/>
Finlay's work and comparing it with that of Beauperthuy and Nott.</p>
<p>I most heartily concur in Dr. Ravenel's statement that &ldquo;the truth of<lb/>
medical history&rdquo; is of more value than the credit given &ldquo;any one particular<lb/>
man.&rdquo; Indeed, the two things are not comparable. I feel sure, however, for<lb/>
this very reason, that he will be <add>glad to</add> have this additional light on<del>e</del> the sub-<lb/>
ject, since, from what I have often heard of him from Father, as well as<lb/>
from his <add>universal</add> reputation for ability and fair-mindedness it will<lb/>
be a satisfaction to him to render justice where justice is due.</p>
<p>I have more data on this subject, but I have gotten out of bed to<lb/>
collect this and, unless you find it insufficient, I will let the rest<lb/>
alone until I am convalescent at any rate, since I think what I am enclosing<lb/>
is sufficiently convincing of the fact that Father's work <hi>did</hi> &ldquo;<hi>determine<lb/>
the direction of Reed's work</hi>&rdquo; and that <del>so</del><add>Reed</add> admitted it.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With hopes that what I am enclosing may be what you wish,<lb/>
Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>L. A. Carter</signed>
Enclosures<lb/>
<unclear>mem. eother</unclear><lb/>
Later<lb/>
See also<lb/>
(a) <unclear>Frost's</unclear> Mem. for the I. H. B <hi>in re</hi><lb/>
Father and <unclear>(b)</unclear> the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> publication by<lb/>
Walter Reed &amp; his associates: The<lb/>
Etiology of Yellow Fever-a Preliminary Note.<lb/>
Public Health Paper &amp; Reports Vol XXVI.<lb/>
<unclear>A.P.H. A. [unclear]</unclear> 1900<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
