<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0314002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article: Minute of the International Health Board Regarding Dr. Henry Rose Carter, [November 4, 1926] [Enclosed in C0314001]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Welch, William H.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0314002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1926-11-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Snow, John</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Edwall, David L.</name>
<name type="person">Flexner, Simon</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">University of Maryland, College Park</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Biloxi (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">United States</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>6 pp.</extent>
<date value="1926-11-04">[November 4, 1926]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0314002</idno>
<title>Article: Minute of the International Health Board Regarding Dr. Henry Rose Carter, [November 4, 1926] [Enclosed in C0314001]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>A statement about Carter's education, career, and accomplishments is incorporated into the permanent record of the International Health Board of the Rockefeller Foundation.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1926-11-04">
<head>Article: Minute of the International Health Board Regarding Dr. Henry Rose Carter, [November 4, 1926] [Enclosed in <xref id="C0314001">C0314001</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0314002"/>
<p>International Health Board<lb/>
of<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
61 Broadway New York</p>
<p>MINUTE OF THE INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD<lb/>
REGARDING DR. HENRY ROSE CARTER</p>
<pb n="2" id="fC0314003"/>
<p>The death of Dr. Henry Rose Carter, assistant surgeon-general<lb/>
of the United States Public Health Service, at his home in Washington on<lb/>
September 14, 1925, in the seventy-fourth year of his age, was reported to<lb/>
the Board at the meeting immediately following his death and was the oc-<lb/>
casion of an appreciative memorial sketch of his life and work in the Bul-<lb/>
letin of the International Health Board of October, 1925. Dr. Carter's<lb/>
relations to the Board during the last decade of his life as a member of<lb/>
its Yellow Fever Commission headed by General Gorgas, and since 1920, of<lb/>
the succeeding Yellow Fever Council, and as the author of the forthcoming<lb/>
<hi>History of Yellow Fever</hi>, the preparation and publication of which have<lb/>
been made possible by aid from the Board, were so important and so highly<lb/>
esteemed, that a minute commemorating his services should find a place in<lb/>
its permanent records.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter, born in Virginia and his life largely spent in the<lb/>
South, was trained in civil engineering, mathematics and the classics at<lb/>
the University of Virginia. His natural endowment of an unusually clear,<lb/>
logical, analytic type of mind was further strengthened by three years of<lb/>
teaching of mathematics, the last one being at his alma mater. Diverted<lb/>
by an accident from the career of a civil engineer, he was graduated in<lb/>
medicine in 1879 at the University of Maryland and at once entered the Ma-<lb/>
rine Hospital Service now the United States Public Health Service, a con-<lb/>
nection which determined for the remainder of his life the direction and<lb/>
range of his professional interests, studies and work.</p>
<pb n="3" id="fC0314004"/>
<p>2.</p>
<p>He showed marked aptitude and ability for clinical work during<lb/>
the early years spent mainly in the hospitals of the Service, but his<lb/>
great opportunity came with his detail in 1888 to the federal quarantine<lb/>
station on Ship Island off Biloxi, Mississippi. Much space would be re-<lb/>
quired to set forth adequately and correctly Carter's personal share in<lb/>
the reform of maritime quarantine principles and practice in the United<lb/>
States. Here it must suffice to state that his achievements in this field<lb/>
are widely recognized and that the improvements which he introduced rank<lb/>
among his major services and were largely instrumental, through the confi-<lb/>
dence which he inspired, in securing the transfer of local city and state<lb/>
quarantine stations to the federal government, thereby placing the system<lb/>
upon a sound and unified basis.</p>
<p>The position which he had attained as an authority and efficient<lb/>
administrator of maritime quarantine is evidenced by his detail in 1898 to<lb/>
organize the quarantine service of Cuba, the most difficult and important<lb/>
assignment in this line of duty which existed at that time, and not less<lb/>
important, his appointment in 1904 to a similar post in the Panama Canal<lb/>
Zone, where from 1905 to 1909 he was director of hospitals and second only<lb/>
to General Gorgas in authority in the sanitary department and probably also<lb/>
in the practical work of sanitation on the Isthmus. Certainly the associa-<lb/>
tion between Gorgas and Carter then and later was of the most intimate per-<lb/>
sonal and friendly character.</p>
<p>Carter's work on yellow fever and on malaria, particularly the<lb/>
former, entitles him to rank among the leading epidemiologists of his gen-<lb/>
eration. It is safe to say that no more acute, brilliant and able epidemi-<lb/>
ological study based solely upon the observation and interpretation of na-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fC0314005"/>
3.<lb/>
ture's confusing experiments in the production and spread of epidemic di-<lb/>
sease, without the aid of human or animal experimentation under controlled<lb/>
conditions, has been made since John Snow's study of cholera and William<lb/>
Budd's of typhoid fever over sixty years ago than Carter's investigations<lb/>
of the intrinsic and extrinsic incubation of yellow fever. Among the con-<lb/>
siderations which determined the direction of Walter Reed's and his co-<lb/>
workers' work in the search for an intermediate host in yellow fever, Reed<lb/>
himself assigned the first importance to these observations of Carter.</p>
<p>The peculiar quality of excellence attaching to all of Carter's<lb/>
work continued to be manifested in his studies and efforts at control of<lb/>
malaria dating from 1913 and continuing throughout the period of the world<lb/>
war, during our participation in which he assumed with striking success<lb/>
particularly arduous duties in the anti-malarial control of the zones<lb/>
around army cantonments. Although the basic principles of control were<lb/>
already established, Carter showed great acumen in noting the existence of<lb/>
many local problems, such as the role of impounded waters, upon the solution<lb/>
of which practical success depended. He clearly recognized in studying the<lb/>
situation in our Southern States that there can be no general program of<lb/>
malaria control of universal applicability and that the problems of each<lb/>
locality must be separately studied, a direction of investigation still<lb/>
further elaborated and pursued by workers of the International Health Board.</p>
<p>While Dr. Carter was interested and widely informed in the whole<lb/>
field of public health and epidemiology, and in addition both within the pro-<lb/>
fession and outside it, was a cultured scholar, his published contributions<lb/>
about thirty in number, were limited to a narrow range of subjects, and these<lb/>
related chiefly to problems presented in the line of his official duties in<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fC0314006"/>
4.<lb/>
the administrative control of epidemic diseases. Dr. Carter is a rare and<lb/>
outstanding example of a man vigorous in action and charged with responsi-<lb/>
bilities of high importance who applies to the successful solution of the<lb/>
problems which he faces those qualities of the enquiring mind, those meth-<lb/>
ods of investigation and that precision of judgment in weighing evidence<lb/>
which characterize the scientific investigator and are rarely combined<lb/>
with efficiency in administration.</p>
<p>Carter's success in securing the confidence and cordial support<lb/>
so necessary to his work, of commercial bodies, teachers, officials, and the<lb/>
public in general by quiet but impressive methods, avoiding over-statement<lb/>
and exaggeration, may well be studied in these days of the conventional and<lb/>
sometimes sensational health propagandist. Fundamentally, it was the rare<lb/>
personality of this gentle, wise, restrained and thoughtful man with com-<lb/>
plete mastery of his subject and with a rich background of experience which<lb/>
at once inspired the confidence and secured the support of those to whom he<lb/>
appealed. These, too, were the qualities which secured the singular loyalty,<lb/>
attachment and affection of his associates, especially of the young men so<lb/>
fortunate as to be trained by Carter in malaria and yellow fever work.</p>
<p>Dr. Carter's authority and well-supported opinions, with those of<lb/>
his colleagues, carried great weight in deciding the International Health<lb/>
Board to initiate the campaign for the complete eradication of yellow fever.<lb/>
He was associated with this undertaking from its inception. His judgment in<lb/>
determining the points of attack and in planning and executing the measures<lb/>
adopted have been of incalculable value. It is a source of great gratifica-<lb/>
tion to the Board to have been able to enlist Dr. Carter for the preparation<lb/>
of the work on the <hi>History of Yellow Fever</hi>, to which the last three years of<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fC0314007"/>
5.<lb/>
his life, in spite of physical disabilities, were ardently devoted. It is<lb/>
believed that the publication of this work, the most important part of which<lb/>
was left practically completed, will be an enduring monument to the ability,<lb/>
scholarship and powers of reasoning of Dr. Carter.</p>
<p>The International Health Board by this minute records its grate-<lb/>
ful appreciation of the invaluable services of Dr. Carter and its profound<lb/>
sense of loss to the Board as well as to science and preventive medicine<lb/>
by his death.</p>
<p>Presented to the Board by its Committee<lb/>
consisting of Dr. William H. Welch, Dr. David L.<lb/>
Edsall, and Dr. Simon Flexner, and adopted by a<lb/>
rising vote at the meeting on November 4, 1926.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
