<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0321010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, October 8, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0321010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-10-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Frost, Wade Hampton</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Boyce, Rupert William</name>
<name type="person">Durham, Herbert E.</name>
<name type="person">Goeldi, Emilio</name>
<name type="person">Cavassa, Nicholas E.</name>
<name type="person">Rand, Isaac</name>
<name type="person">Warren, H.</name>
<name type="person">Tytler, James</name>
<name type="person">Marchoux, Emile</name>
<name type="person">Salimbeni, A.</name>
<name type="person">Simond, P. L.</name>
<name type="person">Warren, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Pringle, John</name>
<name type="person">Nott, Josiah C.</name>
<name type="person">Parrish, Susan Frost</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Susan Haxall</name>
<name type="person">de Mericourt, LeRoy</name>
<name type="person">Busto y Blanco, Fernan del</name>
<name type="person">Fernan del</name>
<name type="place">Boston (Mass.)</name>
<name type="place">Naples (Italy)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health (Baltimore, Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Barbados</name>
<name type="place">Martinique</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-10-08">October 8, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0321010</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, October 8, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter sends a list of bibliographical references for the manuscript of the History of Yellow Fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1928-10-08">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, October 8, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0321010"/>
<opener>
Book, Bibliography<lb/>
Frost<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N.W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
Monday, <date value="1928-10-08">October 8, 1928.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Dr. Wade H. Frost,<lb/>
School of Hygiene and Public Health,<lb/>
615 North Wolfe Street,<lb/>
Baltimore, Maryland.<lb/>
<salute>Dear Jack:</salute>
</opener>
<p>(1) I am herein enclosing completed refs. for<lb/>
i.p.8--- (a) Boyce, Sir Rubert (1911) infection (aegypti) retained 3 months...<lb/>
i. p. 8: Durham, H. E. (vs) Goeldi (though I still hope we can get Goeldi's ref.<lb/>
i.p.11: Cavassa, Nicholas, (1922) <hi>re</hi> effect of temperature on sex-ration aegypti.<lb/>
i. p. 36: Rand, Isaac (1799) Verified quotation.<lb/>
i. p. 36: Warren, H. (1799) as quoted by Tytler, James (1799) <hi>re</hi> epidemic Boston <unclear>1798</unclear>.<lb/>
Library Card for Marchoux, E. Salimbeni, A. and Simond, P. L.<lb/>
ii. p. 52: Lind, James (1792) quoting Sir John Elliott <hi>re</hi> epidemic, Naples 1764)<lb/>
ii. 68-9: " " (1792) O. K. save for expression &ldquo;Coast fevers.)</p>
<p>(2) I am also sending two library cards for Busto y Blanco (a) as quoted by<lb/>
Le Roy de M&eacute;ricourt (the one we used) (b) One for the original edition in<lb/>
case we have a chance to see it later in N. Y. at the Hispanic Library.</p>
<p>(3) Cards for Pringle, Sir John (1810) Incomplete, but we've been over every edition<lb/>
of Pringle in the S. G's Library and its the very best we can do. I'll send<lb/>
you the book when you get to the African section if you so desire, but I am sure<lb/>
the ref. to the &ldquo;appearance of the sick and dead&rdquo; is not there.</p>
<p>(4) <hi>Re</hi> The books you wish sent over, unfortunately I left the N. O. Med. and Sur. Journals<lb/>
containing Nott's articles and I can't get out any more books until I return those.<lb/>
I phoned Miss Fredericks and she says she is sending them to-day.</p>
<p>(4') I think that I can send all of the books you wished to see <hi>except</hi><lb/>
Warren, Henry (1740)<lb/>
Malignant fever in Barbadoes etc.</p>
<p>This book is falling to pieces and cannot be taken from the Library of the S. G.<lb/>
I am, however, enclosing cards containing copy of that part of Warren's book relating to<lb/>
introduction of y. f. from Martinique to Barbadoes. I knew it is much easier to take <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><lb/>
in data when one actually sees the printed page, but this is the very best that can be done<lb/>
short of your seeing it at the S. G's Library.</p>
<p>Sorry for the appearance of this letter, but my typewriter has been much injured by<lb/>
work on Library cards and the elderly drawing pen with which I have addressed the en-<lb/>
velope is equally bad.</p>
<p>With much love to the Susans and<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> trusting to have some more material for your soon,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
Enclosures.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
