<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0329001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 9, 1920</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0329001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1920-01-09</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Brown, Grace</name>
<name type="person">Smiley, Mrs.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Library of Congress (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1920-01-09">January 9, 1920</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0329001</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 9, 1920</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter informs Russell about the progress that she and Frost made over the Christmas holiday and about the maps and bibliographical references for the manuscript of the History of Yellow Fever that she is currently working on.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1920-01-09">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 9, 1920</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0329001"/>
<opener>
Book,<lb/>
<unclear>Misel.</unclear><lb/>
Report. Russell<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1920-01-09">January 9, 1930.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>1: As Dr. Frost may have told you, he and I got in some<lb/>
satisfactory work together during the Xmas holidays. Indeed, he said,<lb/>
on January 2nd., that if <add>he</add> could only get seven more <hi>consecutive</hi> days,<lb/>
he believed that he could complete the final editing. He added, how-<lb/>
ever, that he saw no chance of this and would have to, from that time<lb/>
on, utilize any spare time as it arose, even to hours and half hour<del>.</del><add>s.</add><lb/>
These fragments will, of course, eventually mount up to the necessary<lb/>
total, but it is hard to be &ldquo;so near...and yet so far!&rdquo;...from a defi-<lb/>
nite prognosis as to the time of the completion of this work. Equally<lb/>
hard on Dr. Frost, since we know how anxious he is for the book to go<lb/>
to press.</p>
<p>I came back to Washington on December 27th. for a lot of refer-<lb/>
ence books and other material for Dr. Frost, returning with them to<lb/>
Baltimore on December 29th., after a strenuous session at this end with<lb/>
Miss Brown. Dr. Frost and I worked until about 11.30 the night of my<lb/>
return to Baltimore, which gave us a good start for the next day.</p>
<p>ii. I also brought back with me to Washington, a list, given me by Dr.<lb/>
Frost concerning certain references about which he considers further data<lb/>
advisable. This list I have divided with Miss Brown and we are both<lb/>
actively engaged on it.</p>
<p>iii: I am glad to state that Dr. Frost expected to get Mrs. Smiley<lb/>
started on the typing of the final copy of the Sections he has already<lb/>
edited just as soon as she could do so. Indeed, I expect that she has<lb/>
begun by now. We couldn't have a better person handle this work. Also,<lb/>
her starting now will, of course, greatly lessen the delay in getting<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fc0329002"/>
getting<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
our final copy ready for the printer.</p>
<p>iv: I had my Library of Congress priveleges renewed last<lb/>
December for as much of 1930 as may be necessary..i. e. have been allowed<lb/>
to keep my desk and large accumulation of reference books: also still<lb/>
have access to the stacks and can take home books bearing on Father's<lb/>
MS. But for this, it would have been extremely difficult to cooperate<lb/>
with Dr. Frost in our work during the holdidays or for Miss Brown and<lb/>
myself to continue further research for him.</p>
<p>v: I hope soon to be able to resume what is left of my work on<lb/>
the maps..i. e. (a) write out instructions <hi>re</hi> the inking in of No. i<lb/>
and No. ii: (b) finish checking historical data for our xvi th. Century<lb/>
shore-line map. This, I had intended doing during the holidays, but was<lb/>
more than glad to be able to work with Dr. Frost instead, as the illus-<lb/>
trative material will only be needed after the MS is ready for the<lb/>
printer. Any additional data required by Dr. Frost in the final editing<lb/>
must, of course, take precedence over everything else and, as I have al-<lb/>
ready stated, Miss Brown and myself have been working early and late,<lb/>
since my return, both at the Library of Congress and at my <unclear>apartment</unclear> try-<lb/>
ing to clear things up. Some very good luck: other things, on which we<lb/>
have worked long and hard, still in &ldquo;<hi>status quo</hi>.&rdquo; These things, of course,<lb/>
have all been worked over previously, and belong in the list of &ldquo;dimin-<lb/>
ishing returns,&rdquo; of which Dr. Frost spoke so feelingly in the fall of<lb/>
1928!</p>
<p>With very best wishes, and hoping that the book--<hi>as such</hi>!--may<lb/>
be among the good things the New Year has to give us!</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
Dr. Frederick F. Russell,<lb/>
Director,<lb/>
International Health Division,<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N. Y.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
