<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0327002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wyndham B. Blanton, June 23, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0327002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-06-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Blanton, Wyndham B.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Maury, Bell Moon</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Williams, Jr., Louis L.</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="place">Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">West Africa</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">French Antilles</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health (Baltimore, Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Cape Verde</name>
<name type="place">St. Thomas (V.I.)</name>
<name type="place">Guadeloupe</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-06-23">June 23, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0327002</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wyndham B. Blanton, June 23, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter is interested in Blanton's planned medical history of Virginia and although her father's manuscript does not cover the time period Blanton is interested in, she answers as many questions as she can.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1929-06-23">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wyndham B. Blanton, June 23, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0327002"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
Care Mrs. Bell Moon Maury,<lb/>
&ldquo;Dunlora,&rdquo; Box 453,<lb/>
Charlottesville, Virginia,<lb/>
<date value="1929-06-23">June 23, 1929.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Blanton:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your very interesting letter of June 21st. has just reached me.</p>
<p>A history of medicine in Virginia should certainly be a real contribution<lb/>
to our literature. I shall await its appearance with the greatest interest.</p>
<p><hi>Re</hi> your questions:</p>
<p>1: The number, date, duration and severity of epidemics of yellow fever<lb/>
in Virginia.</p>
<p>(See page 3, this letter <hi>re</hi> Beranger-Feraud's : Trait&eacute; theorique<lb/>
(et clinique...&ldquo; Pub. Paris. 1890)</p>
<p>2.: The authority for these epidemics. <unclear><add>(See page 3, this letter as above)</add></unclear></p>
<p>I regret to say that I <add>personally</add> can give you no <add>further</add> data on either of the above, save that there<lb/>
was certainly no yellow fever in Virginia until well after 1648, the date of the great<lb/>
epidemis of 1648 in Yucatan and the French Antilles (reported by Lopez de Cogolludo and<lb/>
<unclear>P&egrave;r&eacute;</unclear> du Tertre). These<add>,</add> Father counted as the beginning of &ldquo;historic&rdquo; yellow fever in<lb/>
the Americas, as distinguished from the traditional.</p>
<p>As Dr. L. L. Williams, of our Service, may have told you, Father did not live to<lb/>
complete his History of Yellow Fever, although each Section is a complete entity in it-<lb/>
self--&ldquo;like a flight of stairs,&rdquo; as Father once said. This<add>,</add> because he was quite sure<lb/>
he would not live to complete the entire book and would not undertake it until it was so<lb/>
planned that his stopping <unclear>short</unclear> of the end would not interfere with the usefulness of<lb/>
what had already been accomplished. It is true that the Section on Epidemiology (Section 1)<lb/>
covers the ground up to June 30, 1925 (the night before the beginning of his <unclear>final</unclear> illness).<lb/>
Section iii, however (the beginning of the purely historic part of the book) gives <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
epidemiological history of the disease <hi>in detail</hi> only up to 1648 for the Americas<lb/>
and to 1769 and 1778 (Lind and Schotte) for West Africa--i. e. to &ldquo;historic yellow fever&rdquo;<lb/>
in both continents. Notwithstanding the 100 <del>off</del><add>odd</add> years difference between these dates<lb/>
for the two continents, Father considered <add>that</add> yellow fever originated in West Africa. The<lb/>
epidemiological argument for this belief is deduced from many old historic books <unclear>and</unclear> MS<add>S</add><lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fc0327003"/>
MSS<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
in Mayan, Nahuatl, Spanish, French, Latin, Portuguese, and Italian, much of which had<lb/>
never been translated into English until Father and I did sofor his book. I fear then<lb/>
that <add>the citation of</add> this <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> literature would be of little use to you, as some of <del>the literature</del><add>it</add> is<lb/>
quite inaccessible and feel that it would be much more satisfactory if you <add>can</add> wait until the<lb/>
publication of Father's book, which we anticipate will take place in the <add>near</add> future. Dr.<lb/>
Wade Hampton Frost, of the Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene, is doing the final editing,<lb/>
having promised Father to do so before his death. It is a <hi><unclear>perfect</unclear></hi> arrangement, Father<lb/>
thought the world of Frost, both as an epidemiologist and a friend and it means that the<lb/>
the book will not suffer (save in not being completed) by Father's death.</p>
<p>Your No. 4: &ldquo;Whether the <unclear>Stegomyia</unclear> fasciata was indigenous to Virginia or was<lb/>
brought here on sailing vessels!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Father considered that yellow fever was first brought from West Africa (this of<lb/>
course including the islands adjacent thereto (as the Cape de Verdes and S&atilde;o Thom&eacute;): And<lb/>
that, as I have previously stated, it first appeared in the Antilles and Yucatan. These<lb/>
sailing vessels must also have brought the Stegomyia with them as, <add>an epidemic of</add> yellow fever con-<lb/>
tracted by the crews at the port of departure <add>(with no infectable or infected Stegomyia aboard)</add> would have been over long before the end<lb/>
of so long a sea-voyage. <add><del><unclear>Whether it</unclear> have been present on the ships there</del> whether the causative <unclear>organism</unclear> <add>1st</add> came aboard<lb/>
in (a) man or <unclear>(b)</unclear> mosquito wld only matter in (b) adding the<lb/>
period of <unclear>extrinsic incubation</unclear> to the <del>time</del> date of the infectivity of the <unclear>steg,</unclear> &amp; the subsequent <unclear>epidemic</unclear> aboard ship.</add> There are many other reasons for for believing there were no<lb/>
Stegomyia in the Americas at the time of the the arrival of the Spaniards and English into<lb/>
which I have not time to enter. Father's book takes up all these arguments <hi>in extenso</hi>.</p>
<p>No. 3: &ldquo;How yellow fever reached the colony in the <unclear>xvii</unclear> Century when travel by sea<lb/>
was as slow as it was.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This question I have partly answered in the preceeding one. Yellow fever is<lb/>
essentially a ship-borne disease and mosquitoes, either infected prior to leaving the<lb/>
port of departure or breeding aboard and becoming infected from some of the crew in-<lb/>
fected ashore, would stay on the ship indefinitely. <del>Indeed, in the latter.</del> They would<lb/>
thus be capable of biting uninfected men at the port of arrival both aboard-ship and<lb/>
--&ldquo;disembarking,&rdquo; begin breeding in places adjacent to the ship, spreading in time in<lb/>
so far as climatic and sociological conditions permitted. By the latter, I mean that<lb/>
the Stegomyia, in contradistinction to the Anopheles, is an urban <del>not</del> (domestic) form<lb/>
o<del>d</del><add>f</add> mosquito.</p>
<pb n="3" id="fc0327004"/>
<p>mosquito.</p>
<p>-3-</p>
<p><hi>Re</hi> your questions (1) and (2) I think the best book I can recommend is<lb/>
B&eacute;ranger-F&eacute;raud's: &ldquo;Trait&eacute; theorique et clinique de la fi&egrave;vre jaune&rdquo;...<lb/>
Pub. Paris, 1890.</p>
<p>It has a Section (near the front of the book) entitled &ldquo;<hi>Chronologie</hi>,&rdquo; which<lb/>
gives the dates (though not all accurately prior to 1648) of all epidemics of yellow<lb/>
fever in both the Old and the New World. He also cites his original sources, so you<lb/>
should thus be put in touch with an abundance of literature. N.B., however, that as<lb/>
B&eacute;ranger- F&eacute;raud believed in the American origin of yellow fever, you must keep this<lb/>
fact in mind when reading of any epidemics in the New World prior <del>thereto</del> to 1648, in-<lb/>
cluding the &ldquo;<hi>coup de barre</hi>&rdquo; of 1635 in Guadeloupe, which Hirsch, as I recollect, con-<lb/>
siders the beginning of &ldquo;historic yellow fever<del>.</del>&rdquo; in the Americas. I do not recall what<lb/>
B&eacute;ranger-F&eacute;raud says about epidemics of yellow fever in Virginia, but I think you will<lb/>
will find him satisfactory. <add>Copy <unclear>B. F&eacute;raud</unclear> S. G's Library.</add></p>
<p>I am sorry not to be able to answer the above two questions of my own knowledge--<lb/>
Father, of course, could have done so with the greatest ease, but, after he developed<lb/>
angina, we were &ldquo;working against time&rdquo; to such an extent that there was no time <add>for me</add> to<lb/>
get up on the detail of future parts of the work after working 18 hours a day on Section iii</p>
<p>Please give my very best remembrances to Dr. Williams when you see him. Also,<lb/>
should either of you come to Charlottesville within the next month, I do hope that you<lb/>
will come out to &ldquo;Dunlora,&rdquo; and give me some details of the History of Medicine in<lb/>
Virginia. I know of nothing that would give me greater pleasure.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura Armistead Carter</signed>
Dr. Wyndham B. Blanton,<lb/>
828 West Franklin Street,<lb/>
Richmond, Virginia.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
