<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0326001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 1, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0326001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-01-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Brown, Grace</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Susan Haxall</name>
<name type="person">Parrish, Susan Frost</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Library of Congress (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-01-01">January 1, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0326001</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 1, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter and Frost spend Christmas working on bibliographical references for the History of Yellow Fever manuscript. Carter renews her borrowing privileges at the Library of Congress so that she and Brown can keep working efficiently together.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1929-01-01">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, January 1, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0326001"/>
<opener>
Book,<lb/>
<unclear>Misel.</unclear><lb/>
Report (weekly)<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland.<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1929-01-01">January 1, 1929.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>A happy New Year to you and all manner of good therein both<lb/>
for yourself and the International Health Division!</p>
<p>Your very kind letter of December 22, 1928, was forwarded to me<lb/>
in Baltimore, whither I went the Sunday before Xmas to work with<lb/>
Dr. Frost on Father's MS. I looked a good deal like an immigrant<lb/>
when I set out <add>with my literary <hi>impedimenta</hi></add> (four heavy pieces of baggage, one of which was a<lb/>
huge two handled basket full of reference books, which, by the way,<lb/>
Dr. Frost was very glad to see).</p>
<p>Monday (Xmas Eve) I worked mainly by myself, as Dr. Frost was<lb/>
busy all <unclear>morning</unclear> with other things.</p>
<p>Xmas Day we took off.</p>
<p>Wednesday, Dec. 26th. Dr. Frost and I worked from about 9 A. M.<lb/>
to 5.30 P. M. and were both &ldquo;all in&rdquo; when we stopped. However, we<lb/>
got a lot done and agreed on work that I could do over here, in<lb/>
Washington, until we could get together again, our contemplated<lb/>
schedule for working until after New Years Day having been knocked<lb/>
to pieces by conferences, which Dr. Frost has to attend, etc. This<lb/>
mainly on account of the flu situation.</p>
<p>Thursday then, I decided had best see me back in Washington,<lb/>
the more so as Mrs. Frost and her little girl both developed flu<lb/>
while I was there, one on Xmas night, the other 24 hours later. Of<lb/>
course, had Dr. Frost had any more time to give me, I should have<lb/>
moved to an hotel. As it was, however, I began sorting out the mater-<lb/>
ial Dr. Frost wished me to take back with me at 6.15 A. M. and got<lb/>
through in time to catch the 4.16 home. Mrs. Frost was urgent that<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0326002"/>
that<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
I leave the house in the morning lest I contract the flu, but I had<lb/>
already been exposed to it and the extra chance involved in my delay<lb/>
in order to get the bibliographic and library cards Frost wanted me<lb/>
to take from his files was not to be compared with the advantage of<lb/>
having the material here for Miss Brown to work on if I did get sick.<lb/>
We had a &ldquo;night session&rdquo; last week and talked things over (mainly in<lb/>
regard to getting the <add>bibliographic</add> cards in a form in which Dr. Frost feels he can<lb/>
handle them more quickly and in copying, and sending back to his files<lb/>
the accompanying library cards. Miss Brown has already done quite a<lb/>
lot of work on the library cards since my return from Baltimore.</p>
<p>Yesterday, I had to spend a good deal of time in getting my<lb/>
library priveleges renewed at the Congressional Library, they expiring<lb/>
December 31, 1928. This I did, because while most of the work Dr.<lb/>
Frost now wishes me to do can be best done at my apartment, it is a<lb/>
necessity to have the privelege of taking books home for this work, and<lb/>
a great convenience (practically a necessity) to keep my desk, table<lb/>
and reference books at the Library of Congress, in order that Miss<lb/>
Brown be able to work there out of hours and that the reference books<lb/>
be readily available. Also, I shall need to go there myself from<lb/>
time to time.</p>
<p>Miss Brown and I are both very grateful for your good wishes and<lb/>
kind expressions of appreciation about the work on the bibliography.<lb/>
We have worked! We appreciate also what you said about taking off<lb/>
time during the holidays, but--frankly--I'm afraid to stop work save<lb/>
just long enough to get sufficiently rested to go back to it--i. e.<lb/>
late afternoons and sometimes at night. There is too much flu around<lb/>
for me to put off work for recreation. However, even should I contract<lb/>
it--which I most earnestly hope I won't!--it wouldn't be half so bad<lb/>
as it was last year: the bulk of the work is done now and Miss Brown<lb/>
<add>although at considerable inconvenience to herself, <unclear>could</unclear></add><lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0326003"/>
co-operate<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
with Dr. Frost in the remaining work. However, &ldquo;here's hoping&rdquo; I<lb/>
<del>don't</del><add>wont</add> get it--at least until I have a bound copy of the book to<lb/>
read during my convalescence!</p>
<p>Once more, with heartfelt good wishes to you all, at home and<lb/>
overseas, I remain</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
Dr. Frederick F. Russell,<lb/>
Director,<lb/>
International Health Division,<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N. Y.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
