<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0320001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memorandum of talk with Sylvanus Griswold Morley, by Laura Armistead Carter, December 12, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0320001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-12-12</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ojeda, Alonso de</name>
<name type="person">Nicuesa, Diego de</name>
<name type="person">Leake, James P.</name>
<name type="person">Spinden, Herbert Joseph</name>
<name type="person">Jameson, John Franklin</name>
<name type="person">Robertson, James A.</name>
<name type="person">Haring, Clarence H.</name>
<name type="person">Hackett, Charles W.</name>
<name type="person">Rodman, Hugh</name>
<name type="person">Kempff, Captain</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Byam, Eber C.</name>
<name type="person">Archibald, R. G.</name>
<name type="person">Lind, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Schotte, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Holmes, W. H.</name>
<name type="person">Bunker, Frank</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">North America</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">Caribbean</name>
<name type="place">Hispaniola</name>
<name type="place">Santo Domingo (Haiti)</name>
<name type="place">Elmina</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Harvard University</name>
<name type="place">University of Texas</name>
<name type="place">Yucatan (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Tizimin (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Carnegie Institution (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-12-12">December 12, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0320001</idno>
<title>Memorandum of talk with Sylvanus Griswold Morley, by Laura Armistead Carter, December 12, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter writes up notes from a talk with Morley about maps, illustrations, and photographs for the History of Yellow Fever. Reference is also made to Spanish and English translations from the Book of Chilan Balam of Tizimin that Morley has supplied to Carter.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1928-12-12">
<head>Memorandum of talk with Sylvanus Griswold Morley, by Laura Armistead Carter, December 12, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0320001"/>
<p>Memorandum<lb/>
Page 1.</p>
<p><hi>Re</hi> talk with Dr. Sylvanus G. Morley, Dec. 12&sol;28<lb/>
at Carne<del>h</del><add>g</add>ie<unclear>n</unclear> Institution,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.</p>
<p>A: <hi>Re</hi> filling in our three outline maps: <hi>Plate 3</hi>. Mercator's projec-<lb/>
tion West Coast of Africa and adjacent islands with East Coast Middle,<lb/>
North and South America, and adjacent islands. This to show chance<lb/>
cros<del>ee</del><add>s</add>-infection (yellow fever) between the two continents.</p>
<p><hi>Plate 4-a</hi> and <hi>Plate 4-b</hi>: Outlines identical (Middle America,<lb/>
No<del>th</del><add>rt</add>h Coast of South America and islands in the Caribbean). <hi>Plate<lb/>
4-a</hi>, however, to be filled in with centers of Pre-Columbian population:<lb/>
<hi>Plate 4-b</hi> with those after Spanish Conquest. <hi>Plate 4-b</hi> also to be<lb/>
so filled in as to illustrate the wanderings of Ojeda and Nicuesa etc.</p>
<p>Dr. Morley deeply regrets that circumstances have arisen which will<lb/>
make it impossible for him to attend to having these maps filled in,<lb/>
as he had undertaken to do in 1926.</p>
<p>Dr. Morley suggests that in sending our outline<unclear>'</unclear> maps (or, as<lb/>
Dr. Leake thinks might be safer, photostats of somethat reduced size)<lb/>
we ask whoever is selected to fill them them in to indicate <hi>in pencil</hi><lb/>
and <hi>by number</hi> the settlements, towns, etc. to be inserted on the<lb/>
finished maps, with an accompanying legend giving the names corres-<lb/>
ponding to these numbers, and, in cases where there has been a de-<lb/>
cided change in nomenclature, which might confuse the modern reader,<lb/>
that both the original and present name be given; vid. (Espa&ntilde;ola: His-<lb/>
pa&ntilde;ola, Santo Domingo, Haiti): <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> As also A Mina (Elmina)</p>
<p>Incidentally, whoever fills in these maps should have a <hi>readable</hi><lb/>
copy of Father's Ms (or rather of the part relating thereto).</p>
<p>A-2: <hi>Re</hi> the filling in of Plate 4-a (Pre-Columbian centers of<lb/>
population) Dr. Morely suggests that we ask Dr. H. J. Spinden of Har-<lb/>
vard, to do this for us. He considers Dr. Spinden the very best man<lb/>
available. Of course, proper acknowledgement of Dr. Spinden's assis-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0320002"/>
assis-<lb/>
Page 2<lb/>
tance would appear in the book. Dr. Spinden's address is:<lb/>
Dr. H. J. Spinden,<lb/>
Peabody Museum,<lb/>
Divinity Avenue,<lb/>
Cambridge, Massachusetts.</p>
<p><hi>A-3: Re</hi> filling in of outline maps (<hi>Plate 3</hi> and <hi>Plate 4-b</hi>), Dr.<lb/>
Morley considers <add>(1)</add> that Mr. Jameson, of the Library of Congress, would<lb/>
be the best man we could get, partly on account of his being on the<lb/>
spot. If Mr. Jameson is too busy, Morley suggests, in the following<lb/>
order, (2) Dr. James A. Robertson, Editor Florida Historical Society<lb/>
Publications, 54 Flower Street, Takomah Park, Washington D. C.<lb/>
(3) Dr. Clarence H. Haring, Dept. of History, Harvard University and<lb/>
(4) Dr. Charles W. Hackett, Dept of <add>American (?)</add> History, University of Texas,<lb/>
Austin, Texas.</p>
<p><hi>A-4</hi> (1) Tell Jack that Admiral Rodman says Plate-3 (Mercator's<lb/>
<hi>projection</hi>) should be &ldquo;blocked off&rdquo; by one Captain Dempff, an authority<lb/>
on such work, before being filled in. Kempff is a friend of Rodman's<lb/>
and, Rodman' says, will be glad to do it. Rodman states that maps<lb/>
of Mercator's projection are apt to become increasingly inaccurate<lb/>
the farther they go from the equator and that this should be looked<lb/>
into with our outline. Of course, we only want a map to indicate<lb/>
epidemiological conditions, but if one can have it unusually good<lb/>
with very little extra trouble it might be worth while. Que le parece?</p>
<p>(2) Ask Jack for what <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> era we should have this map (Merca-<lb/>
tor's projection) filled in. The historic (or rather pre-historic)<lb/>
part for African yellow fever ends with Lind and Schotte--latter part<lb/>
of Xviii th. Century. However, Father's epidemiological argument<lb/>
for both the Americas <add>and Africa</add><del>goes</del> was continued to June 1925.</p>
<p>(3) If Jack doesn't like Plate 3 (Mercator's projection) ask<lb/>
him how he likes the one in vol. ii, on page 1229, Byam and Archibald's<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0320003"/>
Maps. &rarr; Mem. Gen. Alan Johnson's suggestion <hi>re</hi> &ldquo; Span-Am. Soc&rdquo;<lb/>
of N.Y. (Hispanic?). J.L.'s <hi>re</hi> Pan-American<lb/>
Archibald's<lb/>
Page 3.<lb/>
Practice of Medicine in the Tropics. Oxford Press, (1922). Only,<lb/>
if he prefers this, we'd have to have more islands inserted both<lb/>
off the African Coast and that of the Americas (Middle and South).</p>
<p><hi>B: Re</hi> incomplete bibliographic cards, dealing with Mayan<lb/>
chronology etc., Morley gave me data and addresses of other authori-<lb/>
ties on the subject), through which sources I hope to complete most of<lb/>
these references: (five in all), I took a taxi full of books to the<lb/>
Carnegie and we cleared up a good many things thereby, which would<lb/>
have been very difficult for me to handle otherwise.</p>
<p><hi>C: Re</hi> the three new excerpts from the Book of Chilam Balam<del>of</del><lb/>
of Tizimin, of which Morley sent me the Spanish text in 1926, and<lb/>
which (in their allusion to &ldquo;<hi>V&oacute;mitos de sangre</hi>&rdquo;) strengthen Father's<lb/>
argument as to the absence of yellow fever in Pre-Columbian times,<lb/>
Morley has promised to do his utmost to have all the material sent<lb/>
from Yucatan before we go to press. In this connection see enclosed<lb/>
letter of <del>transmission</del><add>transmittal</add> to Morley (Dec. 12&sol;28), enclosing Spanish text.<lb/>
I am also herein enclosing English translation of the above. It <hi>is</hi><lb/>
important and I hope we will get the Mayan text in time to use it in<lb/>
a foot note.</p>
<p><hi>D: Re</hi> illustrations published by the Carnegie Institution, of<lb/>
which offer has been made us to avail ourselves: Dr. Morley and I<lb/>
have (tentatively--i. e. subject to Dr. Frost's approval) decided that<lb/>
those best suited to our purpose would be <add>(b)</add> the Panoramas of Mexican<lb/>
Cities by Dr. W. H. Holmes (this to show their extent and hence capa-<lb/>
bility of serving as endemic foci, had yellow fever existed in Pre-<lb/>
Columbian times) and (b) Carnegie publication (1928) No. 11, 1st.<lb/>
Photo. (b') Carnegie publication (1927) No. 12, 2nd. photo. These,<lb/>
and such others as we might select the high state of art and archi-<lb/>
tecture (if we can separate them!) prevalent among the Mayas at this<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fC0320004"/>
time.<lb/>
Page 4.</p>
<p>For copies of these illustrations, Dr. Morley has referred me<lb/>
to Dr. Frank Bunker, Editor of the Carnegie publications: Carnegie<lb/>
Institution of Washington, Sixteenth and P Streets, N. W. Washing-<lb/>
ton, D.C. Dr. Bunker will let us have photographs, for reproduction,<lb/>
of anything already published by the Carnegie Institution, suitable<lb/>
acknowledgment being, of course, made for this courtesy.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,<lb/>
(Signed) Laura A. Carter,</p>
<p>Enclosures: Of three new excerpts from book of Chilam Balam of<lb/>
Tizimin, implying arrival of &ldquo;Vomito(s) de sangre&rdquo; with<lb/>
the Spaniards and tentative translation thereof:. Also,<lb/>
carbon of letter transmitting them to Dr. Morley, Decem-<lb/>
ber 12, 1928.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
