<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0328023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, July 29, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0328023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-07-29</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="receipient">Frost, Wade Hampton</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Beeuwkes, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Brown, Grace</name>
<name type="person">Ashburn, P. M.</name>
<name type="person">Doonan, Margaret</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Van Wesep, H. B.</name>
<name type="place">Jamaica</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-07-29">July 29, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0328023</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, July 29, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter understands that the African section of the manuscript, which was written by Henry Rose Carter during his failing health, requires considerable editing.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1930-07-29">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Wade Hampton Frost, July 29, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0328023"/>
<opener>
<hi>Book</hi> <unclear>Misel</unclear>, Frost, W. H.<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.,<lb/>
<date value="1930-07-29">July 29, 1930.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Jack:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of July 27th., <hi>re</hi> the African Section of Father's MS.<lb/>
has just reached me.</p>
<p>I am <hi>not</hi> surprised and I do not expect to be even &ldquo;a bit shocked&rdquo;<lb/>
at the drastic editing you have found necessary.</p>
<p>Your inference that this last Section was written under very dif-<lb/>
ferent conditions from the rest of the MS. is correct. Father began<lb/>
having more frequent, and more severe, attacks of angina some months<lb/>
after his return from the trip to Jamaica; the first soon after the con-<lb/>
ference with Russell, Beeuwkes, Noguchi and White relative to the contem-<lb/>
plated work in West Africa. I do not believe, however, that the conference<lb/>
was a factor in the marked decline of his health at this time. From then on,<lb/>
however, his work was done under extreme physical difficulties. You are<lb/>
correct also about the feeling of &ldquo;stress and hurry&rdquo; about the African Sec-<lb/>
tion, <add>(</add>in such marked contrast to the former part of the work.<add>)</add> Father<lb/>
wanted to get to &ldquo;historic yellow fever&rdquo; in Africa, as he <add>had</add> done for the<lb/>
Americas. <del>a</del><add>A</add>fter, <del><unclear>which</unclear></del><add>this</add> he intended to <add>do</add> no more new work until he had <hi>very<lb/>
carefully</hi> edited that already done. Including the African Section, this<lb/>
would have been a complete entity and, as he told me: &ldquo;A good stopping<lb/>
place, if I have to.&rdquo; As you know, however, this final editing had only<lb/>
been going on a few days before Father's last illness began. I think that<lb/>
he realized that the Section on Africa would need special attention in<lb/>
his final revision, although, of course he did not realize how much. The<lb/>
same applies to myself. I was desperately tired, &ldquo;working against time,&rdquo;<lb/>
with Father and nursing him during his heart attacks. I did, however, real-<lb/>
ize, that the narrative should be more consecutive and that some of the<lb/>
repetitions etc. should be taken out. It was mainly on this account that<lb/>
when, during Father's last illness, Dr. Russell sent me a special delivery<lb/>
letter, telling me that steps were <unclear><add>being</add> taken</unclear> to immediately publish Father's<lb/>
book. I replied asking him <hi>on no account</hi> to do so:---That Father were<lb/>
well enough to know that the book had been published, he would be well e-<lb/>
nough to know that it had been published <hi>before it was as he would have<lb/>
wished it to be</hi>. It was a kind, nay, a beautiful, thought of Russell's and<lb/>
I shall always be grateful to him for it.</p>
<p>Understand, I by no means realized, at that time, the extent of the<lb/>
editing needed for the African Section. I realized it far more fully, so<lb/>
far as the <hi>text</hi> was concerned, during the winter I spent in Baltimore,<lb/>
when I made copious<del>n</del> notes and cross-references, in note books, on the type-<lb/>
writer and on the margin of Father's MS, in the expectation and hope that<lb/>
they would save you work later. However, when we finally got together on<lb/>
the MS I realized that your method of proceedure would be too different<lb/>
from that used by Father and myself for them to be of any use to you. In-<lb/>
deed, I only mention them now because they will show (if you haven't-very<lb/>
properly!-disposed of them as &ldquo;supercargo&rdquo;) that I was even then (1926-7) <unclear><add>much</add></unclear><lb/>
impressed with the difficulties of the African Section.</p>
<p>My worst &ldquo;jolt&rdquo; (in connection with the African Section) <add>however,</add> was in the<lb/>
spring of 1928, when I found (while working at the Library of Congress)<lb/>
that all bibliographic references would have to be verified, even when no<lb/>
verbatim quotations were involved. I wrote you of this in the summer of<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fc0328024"/>
of<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
1928. This in reply to a very considerate letter of your own, in which<lb/>
you stated that you thought that Miss Brown and I were putting in too<lb/>
much work in checking our references. Your experience with the other<lb/>
parts of the book made your assumption almost an inevitable one and I had<lb/>
begun my work <del>(fortunately we started with the African Section)</del> with the<lb/>
same &ldquo;slant&rdquo; on it as your<del>self.</del> <add>own.</add></p>
<p>I feel it Providential that you (the only man capable of doing so)<lb/>
should so generously have placed your great gifts at the service of your<lb/>
old friend! I also feel with you that &ldquo;in justice&rdquo; to him the African<lb/>
Section should be drastically edited. Of course you have probably seen<lb/>
the need of making many changes in matters beyond me, but...I shall not<lb/>
be &ldquo;surprised&rdquo; and I do not expect to be &ldquo;shocked&rdquo;...only profoundly<lb/>
grateful! It is the African Section I have had specially in mind when I<lb/>
have written to Dr. Russell about your turning out the book &ldquo;as Father<lb/>
wished it to be.&rdquo;</p>
<p>You say that I can be of use to you if I am &ldquo;still in Washington by<lb/>
the end of this week.&rdquo; Of course I shall be! What do you think that<lb/>
I am living for? The completion of the book is the one thing left me to<lb/>
look forward to. Please rest assured then that I shall be more than<lb/>
thankful to do anything possible, either here or in Baltimore, that will<lb/>
help you in furthering the routine part of the work. The harder part,<lb/>
alas! no one can relieve you of.</p>
<p>With much love to Susan and looking forward to seeing you both<lb/>
whenever I can be of use,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly your friend,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
<seg>
P. S. I sent you, last Friday, a retyped page from Father's MS (iii, ii, 60)<lb/>
<hi>re</hi> the expedition of &ldquo;Boudewijn Hendricksz&rdquo; (See De Laet and Southey)<lb/>
in 1625. Also, as per your request, additional bibliographic cards on this<lb/>
expedition from other sources. The above was sent, by registered mail,<lb/>
to your office, Susan having not then told me that you were working at<lb/>
home.<lb/>
I also sent you (same day) a letter asking you to &ldquo;lay off&rdquo; Barbot<lb/>
(iii, ii. 81-85) and Commercial Voyages (iii, ii. 105-108) until I sent<lb/>
you retyped pages of the MS (with wide spacing and corrected refs.) and<lb/>
also some additional bib. cards.<lb/>
I further told you that I could let you see such vols. of Hakluyt and<lb/>
Walchenaer (3 or 4 all that are necessary) as would give you additional<lb/>
data on Drake, Commercial Voyages, the Portuguese Pilot etc. You probaly<lb/>
have all this material by now, but repetition is better than omission. <add>in this<lb/>
case.</add><lb/>
L. A. C.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
