<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0326009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, February 8, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0326009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-02-08</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Russell, Frederick F.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Brown, Grace</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Wade Hampton</name>
<name type="person">Morley, Sylvanus Griswold</name>
<name type="person">Frost, Susan Haxall</name>
<name type="person">Ashburn, P. M.</name>
<name type="person">Garrison, Colonel</name>
<name type="person">Neumann, Felix</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Dyar, Harrison G.</name>
<name type="person">Van Wesep, H. B.</name>
<name type="person">Newsholme, Arthur</name>
<name type="person">Hoffman, Frederick L.</name>
<name type="place">Tizimin (Mexico)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Library of Congress (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-02-08">February 8, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0326009</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, February 8, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter describes her progress and the assistance she has received tracking down references for the History of Yellow Fever manuscript.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1929-02-08">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Frederick F. Russell, February 8, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0326009"/>
<opener>
Book, <unclear>Misel</unclear><lb/>
Report (weekly)<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1929-02-08">February 8, 1929.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Russell:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I have just put in another very full week's work for Dr. Frost<lb/>
on the bibliographic cards, including night work with Miss Brown.</p>
<p>I have also received, and will later take over to Dr. Frost,<lb/>
a most interesting, and highly technical! letter from Dr. Morley (a<lb/>
<hi>sequiter</hi> of our interview of Dec. 12&sol;28) <unclear><hi>re</hi></unclear> certain excerpts from the<lb/>
Book of Chilam Balam of <del>Chumayel</del><add>Tizimin</add>. There is no use <hi>sending</hi> it to Dr.<lb/>
Frost as, while the two of us could go over it in short order, it<lb/>
would take him considerably longer by himself to get &ldquo;oriented&rdquo; on the<lb/>
subject of the<add>se</add> particular excerpts--time which he might otherwise be<lb/>
spending on consecutive editing<del>.</del><add>of the History of Yellow Fever.</add> Also, I hope to go over to Baltimore<lb/>
sometime in the<add>[unclear]</add> comparatively near future, Mrs. Frost having called me<lb/>
up on the <unclear>subject</unclear> of spending a week-end with them night before last.<lb/>
I have almost finished another &ldquo;unit&rdquo; of material since the one of which<lb/>
I wrote you in my letter of January 26th., and am &ldquo;working my head off&rdquo;--<lb/>
if one can do so on an &ldquo;Underwood!&rdquo;--to finish it<add>:-</add> putting in the ex-<lb/>
tra verbatim quotations and Memoranda needed to make them clearer than<lb/>
would have been necessary could I have worked <add>with Dr. Frost</add> for the long consecutive<lb/>
time he had planned last fall (when <add>instead</add> he had the &ldquo;flu.&rdquo;) Now with lec-<lb/>
tures, &ldquo;flu&rdquo; investigations etc. his time is more broken up and, as I<lb/>
wrote you before, many of the cards are being retyped in a manner to<lb/>
make them clearer to one less &ldquo;saturated&rdquo; than myself (and Miss Brown)<lb/>
with our original sources of reference.</p>
<p>I spent a good part of to-day at the Library of the Surgeon<lb/>
General of the Army and the Library of Congress respectively. This I<lb/>
did because I wished to renew some books at the S. G.'s Library, Colonel<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fC0326010"/>
Colonel<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
Ashburn having allowed me to continue the privelege of taking books<lb/>
home after I gave up the table on which they were reserved for me at<lb/>
the Library. I had a delightful talk with Colonel Ashburn, indeed<lb/>
going back to the Library was almost like going &ldquo;home,&rdquo; everyone had<lb/>
been so very kind and helpful to Miss Brown and myself, from Colonel<del>s</del><lb/>
Ashburn and <add>Colonel</add> Garrison to the guards, messengers and &ldquo;char-ladies,&rdquo; with the <unclear>I</unclear><lb/>
of whom we were well acquainted, as we frequently reached the Library <add>during the</add> <del>L</del><add>p</add>ast<lb/>
summer before they did. Of course, our medical references were prac-<lb/>
tically completed early last fall, but Mr. Neumann has kept a copy of a<lb/>
few very elusive ones <add>to try to trace for us,</add> (the same <del>are</del><add>list</add> I sent Mr. van Wesep, Dr. L. O Howard,<lb/>
etc. and from which the late Dr. Harrison G. Dyar and myself finally<lb/>
&ldquo;ran down&rdquo; a couple of Portuguese refs., working together one day.) Mr.<lb/>
Neumann has been very kind to us, indeed his ordering the copy of Villalba<lb/>
was a life-saver!</p>
<p>Attended to some necessary details at the Library of Congress also<lb/>
indeed expected to write to you from there but someone has &ldquo;hypothecated&rdquo;<lb/>
my typewriting table. It was quite natural, as I've done no typing there<lb/>
for a long time, my standard Underwood, at home, being far better fitted<lb/>
for work on bibliographic cards than my Remington portable. At that I've<lb/>
had to have them both readjusted <add>twice</add> and the number of ribbons they &ldquo;eat up&rdquo;<lb/>
is a caution!</p>
<p>By the way, would it be asking too much of your Comptroller to<lb/>
ask him if he could let me know how much money I received from the I. H.<lb/>
D. in 1928? reminding him that I sent back a half time salary check from<lb/>
the Hopkins for $150.00 when I was there on sick leave without pay. In-<lb/>
cidentally, I have come to the conclusion that I can never afford the<lb/>
&ldquo;luxury&rdquo; of another long illness, though I might still be able to &ldquo;pull<lb/>
off&rdquo; a &ldquo;satisfactory, simple funeral.&rdquo; However, until the book is fin-<lb/>
ished I shall look ahead to no more distant futures, and at present I am<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0326011"/>
am<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
&ldquo;sufficiently alive&rdquo;--too much so, as regards the neuritis. However,<lb/>
it is not interfering with the typing in the least, the more painful<lb/>
motions being those connected with writing by hand or lifting anything<lb/>
even a glass of water or a book. I've gotten quite expert at using my<lb/>
left hand, however. To return to the beginning of this paragraph, I<lb/>
want the data <hi>re</hi> salary paid me in 1928 in order to make out my income<lb/>
tax return. I could figure it out myself from check book stubs, but<lb/>
I hate to take the time from the work for Dr. Frost. However, if it<lb/>
is not in order for a person on a half time basis to ask for this data <add>(formerly<lb/>
sent me unsolicited)</add> of course I can, as I said, straighten it out myself.</p>
<p>With very best remembrances to yourself and hoping that we<lb/>
shall see you in Washington some time when you do not have to &ldquo;chaperone&rdquo;<lb/>
a foreign delegation and will have more time for the rest of your friends<lb/>
here to have the pleasure the &ldquo;<hi>extranjeros</hi>&rdquo; enjoyed last time,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Very truly yours,</salute>
<signed>Laura A. Carter</signed>
Dr. Frederick F. Russell, Director,<lb/>
International Health Division,<lb/>
The Rockefeller Foundation,<lb/>
61 Broadway, New York, N. Y.<lb/>
<seg>
P. S. Have you seen Sir Arthur Newsholme's book, &ldquo;The Story of Modern<lb/>
Preventive Medecine?&rdquo; Its just out (1929). He very kindly sent me a<lb/>
complimentary copy, as did Dr. Hoff<del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>man</add>, of the Prudential his book on<lb/>
&ldquo;Malaria Problems,&rdquo; dedicated to Father, Gorgas et. al. However, I think<lb/>
I told you of this latter one. Haven't had time to read either of them,<lb/>
nor will I until I finish the work on the book.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
