<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0330009">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Henry S. Wellcome, May 1, 1930</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0330009</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1930-05-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Wellcome, Henry S.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Peru</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1930-05-01">May 1, 1930</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0330009</idno>
<title>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Henry S. Wellcome, May 1, 1930</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Carter tries to determine what artifacts and materials about Henry Rose Carter would be appropriate for the Historical Medical Museum.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1930-05-01">
<head>Letter from Laura Armistead Carter to Henry S. Wellcome, May 1, 1930</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0330009"/>
<opener>
Biographic.<lb/>
<unclear>Carter</unclear><lb/>
Wellcome, Dr. Henry S.<lb/>
<dateline>
The Westmoreland,<lb/>
2122 California St., N. W.<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<date value="1930-05-01">May 1, 1930.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Doctor Wellcome:</salute>
</opener>
<p>This is being typed in order to spare so busy a man as yourself<lb/>
the trouble of &ldquo;decoding&rdquo; the &ldquo;Carter chirography.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I have just return<add>ed</add> from Baltimore and shall probably have to go<lb/>
back again next Monday. During my last stay there I tried to see the<lb/>
photographer, who took the picture you spoke of having enlarged for<lb/>
your Historical Medical Museum, but she was away. I shall try again next<lb/>
week, unless (if you can spare the time for it) you could look over some<lb/>
other pictures of Father, which I got out of storage in Baltimore, among<lb/>
them an excellent one taken about the time he published his first article<lb/>
on the extrinsic incubation of yellow fever. This, as you know, is cited<lb/>
by Walter Reed as one of the three factors determining the direction of<lb/>
the experiments of his Board; cf. his Preliminary Note...1901. It would<lb/>
depend then upon whether you prefer your enlarged picture of Father as<lb/>
he appeared at this time, or the later one as he looked during and after<lb/>
his War wor<del>m</del><add>k</add>, the yellow fever control work in Peru and as the author of<lb/>
his History of Yellow Fever. Naturally, I shall consider it a privelege<lb/>
to arrange for you to have copies of any and all pictures of Father that<lb/>
you wish, or of anything else which I can procure for you.</p>
<p>I should like to have a somewhat more definite idea of just what<lb/>
kind of material you would like, concerning Father for your Museum. Un-<lb/>
fortunately, moving about as we had to do, on account of Father's work, it<lb/>
was practically impossible to preserve many tangible things relating to his<lb/>
life and work. Much then, that, even as a child, I felt should be kept,<lb/>
was promptly eliminated by Father himself in the intersts of efficiency<lb/>
and &ldquo;travelling light.&rdquo; The same feeling that appears in your <hi>delightful</hi><lb/>
anecdote of &ldquo;K. of K.&rdquo;...that &ldquo;mobile troops&rdquo;...should be mobile! As you<lb/>
truly said, Father's interests were &ldquo;world wide,&rdquo; but my indices therefor<lb/>
are mainly more in the nature of data for a biography than for a museum,.<lb/>
i. e. the contents of the trunks and boxes in storage, which I have just<lb/>
been assorting, ranged from note books on yellow fever and malaria, maps,<lb/>
some MS etc. to Greek classics, books on plants and flowers, blocks of<lb/>
native woods, books and notes on mathematics (he got a scholarship for<lb/>
work in the fourth dimension) chemistry, psychiatry, many books on history,<lb/>
exploration, anthropology, poetry and, of course, a preponderance of lit-<lb/>
erature on yellow fever and malaria. I also came across some of the old<lb/>
tin dippers, with which he did his personal dipping in his malarial surveys.<lb/>
His saying: &ldquo;<del>N</del>Never believe what a man tells you about malaria unless he has<lb/>
a dipper in his hand,&rdquo; illustrating his conviction that malarial control could<lb/>
<hi>not</hi> be handled from an office.</p>
<p>Would you have any use for anything in the nature of:</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) reprints</item>
<item><unclear>(</unclear>(b) autobiographic sketch, written about 1912 (MS destroyed)</item>
<item>(c) biographic sketches by Welch: Frost: Gorgas etc. some<lb/>
published, some unpublished. (No MS).</item>
<item>(d) bibliography.</item>
<item>(e) early photographs</item>
<item>(f) snap shots taken from time of occupation of Cuba <add>up</add> to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fc0330010"/>
tp<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
and including <add>his</add> malaria control work in extra cantonment areas during<lb/>
World War.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>As for his diplomas, honorary degrees etc. the chest in which I<lb/>
tried to keep most of them is missing from storage. I found a few<lb/>
scattered ones in trunks and book boxes.</p>
<p>I do hope that there may be a chance of my having the very real<lb/>
happiness of seeing you again. Your all-too-brief visit last week<lb/>
brought back to me, not the <hi>remembrance</hi>, but the <hi>actuality</hi> of far<lb/>
horizons, high advanture and noble achievement. Surely such moments<lb/>
as I owe to you will remain a permanent asset! Equally truly I am ex-<lb/>
tremely anxious to hear more...much more!...especially about your yellow<lb/>
fever experiments and about your Museum, which I note that you planned,<lb/>
as Father did his History of Yellow Fever, beginning &ldquo;with what you know<lb/>
perfectly in your own time and so gradually&rdquo; going &ldquo;back to the times of<lb/>
less knowledge. Also, I must learn the ultimate fate of the Indians, of<lb/>
Metlakahtla!</p>
<p>With all manner of good wishes, I remain,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Most truly yours,</salute>
<signed>(Signed) Laura Armistead Carter.</signed>
<seg>
P. S. I have not forgotten my promise to give you the MS (which I am<lb/>
sure I have) of Father's appreciation of Gorgas, written just after the<lb/>
death of the latter.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
