<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0413014">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Typed manuscript: Early Life of Dr. H. R. Carter U.S.P.H. Service from Birth to Entrance U.S. Marine Hospital Service, by [T. H. D. Griffitts], [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Griffitts, T. H. D.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0413014</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">[s.n.], Isaac</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Robert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kemper, Charles</name>
<name type="person">Vest, Charles</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Eugenia Hook</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Mary Clayborne</name>
<name type="person">Redd, H. Carter</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Clifton Plantation (Caroline County, Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Amherst County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">North River Plantation (Hanover County, Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Maryland, College Park</name>
<name type="place">Boston (Mass.)</name>
<name type="place">Cairo (Ill.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Aspen Hill Academy (Louisa County, Va.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00">[n.d.]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0413014</idno>
<title>Typed manuscript: Early Life of Dr. H. R. Carter U.S.P.H. Service from Birth to Entrance U.S. Marine Hospital Service, by [T. H. D. Griffitts], [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This manuscript details stories of the young Henry Rose Carter including his mathematic ability, his reaction to the Civil War, and his education.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Typed manuscript: Early Life of Dr. H. R. Carter U.S.P.H. Service from Birth to Entrance U.S. Marine Hospital Service, by [T. H. D. Griffitts], [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0413014"/>
<p><hi>Return to</hi> Mary C. Carter<lb/>
H. Carter Redd's home <hi>Ashland, Va</hi></p>
<p><hi>Early life of Dr. H. R. Carter U.S.P.H. Service</hi>.<lb/>
from birth to entrance &ldquo;<hi>U.S. Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service</hi>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The &ldquo;<hi>U.S. Marine Hospital Service</hi>&rdquo; had its name<lb/>
changed <add>by Congress</add> to &ldquo;<hi>U.S. Public Health Service&rdquo;. 1902</hi>.</p>
<p>The &lsquo;<hi>Marine Hospital Service</hi>&rsquo;, was established by Congress<lb/>
in <hi>1798</hi> to care for sick or disabled seamen.<lb/>
The M. H. Service was at first supported by a small<lb/>
monthly tax on American Seamen. This Tax was<lb/>
collected by the Customs Service of the Treasury Depart.<lb/>
The present U.S.P.H. Service is still under the<lb/>
jurisdiction of the Treasury Department.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fc0413015"/>
<p>DATES</p>
<p>
<table rows="11" cols="2">
<row><cell>Henry Rose Carter was born</cell><cell>August 25, 1851</cell></row>
<row><cell>Was 10 years old when Civil War broke</cell><cell>1861</cell></row>
<row><cell>Was 14 years old when war ended</cell><cell>1865</cell></row>
<row><cell>Attended Aspin Hill Academy</cell><cell>1868</cell></row>
<row><cell>Taught in boys' school</cell><cell>1869</cell></row>
<row><cell>Graduated as Civil Engineer (University of Virginia)</cell><cell>1873</cell></row>
<row><cell>Studied Medicine (University of Maryland) graduating</cell><cell>1878</cell></row>
<row><cell>*Entered United States Marine Service</cell><cell>1879</cell></row>
<row><cell>Sent to Ship Island Quarantine</cell><cell>1888</cell></row>
<row><cell>Sent to Cuba,</cell><cell>January, 1899</cell></row>
<row><cell>Sent to Panama,<lb/>
(Was in Panama over 5 years)</cell><cell>December, 1904</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>*Sent to Boston, to Cairo, Illinois, to Memphis, to New Orleans,<lb/>
to San Francisco, to New Orleans again, to Ship Island <add>(His first Quarantine Station)</add></p>
<pb n="3" id="fc0413016"/>
<p>1.</p>
<p>First Fourteen Years</p>
<p>(Part First)</p>
<p>Henry Rose Carter was born on Clifton Plantation, Caroline<lb/>
County, Virginia, August 25, 1851. He manifested an interest in Math-<lb/>
ematics quite early in life. Before his second birthday, he used to<lb/>
amuse himself, standing by a chair, by playing with grains of corn,<lb/>
arranging these in little piles on the seat of the chair. It was ob-<lb/>
served by his Mother, that each pile received exactly the same number<lb/>
of grains, sometimes three grains to each pile, sometimes a different<lb/>
number, but always an equal number in each pile.</p>
<p>When five years old he formed a close friendship with an old<lb/>
negro, who was noted for ability to solve mathematical problems in his<lb/>
head. The two strove to outdo each other in such matters.</p>
<p>Uncle Isaac once produced a bottle, filled with beans of various<lb/>
sizes, and proposed a test of wits. Each should guess the number of beans<lb/>
in the bottle, and the one whose guess proved nearest, should be held<lb/>
the wiser. The boy procured a similar bottle, measured its capacity in<lb/>
cups and counted beans contained in cup, and made a calculation. Uncle<lb/>
Isaac's guess proved the better; it was absolutely accurate.</p>
<p>The child was quite downcast. He puzzled over the matter for<lb/>
some time, then begged the old man to explain the method<unclear>.</unclear> he had used to<lb/>
arrive at the exact number.</p>
<p>The old man replied with a chuckle: &ldquo;Well, little marster,<lb/>
I counted them beans when I put 'em in the bottle.&rdquo;</p>
<p><hi>Insert</hi></p>
<p>He had a real gift for Mathematics. The Principal of Aspin<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fc0413017"/>
2.<lb/>
Hill Academy, where he studied one session, recognized this gift, and<lb/>
placed him in a class alone.</p>
<p>His work at the University of Virginia under Professor Beck<lb/>
was exceptionally fine. When he graduated in Civil Engineering, the<lb/>
entire student body burst into applause as he went up (on crutches) to<lb/>
receive his Degree. His lameness was due to an accident in the preced-<lb/>
ing vacation. Doctors pronounced the lameness incurable, and he was<lb/>
obliged to give up the career of Engineer. He turned to Medicine.<lb/>
Later he recovered entirely the use of his crippled knee. The knowledge<lb/>
acquired was not wasted. It proved to be of great value on many occasions.</p>
<p>At one time he was able to straighten out a mathematical for-<lb/>
mula for Sir Ronald Ross. The great English doctor was trying in vain<lb/>
to work out a formula in connection with his malarial work. Sir Ronald<lb/>
was convinced that it could be done, but his calculations were not<lb/>
working out properly. He was much pleased to have the problem solved,<lb/>
and expressed himself profoundly grateful.</p>
<p>Doctor Carter was a quick student, fond of reading, and poss-<lb/>
essed of a remarkably accurate memory.</p>
<p><hi>End of Insert</hi></p>
<p>From early childhood Doctor Carter was handicapped by ill<lb/>
health, but his energy and his interest in doing things and getting<lb/>
them done made him a leader among the boys of the Plantation, white<lb/>
and black.</p>
<p>When the Civil War broke, it was he, who proposed and<lb/>
carried out the building of a trap to catch Yankees. At that time<lb/>
the family were refugeeing among the Blue Ridge Mountains in Amherst<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fc0413018"/>
3.<lb/>
County, Virginia, and the expectation was that the enemy would come,<lb/>
if they came, by a gap, over a small mountain nearby.</p>
<p>The boys built the trap in secret, in a growth of young<lb/>
pines. It did not catch a Yankee, but it did catch and kill a large<lb/>
pig, belonging to Doctor Carter's Uncle.</p>
<p>The boys were dismayed at this, but Henry promptly pro-<lb/>
posed dragging the dead pig to a nearby river (swollen with rain) and<lb/>
throwing it in.</p>
<p>For a long time the fate of the pig was a mystery.</p>
<p>He also drew up a code of rules, which the boys agreed to abide<lb/>
by. One rule was that the last boy coming through a gate, must shut it.</p>
<p>On one occasion the last boy through, refused to close the<lb/>
gate. Henry instantly siezed Bob and called on the other boys to assist.<lb/>
With some holding his hands, and others his feet, the reluctant Bob<lb/>
was swung against the gate, until it was battered shut. Thus was the<lb/>
law enforced.</p>
<p>(Part Second)</p>
<p>From close of Civil War to United States Marine Hospital Service</p>
<p>The Summer after Lee's surrender, the Carter family returned<lb/>
to their home in Hanover County, Virginia. The move from &ldquo;Clifton&rdquo;<lb/>
to &ldquo;North River Plantation&rdquo; was made during Henry's infancy.</p>
<p>Both armies had visited &ldquo;North River&rdquo;, both had camped<lb/>
there, and repairs of every kind were needed. There was plenty of<lb/>
work for Henry and his three brothers. (The oldest, nineteen years<lb/>
of age, had just been released from prison, &ldquo;Point Lookout.&rdquo;)</p>
<pb n="6" id="fc0413019"/>
<p>4.</p>
<p>Before, and during the War, the three younger boys had re-<lb/>
ceived instruction from governesses. Now they must learn what they<lb/>
could at home, with help from the oldest brother and sister.</p>
<p>Henry worked zealously on the plantation, and studied<lb/>
mostly by himself, doing this in the early morning hours, before the<lb/>
day's work began. He used to rise at 5 A. M. on Winter mornings,<lb/>
first kindle a fire in his Mother's chamber, then go to the stables<lb/>
to feed the team, after that he would return to the now warm chamber<lb/>
to study by light of a kerosene lamp until breakfast. The rest of<lb/>
his day was usually spent in manual labor.</p>
<p>The boys trapped rabbits and partridges, hunted 'coons<lb/>
and 'possums by night, and sometimes (not often) went fishing in<lb/>
the North Anna River. This river bounded the plantation on the<lb/>
North.</p>
<p>When housebound by falling weather, Henry used to mend the<lb/>
family's shoes, and repair the old harness. This he did in the<lb/>
family living room, to the displeasure of his older sister, who often<lb/>
cleared away his scraps of leather and his tools, when he would leave<lb/>
the room for some reason.</p>
<p>He would say: &ldquo;I left everything right in the middle of the<lb/>
floor, where anybody could find them again, and here Nannie has gone<lb/>
and hidden everything somewhere!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He was never idle; always busy doing something or learning<lb/>
something, except when interrupted by severe migraine headaches. He<lb/>
suffered from these until late in life.</p>
<p>Once he was incapacitated for months by an attack of malaria,<lb/>
which left him in such a weakened condition, as to make it impossible<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fc0413020"/>
5.<lb/>
for him to engage in farm work for months. When convalescing he asked<lb/>
his two little sisters to pick up apples in the big orchard and bring<lb/>
them to him, to be peeled and dried in the sun, saying: &ldquo;If I cannot<lb/>
do a man's work, I'll try to do a woman's.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In those days women used to dry fruit for use in Winter.<lb/>
The North River family had an abundance of dried apples that year.</p>
<p>Education</p>
<p>At seventeen years of age Henry was sent to Aspin Hill<lb/>
Academy, Louisa County, Virginia. He was there one session.</p>
<p>The Principal of this school (Mr. Charles Kemper) recog-<lb/>
nized Henry's gift for Mathematics, and his capacity for study. He<lb/>
placed Henry in a class to himself, allowing him to decide the<lb/>
length of his lessons, and to choose his own time for studying them.</p>
<p>Henry taught in an Academy, Nelson County, Virginia, in<lb/>
session 1869-71.</p>
<p>He attended the University of Virginia, graduating in<lb/>
Civil Engineering, 1873. (See Insert, Page 2).</p>
<p>He studied Medicine at the University of Maryland, graduating<lb/>
in 1878 (27 years old). While studying medicine, he taught Mathematics<lb/>
in a boys' school in Baltimore, (Mr. Martin's School).</p>
<p>After graduating, he began practise of Medicine with another<lb/>
young Doctor (Charles Vest, graduate of same class). At this time he<lb/>
was often in real want. For many weeks he could only afford to eat<lb/>
three meals in two days, one meal on one day and two meals the next.</p>
<pb n="8" id="fc0413021"/>
<p>6.</p>
<p>He had an appointment as Intern in the hospital (University<lb/>
of Maryland) and in Spring 1879 a patient (drug-addict) called Doctor<lb/>
Carter's attention to <del>an advertisement</del><add>a paragraph</add> in a paper, announcing that<lb/>
examinations for the United States Marine Hospital Service would be<lb/>
held in Washington the following day. Doctor Carter went to Wash-<lb/>
ington, passed the examination, and entered the &ldquo;Marine Hospital<lb/>
Service&rdquo;, May 5, 1879. He was sent to Boston, to Cairo, Illinois,<lb/>
to Memphis, to New Orleans, to San Francisco, to New Orleans again,<lb/>
to Ship Island Quarantine Station, 1888.</p>
<p>Note: In Cairo, Illinois, Doctor Carter met Miss Laura Hook of<lb/>
St. Louis, Mo. Miss Hook was teaching in one of the Cairo public<lb/>
schools. They were married, September 29, 1880.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
