<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0410002">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: Anti-Malarial Measures for Farm Houses and Plantations, by [Henry Rose Carter], [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Henry Rose</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0410002</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">Darling, Samuel Taylor</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>18 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00">[n.d.]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0410002</idno>
<title>Report: Anti-Malarial Measures for Farm Houses and Plantations, by [Henry Rose Carter], [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[Carter] outlines anti-malarial measures for farmhouses and plantations.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Report: Anti-Malarial Measures for Farm Houses and Plantations, by [Henry Rose Carter], [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fC0410002"/>
<p>Anti-Malarial Measures for Farm Houses and Plantations.</p>
<p>Malaria is essentially a rural disease. It is found in towns<lb/>
only as they approach rural conditions--i.e. in small towns and<lb/>
in the suburbs of large cities--not in the bodies of large cities.<lb/>
It is for this reason that the consideration of anti-malarial meas-<lb/>
ures specially applicable for farm houses and plantations may be<lb/>
of interest.</p>
<p>As is known, the direct cause of malarial fever is the presence<lb/>
af an animal parasite in the blood of the man developing it. This<lb/>
parasite is, in nature, introduced into the blood (only) by<del>n</del> the<lb/>
bite of a certain kind of mosquito, rendered infective by biting a<lb/>
man himself infected with malarial parasites and only thus introduced.</p>
<p>There are certain conditions necessary for infection. Let us<lb/>
note them, as they will show us what to guard against. To become<lb/>
infected with malarial fever it is necessary to</p>
<p>(1) To be bitten by a certain kind of mosquito.</p>
<p>Only mosquitoes of the genus Anophelina--and not all species<lb/>
of that genus--are concerned in the conveyance of malaria. To guard<lb/>
against all mosquitoes is no wiser than to defend one's chickens<lb/>
from all birds because hawks do prey on them.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fC0410003"/>
<p>( 2 )</p>
<p>(2) This mosquito to have been infected by previously biting<lb/>
some man infected with the malarial parasite.</p>
<p>It is not true, as one often hears, that mosquitoes of swamps<lb/>
who have had no access to men can convey malaria. The early English<lb/>
expeditions direct to America as to the Orinoco and Darien rarely<lb/>
recorded fever among them until after meeting Spaniards. Those that<lb/>
came by the Slave Coast of Africa suffered severely.</p>
<p>(3) That some time, usually not less than eight to ten days,<lb/>
must elapse between the infection of the mosquito and the biting<lb/>
which infects the other man.</p>
<p>This is the time for the completion of the sexual cycle of the<lb/>
parasite, which occurs in the body of the mosquito, and for the<lb/>
product of this union--the Sporozoites--to reach her salivary glands.<lb/>
Until this--the extrinsic incubation of malaria--is accomplished<lb/>
the mosquito is not infective.</p>
<p>No description of this mosquito will be given except to say</p>
<p>(1) That in the female, the sex that bites, the palpi--two<lb/>
little projections on either side of the probocis--are nearly as<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fC0410004"/>
( 3 )<lb/>
long as the probocis, while in the other varieties the palpi are<lb/>
less than half as long. The males of other species, and anapholes<lb/>
as well, have palpi as long as the proboscis, but in the males they<lb/>
are covered with long hairs and look like plumes. Males of any va-<lb/>
riety are seldom seen except near the hatching place and are very<lb/>
short lived.</p>
<p>(2) That when resting after a meal of blood the anapholes has<lb/>
her fore legs, proboscis, body and hind legs all in one line, or<lb/>
nearly so, usually at a considerable angle--45&deg; to 90&deg;--with the wall<lb/>
while other mosquitoes are &ldquo;humped up,&rdquo; both fore and hind legs being<lb/>
bent on the body toward each other. It is a slight, graceful mosquito.</p>
<p>Nor shall I go into its life history save only to say</p>
<p>(1) That the female lays her eggs in the shade of grass or<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fC0410005"/>
( 4 )<lb/>
bushes on the surface of clear water in swamps, shallow pools, the<lb/>
edges of little streams, etc. She does not like deep water and the<lb/>
larvae are not found where fish can get at them. The breed espec-<lb/>
ially in water containing green algae, &ldquo;frog-broth&rdquo;, and will even<lb/>
breed in rain barrels containing this growth. Otherwise they will<lb/>
not. It is a swamp--not a house--mosquito.</p>
<p>(2) That it is from 15 to 22 days, or longer, depending on<lb/>
the temperature, from the time the egg is laid to the birth of the<lb/>
adult mosquito.</p>
<p>(3) That the forms between the egg and the mosquito-- larva<lb/>
and pupa--live in water, but breathe air from the atmosphere and<lb/>
must come to the surface every few minutes to get it.</p>
<p>(4) That they are attracted by light for some distance and<lb/>
are conveyed by light winds. How far they travel has not been deter-<lb/>
mined. One species--the white footed anopheles in Panama was found<lb/>
in large numbers nearly a mile from its breeding place. It was<lb/>
found, however, in a village brilliantly lighted by electricity and<lb/>
the conditions were otherwise favorable for conveyance. Generally<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fC0410006"/>
( 5 )<lb/>
speaking, 1&sol;4 to 1&sol;2 of a mile--or even less--would be the usual<lb/>
limit of her flight to such lights as one has at a farm house. Much<lb/>
depends on the direction and character of the winds during the mos-<lb/>
quito season.</p>
<p>(5) That she flies and feeds in the U. S. almost exclusively<lb/>
in the evening and at night. The bite is little painful--one used to<lb/>
the pestiferous day mosquito will not notice it--and the insect is<lb/>
so shy that she rarely bites a moving--i.e. a waking-person-and<lb/>
hence ana<del>h</del><add>p</add>heles frequently exist where there are no complaints of<lb/>
mosquitoes.</p>
<p>(6) That she comes into the house at night, attracted by light<lb/>
(and possibly smell) feeds and, if not exceedingly full, leaves it<lb/>
as soon as it becomes light. If she can not she hides in some dark<lb/>
place during the day, so that not finding anopheles in the day time<lb/>
in a room with open windows is no proof that they were not present<lb/>
at night.</p>
<p>I lay some stress on (5) and (6) because I have known good men<lb/>
puzzled to account for a malarial outbreak where they could find<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fc0410007"/>
( 6 )<lb/>
no evidence of anopheles.</p>
<p>Since malaria is contracted only from the bite of a certain<lb/>
kind of mosquito rendered infective by having fed on a man himself<lb/>
infected with malaria, if we can keep, the infective insect from the<lb/>
well man or the man harboring the malarial parasite in his blood<lb/>
from infecting the insect there will be no spread of malaria. Either<lb/>
method perfectly carried out would extinguish the disease. We will<lb/>
consider the second method first.</p>
<p>I</p>
<p>Measures Involving the Control of the Human Host.</p>
<p>The writer is on record as regarding methods to prevent the<lb/>
access of mosquitoes to men infected with malaria as in practice<lb/>
entirely inefficient for the elimination, or even control, of malaria<lb/>
in villages or thickly settled communities where it is prevalent, as<lb/>
in some parts of the tropics. The reason is the large number of<lb/>
&ldquo;carriers&rdquo;, people who carry malarial parasites in their blood and<lb/>
are infective to mosquitoes with no signs of illness whatever. There<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fc0410008"/>
( 7 )<lb/>
are obviously no practicable means of isolating all such men from<lb/>
mosquitoes save by measures applicable for the whole community--<lb/>
which is impossible.</p>
<p>But for families in farm houses and in plantation houses not<lb/>
too close to colored quarters much may be done on this line. Espec-<lb/>
ially is this true of places in districts not very malarious, or<lb/>
at least, with a long period--winter and spring--during which mala-<lb/>
ria is not contracted so that it is reasonable to expect during some<lb/>
part of the year that none of the household are carriers.</p>
<p>(a) In such cases, then, a case of malarial fever should be<lb/>
treated--as it is--like a communicable disease. No access to anoph-<lb/>
eles mosquitoes should be allowed. It should be kept in a screened<lb/>
room and--not &ldquo;or&rdquo;--under a mosquito bar, especially at night.</p>
<p>(b) For sanitary reasons quinine should be freely administered<lb/>
and in sufficient doses, with such other medication as is necessary,<lb/>
to <hi>cure</hi> the case, to <hi>rid</hi> him of his parasites--not simply to reduce<lb/>
their number--and get him on his feet. Remember that a few--say two--<lb/>
doses of quinine will practically free the blood vessels of the skin<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="fC0410009"/>
( 8 )<lb/>
of malarial parasites and render the man temporarily incapable of<lb/>
infecting the mosquito. The prompt use of quinine then, will greatly<lb/>
lessen the chance of infecting the mosquitoes which, in spite of<lb/>
our efforts do have access to our patient.</p>
<p>Visitors convalescent of malarial fever or from badly infected<lb/>
neighborhoods are so apt to be carriers that the above anti-malarial<lb/>
measures are indicated for them also as far as they can be applied.<lb/>
Parasites in the blood of a carrier can always be demonstrated by<lb/>
blood examination. Negative findings from Ross' thick film may be<lb/>
regarded as conclusively negative.</p>
<p>(c) Killing the mosquitoes which one finds in the sick room<lb/>
each morning, with a fly-flap or small pan of coal oil (for the<lb/>
ceiling) may be made an efficient anti-malarial measure. Anopheles<lb/>
enter the room in the evening or night when the light burns, feeds<lb/>
and remains quiet until morning; then, unless she can quickly get<lb/>
out, and the windows are frequently shut toward morning, or if very<lb/>
full of blood hides herself in dark corners, where she can be easily<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="fC0410010"/>
( 9 )<lb/>
killed. She is frequently found in the early morning--before sun-<lb/>
rise--on the glass of the window trying to get out. This method<lb/>
sounds like child's play, and so the writer considered it, but as<lb/>
done by Le Prince's Inspectors it was far otherwise. Some unscreened<lb/>
, and partially screened, barracks were thus treated in the Canal<lb/>
Zone and although a large number of anopheles were killed--at times<lb/>
as many as 60 or 80 in a single house in one morning--but little<lb/>
malaria developed among some hundreds of men occupying them.<lb/>
Darling's examination of a large number of mosquitoes showed none<lb/>
--I speak from memory--infective. It takes, in Panama, 11 to 12<lb/>
days after biting before a mosquito of the kind examined can convey<lb/>
malaria--and all, or nearly all, that entered these barracks then,<lb/>
either failed to return or were killed before that time had elapsed.</p>
<p>These measures are of little value in a community unless one<lb/>
can be assured that it is free from carriers to start with. It is, I<lb/>
think, of none in houses close to the quarters of negroes, as is fre-<lb/>
quently the case in Southern plantations; so many negroes, espec-<lb/>
ially children, are carriers.</p>
<pb n="10" id="fc0410011"/>
<p>( 10 )</p>
<p>(d) The use of quinine by well people in small doses to pre-<lb/>
vent the development of malaria is not admitted to be efficient<lb/>
universally by sanitarians (and some observations by Medical Offi-<lb/>
cers of the U. S. Navy wouls show that it is certainly not so<lb/>
always). Yet the general consensus of opinion is in its favor and<lb/>
comparative experiments by the Japanese in Formosa and the Germans<lb/>
in East Africa would show it decidedly valuable. There are two<lb/>
methods of giving it, one from three to five grains a day and one<lb/>
a single dose of ten or even fifteen grains once per week. The<lb/>
latter seems to give the best results--certainly in proportion to<lb/>
the quinine taken. The former was mainly the method used on the<lb/>
Canal Zone. It gave, I think, no discomfort to those using it, as<lb/>
a great many of the higher officials and their families did for<lb/>
long periods from '04 to '06 when malaria was prevalent. This method,<lb/>
in the opinion of the writer, is mainly of use to tide over a<lb/>
specially bad season. He is sure it prevents sickness; it may<lb/>
prevent infection.</p>
<p>(e) Personal hygiene, especially the avoidance of getting<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="fc0410012"/>
( 11 )<lb/>
chilled is of value in preventing the <hi>development</hi> of malarial fever<lb/>
but apparently does not prevent becoming infected by it.</p>
<p>II</p>
<p>Measures Involving the Control of the Insect Host.</p>
<p>The measures found efficient for villages, etc., are, of course,<lb/>
efficient for farm houses, but some--and these among the most ef<lb/>
ficient in the former--are not practicable for farm houses on account<lb/>
of the expense involved. Fortunately farm houses are usually better<lb/>
situated with regard to elevation, wind and proximity to marshes<lb/>
than are villages.</p>
<p>It may be taken as a principle in bimomics that when an animal<lb/>
is exceedingly prolific, like rats, mosquitoes, flies, etc., that<lb/>
control of their numbers, far less their extermination, is not pos-<lb/>
sible by killing the individuals. One must destroy their breeding<lb/>
places, their shelters or their food supply. We attempt the first<lb/>
with mosquitoes. These methods under this head are briefly</p>
<p>(1) To prevent breeding of anopheles by destruction of their<lb/>
breeding places. And in addition</p>
<pb n="12" id="fC0410013"/>
<p>( 12 )</p>
<p>(2) To kill their larvae in such breeding places as we fail<lb/>
to destroy.</p>
<p>(3) To prevent the access to the men we would protect of such<lb/>
anopheles as exist in spite of the above attempts to destroy them.</p>
<p>Obviously any one of these methods <hi>perfectly</hi> carried out would<lb/>
be sufficient. Each one is intended to supplement the imperfect<lb/>
success of the others. But the problem is so difficult that imper-<lb/>
fect success with any one--or may be with all--is the most that can<lb/>
be hoped for on most farms and plantations in malarial regions.</p>
<p>(1) To destroy the breeding places, then, one drains all pools,<lb/>
marshes and wet lands near the house and cleans up the banks of the<lb/>
streams.</p>
<p>If this drainage be done by open ditches it is likely enough<lb/>
that they will themselves breed anopheles, although in less-- gen-<lb/>
erally far less--number than formerly. Tile or box or &ldquo;blind&rdquo; drain-<lb/>
age generally is not open to this objection. If the pools and small<lb/>
streams contain fish, cleaning up of their edges so that the fish<lb/>
can get to the larvae will be sufficient.</p>
<pb n="13" id="fc0410014"/>
<p>( 13 )</p>
<p>(2) Ponds which can not be drained are best treated by coal oil.<lb/>
This forms a film on the surface through which the larvae can not<lb/>
pass to get air and without air they die. It takes a very small<lb/>
amount. The oiling in the U. S. Heeds to be done only about once<lb/>
in two weeks, but it is safer to do so every week as one is less apt<lb/>
to forget it. It is of little use in ponds of large surface or with<lb/>
grass growing in them and, in general, is far less dependable than<lb/>
drainage.<add>&cross;</add> <del>Foot note</del><add>Foot note here</add></p>
<p>These last two measures, which are the sheet anchors in anti-<lb/>
malarial work for communities, are less applicable for farms on<lb/>
account of the expense. The area to be freed from breeding places,<lb/>
however, is less--one-half to one-sixteenth less--for the area varies<lb/>
as the square of the distance of flight. In estimating what area<lb/>
is dangerous naturally the seasonal prevailing winds must be taken<lb/>
into consideration as much as, or more than, the distance.<add>&cross; Foot note here</add></p>
<p>(3) To prevent the access of anopheles to man there are three<lb/>
things of service</p>
<p>(a) To cut down the brush and tall weeds about the house.</p>
<p><add>&cross;</add>Foot note for page 17</p>
<p>The use of agents which act by poisoning the larvae, as Pinotas<lb/>
oil, is not taken up. There is a wide field for their use in village<lb/>
and community sanitation, but the need of special material and methods<lb/>
render them, it is thought, little applicable to purely rural work.</p>
<pb n="14" id="fC0410015"/>
<p>( 14 )</p>
<p>These harbor mosquitoes--they do not breed them--and keep a supply<lb/>
close to the house. Porch vines and mostbshrubbery also act in this<lb/>
way. Anopheles can not live long in full sunlight. A treeless,<lb/>
shrubless yard open to the sun and wind--shade being given by gal-<lb/>
leries and awnings--is the most sanitary so far as malaria is con-<lb/>
cerned, but one may pay a higher price in comfort and beauty than<lb/>
the risk is worth. Trees, high branched, furnish little shelter to<lb/>
mosquitoes unless very dense. Aromatic trees and shrubs are usually<lb/>
avoided by them.</p>
<p>(b) Planting a screen of trees some distance from the house<lb/>
between the mosquito breeding place and the house. This probably<lb/>
serves to hide the lights of the house from the marsh or stops the<lb/>
mosquitoes brought by the breeze from it--or both.</p>
<p>(c) Screening and mosquito bars. (a( and (b) are of some value,<lb/>
but screening is our reliance to keep out mosquitoes. Properly ap-<lb/>
plied it will do it. Screening is many fold better then mosquito<lb/>
bars which seldom protect for long if anopheles be abundant. Screened<lb/>
houses, however, are <hi>safe</hi> to intelligent and careful people, provided<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="fC0410016"/>
( 15 )<lb/>
they are well screened. It is, however, quite an art to do this.<lb/>
(The writer was at one time chairman of a board on screening for the<lb/>
I.C.C. and will give a few of their findings applicable to farm<lb/>
houses, although this paper is already too long.)</p>
<p>No. 16 mesh wire is the best for screens. A very few anopheles<lb/>
may pass No. 14, but the mesh is large enought to be painted which<lb/>
will double its time of lasting and hence halve its cost and after<lb/>
one painting no more will pass. If one screens against stegomyia<del>66</del><add>--</add><lb/>
two sizes smaller should be used. The writer has used the ordinary<lb/>
bobinet of mosquito bars, some times single, sometimes double. It<lb/>
is simply tacked over the<del>m</del> entire window opening on the outside. It<lb/>
made a perfect screen and was cheap. It lasted one season.</p>
<p>As few entrances are possible to the screened part of the house<lb/>
should be allowed. It is nearly always possible to cut them down to<lb/>
two. The screens in the windows should, if possible, be fixed so<lb/>
that they can not be opened--especially in the servant's part of<lb/>
the house. Unless they exclude mosquitoes, no matter how the window<lb/>
is opened, i.e. cover the whole window, constant pains must be taken<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="fc0410017"/>
( 16 )<lb/>
to have the screens arranged during the evening and night so as to <lb/>
exclude them.</p>
<p>Screen doors must open outward and the light inside should be<lb/>
arranged so as not to fall on the door when shut--else mosquitoes<lb/>
will gather on it and come in when opened. It should, of course,<lb/>
have a strong spring to close it. It is far better to screen<lb/>
the porch if it runs around a good part of the house, than to screen<lb/>
the doors and windows on that side. It is also more expensive. It<lb/>
will do little good, however, to rely on a screened house and sit,<lb/>
in the evening on an unscreened porch.</p>
<p>When the door of entrance is at the top of a flight of steps,<lb/>
no landing intervening, it should be so placed that the edge of the<lb/>
door opposite the hinge comes as near the middle of the length of<lb/>
the step as may be. This may be done</p>
<p>(a) By ha<del>b</del><add>v</add>ing folding doors, one best stay fastened.</p>
<p>(b) By moving the whole door to the left and fill in the space<lb/>
to the right by screening.</p>
<p>The reason is that one always goes up about the middle of the<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="fc0410018"/>
( 17 )<lb/>
steps, and, if the door opens from the end of the steps, he after<lb/>
beginning to open the door steps down a couple of steps so as to<lb/>
get out of its way, thus opening the door more widely and holding<lb/>
it open longer than advisable. Intelligent people in a screened<lb/>
house become instinctively careful about doors, opening them at<lb/>
night the least possible and keeping them open as short time as<lb/>
possible. The ideal plan is undoubtedly to have a vestibule with<lb/>
double screen doors and in the evening a fumigation between them<lb/>
as I have seen in many small houses in the lower Indian River, red<lb/>
mangrove chips being the fumigant, but this is too much to hope for<lb/>
at present.</p>
<p>Naturally all screens and screen doors must fit tightly and be<lb/>
heavy enough not to warp. Where they do not fit tight and are im-<lb/>
movable the writer has frequently rendered them mosquito proof by<lb/>
caulking the openings with newspapers. An imperfectly screened house<lb/>
is simply a mosquito <hi>trap</hi>. They come in at small crevices, at night,<lb/>
which they find by the light streaming through and, at daylight, fly<lb/>
directly to the screened windows through which they can not go and<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="fC0410019"/>
( 18 )<lb/>
thus remain in the house; the number so remaining accumulating<lb/>
night after night.</p>
<p>To sum up</p>
<p>For farm houses anti-malarial measures based on the control<lb/>
of both the human and the insect host should be used.</p>
<p>Of the first the isolation of men sick of malarial fever from<lb/>
mosquitoes is the most important.</p>
<p>Of the second, draining mosquito breeding land near the house,<lb/>
especially to windward, is of great value.</p>
<p>Of almost equal value is the screening of the house. This is<lb/>
always possible. Drainage, unfortunately, is not inmmany parts of<lb/>
the country. Until drainage is done screening must be our <unclear>anchor</unclear><lb/>
anchor in preventing malarial fever in farm houses.</p>
<p>The problem of drainage should be taken up both by the indi-<lb/>
vidual farmer and by the community just as plantation and county<lb/>
roads are.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
