<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="C0415023">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Speech on yellow fever, by [Laura Armistead Carter], [November 23, 1931]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Carter, Laura Armistead</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>C0415023</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1931-11-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Noleund, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Nott, Josiah C.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">Veracruz [Mexico]</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1931-11-23">[November 23, 1931]</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C0415023</idno>
<title>Speech on yellow fever, by [Laura Armistead Carter], [November 23, 1931]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The document outlines the method, findings, and conclusions of the inquiry into the early history of yellow fever.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1931-11-23">
<head>Speech on yellow fever, by [Laura Armistead Carter], [November 23, 1931]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fc0415023"/>
<p>1<lb/>
1.&sol;2<lb/>
Mr. President, Members of the</p>
<p>I deeply appreciate the honour of being invited to take part in<lb/>
your program this evening.</p>
<p>Also, though feeling myself in no wise deserving of the very kind<lb/>
introduction of Dr. <add>Noland</add> <unclear>----</unclear>, I am thankful to say that I have something <add>new</add> to<lb/>
present to you that <hi>is</hi> deserving of your consideration and on a subject<lb/>
that cannot fail to be of interest to so representative a <del>groupe</del><add>body</add> of the<lb/>
medical profession in the State which can boast a Nott and a Gorgas!</p>
<p>For the past nine years I have been a small part of a great<lb/>
work--an inquiry into the early history of yellow fever. The method,<lb/>
findings and conclusions of this inquiry I shall now <add>endeavor to</add> briefly outline to you.</p>
<p>See p. <del>2</del><add>1</add>.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fc0415024"/>
<p>p. 1.</p>
<p>It would seem natural in investigating the history of any<lb/>
disease to begin by collecting accounts of its occurrence, beginning with<lb/>
the earliest procurable records, and from them to finally deduce our gen-<lb/>
eral principles--<hi>the conditions under which and only under which, it can<lb/>
occur</hi>: the epidemiology of the disease.</p>
<p>A different, almost a reversed, method was followed in this<lb/>
instance: This because certain principles in the epidemiology of yellow<lb/>
fever are established and definitely known, while the early reports of<lb/>
its occurrence (and non-occurrence) are frequently not only only misleading<lb/>
but erroneous. Therefore by beginning our inquiry with a statement of the<lb/>
finally established principles in the epidemiology of yellow fever (<hi>the con-<lb/>
ditions under which, and only under which, yellow fever can occur</hi>) the truth or<lb/>
error of the historical and archaeological evidence examined can be properly<lb/>
evaluated. For instance:</p>
<p>We learn from epidemiological data that in <del>tropical America</del><lb/>
Mexico and Central America an altitude of somewhat over 4,000 ft has proven<lb/>
&ldquo;non-infectible territory&rdquo; for yellow fever (temperature too low for infes-<lb/>
tation by the insect vector). By this we know that the epidemic among the<lb/>
Aztecs in the <hi>year 1 Rabbit (1454)</hi>, which has been interpreted as showing an<lb/>
epidemic of yellow fever, could not have been this disease. The action of<lb/>
the Nahuatl picture for this year took place on the Mexican plateau, about<lb/>
8,000 ft. above sea-level. There yellow fever is out of the question.</p>
<p><hi>Cocolitzle</hi>. Similarly we can judge concerning what is the most<lb/>
<del>m</del><add>f</add>amous and often-quoted passage cited in evidence of the presence of yellow<lb/>
fever in the New World priot to the Spanish Conquest, the &ldquo;<hi>Cocolitzle</hi>&rdquo; of<lb/>
Herrera. Herrera y Tordesillos, official historiographer to Philip ii of<lb/>
Spain, states that before the coming of the Spaniards, the &ldquo;<hi>tierra caliente</hi>&rdquo;<lb/>
(hot low country) around Vera Cruz was rendered so unhealthy a disease, or<lb/>
dise<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fc0415025"/>
or<lb/>
p.2<lb/>
diseases, called &ldquo;<hi>Cocolistle</hi>&rdquo; that it was periodically depopulated. That,<lb/>
whenever this occurred, Montezuma collected a unit of 8,000 families from<lb/>
a healthy part of his kingdom and repopulated it, giving the new settlers<lb/>
houses and land and rendering them free from tribute for many years.</p>
<p>Now we know, from the epidemiology of this disease.</p>
<p>(a) That yellow fever would not depopulate such a large, thickly<lb/>
settled area as the Spaniards found on landing at Vera Cruz. Were yellow<lb/>
fever endemic there, the inhabitants would contract the disease in infancy<lb/>
(with only a small increase in infant mortality) and (one attack conferring<lb/>
immunity) the adult native population would not be affected by it.</p>
<p>(b) Moreover, one cannot conceive of a more effective way of<lb/>
keeping up yellow fever than that cited as being used by Montezuma to<lb/>
counteract its ill effects--the introduction of large bodies of susceptible<lb/>
(non-immune) people. Such an<del>d</del> introduction would, <del>have</del> inevitably, have always<lb/>
created an epidemic.</p>
<p>There is also considerable historical evidence against the fact<lb/>
that this hot, low country was unhealthy before the arrival of the Spaniards.<lb/>
The epidemiological argument, however, would seem sufficient (conclusive)<lb/>
without it.</p>
<p>******************************</p>
<p>In a similar manner (by the light of the established principles of<lb/>
the epidemiology of <del>the</del> yellow fever) were <del><unclear>tested</unclear></del> (interpreted) <add>(from contemporary records)</add> the details<lb/>
<del>(from contemporary records)</del><lb/>
of losses in military expeditions and colonies, sociological conditions and<lb/>
commercial developement, <del>were analysed for the light</del> early communication<lb/>
between suspected continents etc.</p>
<p>In a like manner (by the light of the established principles of its<lb/>
epidemiology) it was possible to throw light on the presence or absence of<lb/>
yellow fever <add><del>epidemiogoly</del> in these early days</add> <unclear><hi><del>by</del><add>to</add></hi></unclear> interpret<del>ing</del> (from contempory records): the details of losses<lb/>
in military expeditions and colonies, <del>by</del><add>to</add> analyzing social conditions and<lb/>
commercial development, to study the conditions of early communication be-<lb/>
tween suspected continents and <unclear><add>finally</add></unclear> to do what at first sight would seem impossible<lb/>
<hi>Speak authoritatively</hi>) (Give a convincing) history of a disease for that pe-<lb/>
riod before we find a <add><unclear>any</unclear></add> definitely recognizable account of its occurrence.<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fc0415026"/>
occurence.<lb/>
p.3</p>
<p>***************************************************************************</p>
<p>I would here state, parenthetically, that since this inquiry into<lb/>
the early history of yellow fever was, naturally, not confined to the<lb/>
Americas, it seemed inadvi<add>s</add>able to use our venacular form <add>(Stegomyia)</add> for the name of the<lb/>
insect vector <add>(in nature) *</add>. This, because while it is the only species of this sub-<lb/>
genus found in the Americas, there are a number of A&euml;des (Stegomyia) species<lb/>
in the Old World. It was decided then to return to the name given it by<lb/>
<del><unclear>Linnaes himself</unclear></del> Linnaous himself: Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti, this name<lb/>
being definitive everywhere)</p>
<p>***************************************************************************</p>
<p><hi>Place of Origin</hi>.</p>
<p>Naturally, one of the most important questions to be<lb/>
determined in the early history of yellow fever was the question <hi>of its place<lb/>
of origin</hi>. And this was a matter of more than academic interest. The<lb/>
Rockefeller Foundation (in consultation with Gorgas and Father) had already<lb/>
<del><unclear>undertaken[unclear]</unclear></del> decided on (and started) its great under-<lb/>
taking for the elimination of yellow fever from the world and it was felt<lb/>
the place of origin might present difficulties in such a campaign not to be <unclear>f</unclear><lb/>
found in places to which the disease had been carried later: (a) greater<lb/>
difficulty of diagnosis, the natives having the disease more mildly after<lb/>
having been subject to it for many generations: (b) the possibility of other<lb/>
<del><unclear>vectors</unclear></del>, carriers than the known vector, the Aedes (Steg.) aegypti mosquito<lb/>
and (c) even the possibility of a resevoir host (as is the wild game of Africa<lb/>
for <del><unclear>se</unclear></del> sleeping sickness.</p>
<p>*******************************</p>
<p>Now from our established epidemiological data we derive <hi>the pos-<lb/>
tulate that &ldquo;for the naturally continued existence of y. f. in any place<lb/>
there are necessary three factors coexistent at that place (1) the causative</hi><lb/>
organism (2) functionally active A. (Steg.) aegypti mosquitoes (3) men sus-<lb/>
ceptible to the infection, the mosquitoes having access to both of the other<lb/>
two.&rdquo; (Carter)</p>
<p>Now for the continued existence of these three factors certain<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fc0415027"/>
certain<lb/>
p.4<lb/>
conditions are necessary: (a) a minimal temperature sufficiently <del><unclear>warm</unclear></del><lb/>
high for the functional activity of (the <add>aegypti</add> insect vector) and for the development<lb/>
of the causative organism in the mosquito. (b) A sufficient<del><unclear>l</unclear></del>y supply of<lb/>
susceptible people to keep up this disease, of which one attack so soon<lb/>
produces immunity, either by (1) immigration (b) birth rate (another form<lb/>
of immigration) (Dutroulau)? or (c) intercommunication between a number of<lb/>
small units of population, none sufficiently large to keep it up alone, but<lb/>
all together forming a &ldquo;regional focus.&rdquo;</p>
<p>(See p. 4')</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
