<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="F0114001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Comment on Memorial in International Health Board Bulletin, by Wade Hampton Frost, 1926</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Frost, Wade Hampton</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>F0114001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1926-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education">YES</term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Carter, Laura Armistead</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Connor, Michael E.</name>
<name type="person">Hanson, Henry</name>
<name type="person">Thayer, William S.</name>
<name type="person">White, Joseph H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">LePrince, Joseph A.</name>
<name type="person">von Ezdorf, Rudolph H.</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University</name>
<name type="place">Cairo (Ill.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Ship Island (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Brunswick (Ga.)</name>
<name type="place">McHenry (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Orwood (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>34 pp.</extent>
<date value="1926-00-00">1926</date>
<idno rend="suppress">F0114001</idno>
<title>Comment on Memorial in International Health Board Bulletin, by Wade Hampton Frost, 1926</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Frost writes a lengthy document providing details about the life and achievements of Henry Rose Carter. He argues that Carter was the foremost figure in the development of quarantine and the management of epidemics, that his studies of the incubation period of yellow fever was the most notable every made in non-experimental epidemiology, and that his indefatigable studies into yellow fever led to his mastery of the subject as evidenced in his book, The History of Yellow Fever.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="book">
<p></p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1926-00-00">
<head>Comment on Memorial in International Health Board Bulletin, by Wade Hampton Frost, 1926</head>
<pb n="1" id="F0114001"/>
<p>Refers to memorial in<lb/>
Int. Health Board Bulletin<lb/>
<hi>9 Oct., 1925</hi></p>
<p>COMMENT ON MEMORIAL IN INTERNATIONAL HEALTH<lb/>
BOARD BULLETIN.</p>
<p>(1) It is hardly correct to say that Dr.<lb/>
Carter was the &ldquo;originator&rdquo; of the Maritime Quarantine<lb/>
System, as it had long been in existence. A more accur-<lb/>
ate statement is that he was the &ldquo;builder&rdquo;, who, more than<lb/>
any other one person, developed it to a high state of<lb/>
efficiency.</p>
<p>(2) Although Carter's education at the<lb/>
University of Virginia was designed to qualify him for<lb/>
the practice of civil engineering, it was more of a<lb/>
classical education than is implied in such a course<lb/>
nowadays. He had Latin and Greek under Gildesleeve,<lb/>
who was then at Virginia and throughout his life continued<lb/>
to read both with ease and keen enjoyment. He had<lb/>
learned to speak French as a child, and in later years<lb/>
acquired a fluent command of Spanish and Portuguese, with<lb/>
fair proficiency in Italian and German and a reading<lb/>
knowledge of Dutch.</p>
<p>About the time he left the University of<lb/>
Virginia he suffered a fracture of the leg and was told<lb/>
that he would be somewhat crippled for life - fortunately<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="F0114002"/>
-2-<lb/>
a mistaken prognosis. It was for this reason that he<lb/>
decided not to follow the profession of civil engineering<lb/>
which would require active field work. He taught for<lb/>
three years, the last of these at the University of Vir-<lb/>
ginia as Assistant in Mathematics. This is significant<lb/>
chiefly as showing his tastes and the quality of his<lb/>
mind which was essentially analytical. In the course<lb/>
of his career he found much use for his engineering edu-<lb/>
cation. I am not aware that he made any professional<lb/>
application of his <hi>higher</hi> mathematics, but in his later<lb/>
years (when I first knew him) he found no difficulty in<lb/>
following the mathematics of modern biometrical methods.</p>
<p>Miss Carter tells me that while teaching<lb/>
mathematics at the University of Virginia her father did<lb/>
some original work in higher mathematics which led to his<lb/>
receiving a fellowship (or scholarship?) in mathematics<lb/>
at the Johns Hopkins University; but that on investigation<lb/>
he was unable to accept it because the work would have<lb/>
required his whole time and he was under the necessity of<lb/>
doing outside work to support himself. Apparently he then<lb/>
turned to the study of medicine, being able at the same<lb/>
time to do some teaching which helped to support him. I<lb/>
presume I can later verify this from contemporary records.</p>
<pb n="3" id="F0114003"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>(3) Although he had some little experience<lb/>
in yellow fever control at Cairo, Illinois, during his<lb/>
first year in the Service (1879) and had occasional de-<lb/>
tails thereafter to epidemic duty, his first nine years<lb/>
in the Service were spent chiefly in clinical work at<lb/>
various marine hospitals. His facilities in these hos-<lb/>
pitals must have been meager, but he was keenly interested<lb/>
in clinical medicine and (as he says) would at this time<lb/>
have preferred to follow it rather than public health<lb/>
work.</p>
<p>By 1888 when he first went into quarantine<lb/>
duty he had established a considerable reputation as a<lb/>
clinician, especially in the southern cities where he had<lb/>
been stationed (Cairo, New Orleans, Memphis) and had before<lb/>
him the prospect of <add>a</add> good consulting practice if he chose<lb/>
to resign from the Marine Hospital Service. He seriously<lb/>
considered doing this but soon became impressed with the<lb/>
opportunities for greater humanitarin service offered by<lb/>
preventive medicine, especially by improvement in the<lb/>
quarantine service which was then of relatively much<lb/>
greater importance than at present. He has said that this<lb/>
was impressed upon him particularly by Surgeon Murray whom<lb/>
he relieved at Ship Island Quarantine in 1888, Murray<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="F0114004"/>
-4-<lb/>
reminding him that whereas the worst mistake in medical<lb/>
or surgical practice cost one life, a single mistake by a<lb/>
quarantine official giving pratique to an infected vessel<lb/>
had actually resulted in a yellow fever epidemic costing<lb/>
some hundreds of lives.</p>
<p>(4) The statement regarding reform of quar-<lb/>
antine is, perhaps, as nearly correct as it could be<lb/>
made within such a brief space. The status of U.S. Quaran-<lb/>
tine practice in 1888 and Carter's work toward improvement<lb/>
are discussed somewhat more fully in my notes on his work.</p>
<p>(5) Carter considered this his most import-<lb/>
ant scientific contribution; and, in fact, quite aside from<lb/>
any influence which it may have had in pointing Reed's<lb/>
work it stands as one of the most acute of epidemiological<lb/>
studies, ranking with the work of Bretonneau, Gendr<del>o</del><unclear><add>i ?</add></unclear>n,<lb/>
Snow and Budd. In the appended memorandum I have made<lb/>
some notes on this study and its significance.</p>
<p>(6) In Havana he served with Gorgas, Juan<lb/>
Guiteras and Carlos Finlay as a member of the Board of<lb/>
Yellow Fever Diagnosis. Already a close friend of Guiteras,<lb/>
he here formed life-long friendships with Finlay and<lb/>
Gorgas. He returned to the United States in the summer<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="F0114005"/>
-5-<lb/>
of 1900, suffering from Meniere's disease, which caused<lb/>
considerable disability for many years thereafter. After<lb/>
his return to the United States in very poor health Carter<lb/>
spent the next four years (1900-1904) chiefly at marine<lb/>
hospitals. He was, however, actively interested in yellow<lb/>
fever during this time, especially in the interpretation<lb/>
of its epidemiology from the new viewpoint of mosquito<lb/>
transmission which he immediately and unhesitatingly ac-<lb/>
capted. As early as November, 1900, a month after Reed's<lb/>
first announcement, Carter, while ill in the Johns Hopkins<lb/>
Hospital, wrote his first discussion of the mosquito<lb/>
theory: &ldquo;A correlation of some facts in the propagation<lb/>
of yellow fever with the theory of its conveyance by the<lb/>
culex fasciatus,&rdquo; which was published in the Phila. Med.<lb/>
Jour. April 6, 1901.</p>
<p>(7) This scant reference to Carter's five<lb/>
years in Panama seems to me rather inadequate. His work<lb/>
there was an important part of his service. As Director<lb/>
of Hospitals he was in charge of one of the divisions<lb/>
(the Division of Hospitals) of the Sanitary Department;<lb/>
and being the senior divisional chief, was next to Gorgas<lb/>
in command of the Department, being in charge whenever<lb/>
Gorgas was absent. I think it is strictly correct to<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="F0114006"/>
-6-<lb/>
say that he was Gorgas' &ldquo;right hand&rdquo;. These two, who<lb/>
were very devoted friends, lived together and worked<lb/>
together in a very intimate relation. The intimacy of<lb/>
this association and the feeling which Carter had for<lb/>
Gorgas are well described in Carter's tribute to Gorgas,<lb/>
written in Peru on the day on which he received a cable<lb/>
announcing Gorgas' death and published in the Southern<lb/>
Medical Journal of September, 1920, p. 688. I think it<lb/>
would equally describe Gorgas' feeling for Carter.</p>
<p>Carter returned to the United States in<lb/>
1909 much broken in health, and from that time until<lb/>
1913 his principal duties were in marine hospitals, al-<lb/>
though, in 1910, he was detailed to Europe for conference<lb/>
and arrangements in regard to maritime quarantine, es-<lb/>
pecially for measures to prevent the spread of cholera,<lb/>
which then threatened.</p>
<p>(8) His promotion to the grade to Assist-<lb/>
ant Surgeon General was by an act of Congress which<lb/>
provided for <hi>each</hi> officer who had served in the Canal<lb/>
Zone for a certain time, an advancement to the next higher<lb/>
grade. The recognition was not personal and individual<lb/>
to Carter. Two other officers of the Public Health<lb/>
Service and several of the Army were similarly advanced at<lb/>
the same time.</p>
<pb n="7" id="F0114007"/>
<p>-7-</p>
<p>(9) In the latter years of his life, after<lb/>
his return from Panama, Carter's most distinguished ser-<lb/>
vices were:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) His work on the study and control of<lb/>
malaria in the United States 1913-1920.</item>
<item>(2) His services as a member of the Inter-<lb/>
national Health Board's Yellow Fever Com-<lb/>
mission 1915-1925.</item>
<item>(3) His work on the history of yellow fever,<lb/>
1922-1925.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>He was entitled to retirement from active<lb/>
duty in the Public Health Service in August, 1916, when<lb/>
he reached the age of 64, and was, moreover, in very<lb/>
poor health. Nevertheless he remained on active duty,<lb/>
and indeed very strenuous duty, in the study and control<lb/>
of malaria until February, 1920.</p>
<p>(10) The extracts from Hanson's and Con-<lb/>
nor's letters I think are very happy and illuminating, <add>especially Connor's</add> and<lb/>
it would be impossible to improve on Thayer's picture.<lb/>
If it lacks anything it is in failing to give a picture<lb/>
of Carter in still another characteristic role, that of<lb/>
a remarkably vigorous man of action. Although he was<lb/>
perhaps by his natural inclination a student and a thinker<lb/>
no one in the Service was more vigorous than he in such<lb/>
strenuous administrative work as was involved in the fight<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="F0114008"/>
-8-<lb/>
to control yellow fever in the south in 1897, 1898 and<lb/>
1899; and even in his latter years, in his work on<lb/>
malaria, his energy and endurance were phenomenal.</p>
<pb n="1" id="F0114009"/>
<p>NOTES ON DR. CARTER'S CONTRIBUTIONS<lb/>
TO SANITARY SCIENCE.</p>
<p>Carter's most important contributions to<lb/>
epidemiology and administrative public health practice,<lb/>
are:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Improvements in maritime quarantine practice,<lb/>
dating from 1888.</item>
<item>(2) His work on the administrative control of yellow<lb/>
fever epidemics in the United States, 1893-98, not-<lb/>
ably (in 1898) his success in suppressing an epidemic<lb/>
at McHenry, La. in mid-summer, and in the presence<lb/>
of a sufficient non-immune population for its exten-<lb/>
sion.</item>
<item>(3) His studies of the epidemiology of yellow fever,<lb/>
beginning with the work which led to his demonstrat-<lb/>
ion of the &ldquo;extrinsic&rdquo; incubation period, and ending<lb/>
with his History of Yellow Fever.</item>
<item>(4) His service with Gorgas on the sanitation of the<lb/>
Canal Zone.</item>
<item>(5) His pioneer work in the study and control of malaria<lb/>
in the United States.</item>
<item>(6) His services as a member of the Yellow Fever<lb/>
Commission of the International Health Board.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>I. IMPROVEMENTS IN MARITIME QUARANTINE<lb/>
PRACTICE.</p>
<p>Carter's work in this field can hardly be<lb/>
appreciated without recalling the status of maritime<lb/>
quarantine in 1888, when he was first assigned to<lb/>
quarantine duty.</p>
<pb n="2" id="F0114010"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Yellow fever was not endemic in the United<lb/>
States, so that it was a menace altogether from without;<lb/>
but it was proven by disastrous experience that when<lb/>
introduced, in summer, into almost any of the southern<lb/>
seaports (the northern ports had already become non-<lb/>
infectible) it would gain a foothold, would spread, and<lb/>
might even, as in 1878, extend far inland in an appalling<lb/>
epidemic. As there was active maritime communication<lb/>
between our infectible ports and tropical foreign ports<lb/>
where yellow fever was more or less permanently endemic,<lb/>
and with others where it was occasionally prevalent, the<lb/>
menace of its introduction was imminent. It was, more-<lb/>
over, a constant menace (in season) year after year, not<lb/>
merely an occasional danger, as from cholera. It is<lb/>
safe to say that no system of quarantine has ever borne<lb/>
such a heavy and continued responsibility as was borne<lb/>
during the latter half of the last century by the maritime<lb/>
quarantine of the United States on account of yellow<lb/>
fever. Every ship from the yellow fever zone bore the<lb/>
potentialities of an epidemic and a single mistake might<lb/>
well mean disaster.</p>
<p>Judged by present standards, the quarantine<lb/>
service as then established was weak and poor. Quarantine<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="F0114011"/>
-3-<lb/>
stations at ports of entry were operated wholly by muni-<lb/>
cipal or State authorities, acting under their own laws<lb/>
and regulations, with no uniformity in their requirements.<lb/>
The Marine Hospital Service, though required by acts of<lb/>
Congress (1878 and 1888) to aid in the enforcement of<lb/>
quarantine, had no actual authority over local quarantines.<lb/>
It was authorized to establish quarantines at such ports<lb/>
as were without local quarantine - a rather hypothetical<lb/>
authority - and at such other places as might be deemed<lb/>
necessary; but<add>,</add> up to 1888, the Federal government actually<lb/>
operated only three quarantine stations<add>,</add> which the Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service inherited from the National Board of<lb/>
Health, one on the Chesapeake, one off the Georgia coast<lb/>
and one at Ship Island, off Biloxi, Miss. These did not<lb/>
supersede any of the city or State quarantines, but were<lb/>
merely &ldquo;Ship Refuges&rdquo; to which ships bound for any port<lb/>
in the district might be remanded for disinfection and<lb/>
quarantine or might come before applying to a local<lb/>
quarantine. The local quarantine officer might accept<lb/>
or reject a pratique issued by one of these Federal<lb/>
Stations. They did not infringe upon the authority of<lb/>
State and local quarantines, but merely aided them by<lb/>
doing disagreeable and expensive work for them. The<lb/>
Marine Hospital Service officers in charge of these<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="F0114012"/>
-4-<lb/>
stations operated under orders which were very general,<lb/>
leaving them wide discretion in their practice.</p>
<p>Carter, coming to Ship Island in 1888, and<lb/>
promptly grasping the importance of a more effective and<lb/>
more reasonable service, set himself the following tasks:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) To ascertain what was <hi>necessary</hi> in the handling<lb/>
of vessels, with due regard to reducing inconvenience,<lb/>
expense and delay to a minimum. This involved a<lb/>
study of the incubation period of yellow fever, of<lb/>
other points in its epidemiology, and of practical<lb/>
efficiency of disinfecting processes.</item>
<item>(2) To secure the confidence of local and State<lb/>
boards of health.</item>
<item>(3) To induce them to waive unnecessary requirement.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>In these undertakings he was allied with<lb/>
Dr. J. H. White, then at the Sapelo Sound (Georgia)<lb/>
quarantine, the two keeping up a long and active corres-<lb/>
pondence.</p>
<p>To follow in detail all that was accomplished<lb/>
by Carter's efforts would involve a more extensive study<lb/>
of correspondence and other records from 1888 to 1910 than<lb/>
I have been able to make, and even then it would be im-<lb/>
possible to exactly appraise his personal share in some<lb/>
of the developments. It is clear, however, that he is<lb/>
to be credited with the following:<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="F0114013"/>
-5-<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) He introduced the principle that the deten-<lb/>
tion of personnel should date from the last<lb/>
possible exposure, i. e. from disinfection of<lb/>
the vessel. This basic principle had not pre-<lb/>
viously been applied, (at least to yellow fever)<lb/>
either in this country or in British ports.</item>
<item>(2) From such data as he could assemble, includ-<lb/>
ing his own observations, he &ldquo;tentatively deduced&rdquo;<lb/>
that 5 days detention of personnel after disin-<lb/>
fection was sufficient to cover the incubation<lb/>
period of yellow fever. Since disinfection of<lb/>
the vessel required 2 days, the full detention<lb/>
period was, in effect, 7 days, which is now<lb/>
known to be sufficient. Not until 1898, however,<lb/>
did he complete his studies on this point,<lb/>
which were later (1900) confirmed experimentally.<lb/>
At the time leading authorities were very in-<lb/>
definite, giving the incubation period as &ldquo;1 to<lb/>
14 days&rdquo;; and detention periods at local quaran-<lb/>
tines varied from 3 to 42 days.</item>
<item>(3) He noted the practical efficacy of sulphur<lb/>
fumigation and adhered to it, though it had be-<lb/>
gun to be questioned by bacteriologists.</item>
<item>(4) He established such confidence in his station<lb/>
that local quarantine officers came to accept<lb/>
his pratique without imposing further conditions.<lb/>
This was an important step toward the establish-<lb/>
ment of more uniform and reasonable practice,<lb/>
the strengthening of the Federal quarantine law<lb/>
(act of 1893) and the eventual voluntary trans-<lb/>
fer of city and State quarantines to the Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service. Incidentally, Carter, in<lb/>
1893, took over, for the Marine Hospital Service,<lb/>
the first (Brunswick, Ga.) quarantine station<lb/>
thus transferred.</item>
<item>(5) As early as 1890, he advocated, and in 1893,<lb/>
(at Dry Tortugas) established the practice of<lb/>
disinfecting vessels from Cuba and Mexico at<lb/>
port of departure or en route in order to shorten<lb/>
the period of quarantine on arrival, thus in-<lb/>
troducing into quarantine practice another<lb/>
principle of basic importance.</item>
<item>(6) In the latter part of 1898 he was detailed<lb/>
to organize the quarantine service of Cuba,<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="F0114014"/>
-6-<lb/>
which was then under the administration of a<lb/>
military governor. Yellow Fever was then still<lb/>
endemic in Cuba, which was the most threaten-<lb/>
ing source of infection for the United States.<lb/>
The organization of a system of defense at the<lb/>
source was a new undertaking, requiring the<lb/>
development of new methods. It was certainly<lb/>
the most difficult and important assignment in<lb/>
quarantine duty that the Marine Hospital Ser-<lb/>
vice had to make at that time, and Carter's<lb/>
selection for it is significant.</item>
<item>(7) He was certainly influential, but I do not<lb/>
know to precisely what extent, in the successive<lb/>
revisions of quarantine regulations, at least<lb/>
up to 1910. In the Public Health Service, he is<lb/>
generally credited with having been the chief<lb/>
adviser of the Bureau in such matters.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The importance of the successive improvements<lb/>
made in quarantine practice is incalculable, when one con-<lb/>
siders their effect in freeing commerce from excessive<lb/>
restrictions while at the same time strengthening the de-<lb/>
fense against yellow fever. It is true that the measures<lb/>
taken against yellow fever were never wholly successful<lb/>
until the principal sources of infection in tropical America<lb/>
had been controlled. However, in the two decades 1881-1900,<lb/>
the invasions of yellow fever into the United States, were<lb/>
fewer and far less disastrous than in the 20 years preced-<lb/>
ing. This was not due to any lessening of the danger,<lb/>
which was probably increasing as regards chances for intro-<lb/>
duction from abroad and potentialities of disastrous<lb/>
epidemics in the south following invasion. It was due to<lb/>
better operation of quarantine, though at reduced incon-<lb/>
venience to shipping; and to better control of the infection<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="F0114015"/>
-7-<lb/>
whenever it was introduced - and in this latter work, as<lb/>
well as in quarantine, Carter was the outstanding figure<lb/>
of the last decade of the nineteenth century.</p>
<p>Since the dramatic conquest of yellow fever<lb/>
after 1900, when the mystery of its transmission was re-<lb/>
vealed, the struggle and the achievement of these last<lb/>
two decades of the &ldquo;dark ages&rdquo; have been forgotten. It<lb/>
was a fight against heavy odds - lack of adequate know-<lb/>
ledge, lack of control over the fighting forces, and at<lb/>
first, lack of public confidence. It was not a vic-<lb/>
tory; yellow fever was not kept out, but at least it was<lb/>
severely checked, and this was a great achievement. Its<lb/>
immediate results in cases and deaths prevented were<lb/>
certainly agreat though they may never be exactly appraised.<lb/>
In addition the work had <add>an</add> important influence upon the future<lb/>
development of public health in the country, especially<lb/>
in establishing the unique relations of mutual coopera-<lb/>
tion between the States and the Public Health Service.<lb/>
It was not and could not be the work of one man, but from<lb/>
1890-1900<del>,</del> Carter was the foremost figure <add>in</add> the development<lb/>
of quarantine and in the management of epidemics. His<lb/>
personal influence with State and local authorities was<lb/>
very great.</p>
<pb n="8" id="F0114016"/>
<p>-8-</p>
<p>II. WORK ON THE ADMINISTRATIVE CONTROL OF YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
EPIDEMICS IN THE SOUTHERN STATES.</p>
<p>The first line of defense against yellow<lb/>
fever, the maritime quarantine, did not always hold, and<lb/>
on four different occasions from 1891 to 1900, yellow<lb/>
fever gained a foothold in the United States. These<lb/>
ourbreaks were:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>1893 Brunswick, Georgia.</item>
<item>1897, Louisiana, Mississippi and other<lb/>
States,</item>
<item>1898, Louisiana and Mississippi,</item>
<item>1899, Florida, Louisiana and Mississippi.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Carter was actively engaged in the measures<lb/>
taken to control all these epidemics. He was in charge<lb/>
in 1893; had charge of one of the larger districts in<lb/>
1897; and in 1898 and 1899 he was in general charge of<lb/>
the work of the Service.</p>
<p>In those days the organization of measures<lb/>
to control the spread of yellow fever was the most com-<lb/>
plex and arduous of all tasks in public health administra-<lb/>
tion. In addition to local measures it was necessary<lb/>
to establish and operate detention camps, to regulate<lb/>
railroad and boat traffic, to maintain inspection of com-<lb/>
mon carriers and of uninvaded territory, to investigate<lb/>
suspicious reports, often to make the &ldquo;official&rdquo; diagnosis<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="F0114017"/>
-9-<lb/>
of yellow fever and to reconcile all this to conflict-<lb/>
ing State and local interests. All this must be done,<lb/>
too, with the utmost expedition, and in the face of such<lb/>
panic as no other disease excited. That Carter was<lb/>
selected to take charge of work so vital to the Service<lb/>
and the country is sufficient evidence that he was<lb/>
deemed by his Bureau to be the most competent of all the<lb/>
officers available and that he was not considered lack-<lb/>
ing in administrative ability. The annual reports and<lb/>
other records of the Service give abundant evidence that<lb/>
he was an excellent, if somewhat original and informal<lb/>
administrative officer, cool in the excitement, far-<lb/>
seeing in his plans, vigorous in his measures and nota-<lb/>
bly successful in his dealings with State officials and<lb/>
commercial bodies.</p>
<p>It is impossible to judge from this distance<lb/>
just what effect the measures taken actually had in<lb/>
limiting the spread of yellow fever. It is certain that<lb/>
they were not comparable in efficacy to the measures<lb/>
taken in 1903 and 1905, which were based upon more accur-<lb/>
ate knowledge of transmission. In many instances, when<lb/>
yellow fever was first reported it had already reached<lb/>
such prevalence that effective local control was hardly<lb/>
possible; but there would seem to be no doubt that the<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="F0114018"/>
-10-<lb/>
spread to other localities was very definitely limited<lb/>
by the measures taken. The detention camps of the period<lb/>
seem to have been really effective, although no special<lb/>
effort was made to prevent the access of mosquitoes.<lb/>
Cases of yellow fever often developed in these camps in<lb/>
persons infected before admission, but cases due to<lb/>
camp infection rarely developed; and I believe there was<lb/>
no instance of uncontrolled spread in a camp or from one in<lb/>
these years.</p>
<p>In 1898, at McHenry, La., Carter, assisted<lb/>
by J.H. White, was definitely successful in suppressing<lb/>
an epidemic which had commenced to gain headway and in<lb/>
preventing the establishment of any outside foci. This<lb/>
is generally cited, correctly I believe, as the first<lb/>
instance in which an epidemic of yellow fever was sup-<lb/>
pressed in midsummer (July), in high<add>ly</add> &ldquo;infectible&rdquo; ter-<lb/>
ritory and in the presence of a non-immune population<lb/>
sufficient to have sustained it. Although the measures<lb/>
taken included much in the way of &ldquo;disinfection&rdquo; which<lb/>
was, of course, superfluous in the light of present<lb/>
knowledge<add>,</add> they were sound in certain principles, viz:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Prompt isolation of cases and suspects,<lb/>
detected by daily inspection,</item>
<item>(2) Removal of contacts (of primary cases)<lb/>
from infected houses to a detention camp,</item>
<item>(3) Disinfection of infected houses as <hi>early</hi><lb/>
as possible, using sulphur.</item>
</list>
</p>
<pb n="11" id="F0114019"/>
<p>-11-</p>
<p>In (2) and (3) Carter was applying principles<lb/>
deduced from his own observations on the &ldquo;extrinsic&rdquo;<lb/>
period of incubation, namely, that the environment of<lb/>
a yellow fever patient, if previously uninfected, did<lb/>
not become infective to others until about ten days had<lb/>
elapsed. <add>With at knowledge of these principal he<lb/>
would not--have been successful.</add></p>
<p>III. CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE EPIDEMIOLOGY OF<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p><hi>A. Determination of extrinsic and intrinsic incubation<lb/>
periods in yellow fever</hi>.</p>
<p>Carter's study of incubation periods in<lb/>
yellow fever began in 1888, as an inquiry essential to<lb/>
the establishment of sound quarantine practice. Sup-<lb/>
posedly authoritative references then gave the incubation<lb/>
period in man as &ldquo;1 to 14 days&rdquo;, and from a search of<lb/>
original references Carter was able to find reliable and<lb/>
determinative observations which numbered &ldquo;less than<lb/>
the fingers of one hand&rdquo; (Carter, 1901). Assembling,<lb/>
one by one, what he considered the most significant and<lb/>
reliable of recorded observations, and adding to them<lb/>
from his own experience, of which he kept careful notes,<lb/>
he was soon able to conclude (&ldquo;tentatively&rdquo; he says) that<lb/>
the incubation period was rarely, if ever, in excess of<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="F0114020"/>
-12-<lb/>
six days, usually less. He noted, however, in a few<lb/>
instances which he observed that the interval between<lb/>
onset of a first case in a <hi>previously uninfected locality</hi><lb/>
and other cases apparently secondary thereto was much<lb/>
longer. Such occasional long intervals between apparent<lb/>
exposure and onset had previously been noted, but had<lb/>
not been systematically investigated or recorded and<lb/>
had served only to confuse determinations of the true<lb/>
incubation period in man.--</p>
<p>Carter was impressed with the regularity<lb/>
of this interval (16-18 days) in the few instances which<lb/>
he observed, and conceived the idea that the excess over<lb/>
the usual incubation in man represented the time required<lb/>
for the environment to become infective. He added con-<lb/>
stantly to his data by personal observations and inquiry,<lb/>
but the opportunities for observations of determinative<lb/>
significance were few, and it was ten years before he<lb/>
found a situation in which it was possible to make a suf-<lb/>
ficient number of observations under circumstances satis-<lb/>
fying all his requirements.</p>
<p>The opportunity occurred in a little epidemic<lb/>
in an isolated rural community, Orwood, Miss. in the sum-<lb/>
mer of 1898. Carter, who was in general charge of epi-<lb/>
demic control measures in the south, could not remain<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="F0114021"/>
-13-<lb/>
long in this place; but he recognized the unique op-<lb/>
portunity, made careful notes during his stay and<lb/>
arranged with two local physicians to check the record,<lb/>
by independent investigation<add>,</add> and to continue it in his<lb/>
absence.</p>
<p>The records were completed in October,<lb/>
1898; but immediately thereafter, Carter was ordered<lb/>
to Cuba to organize the quarantine service of the island<lb/>
and found no opportunity to assemble his data and pre-<lb/>
pare them for publication until the winter of 1899-<lb/>
1900. He published altogether three papers on the<lb/>
subject, namely:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) &ldquo;A note on the interval between infecting and second-<lb/>
ary cases of yellow fever, from the records of the<lb/>
yellow fever at Orwood, and Taylor, Miss. in 1898,&rdquo;<lb/>
New Orleans Med. &amp; Surg. Jour., May, 1900. (Also<lb/>
reprinted in the Annual Report of the Marine Hospi-<lb/>
tal Service for the year 1900).</item>
<item>(2) &ldquo;A note on the spread of yellow fever in houses -<lb/>
extrinsic incubation&rdquo;; Annual Report of the Marine<lb/>
Hospital Service for the year 1900. (Also reprinted<lb/>
in Phila. Med. Jour. June 15, 1901).</item>
<item>(3) &ldquo;The period of incubation of yellow fever; a study<lb/>
from unpublished observations&rdquo;, Med. Record, Mar.<lb/>
9, 1901.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>His contributions to the subject as presented<lb/>
in these three papers, are:<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="F0114022"/>
-14-<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) In a series of observations much more exact<lb/>
and extensive than had ever before been recorded<lb/>
(or than recorded since then except in experiment-<lb/>
al studies) he demonstrated that the incubation in<lb/>
man ranged from 3 to 6 (possibly 8) days following<lb/>
exposure to an <hi>already infective environment</hi>.</item>
<item>(2) He showed that in <hi>every</hi> instance observed where<lb/>
the facts were certain, the interval between onset<lb/>
of the <hi>first case in a previously uninfected environ-<lb/>
ment</hi> and the onset of the first &ldquo;secondary&rdquo; case<lb/>
was much longer, from 12 to 23 days, usually from<lb/>
15 to 20.</item>
<item>(3) He deduced, from sufficient evidence, that fol-<lb/>
lowing the onset of a case of yellow fever in a<lb/>
<hi>previously uninfected environment</hi> there was an <hi>inter-<lb/>
val</hi> of about 10 - 17 days, during which the environ-<lb/>
ment (house and its contents) was <hi>not infective</hi> to<lb/>
other people. He showed that during this interval<lb/>
susceptible people might reside in the house in inti-<lb/>
mate contact with the patient and famites without<lb/>
contracting the disease.</item>
<item>(4) He gave evidence that infection is conveyed to<lb/>
others not <hi>directly from the patient</hi> but by the<lb/>
environment of the patient. It was already gen-<lb/>
erally admitted that infection was frequently con-<lb/>
tracted from the environment, but I think it had<lb/>
not been so clearly established that it was <hi>not</hi><lb/>
conveyed directly from the patient.</item>
<item>(5) He pointed out certain practical applications<lb/>
of these conclusions to the control of yellow fever;<lb/>
namely, that &ldquo;secondary&rdquo; cases might be prevented<lb/>
either by:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(a) Disinfecting the house within which an<lb/>
infecting case has occurred, provided the<lb/>
disinfection be done within 10 days after<lb/>
onset of the first case, or,</item>
<item>(b) Removing contacts from the infected house<lb/>
within 10 days following onset of the<lb/>
infecting case.</item>
</list>
</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>He cites his own successful experience in<lb/>
applying these principles, also notes a highly important<lb/>
<pb n="15" id="F0114023"/>
-15-<lb/>
application to maritime quarantine.</p>
<p>The first note (New Orleans Med. Jour.<lb/>
May, 1900), the only one of the series actually published<lb/>
before Reed's experiments were undertaken and reported,<lb/>
does not, in explicit terms, state all these implications.<lb/>
It does, however, give the most significant and essen-<lb/>
tial of the data<add>,</add> presented in such a way that all these<lb/>
implications are plain to one who carefully studies the<lb/>
paper.</p>
<p>Concerning the importance of these obser-<lb/>
vations in determining the direction of Reed's experimental<lb/>
work, by far the fullest and clearest statement that I<lb/>
have seen is that contained in the first publication<lb/>
on the etiology of yellow fever by Reed, Carroll, Agra-<lb/>
monte and Lazear (Pub. Health Papers and Reports, A.P.H.A.<lb/>
Vol. XVI, Oct. 1900), which I have never seen quoted <hi>in<lb/>
full</hi>. This states that <hi>three</hi> considerations determined<lb/>
the investigators to turn their attention to the theory of<lb/>
transmission by the mosquito, namely:<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
<item>(1) Certain general facts in the epidemiology of the disease<lb/>
(chiefly its sharp seasonal and geographic limitations)<lb/>
which had led Finlay to formulate his theory of mosquito<lb/>
transmission.</item>
<item>(2) The work of Ross and the Italians in demonstrating the<lb/>
conveyance of malaria by the mosquito (development of<lb/>
parasite in the mosquito; limitation to one genus of mos-<lb/>
quitoes)<lb/>
<pb n="16" id="F0114024"/>
-16-</item>
<item>(3) The observations of Carter, which are discussed at<lb/>
more length than the other two considerations, perhaps be-<lb/>
cause they were not so generally known.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Taken together, these three sets of facts<lb/>
formed an impressive train of evidence pointing to the<lb/>
mosquito as the agent of transmission, and it seems to me<lb/>
that it adds to rather than detracts from the brilliance<lb/>
of the experiments which followed that they were under-<lb/>
taken for such good reasons as Reed states rather than<lb/>
merely at a venture. As to the <hi>relative</hi> importance of<lb/>
these three sets of facts, presumably and quite properly<lb/>
that would differ in different minds; and it seems to me<lb/>
utterly futile to debate whether Finlay's, Ross' or Car-<lb/>
ter's observations had the most weight. Probably they<lb/>
had different relative weights in the minds of the sever-<lb/>
al individuals in Reed's own working party.</p>
<p>Quite aside from their significance in<lb/>
helping to determine the direction of experimental work,<lb/>
Carter's studies of the incubation period of yellow fever<lb/>
rank with the most notable that have been made in the<lb/>
field of non-experimental epidemiology. One needs to study<lb/>
the whole series of papers to appreciate Carter's patient<lb/>
persistence in the collection of material, his scrupulous<lb/>
care in excluding every observation that might be subject<lb/>
<pb n="17" id="F0114025"/>
-17-<lb/>
to any question, his skill in analysis of the complex<lb/>
and puzzling data, and the clear logic by which he es-<lb/>
tablishes a conclusion so remarkable as the existence<lb/>
of a definite period of &ldquo;incubation&rdquo; in the environment.<lb/>
Pettenkofer had, of course, formulated a doctrine of<lb/>
something like an &ldquo;extrinsic incubation&rdquo; in the trans-<lb/>
mission of typhoid fever and cholera; but his work is<lb/>
not to be compared with that of Carter, for Pettenkofer<lb/>
did not <hi>prove</hi> his theory - in fact, he willfully disregarded<lb/>
such facts as contradicted it. He merely formulated an<lb/>
ingenious speculative theory, while Carter <hi>proved the<lb/>
existence</hi> of a remarkable phonomenon.</p>
<p>I think the work done by Carter ranks<lb/>
with that of Bretonneau, Budd and Snow, and am especially<lb/>
impressed with its similarity to Snow's work in its<lb/>
purposeful plan, in the instant recognition of an un-<lb/>
usual opportunity to collect determinative data and<lb/>
in the direct and concise presentation. In the second<lb/>
article of this series, as in many of his later writings<lb/>
Carter is especially skillful in his handling and precise<lb/>
in his interpretation of &ldquo;negative&rdquo; evidence. I do not<lb/>
recall ever having seen it so well handled by any other<lb/>
writer on epidemiology.</p>
<p><hi>B. Contributions to the epidemiology of yellow fever after<lb/>
the experimental demonstration of its transmission by the</hi><lb/>
mosquito.</p>
<p>After it had been shown experimentally<lb/>
<pb n="18" id="F0114026"/>
-18-<lb/>
(October, 1900) that yellow fever was transmitted by the<lb/>
mosquito, it remained to reconstruct the whole epidemiology<lb/>
of the disease from a new viewpoint, correlating all the<lb/>
facts known about <del>the</del><add>its</add> occurrence <del>of the disease</del> with<lb/>
this central fact. Carter's writings from this viewpoint<lb/>
began in November, 1900, when, as a patient in the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins Hospital, he wrote his first paper on yellow<lb/>
fever from this angle, (A correlation of some facts in the<lb/>
propagation of yellow fever with the theory of its convey-<lb/>
ance by the culex faseiatus, published in the Phila. Med.<lb/>
Jour. Apr. 6, 1901) and ended with the last work on his<lb/>
History of Yellow Fever, done in the closing days of<lb/>
his last illness in August, 1925.</p>
<p>In the first paper above cited he takes<lb/>
up a series of broad facts or &ldquo;general beliefs&rdquo; con-<lb/>
cerning the occurrence of yellow fever, discussing each<lb/>
from the standpoint of the &ldquo;mosquito theory&rdquo; and showing<lb/>
that those postulates which are proven facts are consistent<lb/>
with the new viewpoint, while those which appear to be in-<lb/>
consistent (e.g. the conveyance of infection in baggage,<lb/>
etc.) are not really proven. Without questioning the<lb/>
mosquito conveyance, which he accepts, he points to apparent<lb/>
discrepancy which needs to be (and later was) cleared up,<lb/>
namely, that ships were known to have been infective as<lb/>
<pb n="19" id="F0114027"/>
-19-<lb/>
long as 40 - 60 days after occurrence of the last case<lb/>
of yellow fever (his own observations) whereas Finlay had<lb/>
reported that the female mosquito did not survive (at sum-<lb/>
mer temperature) more than 8 - 14 days after feeding.<lb/>
So far as I have been able to ascertain this paper is the<lb/>
broadest and ablest discussion of yellow fever from this<lb/>
viewpoint published up to that date. From this time until<lb/>
his death, wherever he might be and on whatever duty, he<lb/>
was an indefatigible student of all that pertained to<lb/>
yellow fever, never missing a chance, whether in Panama,<lb/>
Peru, or Baltimore, to learn more of the habits of &ldquo;stego-<lb/>
myia&rdquo; by personal observations, and constantly revising<lb/>
his philosophy of yellow fever and his strategy of con-<lb/>
trol.</p>
<p>The papers on yellow fever which he<lb/>
published in these years, though they are brief and not<lb/>
numerous, include several which are really important<lb/>
contributions to knowledge and understanding of the disease.<lb/>
Especially notable and characteristic are his papers deal-<lb/>
ing with such broad questions as &ldquo;the permanence of immu-<lb/>
nity&rdquo;, &ldquo;spontaneous disappearance from failure of the<lb/>
human host&rdquo;, &ldquo;the chance of the extension of yellow fever<lb/>
to Asia and Australia,&rdquo; etc. I believe that no one else<lb/>
has so well handled such questions in the epidemiology of<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<pb n="20" id="F0114028"/>
<p>-20-</p>
<p>Finally, there is his History of Yellow Fever,<lb/>
which more nearly than any other work shows his full mas-<lb/>
tery of the subject. It is characteristic in its plan,<lb/>
in that he first lays down, from modern knowledge, the<lb/>
physical, biological and social conditions which determine<lb/>
the characteristic epidemiology of yellow fever. Then,<lb/>
in the light of these conditions, he reviews not the his-<lb/>
tory of yellow fever but the history of the period from<lb/>
the earliest records of Western Africa and America to<lb/>
1648 when yellow fever emerges from obscurity and be-<lb/>
comes recognizable beyond question. In all that may<lb/>
throw light on yellow fever, as in the old Maya and Aztec<lb/>
records, in the details of losses in military expeditions<lb/>
and colonies, in the analysis of social conditions and<lb/>
commercial development<add>,</add> in the study of early communication<lb/>
between Africa and America<add>,</add> he has gone back to contemporary<lb/>
records to an extent which indicates a life study rather<lb/>
than three years' work; and his interpretation of the facts<lb/>
with reference to the light which they throw on the presence<lb/>
or absence of yellow fever is the most delightful epidem-<lb/>
iological analysis that I have ever followed. Merely as<lb/>
an historical research his History of Yellow Fever would<lb/>
be a credit to an historian. As a retrospective study in<lb/>
epidemiology it is altogether unique and, I believe, <del>it</del><lb/>
will be final as to the principal questions which he dis-<lb/>
cusses.</p>
<pb n="21" id="F0114029"/>
<p>-21-</p>
<p>It was one of the happiest circumstances<lb/>
of Carter's life that the International Health Board<lb/>
persuaded him to spend his latter years (1922-25) on<lb/>
this work and made it possible for him to do it more<lb/>
comfortably and effectively. It was happy in the result -<lb/>
a book which no one but Carter could have written, and<lb/>
equally in the joy that it gave him to spend the last<lb/>
of his energies in the work that he loved.*</p>
<p>----------------------------------------------------------</p> 
<p>* The study of yellow fever necessarily involved a<lb/>
parallel study of the early history of malaria in America;<lb/>
and though Carter did not write for publication on this<lb/>
subject, he wrote for one of his friends a brief memoran-<lb/>
dum on the origin and early history of malaria in America,<lb/>
which I think must be of considerable importance.</p>
<p>-----------------------------------------------------------</p>
<p>IV. SERVICE IN THE CANAL ZONE.</p>
<p>Of the details of Carter's service in the<lb/>
Canal Zone (1904-1909) I know almost nothing except what<lb/>
has been told me from time to time by LePrince, Noland and<lb/>
others who were intimately associated with him there. His<lb/>
administration of the hospitals which were under his<lb/>
immediate direction is always highly spoken of; and it is<lb/>
certain that at the same time he was in intimate touch with<lb/>
the sanitary work, especially that relating to the control<lb/>
of yellow fever and malaria, but I do not know what part<lb/>
<pb n="22" id="F0114030"/>
-22-<lb/>
he personally had in it.</p>
<p>V. STUDY AND CONTROL OF MALARIA IN THE<lb/>
UNITED STATES.</p>
<p>Systematic and sustained study of the epidem-<lb/>
iology of malaria in the southern States, with a sustained<lb/>
effort to develop and demonstrate control methods and<lb/>
to arouse active interest in the subject, began<add>,</add> to the<lb/>
best of my knowledge<add>,</add> with the work started by von Ezdorf<lb/>
of the Public Health Service in 1912. This work, which was<lb/>
begun on a small scale and with limited scope<add>,</add> was expanded<lb/>
in 1913, partly under von Ezdorf's direction and at<lb/>
the same time by Carter working independently (i.e. in an<lb/>
official sense, though the personal association was close)<lb/>
and was still further extended under Carter's direction in<lb/>
1914, when LePrince came into the work. These three men,<lb/>
working together in varying official relations but in un-<lb/>
varying cooperation until von Ezdorf's death, laid the<lb/>
foundation of all the work which has since grown up in the<lb/>
south and personally trained a large proportion of those<lb/>
who are now engaged in it.</p>
<p>In the summer of 1913, Carter, unaided, made a<lb/>
trip through eastern North Carolina, visiting some 13<lb/>
localities, making in each an inquiry as to the prevalence<lb/>
<pb n="23" id="F0114031"/>
-23-<lb/>
and types of malaria and a survey of the species and<lb/>
breeding places of anopheline mosquitoes<del>:</del><add>,</add> <del>on which he took</del><add>taking</add><lb/>
with him some of the local officials from each place for<lb/>
demonstration and instruction. How much this was needed<lb/>
may be judged from his report that on the entire trip<lb/>
he met no one who had ever seen and recognized anopheline<lb/>
larvae. His survey, in each place, was followed by an<lb/>
exposition of the subject of malaria control with local<lb/>
applications. This, I believe, was the first tour of its<lb/>
kind undertaken in the south.</p>
<p>The next year, with LePrince and other<lb/>
assistants (von Ezdorf being absent) he continued the<lb/>
survey in a less hurried way and organized, at Roanoke<lb/>
Rapids, N.C. and Electric Mills, Miss. the first local<lb/>
demonstration of malaria control. He also began his<lb/>
study of impounded waters in relation to malaria, and<lb/>
began to develop a group for the systematic study of<lb/>
malaria in the laboratory and in the field. From this<lb/>
time until 1919 he continued in active supervision of<lb/>
all the anti-malarial work of the Public Health Service<lb/>
and most of the time in direct administrative charge of it,<lb/>
spending five or six months of each year actually in the<lb/>
field. Especially in 1918, when very extensive anti-<lb/>
malarial work had to be organized in the zones around Army<lb/>
<pb n="24" id="F0114032"/>
-24-<lb/>
cantonments, this was exceedingly arduous duty.</p>
<p>His personal relation to the work on malaria<lb/>
was equally that of student and teacher. As a student<lb/>
he found many problems to be solved. Although the basic<lb/>
principles of the epidemiology and control of malaria had<lb/>
already been established, much remained to be done in<lb/>
1913, and much remains today, in the way of acquiring a<lb/>
more intimate knowledge of the varying factors concerned<lb/>
in the local prevalence of malaria and developing the con-<lb/>
trol methods best applicable to each situation. This was<lb/>
a field of study for which Carter was peculiarly well<lb/>
fitted by inclination, experience and abilities. His<lb/>
name is especially connected with his studies of impounded<lb/>
waters, but the fact is that he had a large personal share<lb/>
in every one of the studies made under his supervision.<lb/>
He was the pioneer in pointing out the diversity of the<lb/>
malaria problems in the United States and in developing<lb/>
the viewpoint, now generally accepted, that there is no one<lb/>
program of control which is universally applicable.</p>
<p>Even more important than his own personal<lb/>
contributions as a student was his work as a teacher,<lb/>
training men for technical work in the study and control<lb/>
of malaria, and at the same time educating health offi-<lb/>
cers, lay officials and commercial bodies in the importance<lb/>
<pb n="25" id="F0114033"/>
-25-<lb/>
and the elements of malaria control. As a technical<lb/>
teacher his method was that of field demonstration, or,<lb/>
more properly collaboration, working with his men and lead-<lb/>
ing them in their field studies, conducting day after day<lb/>
long &ldquo;walking clinics&rdquo; and informal lectures on malaria.<lb/>
In this way he was not only able to teach his methods of<lb/>
study but to impart to each of his men a share of his own<lb/>
enthusiasm and spirit which they could have caught in<lb/>
no other way, and he was able, too, <unclear>t</unclear>o form very keen<lb/>
estimates of all the men on his staff and to use them<lb/>
according to their abilities.</p>
<p>His teaching was, however, by no means con-<lb/>
fined to his own staff. It extended to all with whom<lb/>
he came in contact - State and local health officers, town<lb/>
councils, county supervisors, chambers of commerce, large<lb/>
industrial establishments, and even the general public.<lb/>
One does not think of Dr. Carter as a &ldquo;propagandist&rdquo;,<lb/>
and he was certainly not one of the conventional type,<lb/>
but he had no small talent for winning support. He had<lb/>
had long experience, especially in his management of yel-<lb/>
low fever epidemics, in dealing with officials and the<lb/>
public. He had, too, a remarkably clear understanding<lb/>
of the minds of people of all classes, so that he was able<lb/>
to address himself to their particular viewpoints; and this,<lb/>
with his mastery of his subject, his obvious modesty<lb/>
and integrity, and his scrupulous care to avoid overstate-<lb/>
<pb n="26" id="F0114034"/>
-26-<lb/>
ment of his case won him confidence and solid support that<lb/>
would not have been accorded to more &ldquo;stirring&rdquo; propagand-<lb/>
ists.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
