<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KACA0010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from George A. Kellogg to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 4, 1941</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kellogg, George A.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KACA0010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1941-03-04</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Cumming, Hugh S.</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Rochester (Minn.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">San Francisco (Calif.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KACA0010</idno>
<title>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 4, 1941</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kellogg informs Kean about revisions to the proposed painting &ldquo;Conquerors of Yellow Fever,&rdquo; and asks for Kean's advice. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1941-03-04">
<head>Letter from George A. Kellogg to Jefferson Randolph Kean, March 4, 1941</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKACA0010"/>
<opener>
Geo A Kellogg March 4&sol;41<lb/>
257 CORNELISON AVENUE<lb/>
JERSEY CITY, N. J.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1941-03-04">March 4, 1941</date>
</dateline><lb/>
General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N Street, N. W.<lb/>
Georgetown<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>Dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>I wish to thank you for your kind letter of February 28th. I have intended<lb/>
writing you for over a week but the passage of events has been too great for<lb/>
me to keep up with my correspondence.</p>
<p>After the delightful visit which Mr. Cornwell, Mr. Withington who, incidental-<lb/>
ly, is with John Wyeth &amp; Brother of Philadelphia, my daughter and I had with<lb/>
you and Mrs. Kean, we left for Rochester to see Doctor Hench, not realizing<lb/>
that he had had the more or less extensive correspondence with you concerning<lb/>
the study on Yellow Fever. Doctor Hench supplied us with a great deal of in-<lb/>
formation and gave us what we believe is a well balanced account of the Yellow<lb/>
Fever story. Unquestionably, Mr. Cornwell and I had been under the influence<lb/>
of the Cubans to too great an extent to do justice to the American Yellow Fever<lb/>
Board. As Doctor Hench said, what we were offering to paint was a perfect<lb/>
picture for Cuba but hardly in line with the facts and certainly not one<lb/>
designed to appeal to Americans. We certainly overemphasized the importance<lb/>
of Doctor Finlay.</p>
<p>Now we are back starting all over again. Doctor Hench would like to have the<lb/>
setting on the porch of the officers' quarters at Camp Columbia and the<lb/>
incident, that of Lazear allowing a mosquito to bite Doctor Carroll. This<lb/>
appeals to us but for a technical reason the artist does not care to have the<lb/>
scene take place on the porch. While it is not in line with the actual facts,<lb/>
we would like to place Lazear and Carroll around the table just below the<lb/>
porch, near one of the steps. This gives the artist an opportunity to place<lb/>
several figures at various levels on the steps and makes the painting more<lb/>
interesting. It is possible that Lazear and Carroll might once have fooled<lb/>
around with a captive mosquito outside, although I will agree that it is not<lb/>
probable. However, we wish to catch the spirit of the Yellow Fever study and<lb/>
present it in a way that will give credit where credit is due. The artist<lb/>
feels disappointed not to be able to use the colorful Cuban patio background<lb/>
of which you saw sketches. It may develop into another picture later on.<lb/>
The present one will include, in addition to Doctors Carroll and Lazear,<lb/>
Doctor Reed, Doctor Agramonte, Doctor Finlay and the soldiers Moran and<lb/>
Kissenger.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKACA0020"/>
<p>Gen. Jefferson R. Kean&nbsp;&nbsp;- 2 -&nbsp;&nbsp;March 4, 1941
</p>
<p>I just had a letter from General Truby in San Francisco in which he<lb/>
suggested that we include Major General Wood. While Wood certainly<lb/>
deserves some credit or, perhaps, a great deal of credit, I feel that<lb/>
to include Wood would necessitate including a great many others who<lb/>
also deserve credit. We don't want a mob scene, as you can well ap-<lb/>
preciate. I would be interested in your opinion as to whether placing<lb/>
General Wood in the picture is a necessity. We will have a good<lb/>
portrait of Doctor Reed, Lazear and Agramonte and Carroll will be there.<lb/>
We will also have a good portrait of Doctor Finlay and the two first<lb/>
volunteers for the experiment but I am afraid I would be asking a little<lb/>
too much of my artist to get a portrait of Wood into what he now con-<lb/>
siders a well-crowded picture. Please don't feel that you have to agree<lb/>
with me in this; we want your candid opinion and would also like your<lb/>
opinion of the setting which I have described earlier in this letter.</p>
<p>I am glad that you are pleased with the Beaumont and Osler paintings.<lb/>
Let me express my thanks again for the delightful hospitality shown us<lb/>
by Mrs. Kean and yourself.</p>
<p>Incidentally, we had a nice visit with two of the executives of the Pan<lb/>
American Union who viewed the possibility of our unveiling the Yellow<lb/>
Fever picture in the Pan American Union Building favorably. Mr. Corn-<lb/>
well recently had a letter from Doctor Cumming and he is much interest-<lb/>
ed. I hope to see Doctor Cumming again within the next ten days or two<lb/>
weeks. The Pan American Union Building is a beautiful place and would<lb/>
provide a splendid setting for any ceremonies which might be arranged.</p>
<p>I am afraid that Doctor Hench does not think it might work out so well<lb/>
since we are withdrawing the emphasis in the painting from Doctor Finlay<lb/>
but I have a feeling that the people connected with the Pan American<lb/>
Union will take a fair attitude in this matter.</p>
<p>With kindest personal regards, I am,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely,</salute>
<signed>George A. Kellogg</signed>
George A. Kellogg<lb/>
EM<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
