<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KADA0010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Article: A Review of Dr. Howard A. Kelly's Book, &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;, Third Edition, The Norman, Remington Company, Publishers, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 19, 1923</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KADA0010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo"> Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1923-10-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Noguchi, Hideyo</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="place">Otsego County (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester County (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>14 pp.</extent>
<date value="1923-10-19">October 19, 1923</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KADA0010</idno>
<title>Article: A Review of Dr. Howard A. Kelly's Book, &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;, Third Edition, The Norman, Remington Company, Publishers, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 19, 1923</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This review of Kelly's book was never published. Kean believed a staff member who was a Carroll propagandist suppressed it. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1923-10-19">
<head>Article: A Review of Dr. Howard A. Kelly's Book, &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;, Third Edition, The Norman, Remington Company, Publishers, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, October 19, 1923</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKADA0010"/>
<p>Biston<lb/>
Oct 19;<lb/>
1923</p>
<p>Note - This review was never published.<lb/>
The Publishers wrote me that the mss had been<lb/>
lost in their office. I think it was suppressed<lb/>
by one of the staff who was a Carroll propagandist.</p>
<p>J. R. K.</p>
<p>A Review of Dr. Howard A. Kelly's Book<lb/>
&ldquo;WALTER REED AND YELLOW FEVER&rdquo;,<lb/>
Third Edition,<lb/>
The Horman, Remington Company, Publishers,<lb/>
by<lb/>
Colonel J. R. Kean, M.C.</p>
<p>Dr. Howard A. Kelly of Baltimore has brought out a third edition<lb/>
of his notable work, &ldquo;Walter Reed and Yellow Fever&rdquo;. In it he has added<lb/>
to his former narrative of the work of Reed and his assistants on the Yellow<lb/>
Fever Commission biographical sketches of Surgeon General George M. Stern-<lb/>
berg and Surgeon General William C. Gorgas, with brief mention of the more<lb/>
recent work of Dr. Hideyo Noguchi of the Rockefeller Foundation. These<lb/>
four, Sternberg, Reed, Gorgas and Noguchi he considers to have supplemented<lb/>
each the work of the other and by their combined labors to have won &ldquo;the<lb/>
greatest battle ever fought for the health of the human race&rdquo;. Of these,<lb/>
all but the last have passed beyond the Veil, and so it is now possible to<lb/>
view from approximately the historical standpoint the epic story of their<lb/>
accomplishment and to estimate the relative value of their contributions<lb/>
to the winning of the great battle. They have been placed in the order of<lb/>
their appearance in the lists to combat that mysterious and mortal enemy<lb/>
of mankind which had routed armies and ravaged cities and had so often<lb/>
brought death and mourning into the homes of America. In this order let<lb/>
us consider them and their contributions to the victory.</p>
<p>George Miller Sternberg was born in Otsego County, New York, in<lb/>
1838, of an old Lutheran family of the Palatinate. He graduated in medicine<lb/>
at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1860. At the outbreak of the<lb/>
Civil War he promptly entered the Army and was captured while caring for<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKADA0020"/>
his wounded at Bull Run. He soon was permitted to escape and after a<lb/>
varied and always creditable record of service during the remainder of<lb/>
the War and thereafter with the scattered detachments of the Regular<lb/>
Army, mostly in the far west, he had his first experience with yellow<lb/>
fever in 1873 at Fort Barrances, near Pensacola, Florida. Again in<lb/>
1874 and 1875 it reappeared and was the object of careful study, but<lb/>
not until the latter year did he suffer an attack. He became thereafter<lb/>
a leading authority on this disease and in 1879 was detailed for duty<lb/>
with the Havana Yellow Fever Commission of our first and only National<lb/>
Board of Health. From this time he became a leader in the newly develop-<lb/>
ing science of bacteriology. In 1887 he visited Rio de Janeiro to in-<lb/>
vestigate the claims of Dr. Freire to have discovered the causative agent<lb/>
of yellow fever and later went to Mexico to look into a like claim of Dr.<lb/>
Carmona de Valle, and was able in each case to make a negative finding.<lb/>
In 1889 he was in Havana studying the organism for which Dr. Carlos Finlay<lb/>
made like claims, to which he also gave the quietus with cold and logical<lb/>
precision. <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> But Dr. Finlay's claim to fame did not rest solely<lb/>
on his micrococcus tetragenus febris flavae and we shall hear from him<lb/>
again later in our story. In 1893 <del>his</del><add>Sternberg's</add> standing as a scientist was sufficient<lb/>
to cause his selection as Surgeon General of the Army, and he immediately<lb/>
did two things of far reaching importance. One was to establish the Army<lb/>
Medical School for the advanced training of young medical officers. The<lb/>
other was to wed genius to opportunity by bringing Walter Reed to Baltimore<lb/>
for a period of study in the pathological <del>hospital</del><add>laboratory</add> of the Johns Hopkins<lb/>
Hospital. He was also able, as the Chief of the Medical Corps, to infuse<lb/>
into it a new spirit of professional enthusiasm and scientific ardor which<lb/>
was later to bear good fruit. The Spanish War was for him a period of<lb/>
-2-<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKADA0030"/>
heartbreaking struggle against the narrow and shortsighted spirit which<lb/>
dominated the War Department. Of the $50,000,000 placed at the disposi-<lb/>
tion of the President for the national defense, not a cent was given to<lb/>
the pitifully small and ill equipped Medical Department, and in the law<lb/>
raising a Volunteer Army no enlisted men were provided for the medical<lb/>
service except a few regimental hospital stewards. As the War Department<lb/>
was the adviser both of the President and of Congress as to the needs of<lb/>
its branches, it must bear the responsibility for those sins of omission.<lb/>
In 1900 he made his final and greatest contribution to the study of yellow<lb/>
fever by sending Walter Reed to Cuba at the head of a group of three as-<lb/>
sistants, Carroll<add>,</add> Lazear and Agramonte, primarily to investigate the claims<lb/>
of the bacillus icteriodes of Sanarelli and those of his own bacillus x<lb/>
to be the causative organism of that disease. They had, however, very broad<lb/>
instructions from the Surgeon General authorizing the study of other tropical<lb/>
diseases. The Hon. Elihu Root wrote of him, after his death, &ldquo;The Medical<lb/>
Corps accomplished what it did largely because the man at the top was a<lb/>
pioneer in bacteriology, an advanced worker in preventive medicine and had<lb/>
the enthusiasm and devotion through which science wins victories.&rdquo; Here<lb/>
we must leave this fine old scientist, who retired two years later, stand-<lb/>
ing, as our author says, like Moses on Nebo, to see another enter the Promised<lb/>
Land, after a lifetime of brave and earnest but fruitless effort, <del>to learn the<lb/>
secret of the Sphinx of Yellow Fever.</del> Although he was as Koch said, the<lb/>
&ldquo;father of American bacteriology&rdquo;, it cannot be said that his efforts had<lb/>
contributed aught to solve this particular problem, except in the way of<lb/>
clearing the field of false claimants. Scientific justice will incline to<lb/>
give his place among the great four rather to Dr. Carlos Finlay of Havana,<lb/>
who had also given twenty years of persistent study and experiment to this<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fKADA0040"/>
facinating and elusive quest and who, though he did not have the disci-<lb/>
plined scientific mind and technical skill and training in laboratory<lb/>
technique of Sternberg, yet by a combination of epidemiological reason-<lb/>
ing and what Gorgas called &ldquo;scientific clairvoyance&rdquo;, had reached the<lb/>
right door, but lacked the scientific skill to open it and convince a<lb/>
doubting world. It would appear, also, that though General Sternberg's<lb/>
part in the sending of Reed's Commission to Cuba was an essential step,<lb/>
so was the cordial support given by General Wood, both pecuniary and<lb/>
moral, including, of course, his sharing the responsibility for the ex-<lb/>
periments which were made at the risk of human lives. Fortunately, no<lb/>
lives were lost in Reed's experiments, if we except the accidental in-<lb/>
fection of Lazear, but in the later series conducted by Guiteras and<lb/>
Gorgas, three patients lost their lives in one week, one of them a train-<lb/>
ed nurse. This put an end to further experimental infections and for-<lb/>
tunately Reed's series was so complete in the care with which all condi-<lb/>
tions were covered, that there was no necessity for further jeopardy of<lb/>
human lives. <del>This</del><add>To discover the secret how yellow fever was transmitted and how it could be prevented</add> was reserved by fate for Walter Reed, who combined the<lb/>
scientific training of <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del><add>Sternberg</add> with the scientific imagination of <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> <add>Finlay,</add><lb/>
and whose ability as an epidemiologist had just been brilliantly manifest-<lb/>
ed in the great study with Vaughan and Shakespeare of the typhoid fever<lb/>
epidemics which swept through the Volunteer Camps of 1898.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was born in Gloucester County, Va., September 13, 1851.<lb/>
His father was a Methodist minister, and in his education he shared the<lb/>
financial limitations of the generation which grew up in the South during<lb/>
the lean years which followed the Civil War. But what was lacking in oppor-<lb/>
tunity was made up in real and industry, and he graduated in medicine at<lb/>
the University of Virginia at the age of eighteen, when most young men are<lb/>
-4-<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fKADA0050"/>
preparing to begin a college course. His hospital courses were taken in<lb/>
New York and he entered the Army in 1875 attracted, it seems, by the de-<lb/>
sire for an assured income which would enable him to marry. For eighteen<lb/>
years he followed the nomadic life and vicissitudes of the Army, most of<lb/>
it at isolated frontier posts, without any chilling of his scientific ardor<lb/>
or discouragement of his professional zeal by these unstimulating surround-<lb/>
ings until at length opportunity rewarded patient waiting and an assignment<lb/>
to duty in Baltimore for a year placed the resources of a laboratory within<lb/>
his reach. No man ever made better use of a year, and when a change of<lb/>
station to Dakota came, he was well grounded in pathology and bacteriology.<lb/>
Two years later came his assignment as Curator of the Army Medical Museum<lb/>
in Washington and promotion to the grade of Major, and he followed the Army<lb/>
life no more, but enjoyed the contacts and opportunities of scientific as-<lb/>
sociations in Washington and Baltimore. We have already seen how the oppor-<lb/>
tunity came in 1900 which carried him to Havana at the head of the board<lb/>
now generally known as the Yellow Fever Commission. When Reed discussed<lb/>
with his Chief the objectives of the Commission and mentioned Finlay's<lb/>
mosquito theory as a possible one, General Sternberg replied, &ldquo;You may<lb/>
do it if you want to, but there is nothing in it&rdquo;. The claims of the<lb/>
latest protendants for the evil fame of being the causative agent Bacillus<lb/>
icteroides <del>and</del><add>of</add> Sanarelli and Sternberg's Bacillus x were soon disposed of<lb/>
by the Commission after its arrival in Havana. In fact, most of the work<lb/>
had been already done by Agramonte, who had worked on these organisms in<lb/>
Reed's laboratory in 1898 and who was now in Cuba.</p>
<p>Three lines of research were now considered by the Commission -<lb/>
a study of the bacterial flora of the intestine in this disease and its<lb/>
comparison with the normal flora, studies of cultures from the blood and<lb/>
-5-<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fKADA0060"/>
<add>various organs, and Finlay's mosquito theory.</add><lb/>
Reed decided to take up the last first. His attention had been attracted<lb/>
to an observation made by Dr. Henry R. Carter in 1898 and published with-<lb/>
out interpretation, which was that when a case of yellow fever occurs in<lb/>
an isolated farm house, secondary cases do not occur for two to three weeks<lb/>
but susceptible individuals who then visit the house fall sick in the usual<lb/>
period of incubation, less than seven days. In talking to the writer soon<lb/>
after his arrival in Cuba, Reed mentioned this observation and asked what<lb/>
it meant. Upon receiving an admission of ignorance, he said, with raised<lb/>
forefinger, &ldquo;Don't you see that the difference between the two periods must<lb/>
represent the time passed in the body of some intermediate host? What<lb/>
are the common biting insects in the South <del><unclear>[unclear]</unclear></del> <add><unclear>,</unclear></add> the bed bug, the flea and the<lb/>
mosquito. Now the bed bug and the flea are common in the mountains of the<lb/>
South, where yellow fever never spreads. The disease also disappears when<lb/>
frost comes, though it does not affect these insects. So it is some southern<lb/>
genus of mosquito that we must suspect&rdquo;. <del>So</del> Reed determined to begin work<lb/>
with the common house mosquito of Havana, then called Culex faciatus, but<lb/>
later named Stegomyia fasciata. He was given by Dr. Finlay a saucer on the<lb/>
side of which were some of the minute eggs of this insect which could be<lb/>
hatched into larvae by simply putting water in the saucer. Dr. Finlay<lb/>
told him that this was the insect used in his experiments and he believed<lb/>
it to be the carrier of yellow fever. Dr. Finlay believed that he had, in<lb/>
a few cases, transmitted the disease by their agency, but the period of<lb/>
incubation was far longer than that commonly accepted for yellow fever,<lb/>
and as the subjects of experiment had not been protected <add>from</add> other sources<lb/>
of infection, these experiments were not accepted as a demonstration of<lb/>
his claims. Dr. Lazear was in charge of the propagation and infection of<lb/>
the mosquitos, a difficult task, since a successful laboratory technique<lb/>
-6-<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fKADA0070"/>
for their propagation, infection, feeding and preservation had to be<lb/>
developed. The first experiments, which were made on Lazear, Carroll,<lb/>
<del>and</del> Dr. Pinto, <del>Volunteer Army Surgeon,</del><add>of the Army</add> and others, were made in pro-<lb/>
found secrecy and were all discouraging failures. These happened while<lb/>
Reed was absent, having been called to Washington to arrange for the<lb/>
publication of the Report of the Commission on Typhoid Fever in Military<lb/>
Camps.</p>
<p>On the morning of August 31,1900, Lazear was at the hospital<lb/>
of Camp Columbia, the camp being then in quarantine against the neighbor-<lb/>
ing infected towns of Marianao and Havana. He went into the ward with<lb/>
several mosquitos in test tubes and said, &ldquo;Who will feed my mosquitos&rdquo;.<lb/>
A private of the 7th Cavalry, in hospital for some minor ailment, offered<lb/>
his arm and was bitten. Those mosquitos had been infected and had previous-<lb/>
ly bitten Carroll. On that very day Carroll came down with a severe case<lb/>
which nearly cost him his life, and some days later the Cavalryman, known<lb/>
in the reports as XY, came down with a mild but well marked case. Great<lb/>
was the wonder at the hospital as to where he got his infection, for he<lb/>
had not left the camp and his obliging donation of blood to Lazear's<lb/>
mosquitos was not thought of by any one else as having any connection with<lb/>
the case. Lazear said nothing but wrote to Reed that he felt like a gambler<lb/>
who had the joker up his sleeve. A searching analysis of his notes reveal-<lb/>
ed the cause of the previous failures in the fact that the female mosquito,<lb/>
after having bitten a case of yellow fever, is not able to transmit the<lb/>
infection until after twelve days - the so called period of extrinsic in-<lb/>
cubation. In writing the report of this crucial case, Reed was in an<lb/>
amusing dilemma. It was necessary to make it quite clear that the subject<lb/>
was protected from every other possible source of infection and was sur-<lb/>
rounded by numerous controls who lived under like conditions, except only<lb/>
-7-<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="fKADA0080"/>
that of not having been bitten. Yet it was important not to betray the<lb/>
secret that a member of the Commission had introduced the dreaded in-<lb/>
fection into a closely quarantined camp where were living 1,300 American<lb/>
soldiers, <add>as this would have caused a great row and disciplinary action by the military authorities.</add> So the name of this important contributor to the advancement<lb/>
of science has never been published. Meanwhile the brave and gifted<lb/>
Lazear had, while feeding mosquitos on cases of yellow fever at Las<lb/>
Animas Hospital in Havana, been bitten by a mosquito which came from<lb/>
a dark corner of the ward. He permitted it to fill itself on his hand<lb/>
and noted it as an additional experiment. In due time he was taken down<lb/>
with virulent yellow fever and a week later he died.</p>
<p>Reed, on October 13th made a flying trip to the United States<lb/>
to read his preliminary note on the etiology of yellow fever before the<lb/>
American Public Health Association and to consult his Chief, General<lb/>
Sternberg, as to further procedures. On the 12th of October, the day<lb/>
before he sailed, he went, accompanied by the writer, to see General Wood<lb/>
and to ask his assistance in the larger task which was to come. It was<lb/>
an experience never to be forgotten to see these two men, both great but<lb/>
differing so greatly, Wood massive in frame and unmoved in expression,<lb/>
Reed tall, slender, keen and emotional, as they stood together in the<lb/>
deep embrasure of a window of the palace looking out on the Plaza des Armas.<lb/>
Reed, with that earnest and persuasive eloquence of which he was a master,<lb/>
described the experiments and the results which would flow from them and<lb/>
then said, &ldquo;General Wood, will you give me the money and the authority<lb/>
necessary to continue these experiments&rdquo;? Promptly came the reply of the<lb/>
Military Governor, &ldquo;I will give you $10,000- and if that is not enough,<lb/>
I will give you $10,000 more&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Although the fact that yellow fever could be conveyed by mos-<lb/>
quitos was now demonstrated, much still remained to be done. The belief<lb/>
-8-<lb/>
<pb n="9" id="fKADA0090"/>
was universal that the infection could be carried by clothing and other<lb/>
inanimate objects, known by the general term fomites. The general re-<lb/>
action at this time was expressed by Gorgas, that the mosquito was not<lb/>
the only way. Therefore Reed built a camp called after Lazear, a mile<lb/>
from any habitation, <del><unclear>in</unclear></del> <add>with</add> two separate buildings divided by a little valley.<lb/>
One was clean and new and everything about it was carefully disinfected.<lb/>
Yet it would be an infected house because infected mosquitos were placed<lb/>
in it. The other contained every filthy article taken from cases of yel-<lb/>
low fever which might possibly carry infection, the soiled sheets and gar-<lb/>
ments on which they had died, soiled with black vomit and dejecta, a place<lb/>
of sights and odors which demanded steady nerves and a strong stomach even<lb/>
to enter. Yet American soldiers were found and an Army doctor<add>,</add> <add>Robert P. Cooke,</add> to live<lb/>
in this place of horrors for twenty days, but no case of infection ever<lb/>
came from it. From the other house, however, came case after case of<lb/>
non-immunes who came down after a bite from the infected Stegomyia. The<lb/>
experiments were so ably devised, each with its controls, to elucidate<lb/>
a definite fact, that they stand as a model of exact scientific method.<lb/>
When a similar Commission was formed in the A.E.F. in 1918 to investigate<lb/>
the etiology of trench fever, it looked up and followed closely the pro-<lb/>
cedures of Reed at Camp Lazear.</p>
<p>The riddle of the Sphinx was solved. Gone was the costly ritual<lb/>
of disinfections of merchandise and personal property, the fear of contact<lb/>
with one's neighbors and the shotgun quarantines. Gone was the fighting<lb/>
in the dark against an invisible and unknown enemy. The deductions as to<lb/>
the future methods of warfare were simple and clear and were adopted as soon<lb/>
as indicated by him. In fact, they were immediately put into operation at<lb/>
the military posts and in the Sanitary Department of Havana under its since<lb/>
-9-<lb/>
<pb n="10" id="fKADA0100"/>
famous sanitary officer, Major W. C. Gorgas. The result was the practical<lb/>
abolition of yellow fever in Havana in the summer of 1901 and its entire<lb/>
extinction in that city and throughout the island in 1902. This happy re-<lb/>
sult Reed lived to see and also to enjoy the beginning of popular recog-<lb/>
nition in degrees from Harvard and the University of Michigan. He died<lb/>
<del>as the result of</del> <add>after</add> an operation for appendicitis in Washington, November 22, 1902.<lb/>
His monument in Arlington bears an inscription quoted from President Eliot's<lb/>
citation when he conferred on him the honorary degree of A.M. at Harvard,<lb/>
&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful scourge, Yellow Fever&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Of great interest and value are the sketches of Reed's assistants,<lb/>
Carroll, Lazear and Agramonte, given in this volume, and it is regretted that<lb/>
the limits of a newspaper article do not permit of a review of them. The<lb/>
tragic death of Lazear has already been noted. Dr. Carroll was, in recog-<lb/>
nition of this work, commissioned in the Medical Corps and raised to the<lb/>
grade of Major. He died in Washington, September 16, 1907. The government<lb/>
has given to the widows of Reed, Carroll and Lazear modest pensions which<lb/>
are now quite inadequate for their support. For the fourth and only sur-<lb/>
viving member of the Commission there has never been any reward or official<lb/>
recognition of his services, and this opportunity will not be lost to join<lb/>
Dr. Kelly in reminding the American people of their obligation to Dr.<lb/>
Aristides Agramonte, in the hope that he may, some day, receive from Congress<lb/>
some appropriate reward. Dr. Agramonte was born in Puerto Principe, Cuba,<lb/>
June 3, 1868. His father was the distinguished Cuban patriot, General Eduardo<lb/>
Agramonte, who fell bravely in battle for his country. Dr. Agramonte re-<lb/>
ceived his education in New York and his degree in Medicine from the College<lb/>
of Physicians &amp; Surgeons of that city. In May 1898 he entered the military<lb/>
service and went to Santiago in July and <add>to</add> Havana in December of that year,<lb/>
-10-<lb/>
<pb n="11" id="fKADA0110"/>
when he was engaged in the study of yellow fever. There he was when<lb/>
Reed's Commission was organized. In addition to the work with the Com-<lb/>
mission, he was in charge of the Army Laboratory of Cuba, which post he<lb/>
retained until the withdrawal of the Military Government in 1902, when<lb/>
he remained <add>in Cuba</add> as a professor of the Medical Faculty of the University of<lb/>
Havana. When a Reform Cabinet was appointed by the Cuban Government in<lb/>
June of last year, he was selected for the Secretaryship of Sanitation<lb/>
and Charities. His strong, independent character and straightforward<lb/>
honesty were not qualities conducive to long political life under pres-<lb/>
ent conditions in Cuba, and before the end of the year he resigned to<lb/>
return to his professorial duties.</p>
<p>The interesting career of Surgeon General Gorgas is given in<lb/>
outline in the last chapter, which has the appropriate heading, &ldquo;Reed's<lb/>
Work Made Effective&rdquo;. William C. Gorgas was born October 3,1854 in<lb/>
Mobile, Ala. His father was a distinguished and able man, a West Point<lb/>
graduate, who took the southern side in the Civil War and became Chief<lb/>
of Ordnance in the Confederate War Department. As the Confederacy lacked<lb/>
the skilled workmen and machinery and many of the raw materials for making<lb/>
ordnance, and such arms as they had were of every known calibre and make,<lb/>
the heartbreaking difficulties of his task can be imagined. His energy<lb/>
and resourcefulness in overcoming them were such that the Confederate sol-<lb/>
diers, although lacking in nearly every necessity of life, seemed always<lb/>
sufficiently supplied with arms and ammunition to make their proximity<lb/>
highly dangerous to their adversaries. After the war he became President<lb/>
of the University of the South at Sewance, where his distinguished son<lb/>
received his education. The latter graduated in Medicine at Bellevue<lb/>
College, New York, and then entered the Medical Corps of the Army.<lb/>
-11-<lb/>
<pb n="12" id="fKADA0120"/>
Soon after, while stationed at Fort Brown, Texas, he made the acquaintance<lb/>
of Yellow Jack and acquired immunity from and interest in that disease by<lb/>
experiencing an attack. The Spanish War found him at Fort Barrancas, Fla.,<lb/>
and being an immune and an authority on yellow fever, he was sent to Havana<lb/>
for duty soon after the Americans took control. There he worked bravely<lb/>
and hopefully but without any particular success as far as the control of<lb/>
yellow fever was concerned until the work of the Reed Commission made suc-<lb/>
cess possible. Just at this time, in April 1900, on the eve of his first<lb/>
great success, he was relieved from duty in Havana and ordered to Santiago,<lb/>
and it is interesting to speculate as to what would have been the effect<lb/>
on his future career if this order had been carried out. He was fortunate<lb/>
enough, however, to get it revoked through the assistance of General Fitzhugh<lb/>
Lee and General Leonard Wood. Our author's statement that Gorgas achieved<lb/>
the remarkable success of cleaning up the Island is not, however, entirely<lb/>
accurate as his sphere of activity never, at any time, extended beyond the<lb/>
municipal limits of the City of Havana. The story of Gorgas's fine work in<lb/>
Panama is told briefly but effectively by our author and for a fuller ac-<lb/>
count the reader is referred to Gorgas's own book, &ldquo;Sanitation in Panama&rdquo;.<lb/>
With the triumphal results the American people are well acquainted, but of<lb/>
the difficulties which he encountered, much is still unwritten history.<lb/>
Our author tells how the recall of Gorgas was requested by the Governor<lb/>
and Chief Engineer in 1905 because they did not believe that mosquitos<lb/>
carried yellow fever and malaria, but the Commission was recalled instead.<lb/>
It is also true that on another occasion the Secretary of War had been<lb/>
persuaded that it was necessary to relieve him, but this was prevented by<lb/>
the valiant support of Gorgas by Surgeon General O'Reilly. Thus, a second<lb/>
-12-<lb/>
<pb n="13" id="fKADA0130"/>
time was he saved to fame by the loyalty of his friends. In the end his<lb/>
patience, his suavity, his unshakeable pertinacity conquered all obstacles,<lb/>
human, insect and inanimate. He returned home the most widely known of<lb/>
American physicians and became in 1914 the Chief of his Corps, to which<lb/>
were added promotion, honors, degrees, decorations and the thanks of Congress.<lb/>
When he died in London, July 4,1921, his funeral services were held in<lb/>
Westminster Abbey.</p>
<p>The chapter in this book which is perhaps the most moving and the<lb/>
fullest of human interest is the tenth entitled &ldquo;The Value of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
Work to the World&rdquo;. He tells of the great epidemics which have ravaged<lb/>
the United States and shows how in former days it spread far to the north<lb/>
of its sub-tropical home. It visited Boston as early as 1691 <del>-</del> New York<lb/>
experienced 14 epidemics and Philadelphia 18 prior to the middle of the<lb/>
last century, including the dreadful visitation of 1793, when one-tenth of<lb/>
the population perished. But to the North yellow fever has been an infre-<lb/>
quent and of recent years a rare visitor. For the South, however, who can<lb/>
estimate the retarding influence to its development of the 90 visitations<lb/>
in two centuries, by the loss of valuable lives, the disturbance of trade<lb/>
and business, the quarantines and the repulsion of desirable immigrants?<lb/>
The epidemic of 1878 is estimated to have cost the country more than<lb/>
$15,000,000 in money, but no statistician can estimate the cost in panic<lb/>
fears in disrupted homes and in the tears of widows and orphans. From all<lb/>
these, the work of Reed's Commission in one short year, with the practical<lb/>
applications of its findings, has delivered us.</p>
<p>We shall end this review with the quotation from the book of<lb/>
Esther, which Dr. Kelly has placed at the head of this chapter,<lb/>
-13-<lb/>
<pb n="14" id="fKADA0140"/>
&ldquo;And the king said, What honour and dignity hath been done to Mordecai<lb/>
for this? Then said the king's servants that ministered to him, There<lb/>
is nothing done for him&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Walter Reed left no fortune and his widow receives from this<lb/>
great government an annuity insufficient for her support. This is also<lb/>
true of the widows of Carroll and Lazear.</p>
<p>Biston<lb/>
Oct. 19&sol;23.<lb/>
-14-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
