<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAEE0010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Harry Clemons, September 22, 1939</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAEE0010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo"> Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1939-09-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Clemons, Harry</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Furnas, Joseph C.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Dominguez [Roldan], Francisco</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Musser, John H.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="1939-09-22">September 22, 1939</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAEE0010</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Harry Clemons, September 22, 1939</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean writes Clemons about the Reed - Finlay controversy, and wants to make sure credit is given to both men. Kean submits testimony indicating that Finlay claimed the mosquito as the agent for the spread of yellow fever, and consequently certainly deserves more acknowledgement in U.S. accounts of the yellow fever investigation. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1939-09-22">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Harry Clemons, September 22, 1939</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAEE0010"/>
<opener>
United States Commission<lb/>
for the Erection of a Permanent Memorial to the Memory of<lb/>
Thomas Jefferson<lb/>
1743--1826<lb/>
COMMISSIONERS<lb/>
------<lb/>
UNITED STATES SENATE<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS<lb/>
UTAH<lb/>
CHARLES L. MCNARY<lb/>
OREGON<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS<lb/>
FLORIDA<lb/>
<lb/>
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH<lb/>
VIRGINIA<lb/>
FRANCIS D. CULKIN<lb/>
NEW YORK<lb/>
FRITZ G. LANHAM<lb/>
TEXAS<lb/>
------<lb/>
THOMAS JEFFERSON MEMORIAL<lb/>
FOUNDATION<lb/>
STUART G. GIBSONEY<lb/>
DR. GEORGE J. RYAN<lb/>
DR. FISKE KIMBALL<lb/>
<lb/>
CHAIRMAN<lb/>
STUART G. GIBBONEY<lb/>
<lb/>
VICE CHAIRMEN<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS<lb/>
CHARLES L. MCNARY<lb/>
<lb/>
SECRETARY<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH<lb/>
<lb/>
PRESIDENTIAL COMMISSIONERS<lb/>
T. JEFFERSON COLLIDGE JOSEPH P. TUMULTY<lb/>
BRIG. GEN. JEFFERSON RANDOLPH KEAN<lb/>
-----<lb/>
EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE<lb/>
STUART G. GIBBONEY<lb/>
ELBERT D. THOMAS<lb/>
CHARLES L. MCNARY<lb/>
CHARLES O. ANDREWS<lb/>
HOWARD W. SMITH<lb/>
FRANCIS D. CULKIN<lb/>
FRITZ G. LANHAM<lb/>
JOSEPH P. TUMULTY<lb/>
DR. FISKE KIMBALL<lb/>
<lb/>
<add>2804 N ST. N. W.</add><lb/>
<del>HOUSE OFFICE BUILDING</del><lb/>
WASHINGTON. D.C.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1939-09-22">Sept. 22, 1939</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>My dear Mr. Clemons:</salute>
</opener>
<p>It seems unreasonable to expect you to take<lb/>
interest in matters that happened nearly four decades<lb/>
ago in Cuba, when such great and terrible events<lb/>
are occurring every day in Europe. But I excuse myself<lb/>
with the fact that this correspondence, which was<lb/>
started by your calling my attention to the article<lb/>
on Moran by Furnas in the Saturday evening Post,<lb/>
is of some historical importance as bearing on a<lb/>
matter which has, in Cuba at least, become a sub-<lb/>
ject of controversy. I would like that the great<lb/>
Library of which you are the head should contain an<lb/>
authoritative statement of the facts in the case<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAEE0020"/>
Reed and Finlay page 2<lb/>
of the relative credit which should be given Reed<lb/>
and Finlay.</p>
<p>It happens that I am, so far as I know, the only<lb/>
person now living who knew well both Major Walter<lb/>
Reed and Dr. Carlos J. Finlay and who was present<lb/>
in an official position of importance at the time and<lb/>
place of occurrence of the events concerned. Therefore<lb/>
I should like to place in your library a statement which<lb/>
will assist future students to judge fairly the re-<lb/>
spective merits of these two eminent and admirable men<lb/>
in bringing to light the true method of transmission<lb/>
of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>I became acquainted with Dr. Finlay during the<lb/>
First Intervention 1898 - 1902 when he was the leading<lb/>
Cuban member of the Yellow Fever Diagnosis Board<lb/>
of which Gorgas also was a member the latter,<lb/>
being at that time the Chief Sanitary Officer of the<lb/>
City of Havana. During the Second Intervention 1906 - 1909<lb/>
Dr. Finlay was Chief Sanitary Officer of the Island<lb/>
and President of the National Board of Health and<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Diagnosis Board. During all<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAEE0030"/>
Reed and Finlay page 3<lb/>
this period I was constantly associated with him and<lb/>
was, as the American Government's representative, his<lb/>
superior officer under the modest title of Advisor<lb/>
to the Sanitary Department. Our relations were most<lb/>
cordial and I became much attached personally<lb/>
to this kindly and learned old man. He let me<lb/>
take home and study his note books in which were<lb/>
carefully noted the records of his experiments in<lb/>
the transmission of Yellow Fever by the bites of<lb/>
mosquitos, extending over many years prior to the<lb/>
Spanish American War. He had correctly fixed<lb/>
the blame on the true culprit mosquito, the common<lb/>
house mosquito of the tropics, then called Culex<lb/>
Fasciatus, Fabr. and later Stegomyia. Now it<lb/>
is called A&euml;des&sol;Aegypti. He had also developed<lb/>
a technique for transporting them in test tubes<lb/>
and applying them to the skin of the infected patient<lb/>
and of the receptive non immune. He supported<lb/>
his theory of transmission by this mosquito with<lb/>
sound epidemiological arguments and believed<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fKAEE0040"/>
Reed and Finlay page 4<lb/>
that he had made a number of experimental infections<lb/>
in this way. In this however it was easy to see<lb/>
that he was mistaken, as I pointed out to him, for not<lb/>
one of his cases got by the <hi>two hurdles</hi> which were<lb/>
discovered by Lazear and Reed, after the latter's study<lb/>
of H. R. Carter's observations on what he afterwards<lb/>
called intrinsic and extrinsic incubation of the<lb/>
infection. The first unsuspected hurdle was that<lb/>
the yellow fever patient can only infect the mosquito<lb/>
in the <hi>first three days</hi> of the disease. When he<lb/>
begins to get yellow and the diagnosis is clear<lb/>
the blood is no longer infective. The second <hi>hurdle</hi><lb/>
was equally upsetting to the unwarned experimenter.<lb/>
The mosquito after having bitten the yellow fever<lb/>
patient, if applied to the nonimmune volunteer<lb/>
at once or for twelve or more days thereafter,<lb/>
will <hi>not cause infection</hi>. If the insect is applied<lb/>
after twelve, or in cool weather, fifteen days<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fKAEE0050"/>
Reed and Finlay page 5<lb/>
to a non immune an attack follows.</p>
<p>Dr. Finlay had no suspicion of these hurdles<lb/>
and so he did not produce any experimental case.<lb/>
Some of his cases, in which their movements were<lb/>
not controlled, afterwards were attacked but only<lb/>
after a much longer period than was found in<lb/>
properly controlled experiments. That Dr.<lb/>
Finlay kept his faith in his theory unshaken<lb/>
by the unbelief and ridicule of all his pro-<lb/>
fessional brethren was an instance, as Gorgas<lb/>
used to say, of &ldquo;wonderful scientific clair-<lb/>
voyance&rdquo;.</p>
<p>When Major Reed arrived in Cuba on June 25, 1900<lb/>
to organize his Yellow Fever Board there was<lb/>
not a doctor in Havana, so far as I know, who<lb/>
had any faith in Finlay's mosquito theory of the<lb/>
transmission of yellow fever. But even before<lb/>
the publication of the Camp Lazear experiments<lb/>
the cases of Carroll and Lazear and of Private<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fKAEE0060"/>
Reed and Finlay page 6<lb/>
W. H. Dean, Seventh Cavalry had convinced the members<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Board and those who kept abreast<lb/>
of the facts of the truth of the Finlay Theory. Ac-<lb/>
cordingly Dr. Juan Guiteras, the Director of<lb/>
Las Animas Hospital, where the yellow fever<lb/>
cases were treated, got up a dinner in honor of<lb/>
Dr. Finlay to celebrate the verification by the<lb/>
Reed Board of the Finlay theory. It may be said<lb/>
that there was no Cuban physician at that time<lb/>
better known and more esteemed by the medical<lb/>
profession in both Cuba and the United States<lb/>
than Dr. Guiteras. Born in Cuba, educated<lb/>
in the United States, he had given up a professor-<lb/>
ship at the University of Pennsylvania to re-<lb/>
turn to his native land after its liberation.<lb/>
About sixty of the leading doctors in Havana<lb/>
were present as were General Wood the Military<lb/>
Governor, the members of the Reed Board, Colonel Gorgas<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fKAEE0070"/>
Reed and Finlay page 7<lb/>
and some other Americans. I sat on Dr. Finlay's right<lb/>
and, as he spoke English perfectly, had much pleasant<lb/>
talk with him. Dr. Guiteras, who presided, made a<lb/>
Charming address, reviewing Dr. Finlay's work and<lb/>
Major Reed's recent demonstration of the agency<lb/>
of the mosquito, as claimed for so many years by<lb/>
Finlay. He said that as regards the credit to<lb/>
be given to Finlay and Reed respectively he thought<lb/>
it was quite like the discovery of the mosquito trans-<lb/>
mission of malaria. This was announced an-<lb/>
thoritatively by Manson, supported by good epidemiological<lb/>
reasons, and later Major Ronald Ross of the<lb/>
British Medical Service in India made the laboratory<lb/>
demonstration of Manson's theory, tracing the de-<lb/>
velopment of the malarial parasite in the mos-<lb/>
quito after she had bitten a case of malaria<lb/>
and then its transmission by the bite of the mosquito<lb/>
to another person. Guiteras said that the<lb/>
scientific world had found no difficulty in giving<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="fKAEE0080"/>
Reed and Finlay page 8<lb/>
due credit to each of them and so it should be with<lb/>
Finlay and Reed. Both of them seemed quite satis-<lb/>
fied with this statement of the case, as did the<lb/>
other guests and Dr. Finlays face beamed with<lb/>
happiness. I have often used this analogy<lb/>
in discussing the matter with Cubans and de-<lb/>
scribed this dinner in my letter to Mr. Moran<lb/>
to which he refers in the fifth paragraph of<lb/>
the letter enclosed. This dinner was given<lb/>
in Havana on December 22, 1900, three days<lb/>
before Moran was taken sick with yellow fever.<lb/>
But Private Kissinger of the Hospital Corps, U.S. Army<lb/>
and three Spaniards had been infected experiment-<lb/>
ally, under rigidly controlled conditions at Camp<lb/>
Lazear. The diagnosis had been verified in<lb/>
each case by the Havana Yellow Fever, <add>Diagnosis</add> Board,<lb/>
most if not all of the members of which were<lb/>
present at this dinner.</p>
<pb n="9" id="fKAEE0090"/>
<p>Reed and Finlay page 9</p>
<p>When Americans feel irritated at exhibitions of<lb/>
partisanship in a question of medical history, as in<lb/>
the case of Dr. Dominguez Roldan as described<lb/>
in paragraph 5 of Mr. Moran's letter enclosed<lb/>
they should remember that Finlay's name is often<lb/>
omitted or slightingly referred to in American<lb/>
Medical publications. I have recently observed<lb/>
that in the excellent treatise on Internal Medicine<lb/>
by Dr. John H. Musser of Tulane University<lb/>
(Lea &amp; Febiger, Phila. 1932) under Yellow Fever<lb/>
page 184 Finlay's name does not appear in<lb/>
the 38 lines devoted to history.</p>
<p>I have had no communication from Dr. Philip<lb/>
H. Hench of the Mayo Clinic (see par. 4 of<lb/>
Moran's letter). If he should visit the<lb/>
Alderman Library, I hope that you will<lb/>
call his attention to this correspondence.</p>
<pb n="10" id="fKAEE0100"/>
<p>Reed and Finlay page 10</p>
<p>It is regretted that the lack of a typist has<lb/>
obliged me to put this communication in long hand,<lb/>
a form which is not attractive to the reader and<lb/>
is certainly very laborious to the writer.</p>
<p>If at any time you should have occasion<lb/>
to have copies of the correspondence made<lb/>
I would be grateful if you would send me<lb/>
a carbon copy as I have none of either<lb/>
letter.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely,</salute>
<signed>Jefferson Randolph Kean</signed>
Inclosing letter of<lb/>
Mr. John J. Moran<lb/>
Havana. Aug. 28, 1939.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
