<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAEG0090">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Harry Clemons to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 19, 1947</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Clemons, Harry</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAEG0090</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1947-11-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Jordan, Harvey E.</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1947-11-19">November 19, 1947</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAEG0090</idno>
<title>Letter from Harry Clemons to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 19, 1947</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Clemons relates a talk by Hench where Kean was enthusiastically mentioned many times. Clemons is trying to get Hench to donate his Reed Collection to the University of Virginia instead of the Mayo Clinic. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1947-11-19">
<head>Letter from Harry Clemons to Jefferson Randolph Kean, November 19, 1947</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAEG0090"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1947-11-19">19 November 1947</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>My dear General Kean:</salute>
</opener>
<p>If your system of what somebody -- perhaps<lb/>
it was Mark Twain -- called &lsquo;mental telegraphy&rsquo; was in operation<lb/>
Monday afternoon from four thirty to five forty-five, the results<lb/>
must have been warming. For Dr. Philip Hench was addressing a<lb/>
group of about one hundred and fifty persons (including President<lb/>
Darden, Dean Jordan, and representatives from the Charlottesville<lb/>
community and the Alderman Library) in the amphitheatre of the<lb/>
University Hospital on details of his investigations concerning<lb/>
Walter Reed and Yellow Fever. It was an address which commanded<lb/>
attention as completely as did your address and that of the<lb/>
surprised Sergeant Moran on a famous occasion several years ago.<lb/>
The wires to 2804 N Street must have been warm because you were<lb/>
not only mentioned a score of times but you were pointed out in<lb/>
several pictures which were projected on a screen -- including a<lb/>
delightful individual photograph of Major Kean. The address was<lb/>
received with notable enthusiasm.</p>
<p>Doctor Hench had lent to the Alderman Library a number<lb/>
of the documents of his collection, and those with a selection<lb/>
from the material which you so generously donated are now on<lb/>
exhibition in the Library. We are angling for Doctor Hench's<lb/>
collection. But it seems that he has placed the Mayo Hospital<lb/>
before the University of Virginia on his list of possible loca-<lb/>
tions, and that our chance depends largely on a possible dis-<lb/>
inclination of the Mayo Hospital authorities to begin a policy<lb/>
of adding historical collections. Doctor Hench states that so<lb/>
far the tendency at Rochester has been to concentrate on point-<lb/>
ing forward and not backward.</p>
<p>Your very fine letter of November twelfth has been<lb/>
read and reread, and it is being held out for reading by Emily<lb/>
and George Vest when they are here this coming weekend. The<lb/>
good counsel about matters of living in Bermuda is most timely,<lb/>
for they are scheduled to start thither by plane next week -- <lb/>
about November twenty-eighth. They have recently been in New<lb/>
York to study shipping matters as a part of the indoctrination<lb/>
course -- and have incidentally been attending one or two of<lb/>
the meetings of the United Nations.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKAEG0100"/>
<p>General Kean &nbsp;&nbsp; 19 November 1947 &nbsp;&nbsp; Page Two</p>
<p>I am concerned that you have been troubled by a chance<lb/>
disappearance of the recent issue of <hi>The Military Surgeon</hi>.<lb/>
You are so generous in donating your personal copies that you<lb/>
must not let such generosity inject such anxieties. One thing<lb/>
on which we are really authorities here is on the tendency of<lb/>
periodicals and books to slip into hiding and occasionally to<lb/>
achieve a complete disappearance. So we hope you will remember<lb/>
that we should much prefer to arrange here for the replacement<lb/>
of a missing copy than to have you bothered by an incident<lb/>
like this.</p>
<p>It has embarrassed me no little that a copy of the<lb/>
recent <hi>Virginia Spectator</hi> has fallen into your hands. That<lb/>
write-up and an astonishing editorial which Mr. Virginius<lb/>
Dabney wrote for the <hi>Richmond Times-Dispatch</hi> one day last<lb/>
August have produced in me a strange mixture of surprise, con-<lb/>
fusion, and gratification. It is certainly unusual for the<lb/>
humdrum work of a librarian (and his Van Dyke beard) to be<lb/>
given such notice. I do not forget that the surprising attitude<lb/>
of this university community was the initial cause of one of the<lb/>
very pleasantest chapters of my librarian life. For it was the<lb/>
chance juxtaposition of a Raven Society election to you and of<lb/>
a Raven award to me that started our acquaintance one fair eve-<lb/>
ning when we sat together at the head table of a Raven banquet<lb/>
at the Farmington Country Club.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Cordially yours,</salute>
<signed>Harry Clemons</signed>
Librarian<lb/>
To General Jefferson R. Kean<lb/>
2804 N Street, N.W.<lb/>
Washington (7), D. C.<lb/>
HC:NG<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
