<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAFA0170">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert U. Patterson, December 17, 1931</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAFA0170</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo"> Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1931-12-17</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Patterson, Robert U.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Driscoll, Daniel L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Smith, William F.</name>
<name type="person">Root, Eilhu</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Fort McIntosh (Tex.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1931-12-17">December 17, 1931</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAFA0170</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert U. Patterson, December 17, 1931</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean strongly believes that Roger Post Ames should not be included in the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1931-12-17">
<head>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Robert U. Patterson, December 17, 1931</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAFA0170"/>
<p><hi>In re Record of Roger Post Ames</hi>.</p>
<p>He infected Pvt Daniel P Driscoll <unclear>Co F</unclear> 26 Inf at<lb/>
Fort McIntosh Texas who was admitted to Hosp Nov. 9, 1903<lb/>
to duty Nov. 30, 1903 but did not recover his <hi>health</hi> &amp;<lb/>
was disch. S. C. D. Sept 26, 1904 for chronic Gastritis following y.f.<lb/>
This wanton and unauthorized jeopardy of human life should weigh<lb/>
heavily against any reward to him or his heirs.</p>
<p>17 December, 1931.</p>
<p>MEMORANDUM for General Patterson:</p>
<p>In re: Record Roger Post Ames, M.D. in Yellow Fever<lb/>
Experimentation at Camp Lazear, Cuba, 1900-1901, with supporting<lb/>
evidence.</p>
<p>This brief is very cleverly prepared but on considering the<lb/>
bases of it, they seem to be founded on assumptions rather than on<lb/>
facts. The following are the statements on which the arguments are<lb/>
based:</p>
<p>II. A. <hi>He was directly in charge of the Experimental<lb/>
Camp Lazear</hi>.</p>
<p>This is true but his duties there were purely administrative<lb/>
and could have been performed by any good sergeant of five years service.</p>
<p>B. <hi>This command was special and not regular duty</hi>.</p>
<p>This seems to be a distinction without a difference. Dr. Ames'<add>s</add><lb/>
duty at Camp Columbia at this time<add>,</add> as well as before and after<add>,</add> was to<lb/>
look after yellow fever cases. He had very little to do at this particular<lb/>
time, and the work at Camp Lazear came naturally and simply into the field<lb/>
of his assignments.</p>
<p>C. <hi>Assisted in securing volunteers for the experimentations</hi>.</p>
<p>Doubtless he did. A number of persons not included in the<lb/>
yellow fever Roll of Honor did the same.</p>
<p>D. <hi>Rendered scientific services of great value upon the<lb/>
success of which depended the success of the entire<lb/>
experiment</hi>.</p>
<p>This claim is, in my opinion, absolutely without any basis in<lb/>
fact. The experiments would have gone on just the same if Dr. Ames<lb/>
had never come to Cuba.</p>
<p>III. A. <hi>Major Reed depended upon Dr. Ames' scientific knowledge<lb/>
of diagnosis and treatment of Yellow Fever</hi>.</p>
<p>Dr. Ames was undoubtedly called in for the diagnosis and treat-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAFA0180"/>
- 2 -<lb/>
ment of all the cases of experimental yellow fever in the Camp<lb/>
Lazear series. The diagnosis, however, was confirmed officially in<lb/>
each case by the Yellow Fever Board from Havana, headed by Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Finlay. <add>and Col W. C. Gorgas.</add></p>
<p>As to the care and treatment of yellow fever cases, it was<lb/>
testified by The Surgeon General in explaining to the Military Committee<lb/>
the necessary limitations of the list of those who should appear on the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Roll; that services in connection with the professional care,<lb/>
diagnosis, and treatment could not be considered, as a large number of<lb/>
doctors, military and civil, had taken part in the care and treatment of<lb/>
yellow fever patients during the epidemic in Quemadas and other epidemics<lb/>
in Cuba. These persons included Medical officers, nurses, non-commissioned<lb/>
officers, and privates of the Hospital Corps, and other persons who came<lb/>
in contact with yellow fever patients, and the clothing, stools, etc. used<lb/>
by them, all of which were believed to be infectious. Unless such a<lb/>
limitation were maintained, the number of applications would be so great<lb/>
that the honor of being on the Roll would be diluted to the disappearing<lb/>
point.</p>
<p>IV. A. <hi>A non-immune, Dr. Ames exposed himself and contracted<lb/>
the fever in carrying out special duties in the advance-<lb/>
of science</hi>.</p>
<p>The statement that Dr. Ames contracted yellow fever in February,<lb/>
1901 (which is supported by the Hospital records) has always been a complete<lb/>
mystery to me. Dr. Ames always claimed to be an immune, and was selected<lb/>
to take charge of the yellow fever cases at Camp Columbia, and to be in<lb/>
charge of the little experimental camp <hi>because he was immune</hi>. This is<lb/>
definitely stated by Dr. Reed. It is my belief that he did have yellow<lb/>
fever in New Orleans at the time stated by him. If the sickness which<lb/>
he had in February, 1901 was in fact yellow fever, it was undoubtedly one<lb/>
of the very rare instances of a second attack. In any event, the illness<lb/>
was a very mild one and he was detained in hospital, I believe, only five<lb/>
days. The experiments at Camp Lazear were at this time completed, and the<lb/>
nature of this illness has no bearing on the question of the conquest of<lb/>
yellow fever.</p>
<p>See also on this subject letter of Surgeon General Ireland to<lb/>
General William R. Smith, U.S. Military Academy, West Point, N.Y., dated<lb/>
12 December, 1930, on file in S.G.O. See also unfavorable report of<lb/>
the Secretary of War on Senate Bill 2817 introduced February, 1928 by<lb/>
Senator Sheppard of Texas, and introduced into the House by Representative<lb/>
Buchanan of Brenham, Texas.</p>
<pb n="3" id="fKAFA0190"/>
<p>The writer of this memorandum acquired yellow fever in<lb/>
contact with the sick in the performance of his duty. He was also<lb/>
officially connected with the Yellow Fever Board in an administra-<lb/>
tive way, and initiated the first proceedings for the warfare<lb/>
against mosquitoes in Cuba. He was also mentioned by the Secretary<lb/>
of War, Mr. Elihu Root, in his report for 1902 for his services in<lb/>
connection with yellow fever. Yet it has never occurred to him,<lb/>
and would never be claimed by him, that he is entitled to membership<lb/>
on the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor.</p>
<p>J.R.K.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
