<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAFA0240">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from the Secretary of War to David A. Reed, March 19, 1932</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAFA0240</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1932-03-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Reed, David A.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Pinto, A. S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1932-03-19">March 19, 1932</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAFA0240</idno>
<title>Letter from the Secretary of War to David A. Reed, March 19, 1932</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This letter states that Pinto's share in the experiments had little or no value, and he should not be included in the Yellow Fever Roll of Honor. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1932-03-19">
<head>Letter from the Secretary of War to David A. Reed, March 19, 1932</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAFA0240"/>
<opener>
<hi>COPY FOR GENERAL KEAN</hi><lb/>
Draft only, submitted for signature of Secretary of War - March 18, 1932.<lb/>
Dr A.S. Pinto<lb/>
Fair Copy<lb/>
WAR DEPARTMENT<lb/>
Washington<lb/>
Assoc'n Military Surgeons, U.S.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1932-03-19">MAR 19 1932</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Secretary-Editor's Office<lb/>
Honorable David A. Reed,<lb/>
Chairman, Committee on Military Affairs,<lb/>
United States Senate,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Senator:</salute>
</opener>
<p>Careful consideration has been given to the Senate bill No. 206,<lb/>
Seventy-second Congress, first session, &ldquo;to recognize the high public<lb/>
service rendered by Doctor A. S. Pinto, and the bravery displayed by him<lb/>
in connection with the discovery of the cause and means of transmission<lb/>
of yellow fever,&rdquo; upon which the views of the War Department were re-<lb/>
quested by your indorsement of reference dated February 24, 1932.</p>
<p>By act of Congress approved February 28, 1929, the Secretary of<lb/>
War is authorized and directed &ldquo;in special recognition of the high pub-<lb/>
lic services rendered and disabilities contracted in the interests of<lb/>
humanity and science as voluntary subjects for the experimentations dur-<lb/>
ing the yellow fever investigations in Cuba&rdquo; to publish annually in the<lb/>
Army Register a roll of honor, and the officers and men whose names were<lb/>
to be placed on the said roll were specifically stated in that act. The<lb/>
part taken by them in the experiments is fully set forth in the reports<lb/>
of the Yellow Fever Board which are published in Senate Document 822,<lb/>
Sixty-first Congress, third session.</p>
<p>Dr. Alva S. Pinto served as Contract Surgeon in the Army from<lb/>
October 3, 1898, to April 4, 1901. He was stationed at Columbia Barracks,<lb/>
near Havana, Cuba, from December 2, 1898, to October 10, 1900. He had<lb/>
no other service in Cuba. When he left Cuba he sent to the Philippines<lb/>
for duty, and served there as Captain and Assistant Surgeon, U. S. Volun-<lb/>
teers, until February 1, 1903.</p>
<p>The investigations referred to in the act of February 28, 1929,<lb/>
were made by a board of which Major Walter Reed, Surgeon, U.S.A., was<lb/>
president, appointed by the Secretary of War May 24, 1900 (SO No. 122,<lb/>
<unclear>AGO</unclear> that date). The board assembled in Cuba in June 1900, and conducted<lb/>
several series of experiments to discover the agency for the transmission<lb/>
of the disease. The first series was conducted during the period August 2<lb/>
to some time in October, 1900, while Major Reed was necessarily absent in<lb/>
the United States. Upon his return to Cuba he instituted a second and<lb/>
more elaborate series which began November 20, 1900, at an experimental<lb/>
camp called Camp Lazear. A third series was instituted the following<lb/>
fall (1901).</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKAFA0250"/>
<p>-2-</p>
<p>Prior to the investigations by this board various theories had<lb/>
been suggested as to the means by which yellow fever is communicated from<lb/>
man to man, among them whether by bodily contact, by contact with the<lb/>
excreta of the sick, or by the bite of an infected mosquito. Dr. Carlos<lb/>
Finlay, of Havana, had several years before advanced the postulate that<lb/>
the mosquito was at least one agency of transmission; but numerous ex-<lb/>
periments made by him on that line had been entirely negative and his<lb/>
theory in August 1900 was generally discredited by the profession. Never-<lb/>
theless, there was sufficient speculative or conjectural basis to warrant<lb/>
further experiments either to confirm it on the one hand, or to exclude it<lb/>
from further consideration on the other. To that end, on August 11, 1900, <lb/>
Dr. Lazear, a member of the board, made the first experiment, consisting<lb/>
of mosquito bites on 9 persons, including himself and Dr. Pinto. The names<lb/>
of the other 7 are not shown on the records and are now unknown. All of<lb/>
these, like the Finlay tests, were unsuccessful (see page 16, Senate<lb/>
Document 822, above), as no adequate measures had then been taken to<lb/>
assure the conditions, which were later discovered, necessary for mosquito<lb/>
transmission of this disease. In other words, at the time these tests<lb/>
were made they were under a theory not generally believed, and these who<lb/>
submitted to them had no serious apprehension of danger therefrom. But<lb/>
within the next four weeks three cases of the disease followed subsequent<lb/>
mosquito bites under conditions which convinced Major Reed that the mos-<lb/>
quito was a transmitting agent, and led to the second series of more<lb/>
rigorous experiments beginning November 20, 1900, which left no doubt in<lb/>
the premises.</p>
<p>Dr. Pinto took no part in those later experiments, having left Cuba<lb/>
on October 10. What he did was to allow himself on August 11 to be bitten<lb/>
by a mosquito, when mosquito transmission was a discredited theory and the<lb/>
bite thereof was believed by most to offer no hazard. In point of fact,<lb/>
the mosquito which bit him was perfectly harmless, and as shown by his<lb/>
medical history he suffered no disability whatever from the bite. The<lb/>
words of the bill referring to his &ldquo;high public service&rdquo; and &ldquo;the bravery<lb/>
displayed by him in incurring disabilities in the interest of humanity&rdquo;<lb/>
are unsupported by any facts of record in the Department.</p>
<p>These who took part in the experiments of November 20 and later, by<lb/>
submitting themselves to the bites of infected mosquitoes, after the theory<lb/>
of mosquito transmission under certain conditions had been practically<lb/>
determined as outlined in Major Reed's preliminary report, did, however,<lb/>
consciously and most heroically put their lives in hazard, and in the view<lb/>
of the Department stand on an entirely different footing. The act of<lb/>
February 28, 1929, was intended to honor them for their bravery and re-<lb/>
ward them for the suffering consequent thereon. To include others within<lb/>
its scope whose bravery was in no sense conspicuous and who incurred no<lb/>
suffering and no disabilities whatever would be to disparage and cheapen<lb/>
the honors and rewards heretofore conferred in this regard.</p>
<p>Dr. Pinto's share in the experiments which have been of such great<lb/>
benefit to mankind was, for the reasons hereinbefore indicated, of little<lb/>
or no value. Certainly it was of no greater value than that of each of<lb/>
the 7 unknowns who were also bitten by harmless mosquitoes on August 11.<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAFA0260"/>
-3-<lb/>
To pass this law, singling his out for special recognition, would at once<lb/>
pave the way for similar measures in behalf of the other 7, without any<lb/>
means of identifying or limiting the persons claiming to be among them.<lb/>
Nor would it be unlikely, considering how these things go, for a whole<lb/>
multitude to spring up, claiming similar recognition who, by reason of<lb/>
service in Cuba at the time the experiments were going on, were bitten by<lb/>
mosquitoes, or had yellow fever, or perhaps attended yellow fever patients,<lb/>
but who contributed in no real sense to the epoch-making experiments which<lb/>
have brought this dread disease under control.</p>
<p>In the Department's view the door to these extraordinary honors<lb/>
should not be opened to those who rendered no extraordinary service and<lb/>
made no measurable contribution to the work, but should admit only the<lb/>
three categories of persons covered in the existing law (or their depend-<lb/>
ants) namely, First, Members of the Yellow Fever Board; Second, Those who<lb/>
offered themselves for experiment by mosquito or blood inoculation and<lb/>
<hi>suffered attacks of yellow fever in consequence</hi>; Third, <hi>Those who took part<lb/>
in the infected bedding experiments</hi>.</p>
<p>Doctor Pinto's services as a contract surgeon and medical officer<lb/>
were wholly creditable to him, but, as in the case of thousands of others,<lb/>
in no wise beyond the call of duty, and do not entitle him in the opinion<lb/>
of the Department to the distinction and annuity proposed by S. 206. It<lb/>
is recommended, therefore, that that bill be not favorably considered.</p>
<closer>
<salute>Sincerely yours,</salute>
<signed>Secretary of War.</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
