<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAFA0200">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 20, 1932</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Moran, John J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAFA0200</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1932-01-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Stark, Alexander N.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Frances F.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Fitzgerald, C. C.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, Sidney Coe</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1932-01-20">January 20, 1932</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAFA0200</idno>
<title>Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 20, 1932</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Moran discusses his contact with the playwright Sidney Coe Howard. He suggests that Kean's impartiality would be best suited to help Howard. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1932-01-20">
<head>Letter from John J. Moran to Jefferson Randolph Kean, January 20, 1932</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAFA0200"/>
<opener>
COMPA&Ntilde;IA SUNOCO DE CUBA, S.A.<lb/>
AGENTES EXCLUSIVOS DE<lb/>
SUN OIL COMPANY<lb/>
SUN OILS<lb/>
CABLE Y } &ldquo;SUNOCO&rdquo;<lb/>
TELEGRAFO }<lb/>
CLAVE BENTLEY<lb/>
TELEFONO U-6148<lb/>
-----<lb/>
SUCURSAL:<lb/>
AGUILERA BAJA NO. 52<lb/>
SANTIAGO DE CUBA.<lb/>
SUNOCO<lb/>
DESTILADO AL MERCURIO<lb/>
<dateline>
AVENIDA MENOCAL NO. 102-A<lb/>
HABANA,<lb/>
<date value="1932-01-20">Jan. 20, 1932.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Gen. Jefferson R. Kean,<lb/>
Army Medical Museum,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear General:-</salute>
</opener>
<p>My sincere thanks for your letter of January<lb/>
11th. Please accept my hearty congratulations upon pro-<lb/>
motion, after retirement as I take it, to the rank of<lb/>
Brigadier General. I was unaware of the fact until I<lb/>
received your letter. No one rejoices more than I, your<lb/>
loyal and devoted humble servant since 1899, that you have<lb/>
been accorded a recognition which does you justice in part<lb/>
at least. I shall never forget how you helped me out in<lb/>
1899-1900 when Captain Quinton began to make things dis-<lb/>
agreeable for me at Guanajay Barracks and you arranged for<lb/>
my transfer to Columbia Barracks under Major Stark who<lb/>
treated me more as a friend than as a subordinate. In the<lb/>
years that you have devoted to the cause of those connected<lb/>
with the yellow fever experiments, the debt of gratitude I<lb/>
owe you has grown. I am sure you are convinced of my<lb/>
sincerity.</p>
<p>With reference to Mrs. Agramonte's case. Last<lb/>
evening, at our regular monthly meeting of the Legion, I<lb/>
showed your letter to Major C. C. Fitzgerald and suggested<lb/>
to him, as I had done on a previous occasion, that he write<lb/>
the National Delegate in Washington of the Veterans of the<lb/>
Spanish-American War to get in touch with as one of those<lb/>
deeply interested in having Congress extend to Mrs. Agramonte<lb/>
the benefits which her late husband enjoyed under the Act of<lb/>
February 28, 1929. The Cuban unit of the Spanish-American<lb/>
War Veterans got busy on behalf of Mrs. Agramonte shortly<lb/>
following the doctors death. Major Fitzgerald promised<lb/>
that he would write the National representative of the SAWV<lb/>
to get in touch with you, so you may expect to hear from him.<lb/>
Few Members of Congress have come to Cuba this year but Major<lb/>
Fitzgerald, prominent here in the American Legion as well as<lb/>
in the Spanish-American War Veterans, as well as myself, will<lb/>
be on the lookout for any members of the National Legislature<lb/>
who may drop in on us here.</p>
<p>COMPA&Ntilde;IA <unclear>LITOGRAFICA</unclear> DE LA HABANA.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKAFA0210"/>
<p><hi>Gen. J. R. Kean</hi>.&nbsp;-- 2 --&nbsp;<hi>Jan. 20, 1932</hi>.<lb/>
</p>
<p>On December 24th I received a letter from Mr. Sidney<lb/>
Howard, Author-Dramatist, informing me that on your recommend-<lb/>
ation he had talked with Mr. Parker about me and my connection<lb/>
with the yellow fever experiments, and that he (Mr. Howard)<lb/>
was desirous of coming to Havana for an interview with me and<lb/>
would make the trip providing he could depend on my assistance<lb/>
and cooperation in the preparation of his &ldquo;story on yellow<lb/>
fever&rdquo;. I replied on the same day I received his letter and<lb/>
told him that I was entirely at his service in a mission which<lb/>
I considered laudable, material interest aside, but my letter<lb/>
evidently went astray so that, to my great surprise and chagrin<lb/>
I learned from his letter dated January 14th, between the lines<lb/>
of which I could see that he was pained and injured at my fail-<lb/>
ure to reply to his original letter, that my amiable reply to<lb/>
his letter had not yet reached him. I can imagine that his<lb/>
thoughts of me in the interim were not any too complimentary,<lb/>
while I was entirely innocent of snobbishness or false pride<lb/>
in connection with the object of his letter and mission. I<lb/>
cabled him at once and forwarded a copy of my reply to his<lb/>
original letter by air mail, receiving a cable from him day<lb/>
before yesterday that he would be here on or about Friday, the<lb/>
22nd instant. Have suggested to him that his notes should be<lb/>
gone over by you. Perhaps he has already done so as he refers<lb/>
to you as his friend. I also suggested that you were the one<lb/>
impartial, living observer of the experiments, since all the<lb/>
rest of us are inclined to view our particular share in the<lb/>
experiements as paramount to the other man's participation and<lb/>
share in same; that you know the underlying motives of each of<lb/>
us who volunteered no matter what our individual opinions may<lb/>
be. I am sure you are sufficient of a psychologist to qualify<lb/>
in the premises. I want you to know that I include myself and<lb/>
my share in the experiments in this opinion. If, therefore,<lb/>
Mr. Howard visits you after he has had an opportunity to hear<lb/>
my side of the story, I am sure you will be able to pick out<lb/>
anything which he has written as coming from me which might<lb/>
sound to you like a deviation from the truth. I would not want<lb/>
you to spare me and should not feel in the least resentful as<lb/>
a result of your &ldquo;checking and correcting&rdquo; any statement of<lb/>
mine. I do not claim infallibility, and while my memory is<lb/>
quite clear on what happened during those memorable two or<lb/>
three months, I cannot lay claim to absolute unselfishness<lb/>
when relating what I know. I have always tried to be honest<lb/>
to myself and all the others concerned in this matter. While<lb/>
your recollection of certain incidents may be in error, you<lb/>
are by and large the one man best qualified to pass final<lb/>
judgment on anything purporting to deal with the actual facts<lb/>
surrounding the experiments and those connected with them.<lb/>
For myself, I bow to that judgment.</p>
<p>Please remember me most kindly to Mr. Parker and<lb/>
accept the homage and loyalty of</p>
<closer>
<salute>Your humble servant,</salute>
<signed>John J. Moran</signed>
PLEASE OVERLOOK<lb/>
MY VOLUBILITY.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
