<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAFA0100">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Congressional Bill #S. 2817, 71st Congress, 2d Session, December 13, 1929</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAFA0100</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1929-12-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Cook, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Olsen, William</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Sheppard, Morris</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, N. May</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, Marie D.</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1929-12-13">December 13, 1929</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAFA0100</idno>
<title>Congressional Bill #S. 2817, 71st Congress, 2d Session, December 13, 1929</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This amendment proposes the inclusion of Roger Post Ames with those honored in H.R. 13060. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-12-13">
<head>Congressional Bill #S. 2817, 71st Congress, 2d Session, December 13, 1929</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAFA0100"/>
<p>OFFICE COPY</p>
<p>71ST CONGRESS<lb/>
2D SESSION<lb/>
-----------------</p>
<p>S. 2817<lb/>
-----------------</p>
<p>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES<lb/>
DECEMBER 13 (calendar day, DECEMBER 21), 1929</p>
<p>Mr. SHEPPARD introduced the following bill; which was read twice and referred<lb/>
to the Committee on Military Affairs<lb/>
-------------------------------<lb/>
&check;</p>
<p>A BILL</p>
<p>To amend an Act entitled &ldquo;An Act to recognize the high public<lb/>
service rendered by Major Walter Reed and those associated<lb/>
with him in the discovery of the cause and means of trans-<lb/>
mission of yellow fever,&rdquo; approved February 28, 1929, by<lb/>
including <hi>Roger P. Ames</hi> among those honored by said Act.</p>
<p>1 <hi rend="italic">Be it enacted by the Senate and House of Representa-</hi><lb/>
2 <hi rend="italic">tives of the United States of America in Congress assembled</hi>,<lb/>
3 That the Act entitled &ldquo;An Act to recognize the high public<lb/>
4 service rendered by Major Walter Reed and those associated<lb/>
5 with him in the discovery of the cause and means of trans-<lb/>
6 mission of yellow fever,&rdquo; approved February 28, 1929, be,<lb/>
7 and the same is hereby, amended by inserting between the<lb/>
8 names &ldquo;Aristides Agramonte&rdquo; and &ldquo;James A. Andrus&rdquo;<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAFA0110"/>
2<lb/>
1 the name &ldquo;Roger P. Ames,&rdquo; so that the Act as amended<lb/>
2 will read as follows:</p>
<p>3 &ldquo;That in special recognition of the high public service<lb/>
4 rendered and disabilities contracted in the interest of human-<lb/>
5 ity and science as voluntary subjects for the experimenta-<lb/>
6 tions during the yellow-fever investigations in Cuba, the<lb/>
7 Secretary of War be, and he is hereby, authorized and di-<lb/>
8 rected to publish annually in the Army Register a roll of<lb/>
9 honor on which shall be carried the following names: Walter<lb/>
10 Reed, James Carroll, Jesse W. Lazear, Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
11 <hi>Roger P. Ames</hi>, James A. Andrus, John R. Bullard, A. W.<lb/>
12 Covington, William H. Dean, Wallace W. Forbes, Levi E.<lb/>
13 Folk, Paul Hamann, James F. Hanberry, Warren G. Jerne-<lb/>
14 gan, John R. Kissinger, John J. Moran, William Olsen,<lb/>
15 Charles G. Sonntag, Clyde L. West, Doctor R. P. Cooke,<lb/>
16 Thomas M. England, James Hildebrand, and Edward<lb/>
17 Weatherwalks, and to define in appropriate language the<lb/>
18 part which each of these persons played in the experimenta-<lb/>
19 tions during the yellow-fever investigations in Cuba; and in<lb/>
20 further recognition of the high public service so rendered<lb/>
21 by the persons hereinbefore named, the Secretary of the<lb/>
22 Treasury is authoirzed and directed to cause to be struck for<lb/>
23 each of said persons a gold medal with suitable emblems,<lb/>
24 devices, and inscriptions, to be determined by the Secretary<lb/>
25 of the Treasury, and to present the same to each of said<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAFA0120"/>
3<lb/>
1 persons as shall be living and posthumously to such repre-<lb/>
2 sentatives of each of such persons as shall have died, as shall<lb/>
3 be designated by the Secretary of the Treasury. For this<lb/>
4 purpose there is hereby authorized to be appropriated the<lb/>
5 sum of $5,000; and there is hereby authorized to be appro-<lb/>
6 priated, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise<lb/>
7 appropriated, such amounts annually as may be necessary<lb/>
8 in order to pay to the following-named persons during the<lb/>
9 remainder of their natural lives the sum of $125 per month,<lb/>
10 and such amount shall be in lieu of any and all pensions<lb/>
11 authorized by law for the following-named persons: Private<lb/>
12 Paul Hamann; Private John R. Kissinger; Private William<lb/>
13 Olsen, Hospital Corps; Private Charles G. Sonntag, Hos-<lb/>
14 pital Corps; Private Clyde L. West, Hospital Corps; Private<lb/>
15 James Hildebrand, Hospital Corps, Private James A. Andrus,<lb/>
16 Hospital Corps; Mr. John R. Bullard; Doctor Aristides<lb/>
17 Agramonte; Private A. W. Covington, Twenty-third Bat-<lb/>
18 tery, Coast Artillery Corps; Private Wallace W. Forbes,<lb/>
19 Hospital Corps; Private Levi E. Folk, Hospital Corps;<lb/>
20 Private James F. Hanberry, Hospital Corps; Doctor R. P.<lb/>
21 Cooke; Private Thomas M. England; Mr. John J. Moran,<lb/>
22 and the widow of Private Edward Weatherwalks.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="document" n="1929-12-13">
<head>Congressional Bill #S. 2817, December 13, 1929</head>
<pb n="4" id="fKAFA0130"/>
<p>71ST CONGRESS }<lb/>
2D SESSION }</p>
<p>S. 2817</p>
<p>============================</p>
<p>A BILL</p>
<p>To amend an Act entitled &ldquo;An Act to recog-<lb/>
nize the high public service rendered by<lb/>
Major Walter Reed and those associated<lb/>
with him in the discovery of the cause and<lb/>
means of transmission of yellow fever,&rdquo; ap-<lb/>
proved February 28, 1929, by including<lb/>
Roger P. Ames among those honored by<lb/>
said Act.</p>
<p>==============================</p>
<p>By Mr. SHEPPARD</p>
<p>==============================</p>
<p>DECEMBER 13 (calendar day, DECEMBER 21), 1929<lb/>
Read twice and referred to the Committee on Military<lb/>
Affairs</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
