<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAFF0010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Carlos J. Finlay to Jefferson Randolph Kean, February 6, 1909</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Finlay, Carlos J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAFF0010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1909-02-06</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Lebredo, Mario G.</name>
<name type="person">Barnet, E. B.</name>
<name type="person">Lopez del Valle, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Rensoli, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Zayas, Alfredo</name>
<name type="person">Rensoli, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Davis, Harry A.</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1909-02-06">February 6, 1909</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAFF0010</idno>
<title>Letter from Carlos J. Finlay to Jefferson Randolph Kean, February 6, 1909</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Finlay informs Kean that nothing has turned up to lessen the belief that Cuba is free of yellow fever, and reports of personnel changes in Cuba's Sanitary Department. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1909-02-06">
<head>Letter from Carlos J. Finlay to Jefferson Randolph Kean, February 6, 1909</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAFF0010"/>
<opener>
80<lb/>
Dr Charlos J. Finlay.<lb/>
(Cuba's grand old man)<lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, <date value="1909-02-06">February 6 1909</date>
</dateline><lb/>
Lieut. Colonel J.K. Kean U.S.A. M.c.<lb/>
Surgeon-General's Office<lb/>
Washington, D.C.<lb/>
<salute>My dear Colonel</salute>
</opener>
<p>Please to excuse my writing in type for fear of<lb/>
taxing too much your ingenuity in deciphering my scrawl and to<lb/>
accept my apologies for not having gone on board to take leave of<lb/>
Mrs. Kean and yourself the day of your departure<add>,</add> as I had intended,<lb/>
owing to an indisposition of no consequence but which kept me sub-<lb/>
sequently two days at home.</p>
<p>I hope you had a pleasant trip and are now once more comfort-<lb/>
ably settled in your home.</p>
<p>You will be glad to know that nothing has turned up to lessen<lb/>
our belief that we are really free from yellow-fever. Two cases report<lb/>
ed as suspects in Santiago de Cuba have proved negative, and Doctor<lb/>
Guiteras <add>intends</add> to send Dr. Agramonte and Lebredo to Oriente for a little<lb/>
while to look carefully into the situation in that part of the Island.<lb/>
The Sanitary Department has been much less subjected to wholesale<lb/>
renewal of the personnel than other Departments, but the few that<lb/>
have been changed are of vast importance. I refer to Barnet and Lopez<lb/>
del Valle. The former has been given a position as Special Inspector<lb/>
in the Secretary's Office while Lopez del Valle has changed places<lb/>
with Dr. Rensoli as Chief of the Tuberculosis Dyspensary. Othe<add>r</add> changes<lb/>
had been spoken of but somehow or other they have not been carried <lb/>
into effect.</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKAFF0020"/>
<p>2</p>
<p>The inaugural session of the Junta Nacional de Sanidad y Beneficen<lb/>
cia was held February 3d. I need not give you the names of the 13<lb/>
active members of which it is composed as I suppose you already know<lb/>
them, and the list has been published in most of our local papers. At<lb/>
the second meeting, the following day, I was pleased tp observe that<lb/>
in the course of the debate Dr. Alfredo Zayas supported with warmth<lb/>
and free from any partisanship certain remarks made by Dr. Casuso in<lb/>
opposition to the views maintained by the Secretary of the Departmt.</p>
<p>Feb. 7th. - I am informed that Dr. Claudio Delgado has been request-<lb/>
ed to present his resignation, but has refused to do so stating that<lb/>
he prefers to await his formal dismissal from the Service.</p>
<p>I have not seen Dr. Guiteras these last few days but I fear that<lb/>
if he is to be deprived of valuable employees at the caprice of poli-<lb/>
ticians he will find his position anything but a bed of roses, and<lb/>
I cannot but congratulate myself for being out of the business, even<lb/>
if I have to put up with certain privations which I knew were to be<lb/>
<unclear>expected</unclear>. He will, I am sure, miss very much the valuable help that<lb/>
Dr. Barnet would have given him, and although Dr. Rensoli is undoubted-<lb/>
ly clever and bright he lacks the personal knowledge which Dr. Lopez<lb/>
del Valle possesses of every nook and corner of the district of Havana<lb/>
and his long experience in the Sanitary Department, having held res-<lb/>
ponsible positions in it since Major Davis' time (1899).</p>
<p>Please to present my kindest regards to Mrs, Kean and believe<lb/>
me, my dear Colonel,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours very sincerely</salute>
<signed>Carlos J. Finlay</signed>
Amistad n&deg; 94 (Altos)<lb/>
Habana.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
