<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAGA0400">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report to the Provisional Governor, by Carlos J. Finlay, November 1, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Finlay, Carlos J.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAGA0400</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc> 
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-11-01</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Barnet, E. B.</name>
<name type="person">Lopez del Valle, Jose A.</name>
<name type="person">Thomason, H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Fauntleroy, P. C.</name>
<name type="person">McMillan, [s.n.]</name>
<name type="person">Delgado, Claudio</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>5 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-11-01">November 1, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAGA0400</idno>
<title>Report to the Provisional Governor, by Carlos J. Finlay, November 1, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Finlay discusses the nationalization of the Cuban Sanitary Department, developments in sanitary procedures regarding mosquitoes and yellow fever, and the control of tuberculosis. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-11-01">
<head>Report to the Provisional Governor, by Carlos J. Finlay, November 1, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAGA0400"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">Havana, November 1, 1908</hi>.</p>
<p>TO THE PROVISIONAL GOVERNOR.</p>
<p>Havana.</p>
<p>Sir:</p>
<p>In compliance with instructions received through the Ad-<lb/>
viser of this Department, I have the honor to transmit herewith<lb/>
the reports of the Administrative Officer (Jefe de Despacho) of<lb/>
the National Sanitary Department, Dr. E. B. Barnet, and of the<lb/>
Local Health Officer of the district of Havana, Dr. Jos&eacute; A. L&oacute;-<lb/>
pez del Valle, relative to the work done in their respective sec-<lb/>
tions.</p>
<p>NATIONALIZATION OF THE CUBAN SANITARY DEPARTMENT</p>
<p>As was to be expected, the beneficial influence of the nation-<lb/>
alization of this Department manifested itself soon after the<lb/>
rules prescribed in your important Decree No. 894 of August,<lb/>
1907, were carried into effect, by a marked decrease in the num-<lb/>
ber of deaths caused by preventable diseases, such as are listed<lb/>
in Bertillon's group of &ldquo;General Diseases&rdquo;, as well as under<lb/>
the headings of &ldquo;Diarrhoea and Enteritis under two years of<lb/>
age&rdquo;, for the control of which constant vigilance on the part<lb/>
of the health officers to provide good milk for the children in<lb/>
their respective districts, is an essential condition. In Cuba yet<lb/>
another cause of death must be included among the preventable<lb/>
ones, namely; Tetanus in new born infants. I have on former<lb/>
occasions called attention to the large number of deaths record-<lb/>
ed under this heading in Cuba, and it is undoubtedly due to the<lb/>
lack of aseptic precautions in the management of the umbillical<lb/>
cord. In point of fact, several years ago, at my solicitation, the<lb/>
presence of the tetanus bacillus was found in five out of six sam-<lb/>
ples of the cotton-wick (pabilo) which, since time immemorial<lb/>
has been used by incompetent or ignorant assistants for ligating<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAGA0410"/>
442<lb/>
the cord of new born infants. In order to remedy this evil, the<lb/>
Sanitary Department has been receiving from a reliable firm of<lb/>
the United States a regular supply of carefully prepared pack-<lb/>
ages containing, in perfectly aseptic conditions, all the material<lb/>
needed for successive dressings of the cord, with ample instruc-<lb/>
tions for the unitiated regarding its employment. These pack-<lb/>
ages are freely distributed to poor expectant mothers or their<lb/>
midwives, and most of our drug stores have them for sale.</p>
<p>In comparing the death returns from the three aforesaid<lb/>
classes of preventable caused, during the twelve months from<lb/>
October 1st, 1907 to September 30th, 1908, in the whole terri-<lb/>
tory of the republic, with those corresponding to the previous<lb/>
similar period (October 1st, 1906 to September 30th, 1907),<lb/>
we find:</p>
<p>For &ldquo;General Diseases&rdquo; 7230 deaths as againts 7860, for<lb/>
&ldquo;Enteritis under two years&rdquo; 4174 as against 5889, and for &ldquo;Te-<lb/>
tanus neonatorum&rdquo; 762 as against 899, showing a total of 2502<lb/>
lives apparently saved, which may fairly be credited to the im-<lb/>
proved conditions which have prevailed in the whole territory<lb/>
in consequence of the nationalization of all the sanitary services.</p>
<p>THE PREVALENCE OF YELLOW FEVER SINCE OCTOBER 31, 1907</p>
<p>The total number of cases of yellow fever occurring in the<lb/>
republic since the date of my last report has been 79, with 29<lb/>
deaths. That report which described the occurrence of this dis-<lb/>
ease from the date of re-infection of the territory of the republic<lb/>
in October, 1905 to October 31, 1907, gave an account of the epi-<lb/>
demic outbreak at Cienfuegos in August, September and Oc-<lb/>
tober, 1907, and of its control by the measures taken under the<lb/>
immediate charge of Captain H. D. Thomason, U. S. A., who<lb/>
was appointed a special commissioner of the Department for<lb/>
that work. Thirteen sporadic cases occurred in Cienfuegos be-<lb/>
tween the 1st of November, 1907 and the 21st of January, 1908.<lb/>
In the nine months since that date, there has been no re-appear-<lb/>
ance of the disease in Cienfuegos. The last occurrence of yellow<lb/>
fever in the province of Santa Clara was in the city of Santa<lb/>
Clara where six cases occurred between the 9th and 18th of Feb-<lb/>
ruary, five of them being soldiers of the American garrison. In<lb/>
the province of Camag&uuml;ey, for the first time, a small focus de-<lb/>
clared itself in the town of Ciego de Avila near the Santa Clara<lb/>
boundary. Ciego de Avila is one of the stations of the Central<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAGA0420"/>
443<lb/>
Railroad where passengers going both ways stop to take a meal,<lb/>
and the infection may have been brought by some ambulatory<lb/>
case traveling on the train. Three cases occurred, the patients<lb/>
being attacked on October 31st, November 6th and November<lb/>
13th, so that the mosquitos causing these cases were probably<lb/>
all infected from a common source, none of the cases being sec-<lb/>
ondary. Captain Thomason was temporarily transferred to Cie-<lb/>
go de Avila, and by his vigorous and comprehensive measures<lb/>
of fumigation and the prevention of mosquito breeding, the<lb/>
focus was promptly and completely extinguished, so that no<lb/>
other case occurred in Ciego de Avila or the province of Ca-<lb/>
mag&uuml;ey. A case occurring in Cienfuegos on December 5th, was<lb/>
found to have come from Santiago de Cuba during its pe-<lb/>
riod of incubation, and evidence was thus afforded of the exist-<lb/>
ence of a focus in the latter city. A very careful sanitary inspec-<lb/>
tion of Santiago, however, failed to localize the focus of infec-<lb/>
tion, or to discover any other case until the 7th of January. Cap-<lb/>
tain Thomason was transferred to station in Santiago and given<lb/>
supervision of the city, and his management proved so far suc-<lb/>
cessful that between December and June when the infection was<lb/>
finally stamped out,, only five sporadic cases developed, one in<lb/>
each of the months of January, February, April, May and June.<lb/>
To this focus in Santiago, however, must be credited the infec-<lb/>
tion among the miners in the Daiquir&iacute; district, where twenty<lb/>
cases appeared in June and July, besides one in a neighboring<lb/>
mine (Concordia) belonging to Firmesa. Strict quarantine by<lb/>
land and sea having been established and energetic fumigations<lb/>
with close vigilance, under the direction of Major Fauntleroy,<lb/>
M. C., U. S. A., as Special Commissioner, extinguished this focus<lb/>
so that no other case has developed there since the 31st of July.<lb/>
Finally at Antilla (northern coast of Oriente province), another<lb/>
case having been infected in the last week of August, the same<lb/>
measures were taken, including quarantine. After this, the only<lb/>
other case recorded was a non-immune Spaniard, found sick<lb/>
with yellow fever at Havana on the 7th of September. Since this<lb/>
last date, in view of the radical measures that have been adopted<lb/>
and the care with which all non-immunes with fever are<lb/>
watched, there is every reason to believe that the yellow fever in-<lb/>
fection has now been stamped out. With reference to our success<lb/>
in our present yellow fever campaign, I beg respectfully to call<lb/>
the attention of the Provisional Governor to Captain Thomason's<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fKAGA0430"/>
444<lb/>
remarkable record as Special Commissioner of this Department<lb/>
at Cienfuegos, Ciego de Avila and Santiago de Cuba.</p>
<p>Our experience in the last three years, during which the<lb/>
Cuban Sanitary Department for the first time, has been called<lb/>
upon to deal with a serious yellow fever infection, has brought<lb/>
to light two important improvements in our former methods for<lb/>
fumigating infected buildings, and for controlling the breeding<lb/>
of mosquitoes in open water containers from which the access of<lb/>
those insects can not well be prevented.</p>
<p>The old process of preparing buildings for fumigation by<lb/>
papering all the openings and chinks in the interior, inclusive<lb/>
of the roof when the latter is not mosquito proof, was open to<lb/>
serious objections. First, the time involved, and secondly, the<lb/>
chasing out of the mosquitoes into the open by the men working<lb/>
inside, displacing the furniture, etc. Instead of this, Captain<lb/>
Thomason, M. C. U. S. A., when he took charge of the infected<lb/>
district of Cienfuegos last year, suggested that these objections<lb/>
might be obviated by simply covering the whole building or<lb/>
several of them together, with an air tight covering of canvas.<lb/>
And this has proved so advantageous that it has now been gen-<lb/>
erally adopted whenever the necessary material can be provided<lb/>
without delay.</p>
<p>For preventing mosquitoes from breeding in open water<lb/>
containers, an old friend and collaborator, Dr. Claudio Delga-<lb/>
do, suggested as the result of his personal observations in Uni&oacute;n<lb/>
de Reyes, in collaboration with the Local Health Officer, two<lb/>
years ago that this might be done by introducing in the contain-<lb/>
ers small fresh water fishes, which he asserted, would greedly<lb/>
devour the larvae and pupae. His suggestion was strengthened<lb/>
the following year by independent observations in the British<lb/>
West Indies, especially at Barbadoes, and when Dr. Delgado's<lb/>
suggestion was given a fair trial, the results were found most<lb/>
satisfactory. In the city of Camag&uuml;ey, in particular, where in<lb/>
the absence of a regular water supply, the generality of the in-<lb/>
habitants rely on rain water collected in very large earthen-<lb/>
ware jars of which several are kept in each house, the employ-<lb/>
ment of small fish, vulgarly called &ldquo;guajacones&rdquo; (Cyprinodon-<lb/>
tidi, gen. Gambusia and girardinus, Poey), has proved most suc-<lb/>
cesful in the hands of the Local Health Officer, Dr. McMillan;<lb/>
so much so, that whereas the proportion of houses free from<lb/>
mosquito breeding places had previously been only fifteen per<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fKAGA0440"/>
445<lb/>
cent of all the inspected houses, after the introduction of the<lb/>
guajacones, the number free from breeding places has been in-<lb/>
creased to 98 per cent.</p>
<p>TUBERCULOSIS</p>
<p>For the control of tuberculosis, a National Sanatorium, &ldquo;La<lb/>
Esperanza&rdquo;, which has been in contemplation and for which<lb/>
an admirable site had been chosen under General Wood's gov-<lb/>
ernment, has now been erected in conformity with the most im-<lb/>
portant modern requisites.</p>
<p>For the district of Havana also, a tuberculosis dispensary<lb/>
has been expressly constructed with a well organized service,<lb/>
which was very much needed in this district. It will be described<lb/>
in the report of Dr. L&oacute;pez del Valle, Health Officer of this<lb/>
district.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,</p>
<p>(Sig.) CARLOS J. FINLAY,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Chief of Sanitation</hi>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
