<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMB0120">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Obituary for Leonard Wood, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [1927?]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMB0120</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1927-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Wood, Leonard</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Harvard University</name>
<name type="place">Massachusetts</name>
<name type="place">New Hampshire</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Plattsburg</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1927-00-00">1927</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMB0120</idno>
<title>Obituary for Leonard Wood, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [1927?]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean gives an account of Wood's military accomplishments. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1927-00-00">
<head>Obituary for Leonard Wood, by Jefferson Randolph Kean, [1927?]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMB0120"/>
<p>Historical V(d) Published in <unclear>Mil. Surgeon</unclear></p>
<p>LEONARD WOOD - PHYSICIAN - SOLDIER - ADMINISTRATOR.</p>
<p>* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
<p>Major General Leonard Wood, U.S. Army Retired, Governor General of the<lb/>
Philippine Islands, died in Boston August 7th after an operation for the removal<lb/>
of a cerebral tumor, which has recurred after successful removal by operation seventeen<lb/>
years ago.</p>
<p>He was born in Winchester, New Hampshire, on October 9, 1860, the son<lb/>
of a physician, but grew up and received his education in Massachusetts. He<lb/>
graduated in medicine at Harvard in 1884 and a year later joined the Army. There he<lb/>
served first as a contract surgeon, while awaiting the occurrence of a vacancy in<lb/>
the Medical Corps. It was not long before he attracted attention by those qualities<lb/>
of physical and intellectual vigor, energy and ability which were destined to push<lb/>
him forward in a career of varied and great accomplishments.</p>
<p>These are recited in the official order of the War Department announcing<lb/>
his death which is given below in full as a valuable historical document which should<lb/>
be available for reference in the files of this magazine. Brief reference will be<lb/>
made, however, to several episodes of his career which are not told in the official<lb/>
order. It is a striking evidence of his force of character that it should have so<lb/>
impressed Theodore Roosevelt that when the latter was offered the command of the<lb/>
Rough Riders <del>that dominant person</del><add>he</add> preferred to serve under Leonard Wood rather than<lb/>
over him. The war brought him promotion, and the success of his government of Santia-<lb/>
go led to the Governor Generalship of Cuba.</p>
<p>In three years of extraordinary activity he had brought that devastated<lb/>
land to prosperity, wealth and health. His moral and financial support of Walter<lb/>
Reed made possible the remarkable series of experiments on men at Camp Lazear which<lb/>
caused the scientific world to accept the theory of Finlay and led to the sanitary<lb/>
triumphs of Gorgas at Havana and Panama. So forceful a character must needs make<lb/>
-1-<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMB0130"/>
-2-<lb/>
some bitter enemies as well as a host of loyal friends and devoted followers. His<lb/>
transfer from the Medical Corps to the Line as Brigadier General occurred while he<lb/>
was Governor General of Cuba, and was without opposition save the muttered grumblings<lb/>
of a few <hi>vieux moustaches</hi>. But when in 1903 he had become the Senior Brigadier and<lb/>
his promotion to Major General was in order, it was bitterly contested in the Senate.<lb/>
General Wood saw the storm coming when he received orders to go to the Philippines<lb/>
and suggested to the Secretary of War that he wait to confront his enemies. But<lb/>
the generous reply of Secretary Root was &ldquo;You go where your duty calls you. I will<lb/>
defend you.&rdquo; And no one had ever an abler champion, so that finally even the<lb/>
doughty Senator Hanna was forced to admit defeat. General Wood's administration as<lb/>
Chief of Staff was marked by the clear headed efficiency which was in all positions<lb/>
characteristic of him.</p>
<p>But the military work which was doubtless the most far reaching in its<lb/>
benefit to the army and the nation was his <add>recognition</add> of the fact that the training of<lb/>
officers was vital to the creation of a great army and that they would be needed by<lb/>
thousands. The administration was opposed to any steps of military preparation, and<lb/>
so General Wood had to undertake on his own initiative and responsibility, and with<lb/>
only such means as he could personally command, this Herculean task. The Plattsburg<lb/>
camps appealed to the college bred men of the country, and at their own expense they<lb/>
came in hundreds to <add>learn the</add> discipline of military training. The Citizens' Mili-<lb/>
tary Training Camps of today, although intended for a younger and less finished class<lb/>
of men, must be recognized as the outgrowth of the Plattsburg idea.</p>
<p>When the War Department sought to check his activities by transferring him<lb/>
from New York to Charleston, they soon found that the result was only to transfer<lb/>
the preaching of the gospel of preparedness to new fields. His nights were spent in<lb/>
sleeping care and his days in conferences and meetings, and soon training camps began<lb/>
to appear in the South also. When war came he was given command of the 89th Division<lb/>
and devoted himself to its training with his habitual energy and contagious enthusiasm</p>
<p>-2-</p>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMB0140"/>
<p>- 3</p>
<p>It would hardly be imagined from the phrase in G.O. No. 13 &ldquo;and while commanding<lb/>
the 89th Division he was with the American forces in France in the winter of 1917 -<lb/>
1918&rdquo;, that one of the two great disappointments of his life came to him in the fact<lb/>
that he was not permitted to take his division to France, but was relieved from its<lb/>
command as it was embarking. The <del>phrase</del><add>sentence</add> quoted refers to his visit there as an<lb/>
observer several months before, and it was at this time that he received a wound<lb/>
in the axilla from the bursting of a Stokes mortar by which his aid was also<lb/>
wounded and several French officers were killed or wounded.</p>
<p>The other great disappointment was his failure to receive the Republican<lb/>
nnomination for President in 1920 by a few votes when he was undoubtedly the most<lb/>
popular candidate with the party and the people at large, but was defeated by a<lb/>
political man<unclear>c</unclear>euvre of the professional politicians who controlled the convention.</p>
<p>His last great task was to check the course of extravagance and maladministration<lb/>
which had followed the turning over of the <add>Philippine</add> government to the Filipinos by his<lb/>
predecessor in office. This was a difficult and ungrateful task which he undertook<lb/>
and carried on with patient determination <add>and for which he sacrificed the honorable and well paid position of Provost of the <unclear>U. of Peru.</unclear></add> One successful incident of his administration<lb/>
which must appeal to the members of this Association, was the change for the better<lb/>
which was wrought in the great leper colony at Culion, from which in the past year<lb/>
1200 patients have been discharged as cured, and only twenty per cent failed to show<lb/>
improvement.</p>
<p>It is doubtless as the great proconsul of our government in the two Indies that<lb/>
General Wood will be best known to history.</p>
<p>J.R. KEAN</p>
<p>This is followed <add>in the Mil. Surgeon</add> by G. O. no. 13. W. D. which sketches<lb/>
Gen. Woods Army Career.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
