<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMC0310">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Congressional Record, 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> session, May 18, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Bland, Schuyler O.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMC0310</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-05-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Pharaba W.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Lemuel S.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Emilie Lawrence</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Vaughan, Victor C.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Benigno, Antonio</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Manson, Patrick</name>
<name type="person">King, A. F. A.</name>
<name type="person">Howard, L. O.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Robert E.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-05-18">May 18, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMC0310</idno>
<title>Congressional Record, 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> session, May 18, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document recounts the speech given by Kean at the dedication of Belroi, the birthplace of Walter Reed. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1928-05-18">
<head>Congressional Record, 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Congress, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> session, May 18, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMC0310"/>
<p>Congressional Record</p>
<p>========================================</p>
<p>SEVENTIETH CONGRESS, FIRST SESSION</p>
<p>========================================</p>
<p>Dr. Walter Reed</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>EXTENSION OF REMARKS<lb/>
OF<lb/>
HON. SCHUYLER O. BLAND<lb/>
OF VIRGINIA<lb/>
IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Friday, May 18, 1928</hi></p>
<p>Mr. BLAND. Mr. Speaker, Dr. Walter Reed was a world<lb/>
hero whose work brought immeasurable blessing to mankind.</p>
<p>On Saturday, October 15, 1927, there was dedicated at Belroi,<lb/>
Gloucester County, Va., the birthplace of Dr. Walter Reed.<lb/>
The house in which Doctor Reed was born is still standing,<lb/>
and it has been restored as nearly as possible to the same con-<lb/>
dition that it was in when Doctor Reed was born there on the<lb/>
13th day of September, 1851. His father was a minister of<lb/>
the Methodist Church and was stationed on the Gloucester<lb/>
circuit at the time of Walter Reed's birth.</p>
<p>This property was purchased by the Walter Reed Memorial<lb/>
Commission for the encouragement of research work upon the<lb/>
direction of the Medical Society of Virginia. Funds were<lb/>
raised by popular subscription. The house has been restored<lb/>
and when sufficient funds have been raised it is intended to<lb/>
complete the restoration of the entire property, to furnish it<lb/>
in keeping with the period when Doctor Reed was born, to<lb/>
inclose the property, to plant shrubs and flowers, and to pre-<lb/>
serve the property as a national shrine in such condition as<lb/>
to make it a fitting memorial to the hero who was born there.</p>
<p>At the dedication on October 15, 1927, there was delivered a<lb/>
notable address by Col. Jefferson Randolph Kean, Medical<lb/>
Corps, United States Army, retired, editor of the Military<lb/>
Surgeon, Washington, D. C., former chief surgeon at Gen.<lb/>
Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters in Cuba when Doctor Reed's ex-<lb/>
periments were conducted. Colonel Kean was an intimate<lb/>
friend of Dr. Walter Reed and had personal knowledge of<lb/>
Doctor Reed's work. His speech is a valuable historical con-<lb/>
tribution to the life, character, and service of Doctor Reed<lb/>
and deserves preservation in the records of the Congress of<lb/>
the country, which Doctor Reed served with such distinction<lb/>
and upon which he reflected such glory by his contribution to<lb/>
humanity.</p>
<p>I have sought and obtained permission to extend my remarks<lb/>
in the RECORD by publishing the speech made by Colonel Kean<lb/>
at the dedication of Dr. Walter Reed's birthplace.</p>
<p>Colonel Kean said:</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, in the lives of great men two places have in<lb/>
all ages and among all peoples had a peculiar interest and sacred<lb/>
quality--that where they are born and that where, when life is ended,<lb/>
their remains are laid to rest in the last sleep. It was my sad duty<lb/>
on a November day in 1902 to select the spot where Walter Reed should<lb/>
rest on a beautiful hillside in Virginia, overlooking the Potomac and<lb/>
the Capitol, in that silent city where the soldier dead of the Republic<lb/>
sleep in their thousands in the consecrated fields that once belonged to<lb/>
the great captain, Robert Lee. I feel it therefore a great privilege<lb/>
and honor to be present also at this spot where Walter Reed was born.</p>
<p>Sir William Osler said in one of his addresses:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Of the altruistic instincts, veneration is not the most highly devel-<lb/>
oped at the present day; but I hold strongly with the statement that<lb/>
it is the sign of a dry age when the great men of the past are held in<lb/>
light esteem.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is my hope and my belief that Virginia may never be dry in that<lb/>
sense.</p>
<p>To the Romans the word &ldquo;pietas,&rdquo; which is our word piety, meant<lb/>
dutifulness, and it had reference not only to their attitude to their<lb/>
parents but to the spirits or <unclear>genii</unclear> of their dead and to the cult of<lb/>
the quaint little gods the Lares and Penates who presided over the<lb/>
family hearth and the domestic affairs. Their cult consisted in<lb/>
offerings of flowers or dainties from the table, and it has survived the<lb/>
ages in the offerings of flowers which we lay upon the graves of those<lb/>
we love.</p>
<p>It is to this Roman belief that he was always the object of observa-<lb/>
tion and solicitude by spiritual beings which he had been taught to<lb/>
108117--4627<lb/>
venerate that gave to the Roman character, in the opinion of Pater,<lb/>
its steadiness and regard for duty and dignity in all the affairs of life.<lb/>
I like to believe that we Virginians are in this sense a pious people,<lb/>
that we hold in high esteem the great men of the past, that in our<lb/>
lives we are not unmindful of them, and that we would like so to live<lb/>
as not to shame them. This is a cult which brings the great men of<lb/>
the past into our lives, and will perpetuate their virtues and reproduce<lb/>
their qualities. It is such a feeling I am sure which has crowded<lb/>
the fair capitol of this State with the statues of soldiers and statesmen,<lb/>
has made shrines at Mount Vernon and M<unclear>'</unclear>onticello, and has impelled<lb/>
your State Medical Society to purchase this humble dwelling, and<lb/>
to dedicate it to the memory of the great man and choice spirit which<lb/>
here first saw the light of day.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was born on this spot September 13, 1851, the fifth<lb/>
and youngest child of Lemuel Sutton Reed and Pharaba White, his<lb/>
first wife. Lemuel Reed, though he spent his adult life in Virginia as<lb/>
a minister of the Gospel, was a North Carolinian by birth, and it was<lb/>
to the old North State that his now famous son went at the age of<lb/>
25 to wed his chosen wife, Emilie Lawrence--the gracious lady whom<lb/>
we have with us here to-day.</p>
<p>Of the 26 years of his Army life, much of interest might be told<lb/>
did time permit, his varied experiences in his stations in the then<lb/>
far distant Arizona, in Nebraska, Alabama, Dakota, and posts farther<lb/>
west. It was not until 1893 that he became professor of bacteriology<lb/>
and clinical miscroscopy in the then newly organized Army Medical<lb/>
School and was able to devote himself to the special branch of medical<lb/>
science in which he attained enduring fame. But for this he had a<lb/>
year of preparation in 1890 when he was stationed in Baltimore and<lb/>
had the rare good fortune to study under that great scientist and<lb/>
grand old man, Dr. William H. Welch, now the Nestor of medical<lb/>
science in America. Never was opportunity more eagerly seized or<lb/>
more profitably pursued. Then was made the liaison between master<lb/>
and pupil which profoundly influenced and guided the 12 brief years<lb/>
of life which the fates then allotted to Reed. I can not now under-<lb/>
take the narrative of even these few years. We have for the story<lb/>
of his life Howard Kelly's admirable biography and many shorter<lb/>
sketches with some of which each of you is doubtless familiar. I will<lb/>
therefore, if you will permit me, depart somewhat from the text which<lb/>
has been assigned me and give you some personal reminiscences of<lb/>
the man as I knew him and of his work in Cuba as it came under my<lb/>
observation. He had been my predecessor at Fort Robinson in the<lb/>
uttermost parts of Nebraska and I had heard much of his professional<lb/>
skill and his devotion to his patients, not only those in the garrison<lb/>
but the poor pioneers who gained a miserable existence by the cultiva-<lb/>
tion of those arid plains.</p>
<p>My first acquaintance with Walter Reed came in July, 1896, when<lb/>
he came to my station at Key West, Fla., attracted by an epidemic<lb/>
of smallpox which then afflicted the town. He wished to study a<lb/>
curious ameboid body which he had observed in the blood of children<lb/>
and of the Rhesus monkey after vaccination, in the hope that it might<lb/>
be the much-sought cause of smallpox. In the mornings we went to<lb/>
the smallpox hospital to take blood from the victims of that loath-<lb/>
some disease; the afternoons he spent over his microscope and the eve-<lb/>
nings were passed in the broad veranda looking out over the tranquil<lb/>
bay or at the strange stars in the southern sky while he told with<lb/>
whimsical humor tales of his life in the West. Except for a few days<lb/>
that I was his guest in Washington, I did not see him again for two<lb/>
years when came the Spanish War and the fever camps of the South.<lb/>
A board was ordered with Major Reed at the head and Majors Victor<lb/>
C. Vaughan and Edward O. Shakespeare, both distinguished in the<lb/>
medical profession, to study these fevers. They went from camp to<lb/>
camp, observed, studied, and advised. They showed how the diagnosis<lb/>
could be made between the milder typhoids and malarial fever for<lb/>
which the former were so commonly mistaken. Thus I saw Reed again<lb/>
when the board came to Gen. Fitzhugh Lee's camp of the Seventh<lb/>
Army Corps at Jacksonville, where the most important hospital hap-<lb/>
pened to be in my charge. The work lasted over a year and their<lb/>
famous report, which shed a flood of light on the whole subject of the<lb/>
mode of spread of typhoid fever in camps, had not been completed<lb/>
when Reed was ordered to Cuba in 1900.</p>
<p>His first visit to Habana was in March when he came to investigate<lb/>
the use by the engineers of a disinfectant called electrozone made by a<lb/>
patented process out of sea water. It was fondly hoped by many that<lb/>
the free use of this fluid on the streets of the city might banish dis-<lb/>
eases as well as smells and even disinfect the sewers and cespools.<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMC0320"/>
2<lb/>
CONGRESSIONAL RECORD<lb/>
As may be imagined this procedure received small support from Reed<lb/>
and was promptly abandoned.</p>
<p>The yellow fever board, or commisison as it is usually called, was<lb/>
created by War Department order, May 24, 1900, and was composed<lb/>
of Maj. Walter Reed and three acting assistant surgeons--James<lb/>
Carroll, Aristides Agramonte, and Jesse W. Lazear. The two latter<lb/>
were already on duty in Cuba when Reed arrived there on June 25.</p>
<p>A severe epidemic was in progress in Habana and at the neighboring<lb/>
town of Marianao, where Gen. Fitzhugh Lee has his headquarters.<lb/>
He was in command of the two Provinces of Habana and Pinar del<lb/>
Rio which include the western end of the island, but the city of<lb/>
Habana was excepted from his command and was under another general.<lb/>
Major Gorgas was the health officer of the city, and I was the chief<lb/>
surgeon of General Lee's Command, and had sanitary control of the<lb/>
outside country. I had been taken with yellow fever on June 21 and<lb/>
was ill when Reed landed on the morning of June 25, and he hastened<lb/>
to visit me in the hospital at Camp Columbia. It pleases me to think<lb/>
that in my person he saw the first case of the dread disease with which<lb/>
his fame will be forever associated. The board was given quarters and<lb/>
laboratory space in a barrack-like wooden building belonging to the<lb/>
hospital and some half mile from General Lee's headquarters.</p>
<p>The other members of the commission were capable and well-trained<lb/>
scientists.</p>
<p>James Carroll had risen from the ranks in the Army and by hard<lb/>
work and Reed's encouragement and assistance obtained his medical<lb/>
education. He had been for several years Reed's laboratory assistant.</p>
<p>Aristides Agramonte was born in Cuba during the 10 years' war<lb/>
in which his father, a Cuban officer, was killed in battle by the Span-<lb/>
iards. His family had refugeed in the United States, and he had been<lb/>
educated in New York. He had graduated from the College of Physi-<lb/>
cians and Surgeons of New York in 1892 and at this time was in<lb/>
charge of the laboratory of the Division of Cuba in Habana. He is <lb/>
the only surviving member of the commission and has for many years<lb/>
been a distinguished professor in the school of medicine of the Univer-<lb/>
sity of Habana. He has never received from the Government of the<lb/>
United States any honor or material reward for his share in the work<lb/>
of the commission.</p>
<p>Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, the fourth member of the commission, was<lb/>
a graduate of Johns Hopkins. He then studied medicine at Columbia<lb/>
and was a classmate of Agramonte's at the College of Physicians and<lb/>
Surgeons. After graduation he studied in Europe, part of the time at<lb/>
the Pasteur Institute. When he came to Cuba he was bacteriologist<lb/>
to the medical staff at Johns Hopkins Hospital and was assistant in<lb/>
clinical microscopy in the university. He spent much time in the<lb/>
study of malaria and was expert in work with mosquitoes.</p>
<p>It seems to me that the time has come and is long overdue when<lb/>
our Government should show its gratitude for the noble and beneficient<lb/>
work of these four men by an adequate and fitting provision for the<lb/>
families of those who died, and by suitable honors and material<lb/>
rewards for the one who survives.</p>
<p>The first work of the board was to study the bacillus icteroides,<lb/>
which had been announced three years before by Sanapelli to be the<lb/>
cause of yellow fever. His claims were generally accepted and had<lb/>
been corroborated by two investigators, Wasdin and Giddings, of the<lb/>
Public Health Service of the United States, who had been at work in<lb/>
Habana since the American occupation of the city. Their claims had<lb/>
been disputed, however, by the findings of Agramonte, and the Reed<lb/>
board was instructed to decide the matter. And they did decide it, in<lb/>
a report so clear, thorough, and conclusive that, though hotly contested<lb/>
by both Wasdin and Sanarelli at the time, their conclusions have ever<lb/>
since stood unshaken.</p>
<p>It was then decided on August 1 to study the theory that yellow<lb/>
fever was conveyed by the mosquito. This theory had been advanced<lb/>
by several observers in preceding years, but its chief and, at that time,<lb/>
only proponent was Dr. Finley in Habana. He had written a paper<lb/>
20 years before advancing this theory and giving good epidemiological<lb/>
evidence in support of it. He had even fixed on the variety of<lb/>
mosquito which was the criminal, and had made many efforts to trans-<lb/>
mit the disease by its agency. He claimed some successes, but these<lb/>
results seemed to be doubtful. The reasons for his failures, for we<lb/>
know now that they were all failures, were the same that defeated<lb/>
the efforts of Reed's board in the first weeks of their work.</p>
<p>Yellow fever had always been the most elusive and puzzling of<lb/>
diseases and had defeated the attempts of a multitude of able investi-<lb/>
gators to find out its secrets. A study of Lazear's wonderfully de-<lb/>
tailed and accurate notes, including the individual history of each of<lb/>
his mosquitoes, uncovered two traps:</p>
<p>The first is that the yellow-fever patient ceases to have the infective<lb/>
agent in his blood after the third day of the disease and can not infect<lb/>
mosquitoes after that time.</p>
<p>The second trap is that after the mosquito has bitten a case of<lb/>
yellow fever, even in the first three days, she is quite harmless for a<lb/>
period of incubation of 12 to 14 days after which she becomes able<lb/>
to infect.</p>
<p>Now, it happens that in most cases yellow fever in the first three<lb/>
days is much like malaria and other fevers, and it is only about the<lb/>
108117--4627<lb/>
third day that the patient begins to take on the characteristic yellow<lb/>
tinge and the diagnosis becomes certain. So it was quite natural that<lb/>
the experimenter would take his mosquito to a well-marked yellow-fever<lb/>
case more than three days old, and she would fail to become infected<lb/>
when she bit.</p>
<p>This was trap No. 1, and if by good luck the experimenter escaped<lb/>
it and hit on a patient in the first three days, what would he do next?<lb/>
Naturally he would take the mosquito to the volunteer who agreed to<lb/>
be bitten, with as little loss of time as possible, for captive mosquitoes<lb/>
in jars and test tubes are delicate creatures and apt to die, or to be<lb/>
eaten by ants or escape. So those who missed trip No. 1 were caught<lb/>
by trap No. 2 and, as we have said, none of Doctor Finlay's experi-<lb/>
ments got by both of them, nor did our board's at first.</p>
<p>Finlay's theory was, as Gorgas once said to me, &ldquo;a wonderful in-<lb/>
stance of scientific clairvoyance.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Reed was called back to the United States during the first week in<lb/>
August on account of the death of Doctor Shakespeare, to put in order<lb/>
the manuscripts of the typhoid fever board and the experiments began<lb/>
in his absence.</p>
<p>They fed the supposedly infected mosquitoes every few days by<lb/>
letting them bite the arm of a member of the board or a volunteer, and<lb/>
these were not difficult to find among the young doctors and orderlies<lb/>
at the post hospital. On August 27 Lazear took his mosquitoes to Las<lb/>
Animas Hospital to be fed on yellow fever patients, but one of them<lb/>
refused to bite. It happened that this insect had bitten a man in the<lb/>
second day of fever 12 days before and was thus past both traps<lb/>
and was what we came to call &ldquo;loaded&rdquo;; but this fact was not then<lb/>
appreciated. As the insect appeared to be weak and liable to die,<lb/>
Carroll offered to feed it on his arm and did so. On the 30th Carroll<lb/>
felt badly and had a chill. He was thought to have malaria, and no<lb/>
one thought of yellow fever until the symptoms of that disease were<lb/>
apparent. Carroll thought so little of the mosquito bite and was so far<lb/>
from regarding it as a scientific experiment that he went into the<lb/>
infected zone and even into the post mortem room, where Agramonte<lb/>
was conducting an autopsy on a yellow fever case. This greatly vexed<lb/>
Reed when he returned and heard of it, as it vitiated to a large extent<lb/>
the value of the case as an experiment. When Carroll's diagnosis be-<lb/>
came clear, Lazear and Agramonte were greatly troubled but deter-<lb/>
mined to verify the virulence of this mosquito by putting her on the<lb/>
first volunteer who presented himself. A young soldier of the Seventh<lb/>
Cavalry, Pvt. William H. Dean, came by the laboratory soon after<lb/>
they had agreed to do this (August 31) and readily agreed to feed the<lb/>
mosquitoes. He became sick five days later, and as he had been in the<lb/>
quarantined camp all the time and so could not have acquired yellow<lb/>
fever in any other way, the demonstration of mosquito conveyance<lb/>
was perfect. A little later Lazear was bitten while feeding his mos-<lb/>
quitoes in a yellow-fever ward by a mosquito not of his flock, and died<lb/>
September 25 after a few days' suffering of yellow fever in its most<lb/>
malignant form. His case as a demonstration was of even less value<lb/>
than Carroll's as he had been in frequent contact with cases of yellow<lb/>
fever. Such were the conditions when Reed returned from the United<lb/>
States a few days after Lazear's death. The three cases, especially<lb/>
that of Dean, convinced him, and he determined to hasten back to the<lb/>
United States to report these cases to the American Public Health<lb/>
Association and also to consult the Surgeon General and his wise men-<lb/>
tor, Doctor Welch, as to the next steps to be taken, for it was evident<lb/>
that this small and imperfectly controlled series of cases was not suf-<lb/>
ficient to convince the medical profession and the general public.</p>
<p>I had at that time returned from a short sick leave in the States<lb/>
and was chief surgeon at Gen. Fitzhugh Lee's headquarters. When<lb/>
Reed mentioned to me on October 11 his intention to go to Habana next<lb/>
day to get General Wood's permission to go to the United States, I<lb/>
offered to get transportation and take him down. Accordingly, through<lb/>
the courtesy of the adjutant general, Major Michie, I got permission<lb/>
to use General Lee's fine horses and carriage, and so we drove down in<lb/>
great style. When we were on the road I urged him to ask General<lb/>
Wood for a considerable sum of money to pay the expenses of a series<lb/>
of experiments and give liberal bonuses to Spanish immigrants, who I<lb/>
was sure could be induced in that way to volunteer, especially as they<lb/>
came to Cuba with always the probability of having yellow fever.<lb/>
He did not commit himself as to what he would do, and I awaited the<lb/>
interview with keen interest.</p>
<p>General Wood received us graciously, as he knew us both well and<lb/>
had taken a course of study under Reed. They stood facing each other<lb/>
in the embrasure of a window of the palace looking out on the Plaza<lb/>
de las Armas and to me, a silent observer, it was a most dramatic<lb/>
scene with all the setting of a great historic moment. Looking out<lb/>
between them I could see Morro Castle and the blue waters of the<lb/>
harbor and on our left the ancient Fort la Fuerza, built by the gallant<lb/>
De Soto before he sailed northward to find his grave in the turbid<lb/>
current of the Mississippi. The two men offered a singular contrast<lb/>
in their appearance. General Wood, massive, leonine, impassive; Reed,<lb/>
slender, alert, with mobile features and sparkling blue eyes as he told<lb/>
the story of the three cases and summed up the evidence. Then, after<lb/>
a moment's pause, he said very earnestly, &ldquo;General Wood, will you<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMC0330"/>
CONGRESSIONAL RECORD<lb/>
3<lb/>
give me $10,000 to continue and complete these experiments?&rdquo; Gen-<lb/>
eral Wood's reply came almost without hesitation--&ldquo;I have this morn-<lb/>
ing signed a warrant for that amount to aid the police in the capture<lb/>
of criminals, and surely this work is of more importance to Cuba than<lb/>
the catching of a few thieves. I will give you $10,000 and if that<lb/>
proves insufficient I will give you $10,000 more.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We said good day to the military governor and with joyous hearts<lb/>
betook ourselves to the Paris restaurant, where we celebrated this<lb/>
happy outcome with a good luncheon, and I pledged his success and<lb/>
future fame with a bottle of Rioja Clarete.</p>
<p>Next day Reed sailed for New York and read his paper before the<lb/>
American Public Health Association on October 24. There he encoun-<lb/>
tered Wasdin full of his demonstration that B. Sanarelli was it cause<lb/>
and that it was transmitted through the respiratory channel like<lb/>
measles or grippe. The clash was sharp, bitter, and personal on Wasdin's<lb/>
part, courteous and impersonal on Reed's, but conclusive that the organ-<lb/>
ism which had led Wasdin and the rest of the world astray was common<lb/>
in the Tropics and was simply accidentally present in the bodies of<lb/>
some cases, and it was in fact a member of the hog cholera group<lb/>
of bacteria.</p>
<p>Reed did not linger to enjoy his victory, and four days later he<lb/>
was back in Cuba eager to take up the work with all the facilities which<lb/>
General Wood's financial and moral support placed in his hands.</p>
<p>When Reed applied for the promised money General Wood told him<lb/>
that he would place it for disbursement in Kean's hands, as he was<lb/>
an officer permanently on duty there and Reed would be saved the<lb/>
worry of it. So this was done, and I acquired in a subordinate and<lb/>
business way a connection with this famous board.</p>
<p>The building of his experimental station, Camp Lazear, where the<lb/>
tests should be made, was at once begun, and Spanish immigrants were<lb/>
readily found who for a handsome sum were willing to be bitten by<lb/>
the &ldquo;little flies,&rdquo; and if they were taken sick to be nursed by the<lb/>
se&ntilde;ioritas Americanas, as they called the nurses. A most dramatic epi-<lb/>
sode of this period was the volunteering of Moran and Kissinger to be<lb/>
the first victims of the experimentation. Kissinger was in fact the first<lb/>
case--a noble offer which has been often and fully told. These were<lb/>
followed by other American soldiers from the Hospital Corps, so that<lb/>
between the Americans and the Spaniards the supply of subjects for<lb/>
experiment was ample. The Spaniards furnished Reed much amuse-<lb/>
ment, especially a jolly young Spaniard peasant named Antonio Benigno,<lb/>
but whom Reed called Boniato, which means a sweet potato, on account<lb/>
of his fondness for that vegetable. His contract with Reed in Spanish,<lb/>
signed by both, hangs on the wall of my office. He was first to recover,<lb/>
and when I took his reward to him I got it in 10 $20 gold pieces. The<lb/>
poor Spaniard had never seen such great coins or so much money, and<lb/>
his joy was that of a child with a new toy.</p>
<p>The revolting test of the infected clothing and bedding by Dr. Robert<lb/>
P. Cook--Virginian, by the way--and his six privates of the Hospital<lb/>
Corps, who slept in them by twos for 60 successive nights, was another<lb/>
heroic episode. All this makes it a wonderful and thrilling story, which<lb/>
is well told in Kelly's admirable work.</p>
<p>Suffice it to say that his demonstrations carried conviction with them<lb/>
to the physicians of Habana, who had remained incredulous during<lb/>
the 20 years that Dr. Carlos Finlay had been laboring to convince them<lb/>
with arguments and experiments of this very thing. So then they<lb/>
bethought themselves of this dear old man who was at the head of the<lb/>
yellow fever board, and 60 doctors of Habana gave him a dinner to<lb/>
celebrate the verification of the Finlay theory.</p>
<p>Dr. Juan Guiteras, who died this year in Habana, presided, and as I<lb/>
recollect the military governor sat on one side of him and Dr. Finlay<lb/>
on the other. Reed, Carroll, and Agramonte were there and Gorgas<lb/>
and I and perhaps other medical officers. Guiteras, with his musical<lb/>
voice and admirable diction, undertook to divide the honors between<lb/>
Finlay and Reed. He compared this work to the demonstration that<lb/>
the anopheles mosquito carried malaria, which had been published by<lb/>
Ross two years before. Finlay was like Patrick Manson, who pro-<lb/>
pounded the theory, and Reed was like Ross, who demonstrated it so<lb/>
that it was accepted by the scientific world. We all agreed that the<lb/>
simile was a good one and the division of credit just. But as the years<lb/>
have passed and the fame of Walter Reed has spread to all corners of<lb/>
the world our Cuban friends have come to feel that Finlay has not<lb/>
had his share. They do not realize that it is to the demonstrator and<lb/>
not to the theorist that the world of science gives the highest place.</p>
<p>About the time that Doctor Finlay made the first announcement of<lb/>
his theory a distinguished physician of Washington, Dr. A. F. A. King,<lb/>
108117--4627<lb/>
read a remarkable paper before the Philosophical Society, which was<lb/>
afterwards published in the Popular Science Monthly, entitled &ldquo;Insects<lb/>
and disease--Mosquitoes and malaria,&rdquo; in which he pronounced his<lb/>
theory that malaria was carried by mosquitoes and gave 19 good<lb/>
epidemiological reasons in support of his theory. But it remained a<lb/>
barren theory, although it had later the powerful support of the<lb/>
father of tropical medicine, Patrick Manson, until Ross furnished the<lb/>
demonstration. Although Doctor King was loved and admired in Wash-<lb/>
ington, as was Finlay in Habana, no one that I have heard has raised<lb/>
the cry that he has been robbed of the fame and credit that is due<lb/>
him, as the Cubans have recently done in an official publication in<lb/>
the case of Doctor Finlay. Goldberger, of the Public Health Service,<lb/>
has stated the case in one pithy sentence, &ldquo;Reed has converted a dis-<lb/>
credited theory into an established doctrine.&rdquo;</p>
<p>My remarks have already taken too much time for me to make even<lb/>
a brief estimate of the value of Reed's work, or of the vast sum of<lb/>
human suffering and loss of life from this terrible plague which he<lb/>
made it possible to bring to an end. Professor Welch said of it in a<lb/>
letter to the Secretary of War:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Doctor Reed's researches in yellow fever are by far the most<lb/>
important contributions to science which have ever come from an<lb/>
Army surgeon. In my judgment, they are the most valuable contribu-<lb/>
tions to medicine and public hygiene which have ever been made in this<lb/>
country with the exception of the discovery of an&aelig;sthesia. They have<lb/>
led and will lead to the saving of untold thousands of lives. I am in<lb/>
a position to know that the credit for the original ideas embodied in<lb/>
this work belong wholly to Major Reed. Such work, if done in Europe,<lb/>
would receive substantial recognition from the government.&rdquo;</p>
<p>General Wood, whose recent death we still mourn, said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I know of no man on this side of the world who has done so much<lb/>
for humaniay as Doctor Reed. His discovery results in the saving of<lb/>
more lives annually than were lost in the Cuban war, and saves the<lb/>
commercial interests of the world from a greater financial loss each<lb/>
year than the cost of the Cuban war. * * * Hereafter it will never<lb/>
be possible for yellow fever to gain such headway that quarantine will<lb/>
exist from the mouth of the Potomac to the mouth of the Rio Grande.<lb/>
Future generations will appreciate fully the value of Doctor Reed's<lb/>
services. His was the originating, directing, and controlling mind in<lb/>
this work and the others were assistants only.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was stated in a recent biography of General Gorgas that Reed,<lb/>
when his demonstration was complete, did not know what to do with<lb/>
it, that he did not see how mosquitoes could be successfully fought, and<lb/>
that his attitude in the first months of 1901 was one of pessimism and<lb/>
depression.</p>
<p>Nothing could be further from the truth. His letter to Dr. L. O.<lb/>
Howard, Chief of the Bureau of Entomology, at Washington, on Janu-<lb/>
ary 13, 1901, rings with joyful anticipation, and in it he says &ldquo;with<lb/>
Howard and kerosene we will soon knock out old culex fasciatus&rdquo; (the<lb/>
name applied at that time to the yellow fever bearing mosquito).</p>
<p>In the paper which he read to the Pan American Congress held in<lb/>
Habana on February 4, the tenth conclusion is:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The spread of yellow fever can be most effectually controlled by<lb/>
measures directed to the destruction of mosquitoes and the protection<lb/>
of the sick against the bites of these insects.&rdquo;</p>
<p>This was written at a time when Gorgas, according to his own state-<lb/>
ment, still was in doubt whether this was the only way or even the<lb/>
common way in which yellow fever was spread.</p>
<p>Such claims grievously misrepresent Gorgas. Between Reed and<lb/>
Gorgas, I am glad to say, there was never any rivalry or any feeling<lb/>
but the most cordial friendship and confidence. Their relation as they<lb/>
saw it was well expressed in a letter from Gorgas to Reed, dated<lb/>
from Habana August 26, 1901, in which he said:</p>
<p>&ldquo;I am very happy to shine in the more humble r&ocirc;le of being the<lb/>
first to put your discovery to extensive practical application.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The fame of Gorgas is secure in the performance of the greatest feat<lb/>
of sanitary administration that the world has seen. That of Reed is<lb/>
admirably stated in the citation of President Eliot, of Harvard Uni-<lb/>
sity, which is the epitaph on Reed's tomb--</p>
<p>&ldquo;He gave to man control of that dreadful scourge, yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We here to-day may make for Walter Reed the proud boast of the<lb/>
Roman poet:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Exegi monumentum aere perennius.&rdquo;</p>
<p>He has indeed &ldquo;built a monument more lasting than bronze and<lb/>
loftier than the pyramids of kings, which neither storms, nor winds,<lb/>
nor the immeasurable flight of time can destroy.&rdquo;</p>
<p>U.S. GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE: 1928</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
