<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD0010">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Victor C. Vaughan and Walter Reed to the Surgeon General, March 21, 1899</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Vaughan, Victor C.</author>
<author>Reed, Walter</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD0010</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1899-03-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Surgeon General</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Smith, Frederick P.</name>
<name type="place">Washington Barracks (Washington, D.C.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="1899-03-21">March 21, 1899</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD0010</idno>
<title>Letter from Victor C. Vaughan and Walter Reed to the Surgeon General, March 21, 1899</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Vaughan and Reed submit a report about their examination of three crematories at Washington Barracks. They ascertain that none of the models submitted by inventors meet all the conditions required by the Army. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1899-03-21">
<head>Letter from Victor C. Vaughan and Walter Reed to the Surgeon General, March 21, 1899</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD0010"/>
<opener>
<del>Chief Surgeon's Office.</del><lb/>
<del>HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.</del> <add>Camp Crematories</add><lb/>
<dateline>
Washington, D. C., <date value="1899-03-21">March 21, 1899.</date>
</dateline><lb/>
To the Surgeon General,<lb/>
U. S. Army,<lb/>
Washington, D. C.<lb/>
<salute>General:</salute>
</opener>
<p>The Board of Medical Officers convened per S.O., 194, Par.<lb/>
40, C.S., Adjutant General's Office, August 18, 1898, had the honor<lb/>
under date of Dec. 22, 1898, and in compliance with S.O., No. 264,<lb/>
Par. 67, C.S. Adjutant General's Office, November 8, 1898, of submit-<lb/>
ting a report relating to the disposal of excreta in military camps,<lb/>
together with plans and drawings of the apparatus recommended by<lb/>
the Board. In that report we stated &ldquo;that methods of incineration<lb/>
of feces have been and are being investigated, but our practical<lb/>
examination has not been sufficiently extensive to warrant us in<lb/>
recommending any of them.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Since the date of that report we have been able to examine<lb/>
the practical operation of three crematories which, with the permis-<lb/>
sion of the Honorable Secretary of War, have been erected for trial<lb/>
at Washington Barracks, this city. We desire now to report upon<lb/>
these.</p>
<p>No. 1. The Combined Camp Crematory for excreta and garbage, designed<lb/>
and submitted by Frederick P. Smith, C.E.</p>
<p>The accompanying circular hereto appended and marked &ldquo;A&rdquo;, gives<lb/>
such a complete description and plan of this Crematory, that we need<lb/>
add but little thereto. Briefly speaking, it consists of a series<lb/>
of hoppers arranged in a circle about a central furnace. The urine<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD0020"/>
2<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
and fecal matter are received upon flat excreta plates, so in-<lb/>
clined that the fluid parts flow towards the central fire and<lb/>
are subjected to a constant drying. The solid part of the excreta<lb/>
is from time to time pushed toward the edge of the fire and when<lb/>
dried, can at any time, be raked on to the grate and burned.</p>
<p>A large evaporating pan is placed above the fire for the<lb/>
reception of fluid and solid garbage. When dried sufficiently, the<lb/>
pan is overturned by means of a lever and the garbage burned.<lb/>
Sufficient draft and ventilation are secured by means of a pipe,<lb/>
3 feet in diameter, which rises to a height of about 40 feet.<lb/>
This Crematory has accomplished, during a trial lasting about<lb/>
four weeks, all that its inventor has claimed for it, in the matter<lb/>
of the dessication and subsequent destruction by fire of both ex-<lb/>
creta and garbage. The closet has been found to be well ventilated<lb/>
and free of odor whenever inspected by Members of the Board. A mod-<lb/>
erate fire was sufficient for this purpose. This Crematory appears<lb/>
to possess durability and is certainly adaptable to any form of<lb/>
fuel that may be at hand in camp. An advantage possessed by it is<lb/>
the possibility of applying the flame immediately beneath the ex-<lb/>
creta plates, in order, if necessary, to hasten the drying and ster-<lb/>
ilization of the excreta, as well as adjacent parts of the appar-<lb/>
atus. The fact that, owing to its peculiar construction, the central<lb/>
fire while drying out the excrement and garbage, does not increase<lb/>
the temperature of the closet, must be considered as another advant-<lb/>
age especially in hot climates.</p>
<p>We are not prepared to express the opinion that this<lb/>
Crematory will entirely prevent the dissemination of the germs of<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMD0030"/>
3<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
typhoid fever by means of flies. Owing to the season of the year,<lb/>
we have not been able to test the ability of this apparatus to des-<lb/>
troy all flies entering through the hoppers. We doubt whether<lb/>
the downward current of air will be sufficient to prevent their<lb/>
egress, nor are we convinced that they would be destroyed by heat,<lb/>
if drawn in the oposite direction, for the reason that there appears<lb/>
to be an upward current of air which is not drawn in immediate<lb/>
contact with the fire.</p>
<p>While this Crematory is transportable, in the sense that it<lb/>
consits of a number of pieces of cast-iron joined together by<lb/>
bolts, and which can be taken apart by ten men in the space of about<lb/>
five or six hours, and re-erected in about the same time, the fact<lb/>
must be borne in mind that the weight of an eight hopper apparatus<lb/>
suitable for a single company is not less than 5200 lbs., and that a<lb/>
fourteen hopper Crematory for two companies would weigh about 7000<lb/>
lbs.</p>
<p>In other words, the portability of this apparatus is only<lb/>
such as would permit of its erection in more or less permanent camps.</p>
<p>No. 2. A Crematory for excreta submitted by the Albany Sanitation<lb/>
Co., of Albany, N.Y. As erected by Mr. Thos. Hyde, representing the<lb/>
Company, this Crematory consists of a furnace and 7 closets. Each<lb/>
closet section is a cylindrical tube, of &frac14; inch cast-iron, 20 inches<lb/>
in diameter and weighing 150 lbs. Rising from each section is a<lb/>
cast-iron hopper, provided with suitable seat and cover. The separate<lb/>
closet sections are provided with flanges by means of which the<lb/>
several sections are securely bolted together, thus forming a contin-<lb/>
nous iron tube, connected at one end with the furnace. Excreta are<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fKAMD0040"/>
4<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
received into this hollow iron tube.</p>
<p>A galvanized iron pipe, 14 inches in diameter, is pro-<lb/>
vided for the purpose of bringing a current of warm air from the<lb/>
furnace and thence conducting it to the distal end of the excreta<lb/>
tube, from which point it is continually drawn over the surface of<lb/>
the excreta. This serves both for the purpose of drying the ex-<lb/>
creta and for the ventilation of the closet.</p>
<p>A urinal is provided, from which the urine is conducted by<lb/>
means of a 3 inch iron pipe to a pit beneath the furnace, where it<lb/>
is subjected to constant evaporation. The furnace is furnished with<lb/>
a smoke stack 16 inches in diameter, rising to a height of about 35<lb/>
feet. Either wood or coal can be used as fuel. When it becomes<lb/>
necessary to destroy the accumulation of excreta, pieces of wood or<lb/>
other combustible material are thrown into the excreta tube and a<lb/>
fire kindled. The debris remaining after the process of incinera-<lb/>
tion can be removed by means of a clean-out door placed at the further<lb/>
end of the tube. This door was not provided in the apparatus sub-<lb/>
mitted for our inspection; nor was any provision made for the burn-<lb/>
ing of garbage as shown in the accompanying drawings, which are<lb/>
hereto appended and marked &ldquo;Fig. No. 1&rdquo; and &ldquo;Fig. No. 2&rdquo;</p>
<p>During the time of our trial, lasting about three weeks,<lb/>
this Crematory has accomplished in the matter of good ventilation<lb/>
and freedom from odors all that was claimed, in this regard, by the<lb/>
Albany Sanitation Company. It has failed to cause a constant cur-<lb/>
rant of warm air to pass through the excreta tube and over the<lb/>
excreta, and hence has not accomplished the drying of the excreta<lb/>
preparatory to incineration as claimed by the in<del>f</del><add>v</add>entors. Practically,<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fKAMD0050"/>
5<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
the deposit or excreta remains in a moist condition and requires<lb/>
a hot fire for its destruction. The fact that the fire must be ap-<lb/>
plied to the upper surface of the excreta, not only renders it more<lb/>
difficult to accomplish its destruction, but prolongs the time re-<lb/>
quired for its complete incineration.</p>
<p>The remarks made concerning the transportability of the<lb/>
Smith Crematory will apply equally to this aparatus. While its<lb/>
weight is estimated to be about 3,000 lbs., the separate closet<lb/>
sections weigh 150 lbs. and are somewhat unwieldly for the purpose of<lb/>
handling. The inventors claim, however, that this weight can be much<lb/>
reduced.</p>
<p>In making a comparison of the foregoing Crematories, we<lb/>
are of the opinion that as submitted to us for trial, the Smith Cre-<lb/>
matory possesses certain advantages over that of the Albany Sani-<lb/>
tation Company. These may be stated as follows.</p>
<p>1st: The constant dessication of both solid and fluid excre-<lb/>
ta, by the direct radiation of heat from the central fire.</p>
<p>2nd: The simultaneous destruction of garbage.</p>
<p>3rd: The possibility of applying flame immediately beneath<lb/>
the excreta plates, for the purpose of sterilizing all parts of the<lb/>
apparatus.</p>
<p>4th: The fact that the furnace fire does not cause any<lb/>
increased temperature of the closet room.</p>
<p><hi>No. 3</hi>: A Crematory for excreta or garbage submitted by the<lb/>
International Household Garbage and Excrement Crematory Company, of<lb/>
Buffalo, N.Y.</p>
<p>This consists of a steel jacket lined with asbestos within<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fKAMD0060"/>
6<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
and provided with a sheet iron covering without. The top and bot-<lb/>
tom of this <del>k</del><add>j</add>acket consist of cast-iron. The excreta are received<lb/>
into a cast-iron pot, having a capacity of 7 gallons, and which<lb/>
revolves on a horizontal axle. A suitable grate, with ash-pit,<lb/>
is provided beneath the pot. An opening of proper dimensions, with<lb/>
seat and cover, is provided for in the cast-iron top of the jacket.<lb/>
Ventilation is brought about by means of a 6 inch stove-pipe flue<lb/>
rising to a height of 12 feet. The Crematory is fully described<lb/>
and explained in the pamphlet of the Company, which is hereto append-<lb/>
ed and marked <hi>&ldquo;B&rdquo;</hi>.</p>
<p>When desired to destroy the contents of the pot, the<lb/>
wooden seat and cover are removed, the opening closed with a gal-<lb/>
vanized iron cover provided for that purpose, and a fire started<lb/>
on the grate below.</p>
<p>In a trial of this Crematory, extending over about one<lb/>
week, we find that the ventilation is not such as to remove all<lb/>
offensive odors, when the cover is lifted. This could hardly be<lb/>
expected. We find that it requires the action of a hot fire for<lb/>
about two hours, in order to thoroughly reduce the excreta to ashes.<lb/>
This time can be reduced somewhat by dumping the excreta, as soon<lb/>
as dried, on the fire beneath. Practically, three hours are required<lb/>
for the incineration and subsequent cooling of the Crematory.</p>
<p>During the process of incineration, pungent and disagreeable<lb/>
odors are perceived. This is more perceptible than with the other<lb/>
Crematories and is probably due to the lesser height at which these<lb/>
disagreeable odors are liberated into the surrounding air.</p>
<p>This Crematory has the advantage of being transportable<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fKAMD0070"/>
7<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
and ready for use at all times. It does not require to be taken<lb/>
apart for purposes of transportation, but can be crated and shipped<lb/>
entire. Its weight is about 330 lbs. When, however, the combined<lb/>
weight of the number required for a single company, estimated at<lb/>
eight (8), is taken into consideration, it will be seen that it hardly<lb/>
falls short of the weight of the other Crematories. If used<lb/>
for the destruction of garbage, two additional crematories would be<lb/>
required for each company.</p>
<p>We are of the opinion that during hot weather, this cre-<lb/>
matory, owing to imperfect ventilation, would be quite offensive.<lb/>
The quantity of fuel required for incineration must be considered<lb/>
as an additional and marked disadvantage.</p>
<p>Letters submitted by the inventors setting forth the cost,<lb/>
weight, &amp;c., of these several crematories, are hereto appended and<lb/>
marked &ldquo;C&rdquo;, &ldquo;D&rdquo; and &ldquo;E&rdquo;.</p>
<p>In submitting this report the Board desire to invite at-<lb/>
tention to the fact that Crematories Nos. 1 and 2, aside from being<lb/>
heavy and not readily transportable, require a certain amount of<lb/>
skilled labor for their erection. Although 10 men working under<lb/>
the supervision of the inventor can put together one of them in<lb/>
about five hours, it does not follow that the same number of sold-<lb/>
iers could accomplish the same result in the same time. Again, this<lb/>
system, like all others submitted, demands constant and intelligent<lb/>
attention in order to accomplish the proper operation of any one of<lb/>
them.</p>
<p>In the opinion of the Board, none of those mentioned above<lb/>
meet all of the conditions of troops in the field, as well or as<lb/>
<pb n="8" id="fKAMD0080"/>
8<lb/>
Chief Surgeon's Office.<lb/>
HEADQUARTERS SEVENTH ARMY CORPS.<lb/>
economically as the apparatus recommended by this Board in its re-<lb/>
port of December 28, 1898. We believe that the apparatus therein<lb/>
described is much easier of construction, far more readily trans-<lb/>
portable and capable of effecting the same results in an equally<lb/>
satisfactory manner as to the disposal of excreta. For large hospitals<lb/>
or permanent camps, the Smith Crematory, if intelligently managed,<lb/>
will suffice for the destruction of both excreta and garbage and for<lb/>
such purposes we believe that it may be recommended.</p>
<closer>
<signed>(Signed) Walker Reed,</signed>
Major &amp; Surgeon, U. S. A.<lb/>
<signed>(Signed) Victor C. Vaughan,</signed>
Major &amp; Division Surgeon,<lb/>
U. S. V.<lb/>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
