<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD0650">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Report: Extract from Surgeon General's Annual Report, 1909</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD0650</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1909-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Fauntleroy, P. C.</name>
<name type="person">Church, Dr.</name>
<name type="person">Thomason, H. D.</name>
<name type="person">Allen, John H.</name>
<name type="person">Bevans, J. L.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1909-00-00">1909</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD0650</idno>
<title>Report: Extract from Surgeon General's Annual Report, 1909</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The report concludes that improved sanitation efforts between 1906 and 1909 left Cuba entirely free of yellow fever. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1909-00-00">
<head>Report: Extract from Surgeon General's Annual Report, 1909</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD0650"/>
<p>Extract from Surgeon General's Annual Report, 1909, page 135:</p>
<p>Sanitary affairs in Cuba have been during the period of intervention<lb/>
under the administrative control of Maj. J. R. Kean, Medical Corps, assist-<lb/>
ed by four medical officers detailed from the army of Cuban pacification,<lb/>
viz, Maj. P. C. Fauntleroy, Maj. J. R. Church, and Capts. John H. Allen and<lb/>
Henry D. Thomason. Capt. J. L. Bevans was also assigned to duty with the<lb/>
provisional government in connection with the administration of hospitals<lb/>
and charitable institutions. The intervention in September, 1906, found<lb/>
the sanitary administration of the Cuban cities outside of Havana in a state<lb/>
of great neglect, due to lack of funds and of proper organization and meth-<lb/>
ods. Yellow fever had also been reintroduced into the island and had<lb/>
spread widely into the small towns and sugar centrals of the interior, dif-<lb/>
fering in this respect from its former habit of clinging to the larger sea-<lb/>
port towns. This change of behavior was due to the great increase in the<lb/>
number of nonimmunes among the country population and to the increased fa-<lb/>
cilities for travel. The method of combating the disease formerly devised<lb/>
by Gorgas for Havana were extended to other foci of infection and modified<lb/>
to suit changed conditions. Political conditions required the distribution<lb/>
of the American troops in the various cities, where they were much exposed<lb/>
to this infection; yet so perfect was the cooperation between the medical<lb/>
service of the army and the sanitary authorities that outbreaks of yellow<lb/>
fever among our soldiers have been few and promptly checked. Since Feb-<lb/>
ruary 18, 1908, there has been no case of yellow fever in the whole island<lb/>
west of Santiago, except one mysterious case in Havana in September, and<lb/>
the outbreak in the extreme eastern end of the island was easily controlled.<lb/>
Yet the freedom of all Cuba except the most eastern of the six provinces<lb/>
from the disease throughout the summer did not save the island from a<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD0660"/>
-2-<lb/>
blanket quarantine by the United States, and this in spite of an interna-<lb/>
tional sanitary treaty to which both nations are parties, which provides<lb/>
among other things for the localization of quarantine.</p>
<p>The termination of the provisional government on January 28, 1909,<lb/>
left the island entirely free from yellow fever, and it has so remained.<lb/>
The sanitary department was also completely reorganized, and the quaran-<lb/>
tine service and department of charities consolidated with it into a de-<lb/>
partment of health and charities, at the head of which is a secretary, who<lb/>
is a member of the cabinte. The sanitary service of all municipalities<lb/>
was nationalized by being placed in charge of sanitary officers appointed<lb/>
by the President. The expenses of the municipal sanitary services are<lb/>
paid from the national treasury, and each municipality, in consideration<lb/>
thereof, pays into the treasury one-tenth of its income. Uniformity of<lb/>
method of administration and adequate financial support being secured by<lb/>
the admirable sanitary law promulgated by the provisional governor, the<lb/>
Republic of Cuba has in sanitary administration advanced to the front<lb/>
rank among the nations.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
