<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD1380">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Speech: Scientific Achievements of the Army Medical Corps, Heroes of the Conquest of Yellow Fever, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [n.d.]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD1380</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>0000-00-00</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Ireland, Merritte W.</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Russell, Frederick F.</name>
<name type="person">Siler, J. F.</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Shakespeare, Edward O.</name>
<name type="person">Dean, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Hanberry, James L.</name>
<name type="person">Hamann, Paul</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Forbes, Wallace W.</name>
<name type="person">Andrus, John H.</name>
<name type="person">England, Thomas M.</name>
<name type="person">Covington, Albert W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Bullard, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Sonntag, Charles G.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Hildebrand, James</name>
<name type="person">Weatherwalks, Edward</name>
<name type="place">Puerto Rico</name>
<name type="place">Philippines</name>
<name type="place">Manila (Philippines)</name>
<name type="place">France</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>8 pp.</extent>
<date value="0000-00-00"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD1380</idno>
<title>Speech: Scientific Achievements of the Army Medical Corps, Heroes of the Conquest of Yellow Fever, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [n.d.]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This document covers the accomplishments of the Army Medical Corps, including the conquest of yellow fever. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="0000-00-00">
<head>Speech: Scientific Achievements of the Army Medical Corps, Heroes of the Conquest of Yellow Fever, by [Jefferson Randolph Kean], [n.d.]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD1380"/>
<p>Scientific Achievements of the Army Medical Corps<lb/>
Heroes of the Conquest of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Memo for<lb/>
an address for<lb/>
Gen. Ireland</p>
<p>President and Members of the Illinois State Medical Association, Ladies and<lb/>
Gentlemen:</p>
<p>When I received the gracious and friendly <add>invitation</add> of your Secretary to meet you here<lb/>
tonight it seemed at first impossible that I would be able to leave Washington<lb/>
in the middle of the short session of Congress when I must at all times be ready<lb/>
to answer the calls of Congressional Committees for information which bears upon<lb/>
the needs of the Army. But when I observed that this meeting was intended to<lb/>
do honor not to individuals merely, but to the Corps as a whole, and not only to<lb/>
commemorate the glorious episode of the conquest of yellow fever but to embrace<lb/>
also the more recent fine accomplishments of the service of which I am at present<lb/>
the Chief, I felt that the call to me was imperative and must be obeyed.</p>
<p>A Spanish officer who resided for some years in Washington used to refer to the<lb/>
war of 1898 as the &ldquo;pleasantest of all wars&rdquo;. He referred of course to the absence<lb/>
of hatred between the opposing combattants and the kindly sympathy which we showed<lb/>
towards our Spanish prisoners of war of which he was one. This war though it was<lb/>
marked by no bitterness and little bloodshed had far reaching and permanent results.<lb/>
For our country it brought it out of its attitude of isolation and introspection<lb/>
and made it a world power. For the Medical Department of the Army with which we<lb/>
are especially concerned tonight, it rudely awoke us from an easy life of small<lb/>
things and thrust upon us large responsibilities in strange environments and distant<lb/>
lands. To this call all that was best in the medical service responded nobly,<lb/>
and some among them &ldquo;seized the skirts of happy chance&rdquo; and because our benefactors<lb/>
by accomplishments which you have shown a generous desire to celebrate tonight.</p>
<p>The Army Medical School had been established in 1891 by General Sternberg who and<lb/>
has been called the Father of Bacteriology in America, I think I may say, the<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD1390"/>
-2-<lb/>
first of our Surgeon Generals who had made a name in the field of scientific<lb/>
research. Within its first decade while yet a small tree the School began to<lb/>
bring forth rich fruits. From its chair of bacteriology Reed and his assistant<lb/>
Carroll went forth to fight the dragon of yellow fever. One of its young men<lb/>
who had studied:-</p>
<p>(1) Parasitology under Stiles, (who then gave lectures to its classes) was after<lb/>
the war stationed in<lb/>
a small town in Porto Rico where he observed among the country population<lb/>
the devast ting blight of tropical anaemia. He recognised in the intestinal<lb/>
discharges of these people a microscopic parasite, the hookworm, which was<lb/>
at that time not known to have invaded our hemisphere. Knowledge in young Bailey<lb/>
Ashford bred active, and he instituted the first organized campaign against<lb/>
this enemy of the poor, which, so far as I am aware, had ever been instituted.<lb/>
Of the vast fruitfulness of his work in Porto Rico, which later was extended to<lb/>
our Southern States and under the Rockefeller Institute to many lands you are<lb/>
all doubtless aware.</p>
<p>(2) I am sure that nome of you have forgotten the terrible ravages of typhoid<lb/>
fever in our mobilization camps in the Spanish war. This epidemic was studied<lb/>
with fruitful results by a Board of which Walter Reed was the chairman, but<lb/>
it was not until Major Frederick Russell improved the method of Wright of the<lb/>
British Army and perfected a vaccine which was highly protective without<lb/>
excessivily severe reactions that this minacious of diseases which slew our<lb/>
young men and maidens in their prime and was the greatest menace to the<lb/>
efficiency of armies could be controlled. So effective was this great triumph<lb/>
of preventive medicine that introduced into our army in 1909, by 1912 typhoid<lb/>
fever had disappeared from our military hospitals.</p>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMD1400"/>
<p>-3-</p>
<p>(3) The attention of our profession is now being called to the appearance<lb/>
of a severe fever called undulant fever the infection of which occurs in cattle,<lb/>
goats and swine and is not infrequently transmitted to mankind. It is worthy<lb/>
of note that the first endemic focus of this disease in the United States was<lb/>
discovered, recognized and reported twenty two years ago by two young army<lb/>
doctors, undergraduates of the Army Medical School.</p>
<p>It was then called Malta fever. Their report may be found in (Jour. A.U.S. or<lb/>
Report Surgeon General).</p>
<p>(4) In our Philippine possessions our medical officers encountered a strange<lb/>
disease beri-beri which paralized the limbs and caused many deaths. Among our<lb/>
Filopino Scouts it was by far the greatest cause of disability and death. The<lb/>
studies of Ashburn Vedder, <add>Siler and others</add> demonstrated that it was a<lb/>
deficiency disease in which a certain constituent now known as Vitamin C was<lb/>
lacking, and it could be quickly cured and prevented by simple changes in the<lb/>
dietary.</p>
<p>(5) Dengue fever occasionally invades our Southern States and though not a<lb/>
fatal disease is a very painful one. In Manila it is the greatest cause of<lb/>
admissions to hospitals. Its epidemiology has been studied by Army Medical<lb/>
Boards and one of my assistants Colonel Silver, at present in my office, has<lb/>
by a remarkable system of experiments following closely the procedure of Reed,<lb/>
and like him making use of the generous self devotion of our soldiers, has<lb/>
demonstrated that it is a non fetal foster brother of yellow fever, transmitted<lb/>
by the same mosquito and with the same incubation period and similar clinical<lb/>
features.</p>
<p>(6) During the World War the Medical Department in France encountered a formidable<lb/>
fever which attacked the soldiers of our allies in the trenches called trench<lb/>
fever. To study it the Chief Surgeon called upon Colonel Richard Strong who<lb/>
<pb n="4" id="fKAMD1410"/>
-4-<lb/>
had been formerly in the Medical Corps (and had been a student at the Army<lb/>
Medical School under Major Reed)</p>
<p>That familiar but not popular companion of the soldier in the field, called by<lb/>
our boys the cootie was under suspicion of carrying this disease and Strong<lb/>
determined to follow step by step the procedure of Reed's classical experiments.<lb/>
Volunteers were needed and were called for from an ambulance company of the<lb/>
Medical Department. Their commander had them fall in, explained to them the<lb/>
lives and painful illness that might result from the infection but the importance<lb/>
to the Army of determining its cause and method of prevention. He then said that<lb/>
any men who were willing to offer themselves should step one pace to the front.<lb/>
The entire company stepped forward. Does not this show the vitality of the<lb/>
glorious tradition of the yellow fever volunteers of 1900, (one of whom we have<lb/>
with us here tonight). &ldquo;As one lamp lights another, nor grows less<lb/>
So nobleness enkindleth nobleness.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Perhaps you may not unjustly suspect me of imitating the young children who<lb/>
when they have strawberries for supper carefully save the biggest until the<lb/>
last. So I have delayed to mention until now that triumph of preventive<lb/>
medicine which, so far as our safety and happiness are concerned, is the<lb/>
greatest since Jenner's discovery of vaccination, the conquest of yellow fever.<lb/>
This came about as you all know in two phases: The first was the brilliant and<lb/>
dramatic demonstration by Reed of how that dreaded and mysterious disease was<lb/>
transmitted. The second was the wonderful campaign of Gorgas and his Lieutenants<lb/>
in which with unwearied patience, admirable skill in the adaption of the agencies<lb/>
available to the new warfare and an unshakeable determination and faith that<lb/>
ridicule and doubt could not discourage an opposition in high places defeat,<lb/>
gave us first Havana cleansed of the ancient plague and then, after long years<lb/>
of conflict, the Isthumus free from the curse of centuries and made a safe<lb/>
<pb n="5" id="fKAMD1420"/>
-5-<lb/>
pathway for the commerce of the world.</p>
<p>When Reed was sent to Cuba by General Sternberg in June 1900 taking with him his<lb/>
laboratory assistant Carroll, the other two members of this famous commission<lb/>
were already there wearing the uniform of the Army and busy in its service.<lb/>
Agrimusite was at the head of the Army Medical Laboratory in Havana. His<lb/>
classmate in graduation at Columbia Medical School in New York, the gifted<lb/>
and accomplished Lazear was on duty at Columbia Barracks, the Army Headquarters,<lb/>
a few miles southwest of Havana. Lazear by Postgraduate study of malaria<lb/>
in Italy and at John Hopkins was admirably fitted for the work with mosquitoes<lb/>
which was to furnish the clues which solved the mystery of the double trap<lb/>
of the infection afterward spoken of as extrinsic and intrinsic incubation.</p>
<p>And while the Board sits on an August day discussing the way in which the<lb/>
problem could be attacked let us say a word of tribute to Dr. Carlos Finlay<lb/>
born of Scotch parents but a native of the West Indies, who for fifteen years<lb/>
had argued on epidemiological grounds that yellow fever was transmitted by the<lb/>
common household mosquito of those regions. He was a gentle and lovable old<lb/>
man, learned in the science of medicine, but a dreamer whose dream came true,<lb/>
but he could not demonstrate it so that others could see it. A Moses he<lb/>
was, who saw the promised land from Pisgah's height, but to him it was not<lb/>
given to leave the desert of sterile theory and lead the children of science<lb/>
into the productive land of demonstrated fact. At this critical time Reed was<lb/>
called north in a flying trip to rescue the precious records of the Typhoid<lb/>
Board whose loss was threatened by the death of Dr. Shakespeare. When he<lb/>
returned a month later Carroll and the cavalryman Private Dean, known in<lb/>
the records as XY were convalescent from experimental yellow fever and<lb/>
Lazear was dead. But he had left behind him the precious notes from which<lb/>
<pb n="6" id="fKAMD1430"/>
-6-<lb/>
Reed unraveled the hidden secret of the centuries. The evidence was however<lb/>
incomplete, the controls were defective. What was then to be done? All<lb/>
efforts to infect laboratory animals had failed. The dread responsibility of<lb/>
experiment on human beings had to be faced or nothing would be accomplished,<lb/>
and Lazear would have died in vain. Fortunately at that time the Governor<lb/>
of Cuba was a great man and one who held at the same time two commissions. He<lb/>
was a Major General of Volunteers and he was a Captain of the Medical Corps<lb/>
in the Regular Army. So to Leonard Wood went Walter Reed and received his<lb/>
approval and promise both of moral and pecuniary support. But this was not<lb/>
quite enough, he also have in so dubious an enterprise where the charge<lb/>
of murder might be laid at his door he wished like a good medical soldier<lb/>
to have the approval of his Chief the Surgeon General. There was another<lb/>
reason why he wished to hasten north. Curiously enough there was another<lb/>
commission of American Medical Officers who had for over a <del>y</del> year been<lb/>
studying the cause of yellow fever in Havana and had arrived at a diametrically<lb/>
opposite conclusion from Reeds commission, for they were about to report<lb/>
to the American Public Health Association which was to meet in this city of<lb/>
Indianapolis, that the cause of yellow fever was the Sanarelli bacillus.<lb/>
The Academy of Medicine of France had already accepted Sanarelli's organism<lb/>
and if the American Public Health Association should become committed to it,<lb/>
the acceptance of the truth which he hoped to prove would be indeed made<lb/>
hard for him. So again he hastened northward, saw the Surgeon General, came<lb/>
to Indianapolis and routed in a fiery debate the advocate<del>d</del><add>s</add> of Sanarelli.<lb/>
In three weeks he was back in Cuba. General Wood gave the promised money, he<lb/>
built Camp Lazear in a lonely valley at a distance from all infections.<lb/>
Agrimusite bred and infected mosquitos and all was ready except the men who<lb/>
should face the dread experiment. He had planned to get Spanish immigrants<lb/>
<pb n="7" id="fKAMD1440"/>
-7-<lb/>
who were then pouring into Havana and furnish[i]ng non<del>0</del><add>-</add>immune fuel for the flames<lb/>
of pestalence, but difficulties arose, the secret got out and the papers of<lb/>
Havana uttered indignant protests against the cruel exploitation of these<lb/>
simple peasants by heartless American scientists. At this fateful emergency<lb/>
came forward two men, young Americans who knew well the risk they ran and also<lb/>
the vast importance to humanity of the question at issue. These two men<lb/>
John J. Moran, Field Clerk at Headquarters and Private John R. Kissinger,<lb/>
Hospital Corps whom we have with us here tonight, stepped into the breach<lb/>
without desire of reward when the chance came to do a great an heroic and<lb/>
noble act. They simply stepped forward and did it simply, modestly and<lb/>
without heroics. After them came twelve other American soldiers who suffered<lb/>
attacks of yellow fever and four who went through the <add>long</add> and repuls<add>ive</add><lb/>
<del>in</del> experience, and, as it then deemed, the <add>more</add> dangerous one of<lb/>
sleeping in the fouled infected bedding. With them <del>were <add>also</add> certain</del> Spaniards<lb/>
also who <add><unclear>later</unclear></add> endured the test for the gold that was offered them, and the not<lb/>
less prized immunity from future attacks. Will you permit me to read the names<lb/>
of these brave men which with the memory of their services to humanity we<lb/>
should carry in our hearts.</p>
<p>Yellow Fever Roll of Honor.</p>
<pb n="8" id="fKAMD1450"/>
<p>Jas. F. Hanberry - Father, W.E. Hanberry, Denmark, South Carolina<lb/>
P. Hamann - Father, August Hamann, Moline, Ill.<lb/>
Levi E. Folk, Home address, 374 S. 3rd Street, Columbus, Ohio.<lb/>
Wallace Forbes, home address, 1523 Irving Ave., Minneapolis, Minn.<lb/>
John H. Andrus, Father, Seth C. Andrus, Elmira, New York.<lb/>
Thos. M. England, Captain M.A.C., 1323 Clifton St., Washington, D.C.<lb/>
A. W. Covington, R.F.D., #3 Cohocton, New York.<lb/>
John R. Kissinger, R.F.D. #8, Huntington, Ind.<lb/>
Clyde L. West, 225 - 3rd St., N.W., Washington, D.C.</p>
<p>John J. Moran<lb/>
John R. Bullard<lb/>
W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> H. Dean<lb/>
Warren G. Jernegan<lb/>
Charles G. Sonntag<lb/>
Dr. R. P. Cooke<lb/>
James Hildebrand<lb/>
Edward Weatherwalks</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
