<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD0790">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Valery Havard to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 19, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Havard, Valery</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD0790</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-04-19</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-04-19">April 19, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD0790</idno>
<title>Letter from Valery Havard to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 19, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Havard recalls Gorgas' hesitance in accepting the conclusions of the Reed commission and his continuance of the expensive disinfection of fomites. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1925-04-19">
<head>Letter from Valery Havard to Jefferson Randolph Kean, April 19, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD0790"/>
<opener>
<hi>From Col. V. Havard</hi> - Med. Corps U.S.A. Ret'd.<lb/>
<hi>Chief Surgeon, Division of Cuba</hi>.<lb/>
Fairfield. Conn.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1925-04-19">April 19. 1925</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>My Dear Colonel Kean,</salute>
</opener>
<p>Your letter of March 19, with editorial<lb/>
from Military Surgeon, were duly received and<lb/>
certainly read with great pleasure and interest. Many<lb/>
thanks for them. This editorial is quite worthy of<lb/>
your pen and in every way admirable. I must<lb/>
apologize for not replying as promptly as I should.<lb/>
A combination of illness and old age had a decided<lb/>
inhibitory effect on my correspondence, even with<lb/>
friends for whom I have always entertained the<lb/>
highest regard. Please forgive this apparent indif-<lb/>
ference.</p>
<p>We are certainly fortunate in having such<lb/>
an organ as the Military Surgeon, but particularly<lb/>
so in having the benefit of your experience and great<lb/>
abilities in its management. I hope that the burden<lb/>
will not be greater than you can bear and that you<lb/>
can get all the assistance you need.</p>
<p>I had already read, with entire approval, your<lb/>
article in the N.Y. Times of April 27. 1924, and had<lb/>
certainly intended to offer you my congratulations at<lb/>
the time, but I presume the combination of disabilities<lb/>
mentioned above made me neglect to to go.</p>
<p>I think you are doing our friend Gorgas full<lb/>
justice and, at the same time, rendering also to<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD0800"/>
<hi>2</hi><lb/>
others the credit which is their due. It is<lb/>
probably impossible to tell every thing and please<lb/>
everybody, but no one can accuse you to say a<lb/>
word not strictly according to facts and truth<unclear>!</unclear></p>
<p>I remember everybody's surprise at Gorgas'<lb/>
attitude in hesitating so long to accept the con-<lb/>
clusions so clearly brought out by Reed, especial<lb/>
ly in <hi>continuing the useless and expensive disin-<lb/>
fection of fomites until August</hi>. In reference<lb/>
to this I may perhaps bring back to your mem-<lb/>
ory the part played by Surgeon General Sternberg<lb/>
in jogging up Gorgas' mind. I remember distinctly<lb/>
calling on General Wood, early in April. 1901,<lb/>
and submitting my draft of Circular no. 5 which<lb/>
had become necessary. He was quite perplexed over<lb/>
the subject of fomites, fearing that the stoppage<lb/>
of disinfection, altho apparently the correct thing<lb/>
to do, would be too sudden a change, and that he<lb/>
was not yet quite decided to assume such respon-<lb/>
sibility. I suggested to send the draft to the Surgeon<lb/>
General (Sternberg) and to be guided by his advice.<lb/>
Gen. Wood thought this a good idea, and the<lb/>
Circular was forwarded at once to Washington.<lb/>
Evidently Sternberg had already made up his mind<lb/>
on this question of fomites. He replied without<lb/>
delay and with full conviction that, after the ex-<lb/>
periments of the Reed Commission, doubt was no longer<lb/>
possible and that the Circular should be published,<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMD0810"/>
<hi>3</hi><lb/>
and <hi>it was</hi> published at once (April 27)<lb/>
Any hesitation after that on the part of Gorgas<lb/>
was incomprehensible and unpardonable.</p>
<p>I am sorry to say that my publisher<lb/>
(W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Wood and Co.) declines to bring out another<lb/>
edition of my Military Hygiene, or any other M.<lb/>
H. He says there is no money in it, or not<lb/>
enough to warrant the trouble and worry. Such<lb/>
being the case the necessary expenses, it appears to<lb/>
me, must come out of the author's pocket -- where<lb/>
there is none -- or still much better, a new plan<lb/>
adopted for this and similar works, namely. They<lb/>
should be declared official, prepared by a board<lb/>
of 2 or 3 medical officers and printed by the Governm't.<lb/>
This seems to me a subject well worth looking into.</p>
<p>My daughter Aline is still under treatment at<lb/>
the Walter Reed Hospital for arthritis. This does not<lb/>
seem to interfere seriously with her literary work.<lb/>
Perhaps you have come across her &ldquo;My Basal Metab-<lb/>
olism&rdquo; in the Atlantic Monthly for February (unsigned)<lb/>
Her books are mostly intended for young people but<lb/>
appear to be as attractive to gray-headed folk. She<lb/>
would be very glad to see you should you happen<lb/>
to visit the hospital.</p>
<p>I am delighted to see the spring flowers and<lb/>
again listen to our familiar birds. Winter has but little<lb/>
comfort for old men and I wish the summer would stay with<lb/>
us to the end--</p>
<closer>
<salute>With best wishes, always sincerely yours.</salute>
<signed>V. Havard</signed>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
