<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD1350">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Laura Wood Roper, April 25, 1943</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD1350</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1943-04-25</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Roper, Laura Wood</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Truby, Albert E.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Cornwell, Dean</name>
<name type="person">Hench, Philip Showalter</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Cornelia Knox</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1943-04-25">April 24, 1943</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD1350</idno>
<title>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Laura Wood Roper, April 25, 1943</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean finds Roper's book admirable, in substance and in literary style. He mentions that her dramatic style of writing has caused her to rely heavily on her imagination. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1943-04-25">
<head>Letter from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Laura Wood Roper, April 25, 1943</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD1350"/>
<opener>
W.R. and Y.F.<lb/>
Copy<lb/>
To Miss Laura R. Wood<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1943-04-25">April 25, 1943</date>
</dateline><lb/>
<salute>Dear Miss Laura.</salute>
</opener>
<p>I realize well that my letter of the<lb/>
17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> must have been a disappointment to you, as it<lb/>
amounted simply to being an acknowledgement of the<lb/>
receipt of your book with my thanks &amp; a promise to<lb/>
write again. Since then I have read it all and<lb/>
thought much about it. By your selection of the dra-<lb/>
matic method of telling your story - by which I mean<lb/>
you do it by putting the words in the months of the<lb/>
dramatic personal and hearing them do it in the<lb/>
parts of vital interest and importance, you have<lb/>
added greatly to the vividness and interest of your<lb/>
story. At the same time you have made a heavy<lb/>
demand on your imagination. Like the novelist<lb/>
you have made it necessary to evolve a clear cut<lb/>
quite definite and more or less intimate conception<lb/>
of each one, so that in a group you have had to<lb/>
select the right man to tell his part of the story<lb/>
and <add>use</add> the appropriate words which he would use to<lb/>
say it. A novelist has a great advantage<lb/>
over the historian in that the characters in the for-<lb/>
mer's story have no existence outside of his mind<lb/>
and so in the act of their creation he gives them veri-<lb/>
similitude: whereas the historian in his story<lb/>
if told dramatically has to fit his acts and words<lb/>
to individuals who have a personality known<lb/>
known more or less accurately to their friends and<lb/>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD1360"/>
2<lb/>
acquaintances. This is some job, and even if<lb/>
you knew Reed and his assistants and family<lb/>
and the other important persons in this great<lb/>
episode, as well as Truby and I for example<lb/>
knew them, you could not make the picture too<lb/>
true to life as we saw it. You could not bring<lb/>
out some of the shadows in the picture. Carroll's<lb/>
dislike of Agramonte (which the latter fully returned)<lb/>
or his jealously of his Chief and benefactor Reed,<lb/>
which let him to consider himself as the real hero<lb/>
who was robbed of the credit of leadership and<lb/>
discovery by Reed and his friends because the<lb/>
latter was a member of the regular Medical Corps<lb/>
while he was only a contract doctor at that time.<lb/>
They had five points too. Of course you could<lb/>
not bring this out in your story, you had more<lb/>
or less to idealize them. &darr; - But I would<lb/>
not put into Carroll's mouth the proposition<lb/>
that the board members would take the first<lb/>
risk (p. 205) His was the first case only because<lb/>
Lazears first bite was not ripe. Carroll did<lb/>
not for a minute believe in the Finlay theory.<lb/>
You may be sure that Reed made that statement.<lb/>
I mention this not as a fault in the book, but<lb/>
as an illustrative of the extraordinary diffi-<lb/>
culty of your task. The visit to Finlay, and<lb/>
who went with Reed, as well as when they went<lb/>
are interesting questions about which I have no<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMD1370"/>
3<lb/>
JRK to L N Wood<lb/>
first-hand information. Dean Cornwell,<lb/>
the painter came to see me to get what infor-<lb/>
mation I had, some months before he painted<lb/>
the Conquerors of Yellow Fever. I did not have<lb/>
much to give him as I was away from Cuba<lb/>
on sick leave from July 3 to Aug 13, 1900<lb/>
But I advised him to paint the patio<lb/>
scene with only Finlay &amp; Reed &amp; his assistants.<lb/>
I always thought Reeds visit to Finlay was<lb/>
before the Pinar del Rio Epidemic. I see you<lb/>
place it after, but in your Appendix II admit<lb/>
that it is not definitely known. These details<lb/>
are of interest, but not of cardinal importance.<lb/>
You have told all of the important facts with<lb/>
admirable accuracy and clarity. It is<lb/>
altogether an admirable book, in substance<lb/>
and in literary style. I hope you have<lb/>
made the Publisher send copies to General<lb/>
Truby and to Col Hench. His last address<lb/>
was the Broadmoor Hotel, Colorado Springs, Colo.<lb/>
I am sure they will both be much pleased<lb/>
with it, and all of us will be proud of the<lb/>
generous credit you have given us.</p>
<closer>
<salute>With my very hearty congratulations and Easter<lb/>
Greetings I am very cordially yours</salute>
<signed>JRK.</signed>
<seg>
P.S. Mrs Kean did not come back to Cuba with me on Aug 13&sol;00<lb/>
She came on the boat with Reed and I met them Oct. 3 at<lb/>
matanzas &amp; came to Havana with them Oct. 4 I told Reed the<lb/>
news of the death of Lazear then.<lb/>
</seg>
</closer>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
