<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="KAMD0910">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Merritte W. Ireland, February 2, 1928</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Kean, Jefferson Randolph</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>KAMD0910</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc> 
<bibl> 
<idno type="callNo">Papers of Jefferson Randolph Kean [manuscript] / Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1860-1950. MSS 628. The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</idno>
</bibl> 
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1928-02-02</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term type="recipient">Ireland, Merritte W.</term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Root, Elihu</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Mabel H.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, Jennie</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">West, Clyde L.</name>
<name type="person">O'Reilly, Robert M.</name>
<name type="person">Roosevelt, Theodore</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1928-02-02">February 2, 1928</date>
<idno rend="suppress">KAMD0910</idno>
<title>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Merritte W. Ireland, February 2, 1928</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Kean supports offering pensions for those who took part in the Reed Yellow Fever demonstration, and for the widows of those who died. He also supports a pension for Agramonte for his important contribution to the Board. [Courtesy of The Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia Library]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1928-02-02">
<head>Memorandum from Jefferson Randolph Kean to Merritte W. Ireland, February 2, 1928</head>
<pb n="1" id="fKAMD0910"/>
<p>From J.R.K.</p>
<p>2 February, 1928</p>
<p>MEMORANDUM FOR GENERAL IRELAND</p>
<p>SUBJECT:- Pensions for those taking part in the Reed Yellow<lb/>
Fever Demonstration, and the Widows of those who died.</p>
<p>In reply to letter of Hon. J. Mayhew Wainwright, M.C.</p>
<p>In the autumn of 1902 the demonstration by Walter Reed and<lb/>
his assistants of the transmission of yellow fever by the house<lb/>
mosquito (then called Culex Fascit<add>us,</add> but now called Aedes Egypti)<lb/>
had been accepted quite generally by scientific men and the City of<lb/>
Havana had been cleared of yellow fever by the application of<lb/>
this discovery. It then seemed to the Secretary of War to be the<lb/>
time to <add>consider</add> the question of awards for this extraordinary<lb/>
scientific work, attended as it was by danger to all taking part<lb/>
in it, and illness and loss of life to some. The Secretary of<lb/>
War, Mr. Elihu Root, accordingly recommended in his annual report<lb/>
to the President that steps be taken to promote Major Walter Reed<lb/>
from the grade he then held to that of Colonel, and promote Major<lb/>
William C. Gorgas to the grade of Lieutenant Colonel. Before<lb/>
this recommendation could be carried out Reed died, November 23,<lb/>
1902, without having received any reward. The promotion recommended<lb/>
for him was given to Gorgas.</p>
<p>A bill was prepared in this office recommending that Congress<lb/>
grant to his widow,who was left with only a small life insurance,<lb/>
as a pension the monthly pay he was receiving at the time of his<lb/>
death, <add>$300.00</add>. This amount, however, was reduced when<lb/>
considered by the Senate Committee to $125.00 per month, which was<lb/>
for some years provided in the Army appropriation bill. A like amount<lb/>
was given to the widow of Dr. Jesse W. Lazear, who lost his life in<lb/>
the course of this work. Dr. James Carroll, who was a contract<lb/>
surgeon, was given a commission in the regular medical corps, and<lb/>
was, before his death, promoted to the grade of Major. After his<lb/>
death in September, 1907 his wife was given the same annuity with<lb/>
the other two widows ($125.00 per month)</p>
<pb n="2" id="fKAMD0920"/>
<p>General Ireland<lb/>
-2-</p>
<p>John R. Kissinger, a private in the Army Hospital Corps, one<lb/>
of the first volunteers to offer himself for experiment in this<lb/>
demonstration, and who contracted a severe case of yellow fever, was,<lb/>
in 1907, given a pension of $12.00 per month, his health having failed<lb/>
him so that he was unable to work. Later this pension was increased to<lb/>
$100.00 per month, which he is now receiving.</p>
<p>Another of the volunteers who suffered an attack of experimental<lb/>
yellow fever, Clyde L. West, at that time also a private in the<lb/>
Hospital Corps, was given a like pension of $100.00 per month by<lb/>
Congress last year.</p>
<p>The above mentioned are the only recipients of any pension or reward<lb/>
from the U.S. government for their part in this great work, although a<lb/>
number of others took part in it. A full list of these with the<lb/>
part taken by each as shown by the official records are published in<lb/>
Senate Document #10, 59th Congress, second session. This document<lb/>
consists of a memorandum for the President from The Surgeon General<lb/>
R.M. O'Reilley, which was forwarded to the Senate and House of Repre-<lb/>
sentatives with a special message by the President which was as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The enclosed papers are transmitted to Congress in the earnest<lb/>
hope that it will take suitable action in the matter. Major Reed's<lb/>
part in the experiments which resulted in teaching us how to cope with<lb/>
yellow fever was such as to render mankind his debtor, and this nation<lb/>
should in some proper fashion bear witness of this fact. Theodore<lb/>
Roosevelt, White House, December 5, 1906.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In my opinion Congress has failed to carry out the recommendation<lb/>
of the President &ldquo;to take suitable action in the matter.&rdquo; I consider<lb/>
that the pensions given were not suitable to meet the necessities of<lb/>
the recipients, or to adequately award so great a work. Since they<lb/>
were given, however, the inadequancy has been greatly augmented by the<lb/>
increase in the cost of living, and the inflation of currency caused<lb/>
by the World War, which have practically reduced their purchasing power<lb/>
and value one half. It seems evident the pensions now being given<lb/>
should all be doubled, and as other claimants arise as participators in<lb/>
this work they should be considered in like manner in accordance with<lb/>
the merits of each.</p>
<p>Only one member of the Board of Medical Officer conducting these<lb/>
experiments remains alive; this is Dr. Aristides Agramonte, who is<lb/>
now Professor in the medical school of the University of Havana.<lb/>
Dr. Agramonte was born in Cuba during the ten years' war for independence<lb/>
fought by the Cubans against Spain. In this war, his father, a Cuban<lb/>
officer was killed in battle, and his family removed to the United States<lb/>
while he was still a small boy. He was educated in New York and<lb/>
graduated in medicine from the College of Physicians and Surgeons in<lb/>
1892. He served for a number of years in the medical corps of the army<lb/>
as Acting Assistant Surgeon, and as such <unclear><del>was</del>as</unclear> appointed a member of the<lb/>
<pb n="3" id="fKAMD0930"/>
General Ireland<lb/>
-3-<lb/>
Board of Medical Officers headed by Major Walter Reed which was sent to<lb/>
Cuba to study yellow fever. This board was appointed by special order<lb/>
122, A.G.O., Washington, May 24, 1900. Dr. Agramonte took a very<lb/>
important part <unclear>in</unclear> the work of the Board. (See note) The fact that<lb/>
he is now a citizen of Cuba in no way diminishes the obligation of<lb/>
the United States to recognise and appropriately reward the work<lb/>
which he did while serving in the U. S. army. I would recommend<lb/>
that he be given a gold medal struck by order of Congress in commemora-<lb/>
tion,of the work of the Board of which he was a member, and that this<lb/>
medal be given also to the heir of each of the deceased members of the<lb/>
Board; also, that Dr. Aristides Agramonte be given an annuity equal<lb/>
to that given to the widows of the deceased members of the Board, and<lb/>
that this annuity be made payable, in the event of his death, to his<lb/>
widow during her life.</p>
<p>J.R. K.</p>
<p>NOTE: I am informed by the officer who prepared the memorandum for<lb/>
the President published in Senate Document #10 referred to above, that<lb/>
in his opinion the statement of Dr. Agramonte's share in the work made<lb/>
in that memorandum does not do justice to Dr. Agramonte. This statement<lb/>
was based upon information believed by the officer to be reliable, but<lb/>
which was afterwards found to be inaccurate. When Dr. Agramonte's<lb/>
attention was called to Senate Document #10 he made a protest against<lb/>
the injustice done him, but there seemed to be at that time no way to<lb/>
correct it.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
