<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N0427001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, September 10, 1905</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N0427001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1905-09-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, William</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William Henry</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia University, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Trinity Hall Military School, Washington (Pa.)</name>
<name type="hospital">Johns Hopkins Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1905-09-10">September 10, 1905</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N0427001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, September 10, 1905</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Windsor Mill Place</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1905-09-10">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, September 10, 1905</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN0427001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1905-09-10">Sept 10, 1905</date>
</dateline>
THE SUN, BALTIMORE, SUNDAY MORNING, <unclear>SEPTEMBER</unclear><lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>WINDSOR MILL PLACE</p>
<p>-------------</p>
<p>An Old Mansion Associated With<lb/>
Baltimore's Early History.</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>PROPOSED PARK BOULEVARD</p>
<p>-----------</p>
<p>Will Pass Through The Estate --<lb/>
Boyhood Home Of Dr. Jesse Wil-<lb/>
liam Lazear, Yellow-Fever Hero.</p>
<p>By EMILY EMERSON LANTZ.</p>
<p>Truly there is a great gulf fixed between<lb/>
things celestial and things of the earth<lb/>
earthy! Most of us affirm, and with entire<lb/>
sincerity, that the end and aim of our<lb/>
earthly endeavor is to attain &ldquo;a house not<lb/>
made with hands&rdquo; in the world to come,<lb/>
yet until this mortal shall have put on<lb/>
immortality the very height of our am-<lb/>
bition is to possess a hand-made house. One<lb/>
of those wide, hospitable dwellings whose<lb/>
stone walls afford cool protection from the<lb/>
sun of midsummer and warmth and shelter<lb/>
from the blasts of winter, the laths of<lb/>
which are turned and the nails and keys<lb/>
wrought by handcraft.</p>
<p>Such houses possess an individuality and<lb/>
character wholly impossible to the so-to-<lb/>
ALONG THE LINE OF THE PROPOSED BOULEVARD<lb/>
speak ready-made houses that are evolved<lb/>
with the suddenness and as little apparent<lb/>
human effort as the wonders of the stage<lb/>
magician.</p>
<p>There are many old houses interesting<lb/>
both of themselves and through the person-<lb/>
ality of those inhabiting them around Bal-<lb/>
timore, and among them is the Windsor<lb/>
Mill place, on the Gwynn's falls, which<lb/>
belongs to the heirs of General Jesse La-<lb/>
zear, a prominent banker and Congress-<lb/>
man of Western Pennsylvania, whose only<lb/>
daughter, Mrs. Alexander Seth, resides on<lb/>
the old estate. Peculiar interest centers in<lb/>
the estate, because through part of it will<lb/>
be laid out the proposed park extension<lb/>
driveway which is destined in the near fu-<lb/>
ture to make the Gwynn's Falls Park road<lb/>
for Baltimore what the Wissahicken drive<lb/>
is to Philadelphia. For years Mrs. Seth<lb/>
and her brothers, joint heirs of the estate,<lb/>
have held themselves in readiness to do-<lb/>
nate a portion of their land to such a proj-<lb/>
ect of local improvement and one of the<lb/>
WINDSOR MILL PLACE<lb/>
most picturesque portions of the proposed<lb/>
forest drive will be that which will pass<lb/>
through Windsor Mill place, which extends<lb/>
for over 4,000 feet along Gwynn's falls.</p>
<p>The old residence of the Windsor Mill<lb/>
place is a stone mansion that crowns one<lb/>
portion of the Windsor Hills and which<lb/>
took its name from a stone mill that once<lb/>
turned tranquil wheels of usefulness on<lb/>
Gwynn's falls at the intersection of the<lb/>
ancient Powhatan road and the Wethereds-<lb/>
ville road that extends along Gwynn's falls.<lb/>
As all roads once led to Rome, so in olden<lb/>
days all roads in the vicinity of what is<lb/>
now Walbrook led to Windsor Mill, the<lb/>
center of neighborhood commercial interest.<lb/>
The mansion overlooking the site of the<lb/>
former mill property is older than the mem-<lb/>
ory of its oldest possessor. The oldest deed<lb/>
extant to the property is dated August 7,<lb/>
1787, and conveys a broad piece of landed<lb/>
estate from William Baxley, gentleman, of<lb/>
Baltimore county, Maryland, to William<lb/>
Bingham, gentleman, of Philadelphia, and<lb/>
Robert Gilmor, gentleman, of Baltimore<lb/>
town and county.</p>
<p>The tract was known as Roger's Enlarge-<lb/>
ment and described in the deed as follow-<lb/>
ing the windings and meadows of Gwynn's<lb/>
falls, and it included a piece of land called<lb/>
Crowley's First Venture.</p>
<p>A later purchaser was the late Rev.<lb/>
Dr. Francis Waters, who was one of the<lb/>
organizers of and gave its name to the<lb/>
Methodist Protestant Church. The cler-<lb/>
gyman was the father of Dr. Edmund G.<lb/>
Waters, residing at 1711 Madison avenue.<lb/>
Rev. Dr. Waters bought the estate, then<lb/>
about 175 acres and extending on both<lb/>
sides of the falls, in 1835 from Oliver Kin-<lb/>
sey.</p>
<p>Half of the original house had at that<lb/>
time been destroyed by fire, but the old<lb/>
house as occupied by Dr. Waters remains<lb/>
unchanged, although a front wing and back<lb/>
building, causing the whole to resemble the<lb/>
letter Z, have been added.</p>
<p>The original stone house has a width of<lb/>
about 75 feet and is but one room deep,<lb/>
with a stone and log kitchen in the rear.</p>
<p>It has three spacious apartments on the<lb/>
first floor, with the same number of rooms<lb/>
above, and a stairway at each end of the<lb/>
building. Curiously enough, a passageway<lb/>
extends across the front of the second story<lb/>
and the bedrooms look westward upon a<lb/>
sweet, placid English court effect formed by<lb/>
the angle of the house. Here a velvet lawn<lb/>
is bounded by alleys of boxwood, after the<lb/>
fashion of the formal garden at Mount Ver-<lb/>
non, and the air is fragrant with the snowy<lb/>
blossoming of old-fashioned &ldquo;day <unclear>lillies</unclear>.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Clambering ivy and other vines scale the<lb/>
walls, seeking to peep in the dormer win-<lb/>
dows of an attic that extends the length of<lb/>
the house. This garret is a treasure trove<lb/>
for those who love the things of the past,<lb/>
and among the quaint things are old hair-<lb/>
covered and leather-covered trunks beaded<lb/>
with brass tacks, iron-bound and rope-tied<lb/>
trunks, as well as &ldquo;boxes,&rdquo; as the English<lb/>
would say, of tin and chests of wood; and<lb/>
in them things old and quaint enough to<lb/>
stock the curiosity shop of a Dickens.</p>
<p>Old wedding and ball gowns of brocade<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
rich and stiff enough to stand alone:<lb/>
steeple-crowned and poke bonnets, all<lb/>
wreathed within with flowers--a fitting<lb/>
frame for some fair flower-like face; dainty<lb/>
lingerie embroidered by hand and laces<lb/>
filmy and weblike, once worn as berthas<lb/>
over low-cut gowns.</p>
<p>The stone walls of the house are of the<lb/>
thickness of a foot and each room on the<lb/>
ground floor has a capacious fireplace, with<lb/>
brass shovel and tongs. The doors are of<lb/>
a solidity that delights the eye, and their<lb/>
handles are of solid brass, egg-shaped, or<lb/>
else loops of brass of the same quaint pat-<lb/>
tern as those at Mount Vernon. The great<lb/>
brass knocker at the entrance is said to be<lb/>
more modern, but it represents an Ameri-<lb/>
can eagle--bird of freedom--and looks old<lb/>
enough to have welcomed patriot and Tory<lb/>
guests to the mansion in generations past.</p>
<p>The mahogany sideboard, graced with<lb/>
silver candlesticks, ancient settees and<lb/>
Chippendale tables that furnish the resi-<lb/>
dence are in keeping with its antiquity<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
and upon the upper floors are stanch ma-<lb/>
hogany wardrobes that inclose chests of<lb/>
drawers in the middle and open at each<lb/>
end for the hanging of dainty gowns.</p>
<p>The window sills everywhere are deep<lb/>
as embattled casements, and one of the<lb/>
quaintest relics of the past is the stone<lb/>
spring house with moss-covered conical<lb/>
roof, while the iron key, nearly a foot long<lb/>
and over 100 years old, of the stone smoke-<lb/>
house is ponderous enough to grant admis-<lb/>
sion to a bastile. Gates through the place<lb/>
yield to weights, instead of latch or bolts,<lb/>
so that the quaintness of the building is not<lb/>
marred by modern surroundings.</p>
<p>The &ldquo;new&rdquo; wing is 40 years old. It was<lb/>
built to afford a spacious drawing room for<lb/>
his only daughter (now Mrs. Alexander<lb/>
Seth) by Gen. Jesse Lazear. The somewhat<lb/>
stately furnishings of the period and the<lb/>
original wall paper outlined in gold leaf<lb/>
continue unchanged, and wide porches ex-<lb/>
tend the length of both the old and new<lb/>
portions of the house.</p>
<p>Rev. Dr. Francis Waters, who bought<lb/>
the Windsor Mill place in 1835 and resided<lb/>
there until <unclear>1852</unclear>, was one of the finest<lb/>
Greek and Latin scholars of his day and<lb/>
one of the leading educators of Maryland.<lb/>
He was at one time president of Washing-<lb/>
ton College, at Chestertown, Md., and later<lb/>
principal of the Princess Anne Academy.<lb/>
Isaac Jones, Attorney-General of Mary-<lb/>
land, was one of those educated by him,<lb/>
and Congressman Crisfield, of Somerset<lb/>
county. In order to have his own sons<lb/>
educated under his supervision by tutors<lb/>
and yet enjoy the companionship of other<lb/>
lads Dr. Waters conducted a school in a<lb/>
stone schoolhouse building then on the<lb/>
place, while some of the boys were resi-<lb/>
dents of his home. The tutor was a native<lb/>
Greek who had received his education in<lb/>
England and at Princeton, and the school<lb/>
flourished until the death of Dr. Waters'<lb/>
eldest son caused him to lose interest in<lb/>
the undertaking. The schoolhouse still<lb/>
stands unoccupied upon a portion of the<lb/>
estate which has since become the prop-<lb/>
erty of Mrs. Gaun Hutton and which ex-<lb/>
tends to the <unclear>Frankiln</unclear> turnpike.</p>
<p>The next owner of the old place was Mr.<lb/>
James H. Carter, of the banking and <unclear>brok-<lb/>
erage</unclear> firm of Lee &amp; Johnston. He bought it<lb/>
of Dr. Waters for $10,000, and at his death<lb/>
the property included 218 acres and ex-<lb/>
tended on both sides of Gwynn's falls. To<lb/>
him is due many of the exterior improve-<lb/>
ments that make the place peculiarly beau-<lb/>
tiful. He planted rare trees, a fine avenue<lb/>
of Norway <unclear>firs</unclear> and cedars, a buckeye tree<lb/>
whose springtime blossoms attract myriads<lb/>
of jewel-like humming birds. There are<lb/>
splendid beech trees and a lofty sugar ma-<lb/>
ple from whose sap many a pound of maple<lb/>
sugar has been secured. There are arbor<lb/>
vitae hedges and a magnificent weeping<lb/>
willow watered by an ancient pump. Tow-<lb/>
ering walnut trees cast their rich shade<lb/>
and a wisteria vine flings an archway of<lb/>
purple blossoms across the drive along the<lb/>
sides of which are beds of myrtle and wild<lb/>
violets.</p>
<p>One of the many improvements made<lb/>
by Mr. Carter was the erection of a gate-<lb/>
keeper's lodge--a rather picturesque struc-<lb/>
ture of semi-Italian design at the entrance<lb/>
to the drive that opens upon the old Weth-<lb/>
eredsville road, facing the falls.</p>
<p>This lodge, now in disuse for its orig-<lb/>
inal purpose, will fall within the area of<lb/>
land donated by General Lazear's heirs to<lb/>
the Park Board for a boulevard. It offers<lb/>
exceptional opportunity, both from a pic-<lb/>
turesque and practical point of view, to the<lb/>
Park Board. The forest drives of Europe<lb/>
abound with quaint chalets and inns,<lb/>
where pleasure-seekers, made hungry by<lb/>
exercise in the open air, may obtain some<lb/>
light refreshment. There is a very definite<lb/>
need in Baltimore parks of some places<lb/>
where those seeking outdoor recreation,<lb/>
and especially those accompanied by small<lb/>
children, could be sure of finding some-<lb/>
where for sale such simple refreshment<lb/>
as a glass of pure milk and a bun. There<lb/>
is small doubt that should the Windsor Mill<lb/>
Lodge be fitted up as an attractive tea<lb/>
room, where a cup of good tea, a glass of<lb/>
fresh milk, cream or country buttermilk<lb/>
could be secured with a biscuit or cracker,<lb/>
there is small doubt that it would fill a<lb/>
long-felt want in this community. The<lb/>
standard of the milk and cream would have<lb/>
to be maintained by frequent official inspec-<lb/>
tion, and the license to sell such edibles<lb/>
made subject to revocation by the Park<lb/>
Board if such regulations were not com-<lb/>
plied with. This is a chance for Major<lb/>
Venable to become the benefactor of old and<lb/>
young alike. There used to be, and per-<lb/>
haps still is, near Monterey, in the Blue<lb/>
Ridge Mountains, a tollgate where the gate-<lb/>
keeper's wife sold cream and buttermilk,<lb/>
and her clean dairy was the Mecca of all<lb/>
pilgrimages through the woods and along<lb/>
mountain roads.</p>
<p>Mr. Carter's occupancy of Windsor Mills<lb/>
was marked by an effort to reclaim the<lb/>
waste meadowland lying between the old<lb/>
Wetheredville road and the stream. He<lb/>
built at his own expense a public road nearer<lb/>
the falls than the old one and sodded the<lb/>
intervening meadows as a spreading lawn.<lb/>
The great flood of July 24, <unclear>1868,</unclear> swept<lb/>
away every vestige of the new-made road-<lb/>
way and not an ounce of earth was left to<lb/>
mark the spot of the sodded lawn. After<lb/>
this disaster travel was resumed on the old<lb/>
Wetheredville road, where it continues.</p>
<p>Windsor Heights was at that time in-<lb/>
cluded in the estate, but through sales to<lb/>
Mr. Francis White and others the place is<lb/>
now limited to about 100 acres.</p>
<p>Through the late Chauncey Brooks, who<lb/>
was the executor of Mr. Carter, Gen. Jesse<lb/>
Lazear, of Uniontown, Pa., became the<lb/>
next owner of Windsor Mill Place.</p>
<p>General Lazear was the grandfather of<lb/>
Dr. Jesse William Lazear, and the old estate<lb/>
has the distinction of being associated<lb/>
with the childhood of a man great and<lb/>
noble enough to lay down his life in the<lb/>
cause of medical science and humanity.<lb/>
Dr. Lazear was a Marylander, born in 1866,<lb/>
and the son of the late William Lazear and<lb/>
nephew of Mr. T. C. Lazear, of Pittsburg.<lb/>
After studying at Trinity Hall Military<lb/>
School, the Johns Hopkins and Columbia<lb/>
Universities he won high honors in the<lb/>
medical profession. Later Dr. Lazear be-<lb/>
came a surgeon in the United States Army<lb/>
and was assigned to special laboratory<lb/>
work at Columbia barracks, near Havana,<lb/>
Cuba. He was appointed in 1900 a mem-<lb/>
ber of a special Government commission<lb/>
for the investigation of yellow fever. This<lb/>
commission made discoveries of the great-<lb/>
est scientific importance in connection with<lb/>
yellow fever, but there came a point in the<lb/>
investigation where further progress in the<lb/>
theory that yellow fever is <unclear>transmitted</unclear><lb/>
solely through the bite of the <unclear>mosquito</unclear><lb/>
depended wholly upon human experiment.<lb/>
Dr. Lazear and a comrade volunteered to<lb/>
subject themselves to infection through<lb/>
the bite of the mosquitoes that had pre-<lb/>
viously bitten sufferers from yellow fever,<lb/>
and both men became infected with the dis-<lb/>
ease and died. Dr. Welch, of the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins Hospital, has referred to the re-<lb/>
port of this commission as the most im-<lb/>
portant contribution to medicine since the<lb/>
discovery of an&aelig;sthesia. At Johns Hopkins<lb/>
Hospital and at Trinity Hall Military<lb/>
School, Washington, Pa., there are tablets<lb/>
honoring the noble man who thus laid down<lb/>
his life for humanity.</p>
<p>From the highest points of the Windsor<lb/>
Mill Place can be had a magnificent view<lb/>
of country and city, and down the Balti-<lb/>
more waterways to the point where river<lb/>
and bay unite. The place abounds in stone,<lb/>
and it is said that many of the cobblestones<lb/>
for paving Baltimore in the vicinity of<lb/>
West Fayette and Lexington streets were<lb/>
hauled in four-horse loads from off the<lb/>
Windsor Mill estate. There are beautiful<lb/>
springs upon the ground, and Somerfield<lb/>
Camp, so named from the noted English<lb/>
divine, was held in the groves on the top<lb/>
of the heights. The colored brethren of the<lb/>
neighborhood are fond also of holding re-<lb/>
ligious meetings beneath these forest trees.<lb/>
There are those who remember a discourse<lb/>
concerning the Master and His &ldquo;twelve ap-<lb/>
prentices,&rdquo; and another occasion when the<lb/>
turning of Lot's wife into a pillar of salt<lb/>
was under discussion and the speaker cas-<lb/>
ually remarked:</p>
<p>&ldquo;That's where all our salt comes from.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The Windsor Mill, spoken of in docu-<lb/>
ments of 1818 as the &ldquo;old Windsor Mill,&rdquo;<lb/>
remained long an unimposing ruin just be-<lb/>
yond the bridge that spans Gwynns Falls<lb/>
beyond Mount Holly. It was removed at<lb/>
a very recent date, but the name lives on<lb/>
in the estate which forms the subject of<lb/>
this sketch.</p>
<p>THE OLD GATEKEEPER'S LODGE</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
