<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N1229012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The News Leader, Richmond, Va., September 15, 1925</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1229012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1925-09-15</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Ross, Ronald</name>
<name type="person">Pasteur, Louis</name>
<name type="person">Welch, William H.</name>
<name type="person">Lister, Joseph</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Gorgas, William Crawford</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Panama</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">Virginia</name>
<name type="hospital">Bellvue Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1925-09-15">September 15, 1925</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1229012</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The News Leader, Richmond, Va., September 15, 1925</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>That &ldquo;Seeketh Not Its Own&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1925-09-15">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The News Leader, Richmond, Va., September 15, 1925</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1229012"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
The News-Leader,<lb/>
Richmond, Va.<lb/>
<date value="1925-09-15">Sept. 15. 1925</date>
</dateline>
Telephone Randolph 7<lb/>
THE<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>THAT &ldquo;SEEKETH NOT ITS OWN.&rdquo;</p>
<p>DR. HENRY CARTER'S brave, unselfish life was one that inspired<lb/>
men long before it ended yesterday.</p>
<p>This Virginian was heir to a great name and to as fine an an-<lb/>
cestry as any American possesses, but he never played the aristocrat<lb/>
or wasted his time among tombs. Entering the public health ser-<lb/>
vice as soon as he was graduated from medical college, he plunged<lb/>
immediately into the study of tropical diseases, notably yellow fever<lb/>
and malaria.</p>
<p>That was in 1879---fourteen years before SIR RONALD ROSS<lb/>
began his malarial investigations and twenty years before the first<lb/>
American experiments in yellow-fever control in Cuba. PASTEUR<lb/>
was then in the fullness of his labors, LISTER'S results were just be-<lb/>
ing accepted, and the first real bacteriological research ever under-<lb/>
taken in America was about to be inaugurated by a young man of<lb/>
28, WILLIAM H. WELCH by name, who was just returning from<lb/>
Germany. WALTER REED was 27 and finding life none too rosy for<lb/>
an assistant surgeon, ranking first lieutenant, U. S. A. That very<lb/>
year WILLIAM C. GORGAS, aged 24, entered on his duties as interne<lb/>
at Bellevue Hospital.</p>
<p>From the hour he saw his first case of yellow fever until the<lb/>
moment of his death, probably not a day passed that DR. CARTER<lb/>
did not think of that disease or of that other malady carried by the<lb/>
mosquito, the dread malaria, the &ldquo;chills and fever&rdquo; of the South. He<lb/>
put into his work every energy of his spirit. Nothing else, except<lb/>
his duty to his family and to his Maker, ever counted with him. If<lb/>
the trail of yellow fever and malaria lay through the media and<lb/>
among the test tubes of a central laboratory, he would work there,<lb/>
but if it carried him through Panama jungles, or along the oozing<lb/>
river-bottoms of South America, or into swamps of his own Virginia<lb/>
whence the insect long ago had driven man, he did not hesitate to<lb/>
follow. He was oblivious alike to the convenience of the laboratory<lb/>
and to the hardships of field surveys, and for the same reason: he<lb/>
never thought about himself, but always and only about his work.<lb/>
He had attained, as few men ever do, to the objective state of<lb/>
mind.</p>
<p>Because he was absorbed in the battle, he never considered the<lb/>
rewards of victory. Had he been mindful of his own fame, even of<lb/>
his own legitimate interests, he might easily have established his<lb/>
claim to much of the credit for the epochal results of the Cuban ex-<lb/>
periments and for the transformation of the canal zone. But he<lb/>
had little time and surely no mind for such things. Let men give<lb/>
REED and CARROLL and their colleagues all praise for establishing<lb/>
the cause of yellow fever. Let GORGAS' be the name the world<lb/>
always remembered when the epic of the conquest of Panama was<lb/>
recited. For his part, the foe was mobilized on so many frontiers<lb/>
and lurked, like scattered partisans, in so many marshes, that he<lb/>
could never come off the fighting line to dispute about honors.</p>
<p>It was so to the last. He returned from South America some<lb/>
years ago completely broken by fever, but he would not relax. His<lb/>
recovery was slow because, as his friends believed, he had overtaxed<lb/>
his strength by his personal exertions in keeping malaria from the<lb/>
precincts of the marine camp at Quantico during the war. Chained<lb/>
at last, he turned to writing a biography of DR. GORGAS, and as<lb/>
the end drew on, he battled for a few more weeks of breath--not to<lb/>
live but to write!</p>
<p><unclear>h</unclear> Y. F</p>
<p>He was, in the bulk and in the lasting results of his achieve-<lb/>
ments, one of the three or four more distinguished native Virginians<lb/>
alive in 1925, and in the devotion of his spirit he was one of that<lb/>
matchless company of great scientists whom the nineteenth century<lb/>
may claim as its sons, but to whom every age will be debtors.</p>
<p>It is to such a life as this--and they are being spent in service<lb/>
everywhere--that the idealist rejoices to turn when his own faith is<lb/>
failing and when the lamp of his own endeavor begins to flicker. For<lb/>
there is no life that so surely strengthens the soul of man as a life<lb/>
reflecting the love that &ldquo;seeketh not its own.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
