<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N1237004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, New York World, February 11, 1926 with autographed note</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1237004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1926-02-11</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kruif, Paul de</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi</name>
<name type="place">Columbia Barracks, Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Pinar del Rio (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Walter Reed Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1926-02-11">February 11, 1926</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1237004</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, New York World, February 11, 1926 with autographed note</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>It Seems to Me</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1926-02-11">
<head>Newspaper clipping, New York World, February 11, 1926 with autographed note</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1237004"/>
<opener>
All<lb/>
good<lb/>
wishes to<lb/>
you from<lb/>
Bess Roche<lb/>
<dateline>
N. Y. World<lb/>
<date value="1926-02-11">11 February, 1926</date>
</dateline>
For Miss Carter:<lb/>
</opener>
<p>THE WORLD: <unclear>THURSD</unclear></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>It Seems to Me</p>
<p>By Heywood Broun</p>
<p>The papers announced yesterday that Gen. Pershing<lb/>
would go to Walter Reed Hospital. Of course, I am<lb/>
familiar with the institution, as it has been mentioned<lb/>
often in the news, but now I make a new association<lb/>
with the name, for I have read the chapter on yellow<lb/>
fever in Paul de Kruif's &ldquo;Microbe Hunters.&rdquo; Until<lb/>
then I knew nothing of this Walter Reed. Possibly<lb/>
my ignorance was personal and it may be that most<lb/>
other people know the story of his campaign. Still, I<lb/>
think that few would recognize the name Jesse<lb/>
Lazear, although a battery has been named for him<lb/>
in Baltimore Harbor, and I am even more certain<lb/>
that Kissinger is quite forgotton.</p>
<p>And this is unfortunate, for these men engaged in<lb/>
an offensive as romantic as any tale of the wars of<lb/>
America. When a Chicago educator recently declared<lb/>
that the school histories devoted too much space to<lb/>
military exploits he was roundly denounced as one<lb/>
intent upon diminishing patriotism. But from any<lb/>
point of view a case may well be made that the con-<lb/>
quest of yellow fever was of greater importance than<lb/>
San Juan Hill or any of the other Cuban skirmishes.<lb/>
It lasted less in memory. Kissinger, who distinguished<lb/>
himself so conspicuously in a major medical engage-<lb/>
ment, is not only forgotten by such casual readers<lb/>
as myself but by the Government as well. He was<lb/>
among the first to volunteer to take a bite in the<lb/>
interest of science, and de Kruif reports:</p>
<p>&ldquo;He didn't die from yellow fever. And they pre-<lb/>
vailed upon him at last to accept $115 and a gold<lb/>
watch, which was presented to him in the presence<lb/>
of the officers and men of Columbia Barracks. He<lb/>
didn't die--but, what was worse, as the yellow fever<lb/>
germs went out of him a paralysis crept into him, and<lb/>
now he sits counting the hours on his gold watch.<lb/>
But what luck! At the last account he had a good<lb/>
wife to support him by taking in washing.&rdquo;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>It would be interesting, I think, for some newspaper<lb/>
to check up on this last account and ascertain how<lb/>
Kissinger fares. So far has he fallen out of popular<lb/>
attention that even de Kruif, his chronicler, seems<lb/>
not to know the first name of his hero, but calls him<lb/>
only &ldquo;Private Kissinger of Ohio.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It is probably true that the paralysis of Kissinger<lb/>
had nothing to do with the yellow fever which he<lb/>
<unclear>ontracted</unclear> for the sake of humanity. And again, in<lb/>
justification of the Government, both Kissinger and<lb/>
his companion, John J. <unclear>Moran,</unclear> civilian clerk, were<lb/>
warned of the dangers which they would undergo in<lb/>
allowing themselves to be bitten by fever-laden mos-<lb/>
quitoes, and, besides, all this happened quite a while<lb/>
<unclear>ago</unclear>. Yellow fever was bad in Havana in 1900, and<lb/>
Major Walter Reed came to Quemados. in Cuba, with<lb/>
<unclear>orders</unclear> &ldquo;to give special attention to questions relating<lb/>
<unclear>to</unclear> the cause and prevention of yellow fever.&rdquo; Major<lb/>
<unclear>Reed</unclear> never took a bite himself, but that was his<lb/>
<unclear>plan</unclear>, and only the insistence of his subordinates pre-<lb/>
vented him. Capt. James Carroll was one of the<lb/>
&ldquo;guinea-pigs&rdquo; who recovered and, after his death<lb/>
seven years later, Congress voted his wife a pension<lb/>
of $1,500, and the same annuity goes to the widow of<lb/>
Walter Reed and to Mrs. Lazear, whose husband did<lb/>
die of the fever.</p>
<p>Jernegan and Folk, privates, took what seemed at<lb/>
the time a fearful risk, though later it proved safe<lb/>
enough. But that they did not know when they spent<lb/>
a night wrapped in the blankets of yellow fever vic-<lb/>
tims. Jernegan and Folk were way up at the head of<lb/>
the column, and in those days science was back in the<lb/>
rear scrambling to catch up. De Kruif seems to have<lb/>
no information as to what happened to either of these<lb/>
men in later life, but anyway they received $300<lb/>
apiece when they undertook the experiment.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Early in his investigation Walter Reed made up his<lb/>
mind that yellow fever was carried by mosquitoes, but,<lb/>
of course, there was no way of proving that without<lb/>
experiment. Animal experimentation might serve to<lb/>
bolster the theory, but the army's concern was with<lb/>
men, and things that are true of animals don't always<lb/>
work out with human beings. De Kruif begins his<lb/>
tale of the episode as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;So, on <unclear>one</unclear> hot night after a day among the dying<lb/>
men at Pinar del Rio, he faced his commission: &lsquo;If<lb/>
the members of the commission take the risk first--<lb/>
if they let themselves be bitten by mosquitoes that<lb/>
have fed on yellow fever cases--that will set an ex-<lb/>
ample to American soldiers, and then&rsquo;--- Reed looked<lb/>
at Lazear and then at James Carroll.</p>
<p>"&lsquo;I am ready to take a bite,&rsquo; said Jesse Lazear,<lb/>
who had a wife and two small children.</p>
<p>"&lsquo;You can count on me, sir,&rsquo; said James Carroll,<lb/>
whose total assets were his searcher's brain and his<lb/>
miserable pay as an assistant surgeon in the army.<lb/>
(His liabilities were a wife and five children).</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Lazear and seven nameless ones were first to make<lb/>
the test and none of them took sick. James Carroll<lb/>
was the next. "He told Lazear to bring out the most<lb/>
dangerous mosquito in his collection--not one that had<lb/>
bitten only a single case, but he must use a mosquito<lb/>
that had bitten many cases--and they must be bad<lb/>
cases--of yellow fever. That mosquito must be as<lb/>
dangerous as possible. On the 27th of August Jesse<lb/>
Lazear picked out what he thought to be his champion<lb/>
mosquito, and this creature, which had fed on four<lb/>
cases of yellow fever, two of them severe ones, set-<lb/>
tled down on the arm of James Carroll.</p>
<p>"That soldier watched her while she felt around<lb/>
with her stinger. . . . What did he think as he<lb/>
watched her swell into a bright balloon with his<lb/>
blood? Nobody knows. But he could think what<lb/>
everybody knows: &lsquo;I am forty-six years old and in<lb/>
yellow fever the older the fewer--get better.&rsquo; He<lb/>
was forty-six years old. He had a wife and five chil-<lb/>
dren, but that evening James Carroll wrote to Walter<lb/>
Reed:</p>
<p>&ldquo;&lsquo;If there is anything in the mosquito theory, I<lb/>
should get a good dose of yellow fever.&rsquo; He did.&rdquo;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Carroll was very ill but recovered, and later William<lb/>
Dean of Grand Rapids, Mich., took a bite and got<lb/>
the fever. But there was a flaw in these experiments.<lb/>
Both Carroll and Dean had moved about freely and<lb/>
their fever might have been contracted from some<lb/>
other source and not from the bite of the mosquito.<lb/>
Kissinger and Moran volunteered when a call was<lb/>
issued for men to meet the experiment and follow it<lb/>
up by living under quarantine conditions, &ldquo;which<lb/>
would make them first class, unquestionable guinea-<lb/>
pigs, above suspicion and beyond reproach.&rdquo;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>I have just an edge of <unclear>suspicion</unclear> that de Kruif has<lb/>
romanticized the scene a little in the telling, but that<lb/>
is excusable, for certainly all the materials of melo-<lb/>
drama are present.</p>
<p>"Then Walter Reed told them of the generosity of<lb/>
Gen. Wood. A handsome sum of money they would<lb/>
get--two hundred, maybe three hundred dollars, if the<lb/>
silver-striped she-mosquitoes did things to them that<lb/>
would give them one chance out of five not to spend<lb/>
the money.</p>
<p>"&lsquo;The one condition on which we volunteer, sir,&rsquo;<lb/>
said Private Kissinger and Civilian Clerk John J.<lb/>
Moran of Ohio, &lsquo;is that we get no compensation for it.&rsquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;To the tip of his cap went the hand of Walter Reed<lb/>
(who was a Major): &lsquo;Gentlemen, I salute you.&rsquo;&rdquo;</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>And so I would like to know how things go now<lb/>
with Moran and Kissinger.</p>
<p>Copyright (New York World) Press Publishing Company, 1926.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
