<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1601001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, New-York Herald, June 21, 1806</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1601001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1806-06-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Smith, Thorowgood</name>
<name type="person">Giraud, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1806-06-21">June 21, 1806</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1601001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, New-York Herald, June 21, 1806</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>On The Yellow Malignant Fever</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1806-06-21">
<head>Newspaper clipping, New-York Herald, June 21, 1806</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1601001"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">Highly interesting to the American Public</hi>.</p>
<p>ON THE YELLOW MALIGNANT<lb/>
FEVER.</p>
<p>Humanity being the first virtue of a physi-<lb/>
cian worthy of a profession so distinguished,<lb/>
and the desire of preserving the existence of<lb/>
his fellow-citizens, the principal inducement<lb/>
to all his researches; it is with the most heart<lb/>
felt satisfaction I announce to the public the<lb/>
discovery of a specific remedy for the yellow<lb/>
fever, that terrible scourge, which for several<lb/>
years past (beginning in 1793) has rendered<lb/>
the most flourishing cities of this fortunate<lb/>
portion of the globe the seat of desolation.</p>
<p>The remedy sovereign, as it certainly is, is<lb/>
produced from a mild substance long since<lb/>
used in medicine in certain particular cases,<lb/>
but whose anti pestilential qualities have nev-<lb/>
er been thoroughly investigated until the hap-<lb/>
py moment, when I turned my thoughts to its<lb/>
analogy with an alkalescent, and turgid bile,<lb/>
which always exists in the commencement of<lb/>
the yellow fever.</p>
<p>Its properties which are opening, dissolvent,<lb/>
alkaline and sudorific, always cause it to neu-<lb/>
tralize the poisonous quality of the bile and ne-<lb/>
ver fail to bring on a salutary crisis. Long ex-<lb/>
perience, and success multiplied and attested<lb/>
by certificates, authentic and irrevocable, pa-<lb/>
tients escaped from the danger of the disease<lb/>
by means of the remedy we announce, place<lb/>
its efficacy as a healing medicine, beyond the<lb/>
possibility of doubt. The simplicity of this<lb/>
remedy, of which the basis is nothing else than<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Castile Soap</hi>, may perhaps furnish a pretext<lb/>
to doubt and disapprove, to such as imagine,<lb/>
that only pharmaceutic monsters are capable<lb/>
of triumphing over a disease dangerous in its<lb/>
results and its contagion. But I appeal to en-<lb/>
lightened physicians, who profess clinical and<lb/>
experimental medicine, whether they fre-<lb/>
quently do not owe their most brilliant success<lb/>
to means often simple in the extreme.</p>
<p>The harmony of nature is simple in its pro-<lb/>
gress, however complicated and beautiful it<lb/>
may be; each plant has its specific virtue,<lb/>
and so also for each distemder there exists<lb/>
the means of curing it.</p>
<p>At the period when the small pox first ap-<lb/>
peared, all the efforts of the greatest Physi-<lb/>
cians, and their most complicated prescrip-<lb/>
tions failed of success against that terrible<lb/>
scourge: it was the hand of time pointed out<lb/>
the simple and fortunate method of subduing<lb/>
it; and it was time which afterwards, at two<lb/>
distant periods, produced Lady Montague,<lb/>
and the celebrated Jenner, who have given to<lb/>
that disease the deathblow.</p>
<p>Were not intermittent fevers, and the sy-<lb/>
philitic disorder for a long time the reproach<lb/>
of the greatest practitioners, and the rock on<lb/>
which they split? Nevertheless, each of those<lb/>
disorders has now its specific. The Peruvi-<lb/>
<unclear>an Bark</unclear> that simple <unclear>Bark [unclear]<lb/>
[unclear]</unclear> vegetation, infallibly destroys the one,<lb/>
and Mercury, that Camelion, a fluid, a metal,<lb/>
properly administered and carefully prepared,<lb/>
annihilates the other.</p>
<p>The remedy of which we speak, in all fam-<lb/>
ilies is in daily use, and appears to have been,<lb/>
by Providence, scattered with profusion not<lb/>
only as a cure for the yellow fever, but also<lb/>
as the means of preservation from it.</p>
<p>The author of this interesting discovery,<lb/>
thoroughly persuaded of its efficacy in a state<lb/>
of sickness, by the favorable results that he<lb/>
<unclear>h</unclear>as uniformly obtained from it, believes also<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>hat this means employed in the predisposition<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>o sickness can preserve as well from the evil<lb/>
<unclear>a</unclear>s from the danger of it.</p>
<p>He even believes this remedy, well applied,<lb/>
might have a happy effect against the plague.</p>
<p>The better to make known to the public<lb/>
both the predisposition and the disorder, he<lb/>
will in the first place lay down the indications<lb/>
of the former, and the symptoms of the latter,<lb/>
and will then add some details on the curing<lb/>
effects of this remedy. This he believes the<lb/>
<unclear>mo</unclear>re necessary, since, for want of informa-<lb/>
tion, and because a professional character is<lb/>
not called in time, and the use of the preser-<lb/>
ving remedy is delayed, the majority of pa-<lb/>
tients labouring under the disorder fall vic-<lb/>
tims to it without a possibility of being suc-<lb/>
coured.</p>
<p>First, the predisposition to the yellow fever;<lb/>
the patient generally complains of a slight in-<lb/>
disposition, such as is usual before the attack<lb/>
of common fevers, a general uneasiness, low-<lb/>
ness of spirits, debility, drowsiness, w<unclear>ea</unclear>riness,<lb/>
followed by pains in the reins, in the thighs,<lb/>
knees, and slight shiverings, which proceed<lb/>
from the lower extremities to the reins, with<lb/>
the quickness of lightning, a difficult and long<lb/>
respiration, the saliva and mucus of the nose,<lb/>
thin, rare and hot, singing in the ears, a hea-<lb/>
viness in the eyes, an involuntary melancholy,<lb/>
a want of appetite and a foul mouth. All these<lb/>
signs, or many of them, exist for a greater or<lb/>
less time before the development of the fe-<lb/>
ver according to the constitution, the state of<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>he atmosphere, or of the contagion; for I<lb/>
have witnessed patients die in time of great<lb/>
infection before experiencing the febrile crisis;<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> instance, a patient who consulted me about<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> indisposition characterized by some predis<lb/>
<unclear>ing</unclear> signs, died at the door at the moment I<lb/>
was feeling his pulse, which was by no means<lb/>
<unclear>f</unclear>everish.</p>
<p>Second, the real symptoms of the state of<lb/>
<unclear>s</unclear>ickness, according to the observations of the<lb/>
<unclear>a</unclear>uthor and acknowledged by the best practi-<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>ioners, are in most instances, but not invaria-<lb/>
<unclear>b</unclear>ly, a chilly fit; in a short time violent pains<lb/>
<unclear>s</unclear>ome on in the fore part of the head, in the<lb/>
<unclear>e</unclear>yes, loins, hips and thighs. The face becomes<lb/>
<unclear>f</unclear>lushed, the eyes of a fiery red, and intolerant<lb/>
<unclear>of</unclear> light, with a stinging or burning heat in the<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>in; the pulse is full, quick and hard, the<lb/>
<unclear>r</unclear>espiration deep and difficult; the tongue is<lb/>
covered with a whitish fur, and moist; the<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>hirst is sometimes excessive, at others mode-<lb/>
<unclear>r</unclear>ate; the stomach is distended, and irritable<lb/>
with pain and burning heat, accompanied by<lb/>
excessive sickness; it is often troubled by vi-<lb/>
olent retching, with a vomiting of mucus or<lb/>
<unclear>h</unclear>eir drink mixed with an acrid greenish mat-<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>er corroding the <unclear>fauces</unclear>; the bowels are cos-<lb/>
<unclear>t</unclear>ive; the patient feels great restlessness and<lb/>
<unclear>d</unclear>espondency, moaning and tossing about the<lb/>
<unclear>b</unclear>ed as if to find some relief from a change of<lb/>
posture; hemorhage at the nose, a difficulty<lb/>
and sometimes a stoppage of urine, &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
<p>The specific remedy opportunely administer-<lb/>
ed operates in the following manner: In the<lb/>
first place; the pains decrease; the muscu<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
lar agitation becomes calm; the urine <unclear>re</unclear>gains<lb/>
its course; the fever abates; the skin <unclear>bec</unclear>omes<lb/>
moist; the respiration free; the thir<unclear>st de</unclear>min-<lb/>
ished; the irritation of the stomach <unclear>di</unclear>sap-<lb/>
pears, and the vomiting ceases; the dryness<lb/>
of the throat is no longer felt, and from the<lb/>
sixth to the seventh day, either a favourable<lb/>
crisis by means of a sweat or stool, and a bili-<lb/>
ous vomit destroys the fever; the 8th day the<lb/>
sickness is terminated, and 3 or 4 days of con-<lb/>
valescence restore to the patient his accustom-<lb/>
ed calm. If the disease should happen not to<lb/>
follow these periods marked by experience, in<lb/>
such case it ought no longer to be classed with<lb/>
the real yellow fever, but would belong to the<lb/>
class of putrid and malignant bilious fevers, of<lb/>
which the symptoms would be nearly destroy-<lb/>
ed, but which would render necessary the use<lb/>
of frebrifuges, in order to complete the effect<lb/>
of this remedy.</p>
<p>This remedy is also eminently adapted to<lb/>
bilious colics; obstructing affections on the li-<lb/>
ver; the jaundice; obstructed perspiration,<lb/>
and in a word, to all cases where the acrid<lb/>
bile or inverted secretions menace life, a dan-<lb/>
ger unfortunately too frequent, in consequence<lb/>
of the inconstancy of the climate we live in.</p>
<p>On the advantages of so important a disco-<lb/>
very I shall forbear to dilate. It is so much<lb/>
the more precious, as, according to the opin-<lb/>
ion of our most learned physicians, we must<lb/>
now consider the yellow fever as an endemic.</p>
<p>The author the better to convince <unclear>h</unclear>is fel-<lb/>
low citizens, will add to a memoir which he<lb/>
proposes to have printed, on the method of<lb/>
treatment, by which he has obtained such sig-<lb/>
nal success, the various cures he has opera-<lb/>
ted by this means in divers epidemics, and du-<lb/>
ring the space of five years since he has com<unclear>-</unclear><lb/>
menced using it. He thought this lapse of<lb/>
time necessary to consolidate his observations<lb/>
on the poisonous ferment of the disorder, and<lb/>
the victorious effect of his remedy.</p>
<p>All those persons whom a well grounded<lb/>
confidence shall induce to adopt the use of it,<lb/>
will doubtless become strenuous advocates of<lb/>
its infallbility, and as well the unfortunate as<lb/>
the rich, will find at their hands the same<lb/>
succour, and the same assistance.</p>
<p>Hereinafter are mentioned more than a hun-<lb/>
dred certificates, which establish the period of<lb/>
the discovery.</p>
<p>We, the subscribers, residents of the city of<lb/>
Baltimore, do hereby certify, that Doctor<lb/>
John J. Giraue, attended us during the pre-<lb/>
valence of the yellow fever, which raged in<lb/>
this city in the year 1800, when laboring<lb/>
under that disorder, and cured us of it by<lb/>
his judicious and salutary treatment, and to<lb/>
testify our persuasion of the truth and effica-<lb/>
cy of <unclear>his</unclear> mode of treatment we have [unclear]<lb/>
to given our signatures,</p>
<p>[Here follows the names of about 100 per-<lb/>
sons, residents of the city of Baltimore.</p>
<p>STATE OF MARYLAND,</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">City of Baltimore, to wit</hi>.</p>
<p>Be it remembered, that on this twenty sixth<lb/>
of March in the year of our Lord eighteen<lb/>
hundred and six, personally appeared before<lb/>
me the subscriber, Mayor of the city of Balti-<lb/>
more, John J. Giraud Physician of the city<lb/>
aforesaid, a citizen of the United States, who<lb/>
being sworn on the Holy Evangelists of Almi-<lb/>
ghty God, deposeth and saith, that in the year<lb/>
1800, during the prevalence af the yellow ma-<lb/>
lignant fever in the said city of Baltimore, he<lb/>
did make the discovery of a medicine, which<lb/>
he is thoroughly persuaded is a certain and<lb/>
specific remedy for the cure, and prevention<lb/>
of that disease; during the period of five years<lb/>
past, he has always administered it to such<lb/>
patients laboring under the above mentioned<lb/>
disease, as were committed to his care, and<lb/>
by means of it has effected their cure, gener-<lb/>
ally in the course of eight days, by using the<lb/>
remedy in the commencement of the disorder,<lb/>
and before the application of any other; that<lb/>
from the happy and uniform effects, which<lb/>
have constantly attended it, he verily belives<lb/>
it to be a certain and specific remedy for the<lb/>
said disease, and that it will stand the test of<lb/>
time and experience: And moreover that he<lb/>
the deponent is ready at all times to submit it<lb/>
to such trial and proof as may be required to<lb/>
establish its efficacy.</p>
<p>In testimony whereof I have hereunto<lb/>
subscribed my name, and caused the<lb/>
corporate seal of the said city to be<lb/>
affixed, on the day and year first above<lb/>
written.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">(Seal.')</hi> THOROWGOOD SMITH,<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Mayor of the city of Baltimore</hi>.</p>
<p>* The editors of the newspapers throgh<lb/>
out the U. S. are requested to copy the for-<lb/>
going.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
