<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1727001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1727001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1878-09-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1878-09-21">September 21, 1878</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1727001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Incidents of the Scourge at the South</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1878-09-21">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1727001"/>
<p>INCIDENTS OF THE SCOURAGE AT THE<lb/>
SOUTH.</p>
<p>THE present epidemic is believed to have broken<lb/>
out in New Orleans in May last, the first case<lb/>
being that of Purser Clark, of the <hi rend="italic">Souder</hi>, and the<lb/>
second that of Elliott, the second engineer of the<lb/>
same vessel, the latter dying on the 29th. From<lb/>
that time until the early part of July there were<lb/>
no doubtful cases reported or heard of. Every<lb/>
known precaution was observed to prevent the<lb/>
spread of the fever, but it was communicated in<lb/>
various ways to Memphis, Grenada, Vicksburg, and<lb/>
a few inland towns of Louisiana; and since the<lb/>
middle of July its progress has been widespread<lb/>
and rapid, until not only the leading Southern, but<lb/>
many of the Northern, cities have become in-<lb/>
fected.</p>
<p>For several weeks the new cases in New Orleans<lb/>
ran from one hundred to two hundred and fifty<lb/>
daily, and the deaths from ten to one hundred.<lb/>
Euterpe Street, between Carondelet and St. Charles<lb/>
Streets, appeared so thoroughly infected that a<lb/>
temporary barricade was erected to prevent the<lb/>
noise of the vehicles passing over the cobble-stone<lb/>
pavement. A few days ago a milkman drove up<lb/>
and insisted upon passing with his cart, saying that<lb/>
he paid his license and intended to drive on any<lb/>
street he pleased. The milkman attempted to force<lb/>
his way through, but was fired on by a citizen and<lb/>
driven off.</p>
<p>At an early stage of the excitement, and while<lb/>
various cities were establishing quarantine against<lb/>
New Orleans and Memphis, the citizens of Iuka,<lb/>
Miss., formally invited refugees to seek the accom-<lb/>
modations of their locality, and within a few days<lb/>
hundreds of people, in all conditions of life and<lb/>
with every species of vehicle, began pouring into<lb/>
the city, where a hearty welcome was extended.</p>
<p>The office of the Recorder of Deaths in New<lb/>
Orleans is on the ground floor of the St. Louis<lb/>
Hotel, and has been the location of many strange<lb/>
and sad spectacles. While sitting there our corre-<lb/>
spondent saw one of the charity wagons, containing<lb/>
two dead bodies, in rough, unpainted pine coffins,<lb/>
driven up for a burial permit. One, containing a<lb/>
woman, was piled upon the top of the other, and<lb/>
surmounting the ghastly heap sat a faithful dog and<lb/>
the woman's husband, who accompanied her re-<lb/>
mains to the Potter's Field, to note the spot where<lb/>
they laid.</p>
<p>The scenes about the aid-centres in New Orleans<lb/>
remind one of the days of the war. Particularly does<lb/>
the waiting crowd of basket-holding people about<lb/>
the Commissary Department awaken in the memory<lb/>
the days following the capture of the city of Savan-<lb/>
nah. Here the crowd is made up of negroes, who<lb/>
sit on the curbing, sit on the pavement of the street<lb/>
beyond the railing of the Commissary Depot, and,<lb/>
clutching their baskets and the orders from ward<lb/>
committees, watch intently the large door, and<lb/>
listen long in vain to hear their own names pro-<lb/>
nounced by the black crier, mounted on the box<lb/>
upon the window's ledge. The crowd is four or five<lb/>
hundred in number during the livelong day. The<lb/>
system of giving rations, as worked by the Relief<lb/>
Committee, is as cautious, as proof against imposi-<lb/>
tion, probably, as it is possible to make it. All ap-<lb/>
plications of the needy are made to ward commit-<lb/>
tee-men, whose duty it is to look into the justice of<lb/>
the claims made to them, and then to give a draft on<lb/>
Commissary Muccabe for the number of rations<lb/>
and the number of days. This draft is presented,<lb/>
and the holder's name and time for drawing and<lb/>
number of rations are entered in a large indexed<lb/>
book. From this book they are fed in turn as long<lb/>
as their drafts specify.</p>
<p>The authorities of Memphis used every reason-<lb/>
able means to keep the fever out, and, now that it<lb/>
had got in in spite of them, they come as near as<lb/>
possible to moving the infected part of the city.<lb/>
The disease was all in a northwestern section. A<lb/>
large number of tents were obtained from the<lb/>
United States Government, and an encampment<lb/>
was made in a salubrious suburb, and named<lb/>
Camp Joe Williams. Those of the residents of the<lb/>
infected district who had not already gone away<lb/>
were sent to this camp, and fed at the city's ex-<lb/>
pense. Not a soul was left in the fever neighbor-<lb/>
hood except the officers who went to disinfect the<lb/>
houses. But the camp was not established without<lb/>
opposition. The spot selected was five miles south<lb/>
of the city. Dr. Noll went there with the tents and<lb/>
several assistants. He was at once surrounded by<lb/>
a mob of negroes, who drove him back to the city.<lb/>
They disliked the invasion by a possibly fever-bear-<lb/>
ing rabble. On the following day the doctor re-<lb/>
turned with two military companies at his back,<lb/>
and the encampment was made without further<lb/>
trouble.</p>
<p>The undertakers have long been unable to bury<lb/>
all the dead, for want of labor and material. This<lb/>
was particularly the case with County Undertaker<lb/>
Walsh, who could not turn a wheel until he received<lb/>
help from the Citizens' Committee. At Elmwood<lb/>
Cemetery the coffins were piled up in tiers, not-<lb/>
withstanding that a large force was constantly em-<lb/>
ployed digging graves. It was the same at all the<lb/>
burying-grounds.</p>
<p>It is a handsome commentary on the generosity<lb/>
and noble-heartedness of the American people<lb/>
that the city and medical authorities, the Howard<lb/>
and Young Men's Christian Associations, and count-<lb/>
less other organizations, were not permitted to<lb/>
struggle alone with the saffron horror. Long before<lb/>
any call for assistance had been made, the people<lb/>
of the United States, irrespective of sections, creed,<lb/>
interests or other distinctions, began sending to the<lb/>
South money and materials in a haste and volume<lb/>
almost unprecedented. And as physicians and pro-<lb/>
fessional nurses gave out or died at the post of self-<lb/>
imposed duty, their places were speedily supplied<lb/>
by volunteers from non-affected districts. The<lb/>
incidents above mentioned are but an indication of<lb/>
many thousands yet to be written; the assistance<lb/>
in money, material and men already rendered our<lb/>
Southern friends is but a tithe of what a humane<lb/>
North and East and West are anxious to extend in<lb/>
the name of Christianity and fraternity.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
