<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1728001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1728001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1878-09-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Vanderpoel, S. O.</name>
<name type="place">Hoffman's Island (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Staten Island (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Seguine's Point (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Dix Island (N.Y.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1878-09-21">September 21, 1878</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1728001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Quarantine Precautions Against Yellow Fever</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1878-09-21">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 21, 1878</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1728001"/>
<p>QUARANTINE PRECAUTIONS AGAINST<lb/>
YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>&ldquo;SO long as yellow fever is abroad, I feel as<lb/>
though I were standing on a volcano,&rdquo; said<lb/>
Dr. S. O. Vanderpoel, the chief of quarantine staff,<lb/>
to the writer, as the steam-launch <hi rend="italic">Mermaid</hi> sped<lb/>
across the flashing waters of the upper Bay <hi rend="italic">en route</hi><lb/>
to fumigate suspected ships, and to purge them of<lb/>
that ghastly occupant, the mere mention of which<lb/>
sends a thrill of apprehension to the very innermost<lb/>
core. What is yellow fever? We are told that it is a<lb/>
distinct species of fever, having its own special<lb/>
cause, that it rarely prevails in any but tropical or<lb/>
sub-tropical regions, the zone being between latitude<lb/>
20&deg; S. and 40&deg; N.; that the special cause is destroyed<lb/>
by a temperature of 32&deg; F.; that it is abrupt in its<lb/>
attack, commencing with a chill, not of a marked<lb/>
intensity, followed by pains in the head and loins,<lb/>
the skin becoming jaundiced or yellow, from whence<lb/>
the name; that then comes the vomiting of blood,<lb/>
called the black vomit, and then--the chances are<lb/>
dead against the sufferer; that the mode of death<lb/>
is generally by exhaustion. It is contagious. It is<lb/>
not infectious. When yellow fever was decimating<lb/>
Gibraltar, Louis, the celebrated French physician,<lb/>
experimentalized upon condemned convicts. He<lb/>
injected black vomit, inoculated them with it, and<lb/>
used every means within his power to bring them<lb/>
within its deadly clutches, but to no purpose; its<lb/>
non-contagiousness proved too much for all his<lb/>
skill.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I'd rather sleep with a corpse dead of yellow<lb/>
fever for a whole night than wear the clothes it<lb/>
used when alive for an hour,&rdquo; was the remark made<lb/>
to us by an experienced disinfector. Not a single<lb/>
nurse in the employ of the New York Quarantine<lb/>
has taken the fever in fifteen years, and Drs. Van-<lb/>
derpoel, Thompson and McCartney, the three<lb/>
Quarantine officers, separately assured us that no<lb/>
difficulty whatever is experienced in obtaining<lb/>
nurses; on the contrary, that the supply is consider-<lb/>
ably greater than the demand.</p>
<p>QUARANTINE</p>
<p>may be defined as a police regulation for the exclu-<lb/>
sion of contagious diseases from a city or state.<lb/>
Sanitary laws are founded upon the assumption<lb/>
that certain diseases depend upon a specific con-<lb/>
tagion, and their professional ends are to prevent<lb/>
exportation, importation and spreading of conta-<lb/>
gious pestilential diseases. Quarantine goes back to<lb/>
the time of Moses, who prescribed (Lev. xiii.) the<lb/>
most stringent precautionary measures to prevent<lb/>
the spread of disease. He not only ordered the<lb/>
lepers to be set apart from the rest of the people,<lb/>
but required that their clothes should be purified,<lb/>
and even that the garments belonging to the most<lb/>
aggravated cases should be burned. Yellow fever<lb/>
visited Philadelphia in 1699, and in 1700 the General<lb/>
Assembly enacted the first quarantine law in this<lb/>
country, imposing a fine of $500 on any un-<lb/>
healthy vessel that landed. The first law on<lb/>
the subject in New York was passed by the<lb/>
Colonial Legislature in 1758, and since the In-<lb/>
ternational Sanitary Conference, held at Constanti-<lb/>
nople in 1865, quarantine has been established on a<lb/>
scientific basis and in accordance with the modern<lb/>
notions of liberty and justice. The Quarantine<lb/>
establishment of New York consists of warehouses,<lb/>
docks and wharves, anchorage for vessels, hos-<lb/>
pitals, convalescent stations, a floating hospital,<lb/>
boarding-station, burying-ground, and residences<lb/>
for officers and men. Connected with the ware-<lb/>
houses are apartments with appliances for special<lb/>
disinfection by forced ventilation, refrigerator,<lb/>
high steam, dry heat, and chemical disintectives.<lb/>
The residence of the chief officer is situated on the<lb/>
high ground inside the Narrows, on the southern<lb/>
shore of Staten Island. It is perched like a watch-<lb/>
dog's box at the gates of the world. Half Swiss<lb/>
chalet, half Norwegian satyr, it resembles the<lb/>
palatial villa of some retired merchant, and little<lb/>
does the passenger on the ocean steamer, as he<lb/>
gazes upon this coquettish edifice, imagine that<lb/>
from its walls emerges the fiat which stays the<lb/>
shadow of death from descending at our very por-<lb/>
tals. The boat-house is perched on a ledge of land<lb/>
beside the dock, and attached to it the telegraph-<lb/>
station through which flash messages from the sea<lb/>
telling of plague-stricken vessels coming up the bay,<lb/>
reeking with pestilence, despair and doom. From<lb/>
the piazza everything that &lsquo;walks the sea&rsquo; can be<lb/>
espied, and so soon as two whistles are sounded<lb/>
from the department-tug, lying in wait at the dock<lb/>
beneath, the chief, or his assistant, Dr. Thompson,<lb/>
are to be seen hurrying down the wooden stairway<lb/>
leading to the dock, for a sailing vessel is being<lb/>
towed up the Narrows, the yellow flag in the main<lb/>
rigging inviting inspection; or a steamer throbs<lb/>
slowly into Quarantine Bay, dropping her anchor,<lb/>
as by law compelled, in that haven of refuge. In<lb/>
ascertaining the sanitary condition of a vessel, the<lb/>
health officer is authorized to examine, under oath,<lb/>
the captain, crew and passengers, and to inspect<lb/>
the bill of health, manifest, log, cargo, etc.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Yellow fever is usually to be found on sailing<lb/>
vessels,&rdquo; said the doctor, &ldquo;and every vessel, steam<lb/>
or sail, hailing from a Southern or suspected port is<lb/>
brought-to in the Lower Bay, where she is de-<lb/>
tained, inspected, and operated on according to her<lb/>
special condition. At the expiration of her deten-<lb/>
tion she is permitted to move to the Upper Bay to<lb/>
unload. Let us begin at the beginning. Here is a<lb/>
bark coming into the Narrows. This may be a<lb/>
simple case of inspection and permit. Come<lb/>
aboard!&rdquo; We, the special artist and writer, in<lb/>
company with the doctor, stepped on to the <hi rend="italic">General<lb/>
Fenton</hi> steam-tug, and proceeded, underneath the<lb/>
flutter of the ghastly yellow flag, to board a stately<lb/>
bark, that all so gracefully-glided like a thing of<lb/>
life into Quarantine Bay. Under her great wooden<lb/>
walls we saucily scooted, her crew gazing down at<lb/>
us in pleased curiosity. A ladder, half-rope,<lb/>
half-wood, all tar, was lowered, and, following the<lb/>
agile doctor, we clambered up the steep sides, feel-<lb/>
ing very much as Jack must have felt whilst en-<lb/>
gaged climbing the never-to-be-forgotten bean-<lb/>
stalk. The captain, wearing the &ldquo;livery of the sun,&rdquo;<lb/>
preceded the doctor to the state cabin, and, seated<lb/>
therein, a series of questions were put, the first<lb/>
being: &ldquo;Are you all well on board?&rdquo; The second,<lb/>
&ldquo;Have you been well all the way?&rdquo; The queries<lb/>
of the doctor having been satisfactorily replied to,<lb/>
&ldquo;all hands&rdquo; were ordered on deck, and the roll<lb/>
called, each man replying to his name. Then the<lb/>
doctor filled up a form, signed it, and handed it to<lb/>
the captain, the document being a permit authoriz-<lb/>
ing the vessel to proceed to the dock.</p>
<p>Transferred to the steam - yacht <hi rend="italic">Mermaid</hi>, we<lb/>
now started on our tour of inspection down the<lb/>
Lower Bay. Away in the distance the Highlands<lb/>
of Navesink, the Hook, and the blue, hazy outlines<lb/>
of the Jersey shore; in the foreground Hoffman's<lb/>
Island, grim and gray; behind it, glowing in white-<lb/>
wash. Dix's Island--a veritable whited sepulchre;<lb/>
and, further still, the hospital hulk <hi rend="italic">Illinois</hi>, resem-<lb/>
bling a gigantic floating coffin. Near the hulk was<lb/>
anchored the Spanish steamship <hi rend="italic">Castilla</hi>, of Barce-<lb/>
lona, on board of which the terrible fever was<lb/>
holding hideous carnival. A bark and two schoon-<lb/>
ers were also impounded beneath the awful folds<lb/>
of the yellow flag. Away on our right stood Se-<lb/>
guine's Point, the last resting-place of those who<lb/>
had been smitten down unto death--low-lying,<lb/>
barren, tawny, out of the world, no better site<lb/>
could have been selected for depositing all that the<lb/>
pestilential breath of the foul destroyer had left.<lb/>
Adjacent to this &ldquo;God's acre&rdquo; stands the whilom<lb/>
factory of Giuseppe Garibaldi.</p>
<p>Hoffman's Island contains three gaunt, separate<lb/>
buildings of a brownish gray--all windows--the<lb/>
sun-blinds bright green. These buildings are used<lb/>
as a place of reception and temporary detention<lb/>
of persons who have been exposed to contagious<lb/>
or infectious diseases, but who are not actually<lb/>
sick. On the occasion of our visit, the island, save<lb/>
for the keeper, his wife and a bulldog, was tenant-<lb/>
less, and, sending ashore some ice, we sped onward<lb/>
to West Bank, or Dix's Island--exclusively used for<lb/>
yellow fever and cholera patients. It rises from<lb/>
the sea a sort of model village. At one end the<lb/>
dock, with its spacious shed and boat-house; at<lb/>
the other, the residence of the superintendent,<lb/>
with whom are his wife and four blooming, healthy<lb/>
children; in the middle, side by side, like the snowy<lb/>
tents in an encampment, the wards--ten in num-<lb/>
ber--each capable of containing two hundred pa-<lb/>
tients; sweet, white, simple single-story cottages,<lb/>
wherein health and happiness should assuredly<lb/>
find sanctuary! As we gazed on the landing-place,<lb/>
Dante's lines, &ldquo;<hi rend="italic">Lasciate ogni speranza voi ch'<lb/>
entrate</hi>&rdquo;--&ldquo;Leave ye all hope behind who enter<lb/>
here,&rdquo; smote us vividly, for how few who ascend<lb/>
these steps ever retrace them again; and how<lb/>
many are borne across the Bay to that lonely rest-<lb/>
ing-place in the yellow sands. One patient, a con-<lb/>
valescent, sat upon the low sea-wall gazing at us<lb/>
from out his saffron-hued eyes. How isolated that<lb/>
Pariah looked, and how he watched our every<lb/>
movement with a morbid and never-to be satisfied<lb/>
interest! The doctor visits this <hi rend="italic">sanitarium</hi> twice<lb/>
daily, and, swept as it is, by the life-giving sea-<lb/>
breeze, and almost by the sea itself, those who are<lb/>
committed to its shelter have every chance afforded<lb/>
them, since the struggle then lies between ozone<lb/>
and blood-poison. From Dix Island we steered for<lb/>
the floating hospital <hi rend="italic">Illinois</hi>, on whose expansive<lb/>
deck we were received by the physician in charge,<lb/>
Dr. McCartney. Around us were anchored plague-<lb/>
stricken ships, and even while we conversed with<lb/>
the doctor a tug-boat approached, towing an in-<lb/>
fected bark. The <hi rend="italic">Castilla</hi> rode at anchor almost<lb/>
within hailing distance, her passengers lounging<lb/>
over the bulwarks, all singly, not in groups, or<lb/>
even in twos, scanning us with longing glances.<lb/>
On the preceding day a man had died on board, of<lb/>
the yellow fever, and on the morning of our visit<lb/>
one of the stewardesses succumbed. The beds<lb/>
were all hung up on nettings or laid out on spars in<lb/>
the glorious dayshine. This ship had been fumi-<lb/>
gated and disinfected, when the dreaded pestilence<lb/>
again made its appearance.</p>
<p>&ldquo;How do the passengers act? Are they para-<lb/>
lyzed with fear?&rdquo; we asked of Dr. McCartney.</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is no fear. There is a gloom and a sort<lb/>
of resignation,&rdquo; was the reply.</p>
<p>When the health officer boards a ship and finds<lb/>
disease, he instantly causes the removal of the sick,<lb/>
and, if a case of small-pox, every person on the ves-<lb/>
sel is vaccinated. The ship is then fumigated, the<lb/>
passengers being mustered on deck. Fumigating<lb/>
material is placed in the steerage and the steerage<lb/>
closed up. The disinfectant used is manganese<lb/>
and salt, over which oil of vitriol is thrown; then<lb/>
uprises a cloud of white smoke, one inhalation of<lb/>
which would knock a man senseless were he strong<lb/>
as Hercules. The manganese and salt are placed<lb/>
in a small tin pail, the oil of vitriol poured from a<lb/>
common stone jar, the pail is lowered by a rope<lb/>
into the compartment to be disinfected, the hatch<lb/>
closed, and the work of killing the intangible<lb/>
spectre goes bravely on. The yellow fever victim,<lb/>
newly attired, is lowered into the steam-launch, and,<lb/>
accompanied by the doctor, brought to Dix's Island,<lb/>
where he is received by the superintendent and<lb/>
nurse. It is one singular feature of the disease that<lb/>
even when within the shadow of death a certain<lb/>
muscular strength remains to the patient. Should<lb/>
he recover, new and disinfected clothes are given<lb/>
him on his quitting Quarantine. Filthy or unhealthful<lb/>
vessels are subject to quarantine for purification.<lb/>
On infected or suspected vessels all clothing, per-<lb/>
sonal baggage, cotton, hemp, rags, paper, hides,<lb/>
skins, feathers, woolens, and other articles of animal<lb/>
origin, are subjected to an obligatory quarantine<lb/>
and purification. Molasses, sugar, and live and<lb/>
healthy cattle, are subjected to quarantine at the<lb/>
option of the health officer.</p>
<p>Leaving the Lower, we steamed into the Upper<lb/>
Bay to witness the process of fumigating unloaded<lb/>
vessels, as all ships coming from suspected ports<lb/>
are compelled to anchor in the Upper Bay, and to<lb/>
undergo fumigation, disinfection and cleansing.<lb/>
For the purpose of unloading and fumigating, gangs<lb/>
of stevedores are employed by contractors, these<lb/>
gangs living upon floating hulks in perfect isolation.<lb/>
Policemen are employed by Quarantine, whose duty<lb/>
it is to see that the vessels are being duly cared for<lb/>
by the special stevedores, to keep off interlopers,<lb/>
and to prevent all shore communication. In the<lb/>
Upper Bay lay an entire fleet of vessels, from a<lb/>
leviathan Havana steamer to a saucy three-<lb/>
masted schooner, some still deep in the water,<lb/>
others high out of it, surrounded by lighters laden<lb/>
to the tops of their masts, the busy cranes clank-<lb/>
clanking, the brawny stevedores working as only<lb/>
stevedores know how to work. A flag flying at the<lb/>
foremast tells the doctor that the ship is ready for<lb/>
inspection.</p>
<p>We boarded the steamer, the fumigating ap-<lb/>
paratus being hauled up after us. Her hold had<lb/>
been emptied, scraped, scrubbed and cleansed,<lb/>
and now awaited the lynx eye of the health officer.<lb/>
Accompanied by his assistant, Dr. Vanderpoel,<lb/>
inspected the ship, preceded by his sub-officer<lb/>
who bore a lantern; and, having satisfied himself<lb/>
that all sanitary requirements had been fulfilled,<lb/>
ordered fumigation. The deadly foe to disease<lb/>
having been lowered into the hold, the hatches<lb/>
were battered down, and in the darkness the two<lb/>
elements were left to contend for mastery. On<lb/>
deck the crew were mustered, the captain at their<lb/>
head. Calling the roll, each man stepped forward in<lb/>
turn. &ldquo;Look me in the eye!&rdquo; exclaimed the health<lb/>
officer, and, casting an incisive glance into the eyes<lb/>
of each of the crew as they passed onwards, Dr.<lb/>
Vanderpoel expressed himself satisfied, and issued<lb/>
the necessary permission for the steamer to pro-<lb/>
ceed to the wharf.</p>
<p>&ldquo;I can tell when there is yellow fever in a ship<lb/>
by the eyes of those on board,&rdquo; observed the<lb/>
doctor, as we steamed over to the ill-fated <hi rend="italic">Ida<lb/>
Laurence</hi>, whose crew, including the captain,<lb/>
were all down in yellow fever, save two, when she<lb/>
arrived at the Delaware breakwater.</p>
<p>We interviewed a mulatto who had been amongst<lb/>
the sufferers. This man had had the yellow fever<lb/>
twice.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Did you give yourself up?&rdquo; we asked.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, sir; never. It come on me awful quick,<lb/>
knocking me on the head, and splitting up my back<lb/>
with pain. I felt a little skeered when the black<lb/>
vomit came on the third day. Oh, but I <hi rend="italic">was</hi> awful<lb/>
sick!&rdquo;</p>
<p>Having inspected several vessels, we steamed<lb/>
back to Quarantine, and took leave of Drs. Vander-<lb/>
poel and Thompson, feeling fully assured that all<lb/>
that zeal, care and efficiency can do to tend off the<lb/>
terrible visitation of yellow fever is being done by<lb/>
these capable gentlemen and the able and ex-<lb/>
perienced staff at their disposal.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
