<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1730001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 28, 1878</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1730001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1878-09-28</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations">YES</term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="place">Vicksburg (Miss.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1878-09-28">September 28, 1878</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1730001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 28, 1878</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Yellow Fever Visitation. Terrible Scenes in New Orleans and Memphis.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1878-09-28">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 28, 1878</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1730001"/>
<p>THE YELLOW FEVER VISITATION.</p>
<p>TERRIBLE SCENES IN NEW ORLEANS AND<lb/>
MEMPHIS.</p>
<p>THE horrors of the yellow fever visitation in New<lb/>
Orleans, Memphis, Vicksburg, and some other<lb/>
Southern cities, continue unabated. The mortality,<lb/>
during the past week, has been frightful, while the<lb/>
pestilence has steadily extended its area, baffling<lb/>
all the efforts to arrest its progress. On September<lb/>
10th, the number of new cases reported in New<lb/>
Orleans was 654. On the 11th it was 623, with an<lb/>
average mortality of ninety daily. In Memphis, on the<lb/>
11th, there were 104 deaths and 277 new cases. At<lb/>
Vicksburg, on the same day, there were seventy-one<lb/>
deaths. The latter city, at the date named, was a<lb/>
vast hospital with every chamber occupied. In all<lb/>
these cities the demand for help grows in intensity.<lb/>
In Vicksburg, the number of persons fed daily has<lb/>
been about 14,000. The total daily expenses of the<lb/>
Howard Association and Citizens' Relief Committee<lb/>
are about $11,000. If the fever continues one month<lb/>
longer, as is likely, with a gradual abatement<lb/>
within that time, from $150,000 to $200,000 and<lb/>
about 300,000 rations will be required. Mattresses,<lb/>
blankets, sheets and pillows are needed every day<lb/>
to replace those destroyed by order of the Board<lb/>
of Health, on which persons have died.</p>
<p>The Government has supplied tents and rations<lb/>
as far as it has been able to do so; and in New<lb/>
Orleans Government rations are issued to personal<lb/>
applicants.</p>
<p>The fever, during the last fortnight, has extended<lb/>
to Baton Rouge, La.; Canton, in Miss., where<lb/>
a large number of deaths have occurred; Holly<lb/>
Springs, Miss., where the deaths have averaged<lb/>
twelve daily; Brownsville, Tenn.; Hickman, Ky.,<lb/>
and other towns. Five thousand Government<lb/>
rations have been sent from Chicago to Canton.</p>
<p>The gloom which pervades the stricken cities is<lb/>
<unclear>inde-cribable</unclear>. In New Orleans, Canal Street, the<lb/>
Broadway of the city, is the only thorough-<lb/>
fare that presents anything like an appearance<lb/>
of life. Even here the showing at its best<lb/>
is sombre enough. It is much as though<lb/>
shadowed with a veritable pall. The large and<lb/>
fashionable stores are almost wholly bereft of<lb/>
their customers. The few remaining clerks<lb/>
are lounging listlessly about, gloomy and dejected,<lb/>
and sadly in want of something to do. The people,<lb/>
as is evident, save of a stern necessity, remain at<lb/>
home. Here is the one avenue of all others, too,<lb/>
for the fashionable drives. There are none of the<lb/>
usual fancy turnouts to be met. There can be no<lb/>
driving for pleasure under the shadows of pest-<lb/>
<unclear>ilence</unclear>. The one thing which casts the final gloom<lb/>
is the appearance of the long and well-nigh contin-<lb/>
uous lines of funeral processions. Canal Street is<lb/>
the thoroughfare leading to the principal city ceme-<lb/>
teries. From the turnings at the various cross<lb/>
streets the dread cavalcades of death are almost<lb/>
constantly filing in. They turn the corners from<lb/>
every quarter; they wind their long and sinuous<lb/>
way--the silent march of the dead--so many shad-<lb/>
owy spectres, beckoning all in their train.</p>
<p>The dead are found everywhere. Two tramps,<lb/>
for instance, were found dead in Jackson Square,<lb/>
and not unfrequently bodies are found in obscure,<lb/>
out-of-the-way places, where the victims have<lb/>
crawled and died alone. One very pitiable case,<lb/>
which stands for many, is that of a family in which<lb/>
a child died suddenly; the father, upon looking for<lb/>
his money and jewels, to make purchases for the<lb/>
burial, found that he had been robbed; he went a<lb/>
few hours later to the police station, and while<lb/>
there, giving a description of the jewels to the<lb/>
affidavit clerk, received a message stating that his<lb/>
wife had fallen a victim to the fever. Not waiting<lb/>
to sign the affidavit, which was almost ready, he<lb/>
frantically rushed from the court-room to his home<lb/>
to attend to the wants of his wife. The death of<lb/>
his child, the sudden illness of his wife, and the<lb/>
loss of all that remained of his money, so worked<lb/>
upon his nervous system that he also was claimed<lb/>
as a fit subject for the fever. The child was buried<lb/>
by friends. Within a day after the funeral the<lb/>
father expired, and the day after the mother's spirit<lb/>
followed that of her child and husband.</p>
<p>Among the institutions into which the pestilence<lb/>
has found an entrance is the St. Vincent's Infant<lb/>
Asylum, where there were 200 infants in charge of<lb/>
Sisters of Charity. At last accounts over seventy of<lb/>
the little ones had been smitten. In many parts of<lb/>
the city fires are burned at night for the purifica-<lb/>
tion of the atmosphere; but they seem of little<lb/>
avail.</p>
<p>In Memphis the daily scenes are still more terrible,<lb/>
if possible, than in New Orleans. Our correspond-<lb/>
ent says, in a description of daily events: &ldquo;A<lb/>
doctor will go out in the morning with enough cases<lb/>
on his list to keep him busy all day, and so he has<lb/>
to refuse all appeals. I have seen a doctor with<lb/>
women and children on their knees begging him to<lb/>
come to their husbands and fathers and mothers--<lb/>
some of them trying to drag him in. When you go<lb/>
into some of the houses you see horrible sights. I'll<lb/>
never forget one place on Jefferson Street. The<lb/>
whole family--father, mother, and seven children--<lb/>
all were in one room. The father was dead, and his<lb/>
body hung across the bed with his head hanging<lb/>
down, and the black vomit spattered all over the<lb/>
bed and the room. The mother was dying, and the<lb/>
horrible black vomit--it looks like coffee-grounds--<lb/>
was running out of her mouth into the face and<lb/>
breast of one of the children that lay on the floor<lb/>
by the bed. Ugh! it makes me sick to think of it.<lb/>
All the children but one were down with the fever,<lb/>
and they rolled around on the floor and screamed<lb/>
and groaned so, it seemed as if hell had been moved<lb/>
up on earth. There is no telling the amount of<lb/>
suffering there is there. Many a man has been taken<lb/>
while away from home, and the poor fellow has<lb/>
crawled into some hole, where his body has been<lb/>
found days after, twisted out of all shape, and found<lb/>
only by the horrible smell of the decaying flesh. A<lb/>
number of houses have been broken into, and<lb/>
whole families have been found with the bodies<lb/>
falling to pieces. One of the most horrible things<lb/>
that occurred here was the death of Mrs. Zonane.<lb/>
She lived on Jefferson Street. The doctor who at-<lb/>
tended her did not let her family know that it was the<lb/>
yellow fever until just before she died. Then he told<lb/>
them, and the five children--ranging from ten to<lb/>
twenty years old--came to say good-by. She had<lb/>
the black vomit, and they were told they had better<lb/>
not kiss her, but they did, and as they came up one<lb/>
after the other, and gave her the last kiss on earth,<lb/>
their lips were stained with that horrible stream of<lb/>
death. And what is almost miraculous, none of them<lb/>
have caught the fever yet.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A Washington physician, who spent some days in<lb/>
Memphis, says: &ldquo;The provision-stores are closed,<lb/>
and the only way to obtain supplies from them is<lb/>
to break them open, which is sometimes done.<lb/>
Even the drug-stores are all closed except three,<lb/>
and it is difficult to get medicine, even when medi-<lb/>
cal attendance has been had and prescriptions<lb/>
written. The banks are open but one hour a day.<lb/>
The commissary depots, established by the Howard<lb/>
Association, are besieged by throngs of negroes,<lb/>
many of whom come in from the surrounding coun-<lb/>
try, risking the pestilence in order to get free pro-<lb/>
visions. No vehicles are seen in the streets except<lb/>
the dead-carts and the doctors' buggies, with an<lb/>
occasional hearse conveying the remains of some<lb/>
wealthier victim. At night the streets are here and<lb/>
there lit up with the baleful gleam of the death-fires<lb/>
that burn in front of each house that contains a<lb/>
corpse. Not of each house either, for many a vic-<lb/>
tim dies alone after suffering unattended, and there<lb/>
is no one to put out the customary signal.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Of course, there are some cases of inhumanity in<lb/>
the more rural districts, where the scare is greatest.<lb/>
A correspondent recently, in journeying by rail,<lb/>
saw at Grand Junction, Tenn., a lady from Memphis<lb/>
alone in the weeds by the side of the track, dying<lb/>
of yellow fever, and three doctors within fifty<lb/>
yards, who refused to go near. Deserted stores,<lb/>
empty houses, abandoned fields and public roads,<lb/>
unmarked by a wagon-track, extended one hundred<lb/>
miles. Grenada, passed in the night, contained a<lb/>
single light, which illuminated the yellow face of a<lb/>
corpse lying on the railway platform.</p>
<p>The total mortality in the stricken district is now<lb/>
stated at 4,800.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
