<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1732001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, October 5, 1878</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1732001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1878-10-05</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1878-10-05">October 5, 1878</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1732001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, October 5, 1878</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Lessons of Calamity</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1878-10-05">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, October 5, 1878</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1732001"/>
<p>THE LESSONS OF CALAMITY.</p>
<p>IT has often occurred to us that a thrilling<lb/>
chapter in psychology and morals might<lb/>
be compiled from the observed effects<lb/>
produced on society by those great plagues<lb/>
which periodically afflict the world, wher-<lb/>
ever, as the Holy Book phrases it, &ldquo;the<lb/>
pestilence walketh in darkness and de-<lb/>
struction wasteth at noonday.&rdquo; And we<lb/>
are not without sufficient materials for the<lb/>
compilation of such a chapter in the<lb/>
sketches left us by three great literary<lb/>
artists, who have described the three most<lb/>
famous plagues of history--Thucydides,<lb/>
in his picture of the plague in Athens;<lb/>
Boccaccio, in his picture of the plague in<lb/>
Florence; and Defoe, in his picture of the<lb/>
plague which desolated London in the year<lb/>
1665. It is found that when the spectre of<lb/>
death sits at every fireside, and when the<lb/>
bands of social order are snapped by its<lb/>
skeleton touch, the King of Terrors, in-<lb/>
stead of awing the living into silence, is<lb/>
often seen to fling a door wide open for the<lb/>
entrance of every epicurean appetite,<lb/>
armed, at such times, with even more than<lb/>
cynical insolence in its quest of sensual<lb/>
indulgence. The fact affords a fearful<lb/>
commentary on the latent tendencies to<lb/>
evil which may lurk in the bosom of de-<lb/>
praved humanity, and which require naught<lb/>
but the removal of outside social forces for<lb/>
their development into acts which make a<lb/>
pandemonium on the earth.</p>
<p>Happily, there is another side to the<lb/>
picture, and it is simply in order to<lb/>
heighten <hi rend="italic">its</hi> light that we bring this dark<lb/>
background into preliminary relief. We<lb/>
refer to the moral heroism which prompts<lb/>
a few noble souls, instinct with the spirit<lb/>
of martyrdom, to offer themselves as a living<lb/>
sacrifice to the welfare or relief of their<lb/>
fellows; and we refer, besides, to that pure<lb/>
and unselfish benevolence, which, at the<lb/>
call of human calamity, however remote<lb/>
from our doors the call may be, is heard to<lb/>
answer with words of sympathy and acts of<lb/>
kindness from all parts of the land.</p>
<p>It is to this latter aspect of the moral<lb/>
lessons taught by the noisome pesti-<lb/>
lence which is now afflicting a portion of<lb/>
the South that we wish more especially to<lb/>
advert. It is not in any spirit of pride<lb/>
or vainglory that we cite the large and<lb/>
liberal benefactions which have been<lb/>
poured by the people of the North, of the<lb/>
East and of the West, into the laps of the<lb/>
Southern communities which have been<lb/>
stricken by the yellow fever scourge. In<lb/>
so doing, we should do despite to the<lb/>
purity of the benevolence in which we<lb/>
exult, and thereby dim the glory of the<lb/>
&ldquo;fine gold&rdquo; with which we would fain en-<lb/>
chase the strong and massive lines of our<lb/>
national character.</p>
<p>But we cannot forbear to remark the<lb/>
omens for good visible in this free and<lb/>
noble expression of fraternal sympathy<lb/>
between the people of the two great<lb/>
sections which lately were embroiled in an<lb/>
internecine struggle. When the ferocity<lb/>
engendered by actual war has been<lb/>
exchanged for works of mercy on the<lb/>
one side and words of thanksgiving on<lb/>
the other, is it not time to bid a truce<lb/>
to the ferocity of our <hi rend="italic">political</hi> warfare?<lb/>
If there still be those at the North who<lb/>
would flaunt the &ldquo;bloody shirt&rdquo; in the<lb/>
face of their countrymen, is it not time<lb/>
that the &ldquo;Angel of Mercy,&rdquo; hovering over<lb/>
Grenada and Vicksburg, over Memphis and<lb/>
New Orleans, should cast the shadow of her<lb/>
wings across the hustings from which mad<lb/>
party leaders would sound the notes of parti-<lb/>
san strife? If there be those at the South<lb/>
who would still nurse their wrath in pious<lb/>
memory of &ldquo;the lost cause,&rdquo; and who, to<lb/>
use the words of the eloquent Choate,<lb/>
&ldquo;would keep the keen, deep and precious<lb/>
hatred set on fire of hell,&rdquo; is it not time<lb/>
that they should mitigate their malice and<lb/>
uncharitableness while the charity of the<lb/>
North, East and West is dropping like the<lb/>
dew of heaven upon so many hearts and<lb/>
homes in the afflicted section of our land?</p>
<p>It is the profound saying of our great<lb/>
English dramatist, who has portrayed all<lb/>
passions, all phases and all situations of<lb/>
human life, that</p>
<p>&ldquo;There is some soul of goodness in things evil,<lb/>
Would men observingly distill it out.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Terrible indeed is the &ldquo;evil&rdquo; which has<lb/>
come to blight the plague-smitten cities of<lb/>
the South. Its baleful shadow spreads far<lb/>
and wide. And yet, if we will but scan it<lb/>
with the observation due to such a portent,<lb/>
we shall be able to distill from it &ldquo;some<lb/>
soul of goodness&rdquo; in more relations than<lb/>
one. In the first place, it is a cause of<lb/>
thanksgiving, alike to the Southron proud<lb/>
of his section, and to the American proud<lb/>
of the national name, that the communi-<lb/>
ties more immediately visited by the dire<lb/>
infection have not been called to blush at<lb/>
any deplorable excesses like those which,<lb/>
in other lands and other days, have turned<lb/>
the dance of death into a masquerade of<lb/>
vice and license. There must be a good<lb/>
degree of moral sanity in the constituent<lb/>
elements of a social organism which is<lb/>
able to preserve so much of order and<lb/>
decorum under the stress of such de-<lb/>
moralizing forces. And, in the second<lb/>
place, we may be grateful that this sad<lb/>
extremity of our Southern fellow-citizens<lb/>
has proved to so many men and women<lb/>
the privileged opportunity of showing the<lb/>
&ldquo;soul of goodness&rdquo; which resides in the<lb/>
hearts of the brave physicians who die at<lb/>
their posts of duty, of the Sisters of Charity<lb/>
and Mercy who watch at the couch of pain,<lb/>
and of those noble associations which bear<lb/>
the name and exemplify the philanthropy<lb/>
of Howard. And, lastly, we may hope that<lb/>
if, in the inscrutable order of nature, there<lb/>
is a needs be for the &ldquo;partial evil&rdquo; which<lb/>
darkens so many Southern homes, there<lb/>
will also be to thoughtful minds some<lb/>
ground of compensation for this heavy woe<lb/>
in the &ldquo;universal good&rdquo; it may hereafter<lb/>
work for the whole American people, by<lb/>
imbuing the hearts of men in both the<lb/>
lately belligerent sections with &ldquo;the<lb/>
quality of mercy,&rdquo; which is called twice<lb/>
blessed, because &ldquo;it blesseth him that<lb/>
gives and him that takes.&rdquo;</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
