<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
]>
<TEI.2 id="N1760001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, August 23, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1760001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-08-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph">YES</term>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-08-23">August 23, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1760001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, August 23, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Yellow Fever in Memphis</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1879-08-23">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, August 23, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1760001"/>
<p>TENNESSEE.--ARREST OF YELLOW-FEVER REFUGEES BY THE SAFETY<unclear>.</unclear>PATROL OF MEMPHIS.--FROM A SKETCH BY OUR SPECIAL ARTIST.--<del>SEE PAGE 411.</del><add>1879</add></p>
<pb n="2" id="fN1760002"/>
<p>YELLOW FEVER IN MEMPHIS.</p>
<p>ALTHOUGH day after day new cases of yellow<lb/>
fever and additional deaths are reported in<lb/>
Memphis, there is quite a general feeling that even<lb/>
if the affliction should last until frost sets in its range<lb/>
will be very much restricted and its ravages few in<lb/>
comparison with those of last season. The authori-<lb/>
ties are fighting the fever bravely. Cities and<lb/>
towns on the lines of communication with Memphis<lb/>
very promptly established a strict quarantine at the<lb/>
first outbreak. Many of the cases this year have<lb/>
proved very slight, readily yielding to the prescribed<lb/>
treatment. The streets and alleys were never so<lb/>
clean or in so good sanitary condition as at present,<lb/>
and Bayou Gayoso was never so free from foul mat-<lb/>
ter or odors. Because the city is almost depopu-<lb/>
lated no filth or garbage is produced, and the late<lb/>
rains have washed out the streets, alleys, and bayou.<lb/>
The erroneous statements in Northern journals as<lb/>
to the present filthy condition of the city are incor-<lb/>
rect in almost every respect.</p>
<p>From these facts a strong probability may be de-<lb/>
duced that the fever will be localized in the main,<lb/>
the cases appearing in other places being of success-<lb/>
ful refugees or persons engaged in steamship traffic.</p>
<p>The Howard Association is at work, but have not<lb/>
yet been obliged to solicit outside aid. The Safety<lb/>
Patrol, an organization effected for the purpose of<lb/>
<unclear>scouring</unclear> the suburbs and preventing the flight of<lb/>
panic-stricken citizens, is doing a vast service in<lb/>
confining the fever to the city.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, August 6th, the weather was in-<lb/>
tensely hot, just the state for the breeding of the<lb/>
fever, and twenty-two new cases and four deaths<lb/>
were reported. On the 6th the Secretary of War<lb/>
ordered 500 army-tents to be sent to Memphis for<lb/>
the use of fever refugees in camp, with the under-<lb/>
standing that they are to be paid for by the Na-<lb/>
tional Board of Health, if upon investigation it shall<lb/>
appear that the latter has funds available for that<lb/>
purpose. The Board of Health at New Orleans, on<lb/>
August 7th, then adopted a resolution declaring that<lb/>
there was not a single case of yellow fever in the<lb/>
city or environs; that in its opinion there is no<lb/>
danger of an epidemic arising this Summer from<lb/>
past or future cases, should such occur, and that<lb/>
the Board will use the strictest and most unremit-<lb/>
ting vigilance against the introduction of foreign<lb/>
cases. The resolution suggested that quarantines<lb/>
against New Orleans be removed.</p>
<p>On the 8th John Johnson, Superintendent of Quar-<lb/>
antine, and D. A. Porter, Chief Executive of Mem-<lb/>
phis, issued an order to inspecting and police officers<lb/>
that until further orders they shall not permit any<lb/>
person to be landed at that port or to enter the<lb/>
town by any road who has not had yellow fever and<lb/>
in addition cannot give satisfactory assurances that<lb/>
he will be able to provide for himself.</p>
<p>Dr. Jerome Cochrane, of Mobile, arrived at Mem-<lb/>
phis on the 8th, having been ordered there by the<lb/>
National Board of Health to take charge of affairs<lb/>
as the representative of the National Board, during<lb/>
the temporary absence of Dr. R. W. Mitchell, who<lb/>
has gone to Washington. The fever was officially<lb/>
declared epidemic on the 9th. This action was<lb/>
rendered necessary by the spread of the plague in<lb/>
the latter part of the week, twenty-two cases being<lb/>
reported on the 8th. A large majority of the cases<lb/>
this year have been among the colored people.</p>
<p>Nearly all the cases in New York and Philadel-<lb/>
phia have been traced to infection in Havana. The<lb/>
strictest precautions have been taken by the health<lb/>
authorities of each city, and the sickness has been<lb/>
confined to those who reached the ports under its<lb/>
preliminary influence.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
