<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1762001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 20, 1879</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Leslie, Frank</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1762001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1879-09-20</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion">YES</term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Smith, W. J.</name>
<name type="person">Gould, Jay</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1879-09-20">September 20, 1879</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1762001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 20, 1879</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Memphis Under Quarantine Rule</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1879-09-20">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, September 20, 1879</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1762001"/>
<p>RELIEVING THE GUARD OF THE COLORED PATROL.</p>
<p>EXAMINING THE CREDENTIALS OF PASSENGERS BOUND TO AND FROM MEMPHIS BY RAILROAD.</p>
<p>CAMP OF THE M'CLELLAN GUARDS AND ZOUAVES ON THE BLUFF.</p>
<p>HEADQUARTERS OF THE BOARD OF HEALTH--DISINFECTING-WAGONS ABOUT TO START ON THEIR ROUNDS.</p>
<p>METHOD OF BRINGING FOOD INTO THE CITY.</p>
<p>TENNESSEE.--MEMPHIS UNDER QUARANTINE RULE--SCENES IN THE PLAGUE-STRICKEN CITY. --FROM SKETCHES BY MOISE.--<del>SEE PAGE 43.</del><add>1879</add></p>
<p>TENNESSEE.--MEMPHIS UNDER QUARANTINE RULE--SISTERS OF CHARITY ADMINISTERING TO SICK AND DYING VICTIMS OF YELLOW FEVER.<lb/>
FROM SKETCHES BY MOISE.<del>--SEE PAGE 19</del><add>1879</add></p>
<pb n="2" id="fN1762003"/>
<p>MEMPHIS UNDER QUARANTINE RULE.</p>
<p>THE situation of affairs in plague-stricken Mem-<lb/>
phis cannot be said to improve. While the<lb/>
yellow-fever continues its ravages with but little<lb/>
abatement, thieves and incendiaries embrace every<lb/>
opportunity to plunder and destroy. Companies of<lb/>
military and mounted patrols of citizens do duty<lb/>
day and night in protecting property and arresting<lb/>
suspicious persons. It is a curious anomaly that<lb/>
all the baser persons of the baser sort of people<lb/>
come to the surface in the presence of the worst<lb/>
and most hideous forms of pestilence and plague.<lb/>
A correspondent pictures the situation as follows:<lb/>
&ldquo;Business has almost ceased except for the neces-<lb/>
saries of life; doctors, nurses, lounging negroes,<lb/>
Howard visitors, members of relief-organizations,<lb/>
State troops, police, firemen and newspaper re-<lb/>
porters are all the people you see on the street.<lb/>
Occasionally some woman or child comes along<lb/>
to remind us of the past, but even that woman or<lb/>
child is acclimated.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A physician of the city who has been conspicuous<lb/>
in fighting the pestilence, describes the city as<lb/>
practically cut off from the world. There are no<lb/>
trains running into or out of the town, and nobody<lb/>
leaves the place without the authorities knowing it.<lb/>
No steamboats land there at all. The supplies are<lb/>
all brought down on barges, which are dropped by<lb/>
steamboats a couple of miles above the city, and<lb/>
allowed to float down. When they arrive at the<lb/>
city, men in skiffs or tugs secure them and bring<lb/>
them to the landing, as shown in our illustration.<lb/>
If there is any fever carried abroad it is done by<lb/>
some daring peddler who runs his wagon of supplies<lb/>
into the town on a venture, sells out, and then gets<lb/>
away as speedily as possible.</p>
<p>The Memphis Committee of Safety, under the<lb/>
chairmanship of Dr. D. T. Porter, have established<lb/>
camps on the Raleigh dirt road, and on the Missis-<lb/>
sippi and Tennessee Railroad; besides which there<lb/>
are Camps Marks, Father Matthew, Benjes, Burke,<lb/>
Langstaff, Teutonia, and one on the bluffs for the<lb/>
soldiers engaged in patrol duty, and their families.<lb/>
On September 2d the National Board of Health ap-<lb/>
proved of the site submitted by Mr. Johnson, Super-<lb/>
intendent of Quarantine, for the establishment of a<lb/>
quarantine picket, encircling the entire city and<lb/>
suburbs. Fifty mounted policemen were assigned<lb/>
to patrol duty at once to enforce this new regula-<lb/>
tion. Ingress and egress to and from the infected<lb/>
regions will be practically cut off, save in excep-<lb/>
tional cases, where passes will be required certify-<lb/>
ing the bearer has had the fever. This is the only<lb/>
practical measure set on foot to prevent the intro-<lb/>
duction of the plague to the surrounding hamlets<lb/>
and villages, now free from infection. By this means<lb/>
the conveyance of all baggage, plunder, bedding,<lb/>
goods and wares, in which infection may be se-<lb/>
creted, will be effectually checked. Heavy penal-<lb/>
ties will be attach to all willful infractions of the<lb/>
rules. No effort will be spared to institute effectual<lb/>
quarantine.</p>
<p>Quarantine regulations are also enforced at the<lb/>
transfer stations along the line of the Louisville and<lb/>
Nashville and the Memphis and Charleston Rail-<lb/>
roads. The fever has broken out at Buntyn's Sta-<lb/>
tion, six miles east of Memphis, in the district of Dr.<lb/>
Huber Jones, a Howard physician. Under the<lb/>
direction of the National and State Boards of<lb/>
Health the city is undergoing a thorough system of<lb/>
disinfection. Every house where the fever has de-<lb/>
veloped and a death occurred is being fumigated<lb/>
and cleansed. All privy-vaults are being disin-<lb/>
fected and covered with lime, preparatory to being<lb/>
emptied and filled with earth as soon as cold<lb/>
weather sets in. Sixty men and twelve teams are<lb/>
engaged in the work. The force use daily near<lb/>
200 barrels of lime and 5,000 gallons of solution of<lb/>
copperas. All nurses sent out by the Howards are<lb/>
furnished with a package of copperas and sulphate<lb/>
of zinc. The copperas is used for disinfecting the<lb/>
discharges of patients. When a death occurs the<lb/>
corpse is washed with sulphate of zinc, then<lb/>
wrapped in a sheet wet with the same solution and<lb/>
buried at once.</p>
<p>The funds of the Howard Association are at last<lb/>
exhausted, and on September 1st, President Lang-<lb/>
staff left for the principal cities of the West, North<lb/>
and East, to consult with the parties who last year<lb/>
so nobly aided in soliciting contributions for the re-<lb/>
lief of the sufferers from yellow fever.</p>
<p>No religious services are held in the churches,<lb/>
the authorities deeming a collection of people un-<lb/>
favorable, and about the only events of a pleasant<lb/>
character are the occasional dress-parades of the<lb/>
soldiers on the bluffs.</p>
<p>Father Walsh, who organized and superintended<lb/>
the Father Mathew camp last year, and took care<lb/>
of the sick and destitute of every class and denom-<lb/>
ination, is at his grand work again, and, we regret<lb/>
to learn, is sorely pressed for funds, having ex-<lb/>
hausted all his private means, and being without<lb/>
material outside help.</p>
<p>Nineteen new cases and thirteen deaths were re-<lb/>
ported on September 4th. On the same day the<lb/>
rules and regulations governing pickets and patrols<lb/>
on duty in the suburbs were promulgated. The<lb/>
most important of the rules provides that neither<lb/>
lint-cotton nor seed-cotton will be allowed to enter<lb/>
Memphis during the epidemic. A petition, signed<lb/>
by every merchant in the city, protesting against<lb/>
the enforcement of this rule, has been presented to<lb/>
Superintendent of Quarantine Johnson.</p>
<p>Jay Gould telegraphed the following from New<lb/>
York on the 5th:</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">To W. J. Smith, Acting President Howard Association,<lb/>
Memphis, Tenn.</hi></p>
<p>I send you by telegraph $5,000 to aid the Howard Asso-<lb/>
ciation. I am certain the generous people throughout<lb/>
the country will contribute liberally to aid your stricken<lb/>
city. At any rate keep on at your noble work till I tell<lb/>
you to stop, and I will foot the bill. What are your daily<lb/>
expenses? Answer.<lb/>
JAY GOULD.</p>
<p>The money was forwarded through the Bank of<lb/>
New York, which will forward money free of charge<lb/>
for all persons desiring to make contributions.<lb/>
During the afternoon Mr. Gould received the follow-<lb/>
ing reply:</p>
<p>MEMPHIS, September 5th.</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Jay Gould, Esq., New York City:</hi></p>
<p>Your handsome donation of $5,000 to the Howard Asso-<lb/>
ciation of Memphis, to be used in relieving the sick<lb/>
under our care, is most gratefully acknowledged. The<lb/>
grand sentiment you express to continue our noble work,<lb/>
and, in the event that our appeal to the generous people<lb/>
throughout the Union is not heeded, that you would foot<lb/>
the bill, has nerved us all and strengthened our faith in<lb/>
the cause we are now engaged in. Such liberality as you<lb/>
have shown will, we have no doubt, find a responsive echo<lb/>
in the breasts of the charitable of the nation. Our ex-<lb/>
penses now aggregate $1,000 per day, and should the<lb/>
fever continue to spread, the expenses must necessarily<lb/>
increase.<lb/>
W. J. SMITH,<lb/>
Acting President Howard Association.</p>
<p>Our front-page illustration represents a Sister of<lb/>
Charity on her errand of mercy--a scene from real<lb/>
life. The room is miserable, squalid, plague-<lb/>
stricken. It is divested of every superfluous<lb/>
article of furniture, all of which has gone to pro-<lb/>
cure medicine and nourishment for the unfortunate<lb/>
man who now lies in the last dread pangs of the<lb/>
ghastly yellow fever. The terrible shadow of a<lb/>
terrible death is in that apartment. The wife now<lb/>
fears for her child, her famine-stricken child, who,<lb/>
already in the nausea of sickness, has ceased to<lb/>
clamor for food. Her husband dying, her child<lb/>
stricken--what a picture of utter desolation, of<lb/>
utter despair! A timid knock comes to the door;<lb/>
it remains unheeded. A second knock, and the<lb/>
crushed woman drags her tottering limbs to the<lb/>
portal. A ray of God's sunlight leaps into the<lb/>
room. In the doorway stands the messenger of<lb/>
consolation, the gentle messenger who will pour oil<lb/>
upon the bleeding wounds, and who will repeat<lb/>
the great grand lesson of the Good Samaritan.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
