<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N1927001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Argonaut, August 14, 1899</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N1927001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1899-08-14</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Rathom, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Echeverria, Jose R.</name>
<name type="person">Guiteras, Juan</name>
<name type="person">Shafter, William R.</name>
<name type="place">Siboney (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1899-08-14">August 14, 1899</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N1927001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Argonaut, August 14, 1899</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>In a Yellow-fever Camp: How the Pestilence Made Its Presence Known in Siboney---The American Hospital Tents in the Mountains--A Brave Physician and His Scanty Equipment</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1899-08-14">
<head>Newspaper clipping, the Argonaut, August 14, 1899</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN1927001"/>
<p>AUGUST 14, 1899.<lb/>
THE ARGONAUT.</p>
<p>IN A YELLOW-FEVER CAMP.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>How the Pestilence Made Its Presence Known in Siboney--The<lb/>
American Hospital Tents in the Mountains--A Brave<lb/>
Physician and His Scanty Equipment.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>While the troops were in Tampa, preparing for the in-<lb/>
vasion of Cuba, thousands of pamphlets, giving instructions<lb/>
how to avoid yellow fever, were distributed in the camp by<lb/>
General Howard and other good Samaritans. Many of the<lb/>
soldiers undoubtedly gave attention to the advice thus tend-<lb/>
ered, but, landed on Cuban soil, they soon understood the<lb/>
impossibility of following the instructions. Every one of the<lb/>
&ldquo;health laws&rdquo; was violated, not once, but continually, and<lb/>
perforce. The men slept on the ground because the ground<lb/>
was all they had to sleep on. They drank such water as<lb/>
they could get, and without boiling, as fires and utensils for<lb/>
boiling were not to be had. When the first outbreak of<lb/>
fever came, the victims were taken wholly by surprise, and<lb/>
many who attempted to continue in their round of duties<lb/>
fell upon the sand and lost consciousness before they realized<lb/>
that their symptoms presaged a most serious condition.</p>
<p>Among the first ten stricken down was John R. Rathom,<lb/>
a correspondent of the San Francisco <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>, and one of<lb/>
his letters to that paper deserved more than transient<lb/>
notice, as it gave a vivid picture of the terrors of the<lb/>
pestilence, the suffering of the afflicted, and the heroic<lb/>
efforts by physician and nurses. Mr. Rathom, with his com-<lb/>
panions, had been lying for days in a wet trench on San<lb/>
Juan Hill, with no covering from the dew or rain, and they<lb/>
were fit subjects for the fever germs. The certainty of the<lb/>
presence of the yellow scourge was established:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The unfortunate ten were carried down to the railroad track, a few<lb/>
yards from the house, and lifted on stretchers aboard the cars. I recol-<lb/>
lect how hundreds of wounded men came staring about us and craning<lb/>
their necks to see what people with yellow fever looked like. Then Dr.<lb/>
Guiterez, the army expert on yellow fever, made us a kindly little<lb/>
speech, told us that everything possible was being done that could be<lb/>
done under the circumstances, that he was as much distressed as we<lb/>
could be, that medical supplies and nurses were fearfully scarce, and<lb/>
asked us to keep up our pluck and try to pull through. We were put<lb/>
on two old open freight-cars, and, in a blinding rain-storm that soaked<lb/>
us to the skin before we had gone a mile, were taken up to the location<lb/>
that had been selected for a yellow-fever hospital. When we reached<lb/>
our journey's end, a dozen hospital-corps men were busy putting up<lb/>
two big tents, with a capacity of ten inmates each, and we had to wait<lb/>
on the cars for an hour until this work was finished. Here we first met<lb/>
Dr. Escheverria. He was half Spaniard, half Cuban, but had resided<lb/>
for twenty years in Florida, and had gone through six yellow-fever<lb/>
epidemics. No man who went to Cuba in Shafter's army was more<lb/>
devoted, more heroic, or more self-sacrificing. He never knew fatigue,<lb/>
worked among us like a father, and never complained, though often<lb/>
fearfully handicapped. Finally we were put into cots, and there, day<lb/>
after day, while the disease grew on us and sapped every bit of strength<lb/>
in our bodies, we watched the camp grow.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Nine days after the first appearance of the fever there were<lb/>
three hundred and eighty patients in the camp, not taking<lb/>
into account the thousands held down at Siboney with<lb/>
malaria and typhoid. Another week and the total had<lb/>
grown to nearly seven hundred, and there were two hundred<lb/>
graves on the hillside:</p>
<p>&ldquo;We lay thus among the stagnant high grasses the dew dripping<lb/>
through our tents all night and the steam arising from the ground<lb/>
about us all day. Flies, gnats, and every conceivable insect pest made<lb/>
life almost unbearable. Up to the time we had four hundred men<lb/>
down (and it seems almost an incredible statement to make) the<lb/>
medical staff of the whole camp consisted of Dr. Escheverria, one<lb/>
young assistant, and five negro nurses. Escheverria worked from six<lb/>
o'clock in the morning until two o'clock the next morning, twenty<lb/>
hours every day, making his rounds constantly. With him he carried<lb/>
a bucketful of simple medicines and half a dozen temperature ther-<lb/>
mometers. Calomel, charcoal,and quinine formed the staple reme-<lb/>
dies. We ran out of calomel, the charcoal became soggy in the moist<lb/>
climate and was soon unfit for use, and for several days there was not<lb/>
an ounce of quinine in the whole camp that a patient could take.<lb/>
The medical department had provided ten-grain capsules of quinine,<lb/>
with the capsule covers so hard and leathery that it took hours to digest<lb/>
and soften them. Escheverria, with infinite labor, opened thousands<lb/>
of these capsules and tried to gather the quinine into a heap of powder.<lb/>
The drug, however, was found to be the poorest kind of trashy imita-<lb/>
tion, and very little of it was used. It was not until twenty days after<lb/>
the hospital had been established that any good quinine was sent to us.<lb/>
Many men died very suddenly. One-half of those who succumbed<lb/>
were approaching convalescence when they took a turn for the worse.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The record of deaths was kept in a haphazard way, and<lb/>
even that incomplete list was burned when Siboney was con-<lb/>
signed to the flames. The physician's treatment of the pa-<lb/>
tients was simple but heroic:</p>
<p>&ldquo;We were allowed to touch no food whatever, with the exception of<lb/>
a little condensed milk, mixed thin with water and the juice of small,<lb/>
tasteless Cuban limes. Once in a while, when we were very low, stiff<lb/>
doses of brandy were prescribed. During the thirty days I was at the<lb/>
hospital, Red Cross nurses came into the hills on one day only and<lb/>
went back the same afternoon. That was all we saw of them. Nor<lb/>
was there a Red Cross delicacy of any character brought into the<lb/>
yellow-fever hospital during the whole month. It is fair to the mem-<lb/>
bers of that organization, however, to say that the fault was not theirs.<lb/>
The medical department of the United States Government saw fit to<lb/>
tell them that they were not wanted, and that at a time when United<lb/>
States soldiers were dying all round us for need of the very things they<lb/>
had come and offered so freely. The camp kitchen was supplied with<lb/>
oatmeal, ginger ale, and barley--nothing more. It had two cooks, and<lb/>
both of these were musicians in the regular army who had never done<lb/>
a day's cooking before in their lives. The oatmeal they turned out was<lb/>
about one-third cooked, and the barley was served practically raw.<lb/>
Escheverria did his best to keep patients from eating such food, but a<lb/>
dozen or so of them bribed the cooks to bring it to their cots, and all<lb/>
paid the penalty with their lives.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In three weeks from the beginning the worst was over, and<lb/>
Dr. Escheverria was beset with applications for release:</p>
<p>&ldquo;Everybody was crazy to go, and I remember how, day after day,<lb/>
toward the end, whenever we heard the doctor's step, we would rub our<lb/>
cheeks with the coarse blankets to get some color in them, and hold<lb/>
water in our mouths so as to beat the thermometer when it was applied<lb/>
and make it register a false temperature. Two or three times things<lb/>
looked favorable for some of us. Our temperatures were down and<lb/>
everything seemed to be going well, but we would get ourselves into<lb/>
such a pitch of excitement at the prospect of leaving the hospital that<lb/>
five minutes before Escheverria arrived we would be having chills.<lb/>
Finally a batch of six of us were released together. All our clothing<lb/>
had been burned, and we were given new Kharkee privates' uniforms<lb/>
with blue facings. Then like men released from the portals of death,<lb/>
we boarded the little car on the track, yellow, weak, and scarcely able<lb/>
to stand, and were whirled away, jubilant over our departure.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The last view of the camp taken by the convalescents as<lb/>
they were carried around a curve, showed the old physician<lb/>
waving his battered straw hat in good-by, a picture of un-<lb/>
selfish devotion.<lb/>
jahart</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
