<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N2158004">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, New York Evening Post, October 24, 1900 [Enclosed in 02158001]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2158004</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Papers of Henry Rose Carter [manuscript] ; HEALTHSCI MS-10.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1900-10-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Washington (D.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1900-10-24">October 24, 1900</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2158004</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, New York Evening Post, October 24, 1900 [Enclosed in 02158001]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Yellow-Fever Figures: Explanation by Governor-General Wood [Courtesy of the National Archives and Records Administration]</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1900-10-24">
<head>Newspaper clipping, New York Evening Post, October 24, 1900 [Enclosed in <xref id="t2158001">02158001</xref>]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2158004"/>
<p><unclear>Y,</unclear> OCTOBER 24, 1900.</p>
<p>==============</p>
<p>YELLOW-FEVER FIGURES.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>EXPLANATION BY GOVERNOR-<lb/>
GENERAL WOOD.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>How the Extent of the Outbreak Came<lb/>
to Be Concealed a Year Age--His<lb/>
Own Policy--Present Sanitary Con-<lb/>
ditions in Havana.</p>
<p>-----</p>
<p>[Special Dispatch to The Evening Post.]</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, October 24.--Gen. Leonard<lb/>
Wood when asked this morning by your<lb/>
correspondent why the figures of the yel-<lb/>
low-fever epidemic in Havana for last De-<lb/>
cember and January had been concealed, as<lb/>
he had been quoted as saying they were,<lb/>
answered that he had been misinterpreted<lb/>
in some of his statements. He did not say<lb/>
that the figures for December and January<lb/>
had been concealed, but merely that up to<lb/>
the beginning of the present year it had not<lb/>
been the practice to publish current re-<lb/>
ports of the development of the fever. He<lb/>
entered upon his duties about the 20th of<lb/>
December, but did not at first give the<lb/>
matter any attention, because it did not<lb/>
come up.</p>
<p>Early, in the present year, however, the<lb/>
representatives of two leading press asso-<lb/>
ciations came to him and said: &ldquo;General,<lb/>
we would like to have the yellow-fever fig-<lb/>
ures for the last six months to print. We<lb/>
have not been printing these statistics here-<lb/>
tofore, but it seems to us that it would<lb/>
be well to do so hereafter.&rdquo; He gave them<lb/>
permission, and from that time forward the<lb/>
press always had access to the figures.</p>
<p>He had never intended to intimate that<lb/>
there had been an attempt to deceive the<lb/>
public, but probably the subject had been<lb/>
passed over, with the assent of the press<lb/>
representatives, on account of the panicky<lb/>
conditions of public feeling in the United<lb/>
States.</p>
<p>Army officers in Cuba had been deluged<lb/>
with anxious letters from mothers, widows,<lb/>
and sisters of enlisted men, who assumed<lb/>
that the fever was going to make great in-<lb/>
roads in the army; and it was possibly with<lb/>
the desire of averting the distress of inno-<lb/>
cent persons at a distance, which could help<lb/>
nothing, that the matter was virtually ig-<lb/>
nored in the newspapers. For himself, he<lb/>
thought nothing was to be gained by keep-<lb/>
ing the public in ignorance of the facts, and<lb/>
he had never done so.</p>
<p>It was true, he said, that the fever last<lb/>
December made a worse showing than at<lb/>
any time during the previous ten years.<lb/>
Nevertheless, it was an eloquent tribute to<lb/>
the work the Americans had done there, that<lb/>
whereas under the old Spanish rule the mor-<lb/>
tality from the fever ran as high as 40 or<lb/>
45 per cent. of the cases, it now ranges about<lb/>
9 or 10, not half so high as the percentage<lb/>
from consumption, for instance.</p>
<p>Of course all talk about &ldquo;stamping out&rdquo;<lb/>
the fever is ridiculous. It has got to be a<lb/>
slow patient process, such as was pursued in<lb/>
Jamaica, which is now called free from yel-<lb/>
low fever, although an occasional case is<lb/>
still known there. There is no way of erad-<lb/>
icating yellow fever quickly.</p>
<p>Its means of communication are so subtle<lb/>
that it found its way even into a new army<lb/>
post, established in the very heart of the<lb/>
island, on virgin soil, with the most perfect<lb/>
policing ever given to such a spot. If the<lb/>
troops there had not been ordered off to<lb/>
the Orient this post would have had to be<lb/>
abandoned on account of the fever. One<lb/>
thing has been made plain by the studies<lb/>
of the sanitarians, namely, that the increase<lb/>
in the fever keeps uniform pace with the<lb/>
increase of immigration. A tobacco plant-<lb/>
er, for instance, imports a gang of several<lb/>
hundred laborers for his plantation by way<lb/>
of Havana. Naturally, he does not send<lb/>
them to a hotel, but provides for them in<lb/>
one of the vacant places in his warehouse<lb/>
where they all eat and sleep together, and<lb/>
before any one realizes what is coming the<lb/>
yellow fever breaks out among them. Per-<lb/>
haps 10 per cent. of the immigrants are im-<lb/>
mune; the rest may be sturdy, splendid spec-<lb/>
imens of health and strength, but they are<lb/>
not spared on that account.</p>
<p>With regard to the condition of the city,<lb/>
Gen. Wood said that a misunderstanding<lb/>
would be very natural from the remark he<lb/>
was quoted as making concerning its clean-<lb/>
liness a year ago. What he had intended<lb/>
to convey was an idea of comparison be-<lb/>
tween conditions a year ago and conditions<lb/>
now, for the sanitary corps have been at<lb/>
work steadily in all the intervening time,<lb/>
and necessarily the city must be in a much<lb/>
more wholesome state than ever heretofore.<lb/>
The streets as far as their outward filth<lb/>
is concerned are no better because when<lb/>
they had been cleaned five or six times<lb/>
they were as clean as they could ever be.<lb/>
Excellent work had been done, however, in<lb/>
the renovation of the dwelling-places of the<lb/>
people.</p>
<p>Col. Black of the engineers, who had had<lb/>
charge of that business during Gen. Lud-<lb/>
low's time, had gone on with it ever since.<lb/>
Old rattle-trap houses built against the city<lb/>
walls had been torn down by the dozen, and<lb/>
grassplots and clean walks laid out in<lb/>
their places. Old wells had been filled up,<lb/>
vaults and cesspools cleaned again and<lb/>
again, and the city kept in as perfect a<lb/>
state of order as possible from a sanitary<lb/>
point of view. So thorough is the system<lb/>
that an average of 600 houses are examined<lb/>
every day, the inspectors making a com-<lb/>
plete tour of the city in periods of from<lb/>
thirty to forty days each, and when a sus-<lb/>
picious case is reported at headquarters an<lb/>
average lapse of not more than three hours<lb/>
occurs between the discovery of the case<lb/>
and the appearance of the sanitary squad<lb/>
at the spot, ready for work.</p>
<p>&ldquo;It is sometimes asked.&rdquo; said Gen. Wood<lb/>
in conclusion, &ldquo;why we do not at once put<lb/>
in a complete new system of sewers and<lb/>
pavements instead of keeping the old ap-<lb/>
paratus cleansed. This will come in time,<lb/>
and before long. I hope; but it is a big un-<lb/>
dertaking, involving an expenditure of per-<lb/>
haps $10,000,000, and will be put out by con-<lb/>
tract after some weeks after advertising in<lb/>
American newspapers.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;Does not the Dady contract, of which we<lb/>
hear so much, cover this matter?&rdquo; asked<lb/>
your correspondent.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Such a contract,&rdquo; answered Gen. Wood,<lb/>
&ldquo;does not exist.&rdquo;</p>
<p>-------</p>
<p>Result of the Sealing Season in Bering<lb/>
Sea.</p>
<p>VICTORIA, B. C., October 24.--During the<lb/>
season just closed thirty-four sealing<lb/>
schooners took 16,000 skins in Bering Sea,<lb/>
which is 8,000 less than the number taken<lb/>
by twenty-five schooners last year. The<lb/>
spring schooners took 16,517 skins on the<lb/>
coast, bringing the total for the season up<lb/>
to 32,517. Only fifty-five branded seals were<lb/>
killed in Bering Sea.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
