<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N2459001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Washington Post, April 18, 1901</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2459001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-04-18</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">West Indies</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Rio de Janeiro (Brazil)</name></p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-04-18">April 18, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2459001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Washington Post, April 18, 1901</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Yellow Fever Germs</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1901-04-18">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Washington Post, April 18, 1901</head>
<pb n="1" id="fn2459001"/>
<p>THE WASHINGTON POST, THURSDAY, APRIL 18, 1901.</p>
<p>10</p>
<p>YELLOW FEVER GERMS</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Gen. Sternberg Positive Mos-<lb/>
quitoes Spread Them.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>DEMONSTRATED BY EXPERIMENT</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>His Interesting Statement Before American<lb/>
Social Science Association--Tests Made in<lb/>
Havana Described--Transmission of Dread<lb/>
Disease by Contagion Declared Impos-<lb/>
sible--Says the Germ of the Disease Has<lb/>
Not Been Discovered with Microscope.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>The sessions of the annual convention<lb/>
of the American Social Science Associ-<lb/>
ation were continued yesterday at Colum-<lb/>
bian University, with largely increased<lb/>
audiences. Several papers of interest were<lb/>
read and discussed. &ldquo;Health&rdquo; was the<lb/>
general subject, and it was treated in its<lb/>
widely diversified branches. Nutrition,<lb/>
factory hygiene, health fads, and the so-<lb/>
cial effect of insanitation in dwellings<lb/>
were the subjects of the morning discus-<lb/>
sions and papers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Transmission of Yellow Fever by the<lb/>
Mosquito,&rdquo; the subject of an address by<lb/>
Surgeon General George M. Sternberg, U.<lb/>
S. A., which opened the evening session,<lb/>
proved the most interesting of the day.<lb/>
Gen. Sternberg recited a series of experi-<lb/>
ments made by army surgeons in Cuba<lb/>
within the past year, which, by a process<lb/>
of elimination, as well as by direct re-<lb/>
sults, he regarded as establishing conclu-<lb/>
sively that the yellow fever germ infects<lb/>
the blood; that it may be transmitted by<lb/>
infusion, or by the bite of a particular<lb/>
species of mosquito after the insect has<lb/>
filled itself with the blood of a person<lb/>
suffering from yellow fever.</p>
<p>A feature of the conclusions drawn by<lb/>
the surgeon general was that the fumiga-<lb/>
tion of clothing, bedding, &amp;c., which has<lb/>
been exposed to supposed contagion by<lb/>
contact with infected persons, is abso-<lb/>
lutely valueless, unnecessary, and with-<lb/>
out any scientific basis.</p>
<p>Considerable discussion of yellow fever<lb/>
took place at the conclusion of Gen.<lb/>
Sternberg's address, but his statements<lb/>
as to transmission of yellow fever by mos-<lb/>
quito bite was not challenged. The talk<lb/>
was directed entirely to correlative is-<lb/>
sues.</p>
<p>The evening session was opened by<lb/>
President Kingsbury, who announced that<lb/>
the association was extremely gratified<lb/>
by the large attendance at its meetings,<lb/>
and had decided to hold its annual con-<lb/>
vention here next year in the early<lb/>
spring. This announcement was greeted<lb/>
with applause. President Kingsbury then<lb/>
introduced Gen. Sternberg, who spoke<lb/>
extempore, and excused himself for not<lb/>
having a paper prepared.</p>
<p>History of Yellow Fever.</p>
<p>Gen. Sternberg first reviewed the his-<lb/>
tory and described the characteristics of<lb/>
yellow fever. Several theories as to its<lb/>
original transplanting to the West Indies<lb/>
existed, he said--one that it was brought<lb/>
from Africa by slave ships. Havana, he<lb/>
said, had suffered a severe epidemic of<lb/>
the disease in the early history of the city,<lb/>
and then for more than a hundred years<lb/>
had been entirely free from the disease.<lb/>
Rio de Janeiro never knew yellow fever<lb/>
until 1848, when it was carried to the<lb/>
Brazilian city by an infected vessel from<lb/>
Havana. From this, Gen. Sternberg ar-<lb/>
gued that yellow fever does not originate<lb/>
from climatic conditions, and in support of<lb/>
this view recalled that for years there<lb/>
was annually an epidemic of the disease<lb/>
in New Orleans, so that the people be-<lb/>
lieved that it was a necessary concomi-<lb/>
tant of warm weather. For many years<lb/>
past, Gen. Sternberg said, there had been<lb/>
no yellow fever in New Orleans of an<lb/>
epidemic character.</p>
<p>He also stated that at Vera Cruz, Mex-<lb/>
ico, yellow fever is epidemic every year,<lb/>
as it is at Rio de Janeiro. Persons from<lb/>
the City of Mexico go to Vera Cruz, con-<lb/>
tract the disease, return and often die of<lb/>
it in Mexico City, but no one there had<lb/>
ever been known to catch it from a dis-<lb/>
eased person, and it never occurs there.<lb/>
This was likewise true of Pedropolis, a<lb/>
suburb of Rio de Janeiro, which, like the<lb/>
City of Mexico, is at a considerable eleva-<lb/>
tion above the sea level.</p>
<p>Not Caused by Climatic Conditions.</p>
<p>Other features of the disease, as de-<lb/>
scribed by Gen. Sternberg, were the need<lb/>
of an elevated temperature and of mois-<lb/>
ture for its development. Its develop-<lb/>
ment, he said, depends upon climatic con-<lb/>
ditions, but is not caused by them. In<lb/>
general, he asserted, it is known that<lb/>
every outbreak of the disease can be<lb/>
traced to the arrival of infected persons<lb/>
in the community in which it occurs. It<lb/>
is carried by ships from infected ports,<lb/>
and when it breaks out in a city travels<lb/>
from block to block and through channels<lb/>
that are directly in contact with the in-<lb/>
fected area. High stone walls about build-<lb/>
ings, Gen. Sternberg said, are known to<lb/>
operate as a preventive. Gen. Sternberg<lb/>
then briefly described his own investiga-<lb/>
tions of yellow fever in the West Indies<lb/>
and South and Central America, covering<lb/>
a number of years.</p>
<p>The specific cause of yellow fever, he<lb/>
said, has not yet been demonstrated,<lb/>
though many physicians have believed<lb/>
that they had found it. Dr. Sanarelli, he<lb/>
said, had studied the disease in Brazil,<lb/>
found what he thought was the germ,<lb/>
and received a prize offered by the gov-<lb/>
ernment of that country of $10,000 as a<lb/>
result of his investigations. In the light<lb/>
of recent investigation Gen. Sternberg<lb/>
stated that he was compelled to assert<lb/>
his belief that Sanarelli's germs were not<lb/>
the yellow fever bacteria.</p>
<p>Proceeding to the main subject of his<lb/>
lecture, Gen. Sternberg stated that it had<lb/>
been definitely proven that malarial fever<lb/>
is transmitted by mosquitoes. The germ<lb/>
of that disease has been identified by<lb/>
miscroscopy, he said, and had been found<lb/>
in the blood of a healthy person after he<lb/>
had been bitten by a mosquito which had<lb/>
been permitted to feed upon the blood of<lb/>
a person suffering from the disease.</p>
<p>Transmission by Mosquitoes.</p>
<p><hi>Dr. Finl<del>e</del><add>a</add>y, of Havana</hi>, said Gen. Stern-<lb/>
berg, <hi>was the first to suggest</hi>, some fifteen<lb/>
years ago, that yellow fever was trans-<lb/>
mitted by mosquitoes. Dr. Finley's exper-<lb/>
iments had been by <hi>no means confirma-<lb/>
tory of this theory, however</hi>. The profes-<lb/>
sion did not accept his view, and it gained<lb/>
no supporters until last year, when a<lb/>
board of yellow fever experts had been<lb/>
sent to Cuba under the direction of the<lb/>
Surgeon General's office to investigate<lb/>
this theory of transmission. The first ex-<lb/>
periments were made by Drs. Reed, Jesse<lb/>
&cross; H. Lazear, and Carroll. They first isolat-<lb/>
ed themselves for a longer period than<lb/>
that of incubation of yellow fever--three<lb/>
to five days--and then inoculated them-<lb/>
selves by permitting mosquitoes which<lb/>
had filled themselves with the blood of in-<lb/>
fected persons, to bite them. Dr. Reed<lb/>
and Dr. Carroll developed yellow fever,<lb/>
but Dr. Lazear did not.</p>
<p>&cross; The latter then entered a dead house,<lb/>
where were the bodies of persons who<lb/>
had died of yellow fever. While there he<lb/>
observed a mosquito upon his hand, and<lb/>
thinking he would surely become inoculat-<lb/>
ed if he permitted the insect to bite him,<lb/>
he did so, developed the disease, and died.</p>
<p>&cross; &ldquo;He fell a martyr to his zeal for his<lb/>
profession,&rdquo; said Gen. Sternberg. The<lb/>
others--Carroll and Reed--had severe at-<lb/>
tacks of the disease, but recovered.</p>
<p>Satisfied that they were upon the right<lb/>
track, these physicians then made elabo-<lb/>
rate preparations for an extended experi-<lb/>
ment. Gov. Gen. Wood supplied the funds<lb/>
from the revenues of the island as a mat-<lb/>
ter of vital interest to its inhabitants, and<lb/>
an experiment station was erected at a<lb/>
sufficient distance from Havana to insure<lb/>
the subjects of the experiment from con-<lb/>
tagion by other means than that pro-<lb/>
posed. Volunteers were secured from the<lb/>
army and from the ranks of newly ar-<lb/>
rived emigrants from Spain, who took the<lb/>
view that they would surely have yellow<lb/>
fever anyhow in Cuba, and that it would<lb/>
be better to have it where they would be<lb/>
well cared for and receive a considerable<lb/>
money bonus, as each of the volunteers<lb/>
for this experiment did receive.</p>
<p>Positive Results by Experiment.</p>
<p>The result of the experiments was en-<lb/>
tirely satisfactory, said Gen. Sternberg,<lb/>
and extremely positive. The scores of<lb/>
people at the experiment station were kept<lb/>
isolated there for several days over the<lb/>
extreme incubation period of yellow fever,<lb/>
and were then inoculated by the bite of<lb/>
mosquitoes which had been infected as in<lb/>
the other cases. Over 80 per cent. of the<lb/>
volunteers had real yellow fever. For-<lb/>
tunately none died. Gen. Sternberg said,<lb/>
in this connection, that Dr. Reed's experi-<lb/>
ments were successful and Dr. Finley's<lb/>
unsuccessful, because the former took the<lb/>
mosquito just after it had fed on the blood<lb/>
of an infected person and permitted it to<lb/>
bite a person not infected. There was no<lb/>
inoculation resultant. Dr. Reed had kept<lb/>
the infected mosquitoes for twelve or four-<lb/>
teen days after they had bitten the per-<lb/>
sons suffering from the disease, and dis-<lb/>
covered that this was necessary to obtain<lb/>
positive results. He believed that the<lb/>
germs multiplied in the mosquito's body<lb/>
and found their way into all its parts, in-<lb/>
cluding the salivary glands, through which<lb/>
they distributed the infection. From the<lb/>
experiments in the transmission of ma-<lb/>
laria by mosquitoes, Dr. Reed took his<lb/>
cue about keeping the infected mosquitoes.</p>
<p>It was determined furthermore, said<lb/>
Gen. Sternberg, that the bite of a newly<lb/>
infected mosquito neither causes infection<lb/>
nor makes the person bitten immune, as<lb/>
was supposed by some. This discovery<lb/>
about the germs requiring time to de-<lb/>
velop in the body of the mosquito, he<lb/>
said, cleared up the mystery about the<lb/>
spread of the disease in cities where it<lb/>
had been studied, and where it was found<lb/>
that secondary cases did not occur until<lb/>
fifteen or twenty days after the initial<lb/>
cases arrived.</p>
<p>In summarizing the result of Dr. Reed's<lb/>
experimenting, Gen. Sternberg stated that<lb/>
it had been positively determined that<lb/>
the mosquito known as the culex fascia-<lb/>
tus distributes the disease, as stated, and<lb/>
that it is not transmitted by the species<lb/>
of mosquito which is found at greater<lb/>
altitudes. It had also been found that<lb/>
a minute quantity of blood drawn from a<lb/>
person suffering from yellow fever and<lb/>
injected into the blood of a healthy per-<lb/>
son would give the latter the disease.</p>
<p>The yellow fever germ itself, he declar-<lb/>
ed, had not been discovered, and it is be-<lb/>
lieved to be ultramicroscopical, as in the<lb/>
case of the germ of the foot and mouth<lb/>
disease, which can be separated by a<lb/>
mechanical process, but gives negative re-<lb/>
sults under the microscope.</p>
<p>No Transmission by Contagion.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most interesting portion of<lb/>
Gen. Sternberg's address covered the sub-<lb/>
ject of other forms of contagion. He con-<lb/>
tended that there are none, and asserted<lb/>
positively that the yellow fever germ can<lb/>
be transmitted only by direct introduction<lb/>
into the blood. He stated that a new set<lb/>
of volunteers submitted to a second test<lb/>
at the Cuban experiment station, after<lb/>
those inoculated by mosquito bite had<lb/>
been discharged. The second volunteers<lb/>
put on clothing taken from persons suf-<lb/>
fering from yellow fever, slept in bed-<lb/>
clothes which had just been taken from<lb/>
the cots of victims, sick and dead, and<lb/>
made every effort, under direction of the<lb/>
attendant physicians, to acquire yellow<lb/>
fever by contagion from such clothing and<lb/>
garments. These efforts, said Gen. Stern-<lb/>
berg, were wholly without success. Not<lb/>
a single one of the volunteers was made<lb/>
even unwell by days of close contact with<lb/>
clothing which would have been declared<lb/>
fit only to be burned under the old views<lb/>
as to this means of disseminating the<lb/>
dread disease.</p>
<p><hi>Gen. Sternberg then read extracts from<lb/>
an order of the War Department covering</hi><lb/>
the extermination of mosquitoes and their<lb/>
exclusion from dwellings in lands subject<lb/>
to yellow fever. At the close of the paper<lb/>
questions were asked regarding the al-<lb/>
leged protection afforded by high walls<lb/>
against the progress of yellow fever epi-<lb/>
demics. The surgeon general explained<lb/>
that the mosquito which carries the yel-<lb/>
low fever germ flies low, and this fact<lb/>
about insect pests was corroborated by<lb/>
the experience of President Kingsbury.</p>
<p>The session concluded with the reading<lb/>
by Secretary Rcot of an abstract of a pa-<lb/>
per on &ldquo;Food as the Principal Factor in<lb/>
the Cause of Disease,&rdquo; of which Dr. El-<lb/>
mer Lee, of New York, was the author.<lb/>
Dr. Lee declared the swallowing of food<lb/>
without proper mastication and satura-<lb/>
tion with saliva a fruitful scource of dis-<lb/>
ease, and called food so taken into the<lb/>
system raw, saying that it is poisonous.</p>
<p>Proper, natural swallowing of food is<lb/>
unconscious, he said, and to swallow food<lb/>
before it ceases to have taste and zest<lb/>
and slips naturally down the throat is to<lb/>
expose the system to the action of in-<lb/>
jurious elements, which may lead to dis-<lb/>
ease at any time.</p>
<p>Announcement of the programme for to-<lb/>
day was coupled with a renewal of the<lb/>
invitation of the association to the public<lb/>
to attend.</p>
<p>Factory Sanitation and Health Fads.</p>
<p>The morning session was devoted to the<lb/>
discussion of questions of hygiene, this<lb/>
department being under Dr. W. H. Daly,<lb/>
chairman, and Dr. Elmer Lee, secretary.<lb/>
A large majority of those in attendance<lb/>
were women, who seemed to take great<lb/>
interest in the papers read. The first was<lb/>
by John H. Patterson, of Dayton, Ohio,<lb/>
who described the large manufacturing<lb/>
establishment of which he is the head. He<lb/>
said that it had been found to the pe-<lb/>
cuniary benefit of that institution to pro-<lb/>
vide for the comfort, sanitary surround-<lb/>
ings, and agreeable environment of the<lb/>
employes while at work. He described the<lb/>
buildings and their close adherence to the<lb/>
principles of hygiene and artistic effect.<lb/>
&ldquo;We have demonstrated,&rdquo; said Mr. Pat-<lb/>
terson, &ldquo;that this system pays the em-<lb/>
ploye, the manufacturer, and the buyer<lb/>
in the health of one, the profit of the<lb/>
second, and the improved quality of<lb/>
the product purchased by the third.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. Grace Peckham Murray, of New<lb/>
York, read a paper on &ldquo;Health Fads of<lb/>
To-day.&rdquo; She said they were number-<lb/>
less, and declared that charlatans had<lb/>
taken advantage of the general feeling<lb/>
that health is of the greatest importance.<lb/>
Christian Science and osteopathy were ar-<lb/>
raigned severely by the lecturer, who de-<lb/>
clared that they should be subjected to<lb/>
the same close and direct supervision as<lb/>
other methods of healing. She declared<lb/>
that the spread of pestilential diseases<lb/>
in large cities was most often due to<lb/>
quacks, who claim that there can be no<lb/>
contamination by association with a dis-<lb/>
eased person, and conceal the character<lb/>
of the cases they are &ldquo;treating.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. C. W. Chancellor, of Washington,<lb/>
D. C., described &ldquo;Social Evils Resulting<lb/>
from Unsanitary Dwellings.&rdquo; Dr. Chan-<lb/>
cellor declared that 33 per cent. of the<lb/>
deaths among the poor were due to the<lb/>
absence of sanitary arrangements in their<lb/>
places of abode, and particularly in the<lb/>
failure to provide for pure air. He de-<lb/>
clared that one out of four infants born<lb/>
to parents of the tenements and squaled<lb/>
lodging places dies within a year, and at-<lb/>
tributed this mortality to lack of sanita-<lb/>
tion. In the opinion of the lecturer it<lb/>
should be impossible, under the law, for<lb/>
owners to maintain unsanitary dwellings<lb/>
for the occupation of human beings, and<lb/>
that in the event of their failure to make<lb/>
their properties suitable for healthful<lb/>
habitation, the law should permit and de-<lb/>
mand the destruction of such dwellings.</p>
<p>Dr. Irving C. Rosse, of Washington, D.<lb/>
C., who was to have read a paper on the<lb/>
general relation of social to sanitary con-<lb/>
ditions, was absent.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
