<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;]>
<TEI.2 id="N2455001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The New York Times, March [31, 1901]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>Bayles, James C.</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2455001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1901-03-31</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics">YES</term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Ames, Roger Post</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert P.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Quemados (Cuba)</name>
<name type="hospital">Las Animas Hospital</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1901-03-31">March 31, 1901</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2455001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The New York Times, March [31, 1901]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Etiology of Yellow Fever</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1901-03-31">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The New York Times, March [31, 1901]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fn2455001"/>
<p>THE ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Its Propagation by the Mosquito--Impossibility of Infection Through Clothing,<lb/>
Bedding, or Merchandise--The Inutility of Quarantine Precautions.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Last year Surgeon Reed of the United<lb/>
States Army, stationed in Cuba, applied to<lb/>
Gen. Leonard Wood for a fund of $5,000 for<lb/>
experiments relative to the means by which<lb/>
yellow fever is communicated from the sick<lb/>
to the well. This money was needed for<lb/>
the establishment of an experimental sta-<lb/>
tion where subjects selected for test could<lb/>
be exposed to infection under conditions<lb/>
which would permit all the phenomena<lb/>
connected with the etiology of this disease<lb/>
to be accurately observed. The request<lb/>
was acceded to on the condition that all<lb/>
who were experimented upon should sub-<lb/>
mit voluntarily, with full knowledge of the<lb/>
nature and objects of the tests to be made<lb/>
upon them, and that in the case of Spanish<lb/>
subjects the assent of the Spanish Consul<lb/>
should also be obtained. The ethics of the<lb/>
experiment were carefully considered, and<lb/>
the first to submit himself to the experi-<lb/>
ment was a member of the board, Dr.<lb/>
James Carroll, Acting Assistant Surgeon,<lb/>
United States Army. The senior medical<lb/>
officer of the board had intended to sub-<lb/>
mit himself to the operation, but was unex-<lb/>
pectedly called North and could not. From<lb/>
this it appears that the courage of leader-<lb/>
ship is found among the non-combatants of<lb/>
the medical staff, as well as in the line.</p>
<p>Under the conditions outlined, the work<lb/>
of Dr. Reed and those associated with him<lb/>
has given results of the greatest interest<lb/>
and importance. At first glance it seems<lb/>
to have upset all theories relative to quar-<lb/>
antine, and to have laid the foundation for<lb/>
a more rational system of restricting the<lb/>
spread of the disease than that which<lb/>
places an embargo upon so large a share of<lb/>
the commerce of the world and to so seri-<lb/>
ous an extent interferes with the inter-<lb/>
course between nations. The experiments<lb/>
here recounted in outline were made under<lb/>
conditions permitting them to be surround-<lb/>
ed by every safeguard against misleading<lb/>
results. The facts presented in this article<lb/>
were set forth at great length in a paper by<lb/>
Drs. Reed, Carroll, and Agramonte, read at<lb/>
the Pan-American Medical Congress held in<lb/>
Havana in February last.</p>
<p>CAMP LAZEAR.</p>
<p>In order to exercise the most perfect con-<lb/>
trol possible over the movements of the in-<lb/>
dividuals selected for experimentation, a<lb/>
location was selected in an open and un-<lb/>
cultivated field near Quemado, Cuba, where<lb/>
an experimental sanitary station was estab-<lb/>
lished, named Camp Lazear, in honor of Dr.<lb/>
J. W. Lazear, who contracted a fatal case<lb/>
of yellow fever while conducting investiga-<lb/>
tions in connection with this disease. The<lb/>
personnel of the camp consisted of Dr.<lb/>
Ames, an immune, in charge; Dr. Cook, a<lb/>
non-immune; an immune hospital steward,<lb/>
nine privates of the Hospital Corps, only<lb/>
one of whom was an immune, and an im-<lb/>
mune ambulance driver. Suitable accom-<lb/>
modations were provided, and every precau-<lb/>
tion was taken to make the local condi-<lb/>
tions as favorable as possible. The camp<lb/>
was established in November, 1900. It was<lb/>
strictly quarantined from the outset, and<lb/>
every safeguard was established to prevent<lb/>
introduction of the infection of yellow fever<lb/>
from the outside. A few Spanish immi-<lb/>
grants, lately arrived from the Port of<lb/>
Havana, were received from time to time,<lb/>
under the arrangement above noted, but<lb/>
no non-immune leaving the camp for any<lb/>
purpose was permitted to return to it. The<lb/>
temperatures and pulses of all non-im-<lb/>
munes in the camp were taken three times<lb/>
a day.</p>
<p>INOCULATION BY MOSQUITO BITES.</p>
<p>When everything was as satisfactory as<lb/>
the judgment of the experimenters could<lb/>
suggest, a system of inoculation was be-<lb/>
gun. Every person taking part in these ex-<lb/>
periments as a subject did so with full<lb/>
knowledge of the risk he was incurring and<lb/>
the nature of the service he was rendering<lb/>
in the cause of science. The men who con-<lb/>
sented to subject themselves to inoculation<lb/>
were as heroic as the bravest of those who<lb/>
charged up San Juan Hill, and should have<lb/>
a special medal of honor, if it were the<lb/>
custom of this Government to recognize<lb/>
such acts as win for British soldiers the<lb/>
Victoria Cross. The following is a brief<lb/>
summary of the records of the experiments.</p>
<p>Case 1. Private John R. Kissinger, Hos-<lb/>
pital Corps, United States Army, permitted<lb/>
himself to be bitten by a mosquito (culex<lb/>
fasciatus, Fabr,) which, eleven days be-<lb/>
fore, had bitten a patient with a severe<lb/>
case of yellow fever in the fifth day of its<lb/>
development. The same insect had also<lb/>
bitten a fever patient six days before, and<lb/>
still another three days before. Three days<lb/>
after his first inoculation Kissinger per-<lb/>
mitted himself to be bitten a second time<lb/>
by the same mosquito. Both innoculations<lb/>
were negative. The conclusion drawn from<lb/>
this experiment was that the insect was<lb/>
incapable of carrying any infection on the<lb/>
eleventh or fourteenth day after it had<lb/>
bitten a severe case of yellow fever.</p>
<p>About a week later Private Kissinger per-<lb/>
mitted himself to be bitten by five mos-<lb/>
quitoes of the same variety, (C. fasciatus,)<lb/>
two of which were known to have bitten<lb/>
fatal cases of yellow fever on the second<lb/>
day of the development of the disease, fif-<lb/>
teen days before they were given access to<lb/>
Kissinger--one a severe case on the sev-<lb/>
enth day of its development, nineteen days<lb/>
previously--and two insects a mild case on<lb/>
the third day of development, twenty-one<lb/>
days before. Three days later Kissinger<lb/>
came down with a typical case of yellow<lb/>
fever. The exact period of incubation in<lb/>
this case was three days, nine and a half<lb/>
hours. It was a case of moderate severity,<lb/>
and the patient recovered.</p>
<p>Case 2. John J. Moran, a non-immune<lb/>
American civilian, submitted to the test<lb/>
and permitted himself to be bitten by a<lb/>
mosquito which twelve days before had<lb/>
bitten a patient with a case of yellow fever<lb/>
of moderate severity in the third day of its<lb/>
development. It had also, ten days pre-<lb/>
viously, bitten a well-marked case in the<lb/>
second day of its development. Three days<lb/>
later Moran was again bitten by the same<lb/>
insect. Both inoculations gave negative<lb/>
<unclear>results</unclear>, warranting the conclusion that the<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> was incapable of imparting the in-<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear] u</unclear>nder the conditions noted.</p>
<p><unclear>[unclear]</unclear> A Spanish immigrant allowed<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear] t</unclear>o be bitten by four mosquitos, all<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> were known to have bitten yellow<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> patients at different stages of de-<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear>nent at periods of seventeen to twen-<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear>our days previously. He took the dis-<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear> and developed a typical case after an<lb/>
<unclear>[unclear]</unclear>cubation of 5 days and 17 hours.</p>
<p>Case 4. A Spanish immigrant was vol-<lb/>
untarily bitten three times, at intervals<lb/>
<unclear>o</unclear>f three days, by one mosquito which had<lb/>
previously bitten a severe case; also by<lb/>
a second insect which had bitten a fatal<lb/>
case. The results were negative. Thirteen<lb/>
days later the same subject was bitten by<lb/>
a mosquito which had been infected nine-<lb/>
teen days before by biting a fatal case on<lb/>
the second day of its development. This<lb/>
was effective, and the subject developed<lb/>
a typical case of yellow fever after an<lb/>
incubation of 3 days 11&frac12; hours.</p>
<p>Case 5. A Spanish immigrant was twice<lb/>
bitten by insects known to be infected from<lb/>
observed contact with typical cases twelve<lb/>
and eighteen days previously. The results<lb/>
were negative. Nine days later the sub-<lb/>
ject was bitten by the same four insects<lb/>
which had been experimented with in Case<lb/>
3. This time it gave positive results. After<lb/>
an incubation of 3 days 19&frac12; hours the<lb/>
subject developed a typical case of yellow<lb/>
fever.</p>
<p>Case 6. A Spanish immigrant was bitten<lb/>
by four mosquitos infected seventeen days<lb/>
before by biting a mild case of the dis-<lb/>
ease on the first day of its development.<lb/>
It was effective, and brought him down<lb/>
with an unmistakable attack in 3 days 22&frac12;<lb/>
hours.</p>
<p>From the foregoing experiments, of which<lb/>
only the barest outline has been given in<lb/>
this synopsis, it is assumed that the func-<lb/>
tion of the Culex fasciatus as a carrier and<lb/>
inoculator of the parasite of yellow fever<lb/>
is very clearly shown. Six tests were made<lb/>
upon persons who had been strictly quar-<lb/>
antined, as follows: Case 1. 15 days; Case<lb/>
2. 18 days; Case 3. 9 days: Case 4, 19 days;<lb/>
Case 5, 21 days; Case 6, 9 days. The only<lb/>
non-immunes in Camp Lazear who had<lb/>
yellow fever were those which submitted<lb/>
to be bitten by mosquitos known to have<lb/>
been infected. The local epidemic caused<lb/>
by these experiments having subsided by<lb/>
Dec. 15 and no new cases appearing, the<lb/>
tests were resumed with the following re-<lb/>
sults:</p>
<p>A Spanish immigrant was bitten by four<lb/>
mosquitoes known to be infected from con-<lb/>
tact with a recognized case seventeen days<lb/>
before. In less than four days he was<lb/>
taken with the disease and had a bad case<lb/>
of it. He had been in strict quarantine for<lb/>
twenty-two days prior to the test.</p>
<p>In considering the character of the in-<lb/>
duced attacks in the cases above recorded<lb/>
it should be remembered that the subjects<lb/>
were all young men, in good general con-<lb/>
dition, and with as good an environment as<lb/>
science could provide. So far as can be<lb/>
seen, they had no other way of contracting<lb/>
the disease than that provided in the test.<lb/>
It will probably be regarded as curious that<lb/>
attempts to induce an attack of the disease<lb/>
by the bite of the mosquito under twelve<lb/>
days of the date of its contamination were<lb/>
generally unsuccessful. Eleven days was<lb/>
the shortest period in which the mos-<lb/>
quito was found able to communicate the<lb/>
disease to a human being after taking up<lb/>
the poison from a patient sick with it. Dr.<lb/>
Reed's observations would seem to show, as<lb/>
he assumes that they do, that after the<lb/>
parasite of the disease has been taken into<lb/>
the stomach of the mosquito a certain<lb/>
length of time must elapse before it is ca-<lb/>
pable of reconveying it to man. This has<lb/>
been found to range from twelve days in<lb/>
Summer to eighteen days in cooler weather.</p>
<p>CASES INDUCED BY INJECTIONS OF<lb/>
BLOOD.</p>
<p>To determine if the parasite of the dis-<lb/>
ease really exists in the blood of the hu-<lb/>
man subject in such condition that the<lb/>
mosquito could absorb it with what he<lb/>
draws from a person bitten, tests were<lb/>
made by injecting into the circulation of<lb/>
well persons blood taken from the general<lb/>
circulation of one having the disease. Out<lb/>
of four such tests three induced the dis-<lb/>
ease after brief incubation. The one case<lb/>
in which this experiment was unsuccess-<lb/>
ful was that of a Spanish immigrant, who<lb/>
proved also non-susceptible to the bites of<lb/>
infected mosquitoes and was assumed to<lb/>
be a natural immune. The blood-injection<lb/>
tests seem to warrant the conclusion that<lb/>
the parasite of yellow fever is present in<lb/>
the general and capillary circulation, at<lb/>
least during the early stages of the dis-<lb/>
ease, and that it may be conveyed, like<lb/>
the malarial parasite, either by the direct<lb/>
transfusion of blood or by the variety of<lb/>
mosquito which appears to have been es-<lb/>
pecially provided by nature for this pur-<lb/>
pose. Its designation as C. fasciatus has<lb/>
been questioned by entomologists, but that<lb/>
is unimportant. He differs from the ma-<lb/>
laria insect known as C. Anopheles. Prob-<lb/>
ably the yellow fever mosquito will be<lb/>
known as the Stegamina, but this is sim-<lb/>
ply a distinction of interest to specialists<lb/>
in insect terminology. The fact of greatest<lb/>
biological interest in connection with the<lb/>
blood-transfusion experiments is that care-<lb/>
ful cultures from the same blood taken<lb/>
immediately after the injection failed to<lb/>
show the presence of Sanarelli's bacillus.</p>
<p>IS QUARANTINE A SUPERSTITION?</p>
<p>It has been held as an indisputable truth<lb/>
by all who have given the subject consid-<lb/>
eration, and especially by the medical pro-<lb/>
fession, that yellow fever is conveyed by<lb/>
fomites. Epidemics of this disease have<lb/>
been repeatedly &ldquo;traced&rdquo; to merchandise<lb/>
and baggage shipped from ports in which<lb/>
the disease existed; and it would have been<lb/>
held a rank heresy to question the theory<lb/>
that infected clothing, bedding, and even<lb/>
the fabrics used as packing for merchan-<lb/>
dise, were capable of bringing it to ports<lb/>
where it was not indigenous. Hence the<lb/>
stringent quarantine regulations deemed<lb/>
necessary to prevent the importation of<lb/>
this dread disease into the United States,<lb/>
which have required the thorough disinfec-<lb/>
tion of clothing, bedding, &amp;c., suspected of<lb/>
contamination, or which has come, after<lb/>
the briefest possible sojourn there, from a<lb/>
port where the disease existed. To deter-<lb/>
mine whether clothing, bedding, and arti-<lb/>
cles of personal use like towels, known to<lb/>
have been in close and protracted contact<lb/>
with persons sick with yellow fever, were<lb/>
capable of communicating the disease to<lb/>
non-immunes, some very important and<lb/>
even startling experiments were made at<lb/>
Camp Lazear. A brief statement of the<lb/>
methods and results will be both interest-<lb/>
ing and instructive.</p>
<p>For this purpose a special building was<lb/>
erected, so designed as to insure defective<lb/>
ventilation and render it difficult to change<lb/>
the residual air of its interior by natural<lb/>
draughts. Its walls were as nearly imper-<lb/>
vious as they could be made. It faced the<lb/>
south, and had only two small windows,<lb/>
both on the south side and guarded by<lb/>
fine wire gauze screens fixed in place be-<lb/>
hind glass. The windows were also closed<lb/>
by heavy wooden outside shutters to ef-<lb/>
fectually exclude sunlight. The entrance<lb/>
was guarded by a double system of solid<lb/>
and wire gauze doors. Until after sunset<lb/>
the house was kept as dark as a pocket,<lb/>
and was never permitted to have a temper-<lb/>
ature below 92 to 95 Fahrenheit. Artificial<lb/>
humidity was also secured by evaporating<lb/>
appliances. The idea was to create the<lb/>
conditions most favorable to the develop-<lb/>
ment of the parasites of yellow fever and<lb/>
to exclude all conditions tending to their<lb/>
destruction. The conditions inside the<lb/>
building were as bad as could be found in<lb/>
the hold or steerage of a ship making a<lb/>
tropical voyage in hurricane weather, with<lb/>
the hatches battened down and the inside<lb/>
temperature fluctuating between 90 and 100<lb/>
Fahrenheit. When this model pest-breed-<lb/>
ing building was ready for occupation, it<lb/>
was devoted to the use for which it was<lb/>
designed.</p>
<p>Three large boxes filled with sheets,<lb/>
pillow slips, blankets, &amp;c., contaminated by<lb/>
contact with cases of yellow fever and their<lb/>
discharges, were received and placed there-<lb/>
in. The majority of the articles had been<lb/>
taken from the beds of patients sick with<lb/>
yellow fever at Las Animas Hospital, Ha-<lb/>
vana, or at Columbia Barracks. Many of<lb/>
them had been purposely soiled with a<lb/>
liberal quantity of black vomit, urine, and<lb/>
fecal matter. A dirty comfortable and<lb/>
much-soiled pair of blankets, removed from<lb/>
the bed of a patient sick of yellow fever in<lb/>
the town of Quemados, were contained in<lb/>
one of these boxes. The same day at 6<lb/>
P. M. Dr. R. P. Cook, Acting Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon, United States Army, and two<lb/>
privates of the Hospital Corps, all non-<lb/>
immune Americans, entered this building<lb/>
and deliberately unpacked these boxes,<lb/>
which had been kept tightly closed and<lb/>
locked for a period of about two weeks.<lb/>
They were careful at the same time to give<lb/>
each article a thorough handling and shak-<lb/>
ing in order to disseminate through the<lb/>
air of the room the specific agent of yel-<lb/>
low fever, if contained in these fomites.<lb/>
These soiled sheets, pillow cases and<lb/>
blankets were used in preparing the beds in<lb/>
which the members of the Hospital Corps<lb/>
slept. Various soiled articles were hung<lb/>
around the room and placed about the bed<lb/>
occupied by Dr. Cook. Thereafter, for<lb/>
twenty days, this room was occupied every<lb/>
night by these three non-immunes. Each<lb/>
morning the various soiled articles were<lb/>
carefully repacked in the boxes in which<lb/>
they had come, and at night again un-<lb/>
packed and distributed about the room.<lb/>
During the day the occupants of this house<lb/>
were permitted to use a tent pitched in the<lb/>
immediate vicinity, but were kept in strict<lb/>
quarantine. After twelve days a fourth<lb/>
box of clothing and bedding was received<lb/>
from Las Animas Hospital, all of which<lb/>
had been used on the beds of yellow fever<lb/>
patients and had been purposely soiled with<lb/>
the discharges of patients who had died.<lb/>
As this box had been packed for a number<lb/>
of days, the odor was so offensive as to<lb/>
drive Dr. Cook and his assistants away<lb/>
from the building; but they courageously<lb/>
returned in a short time and spent the night<lb/>
as usual amid these gruesome and ap-<lb/>
parently deadly surroundings. After twen-<lb/>
ty days' exposure to this test the three non-<lb/>
immunes who had taken part in it were<lb/>
placed in quarantine for five days, which,<lb/>
as we have seen is longer than the period<lb/>
of incubation. They remained in perfect<lb/>
health.</p>
<p>Some of the conditions of this exposure,<lb/>
while necessarily of record in a history of<lb/>
the experiment, are so disagreeable and<lb/>
involved such a complete surrender of every<lb/>
condition of comfort and even of decency,<lb/>
that we prefer to refer the reader who de-<lb/>
sires full particulars to the original docu-<lb/>
ments, embodied in the transactions of the<lb/>
Pan-American Medical Congress.</p>
<p>After the first party had been discharged<lb/>
additional supplies of infected clothing and<lb/>
bedding were obtained and added to the<lb/>
collection. Meanwhile the building was<lb/>
kept hot, damp, and dark. It was, how-<lb/>
ever, occupied for twenty days by two<lb/>
young American non-immunes, who did all<lb/>
that ingenuity could suggest to expose<lb/>
themselves to infection. They remained<lb/>
well, and after five days' quarantine were<lb/>
discharged. Then a third party took pos-<lb/>
session, went through the same experience,<lb/>
and were discharged as well as when they<lb/>
entered. It may be assumed that if the<lb/>
disease is communicable by fomites, at<lb/>
least one of the seven non-immunes who<lb/>
went through this terrible test would have<lb/>
contracted the disease. Not one of them<lb/>
did.</p>
<p>It having been found impossible to infect<lb/>
a house with yellow fever by the means<lb/>
which have been held to be its favorite me-<lb/>
dia of propagation and transmission, a<lb/>
second building was put up. This differed<lb/>
from the one last described in having doors<lb/>
and windows placed on opposite sides, so as<lb/>
to insure through and through ventilation.<lb/>
It was divided by a wire screen partition<lb/>
extending from floor to ceiling. Every-<lb/>
thing admitted to this building was thor-<lb/>
oughly disinfected and sterilized by steam,<lb/>
and as much care was taken to keep it free<lb/>
from infection as had been taken in the<lb/>
case of Building No. 1 to infect it. When<lb/>
everything was ready there were turned<lb/>
loose in one room of this building fifteen<lb/>
mosquitoes (culex fasciatus) which had<lb/>
been previously contaminated by biting yel-<lb/>
low fever patients. The first to take the<lb/>
test was the young civilian non-immune,<lb/>
Moran, whose unsuccessful attempt to take<lb/>
the disease was recounted in Case 2 of the<lb/>
preceding narrative. He was bitten several<lb/>
times, taking three exposures within two<lb/>
days. After an incubation of three days<lb/>
and twenty-three hours from his first en-<lb/>
try into the building, he came down with a<lb/>
typical case of yellow fever. Two non-im-<lb/>
munes who remained in the building con-<lb/>
tinuously, but on the opposite side of the<lb/>
screen from that occupied by the mosqui-<lb/>
toes, remained perfectly well. After biting<lb/>
Moran the mosquitoes seemed to develop<lb/>
some kind of an epidemic of their own, for<lb/>
they died off and the Moran experiment<lb/>
could not be repeated. It is interesting,<lb/>
however, to note that whereas all those<lb/>
exposed to intimate and protracted con-<lb/>
tact with the fomites for an average of<lb/>
twenty-one nights each escaped without in-<lb/>
jury; of the two exposed to the bites of<lb/>
mosquitoes in Building No. 2; where every-<lb/>
thing except the insects was strictly asep-<lb/>
tic, one was infected. The escape of the<lb/>
other was expected, for the reason that at<lb/>
the time of his exposure it was not be-<lb/>
lieved that any insect remained alive<lb/>
which had been infected long enough to be<lb/>
capable of conveying the disease to a hu-<lb/>
man being.</p>
<p>RECAPITULATION.</p>
<p>Dr. Reed thus summarizes the results of<lb/>
the work above described, and which is<lb/>
entitled to rank with the most important of<lb/>
modern contributions to medical litera-<lb/>
ture: &ldquo;Of seven non-immunes whom we at-<lb/>
tempted to infect by means of the bites of<lb/>
contaminated mosquitoes, we have succeed-<lb/>
ed in conveying the disease to six, or 85.71<lb/>
per cent. On the other hand, of seven non-<lb/>
immunes whom we tried to infect by means<lb/>
of fomites under particularly favorable cir-<lb/>
cumstances we did not succeed in a single<lb/>
instance. Out of a total of eighteen non-<lb/>
immunes whom we inoculated with con-<lb/>
taminated mosquitoes since we began this<lb/>
line of investigation eight, or 44.4 per cent.,<lb/>
have contracted yellow fever. If we exclude<lb/>
those bitten by mosquitoes that had been<lb/>
contaminated less than twelve days, and<lb/>
which were therefore probably incapable of<lb/>
conveying the disease, we have to record<lb/>
eight positive and two negative results--80<lb/>
per cent.&rdquo;</p>
<p>The following are the conclusions which<lb/>
Dr. Reed and his associates have reached<lb/>
as the result of their valuable and inter-<lb/>
esting work:</p>
<p>CONCLUSIONS.</p>
<p>
<list type="ordered">
<item>1. The mosquito, Culex fasciatus, serves<lb/>
as the intermediate host for the parasite<lb/>
of yellow fever.</item>
<item>2. Yellow fever is transmitted to the non-<lb/>
immune individual by means of the bite of<lb/>
the mosquito that has previously fed on the<lb/>
blood of those sick with this disease.</item>
<item>3. An interval of about twelve days, or<lb/>
more, after contamination, appears to be<lb/>
necessary before the mosquito is capable<lb/>
of conveying the infection.</item>
<item>4. The bite of the mosquito at an earlier<lb/>
period after contamination does not ap-<lb/>
pear to confer any immunity against a<lb/>
subsequent attack.</item>
<item>5. Yellow fever can also be experimental-<lb/>
ly produced by the subcutaneous injection<lb/>
of blood taken from the general circulation<lb/>
during the first and second days of this<lb/>
disease.</item>
<item>6. An attack of yellow fever produced<lb/>
by the bite of a mosquito confers im-<lb/>
munity against the subsequent injection of<lb/>
the blood of an individual suffering from<lb/>
the non-experimental form of this disease.</item>
<item>7. The period of incubation in thirteen<lb/>
cases of experimental yellow fever has<lb/>
varied from 41 hours to 5 days, 17 hours.</item>
<item>8. Yellow fever is not conveyed by fo-<lb/>
mites, and hence disinfection of articles of<lb/>
clothing, bedding, or merchandise sup-<lb/>
posedly contaminated by those sick of this<lb/>
disease is unnecessary.</item>
<item>9. A house may be said to be infected<lb/>
with yellow fever only when there are<lb/>
present within its walls contaminated<lb/>
mosquitoes capable of conveying the para-<lb/>
site of this disease.</item>
<item>10. The spread of yellow fever can be<lb/>
most effectually controlled by measures di-<lb/>
rected to the destruction of mosquitoes<lb/>
and the protection of the sick against the<lb/>
bites of these insects.</item>
<item>11. While the mode of propagation of<lb/>
yellow fever has now been definitely de-<lb/>
termined, the specific cause of this disease<lb/>
remains to be discovered.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>JAMES C. BAYLES, Ph. D.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
