<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY n2614001 SYSTEM "n2614001.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY n2614001 SYSTEM "n2614001.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY n2614001 SYSTEM "n2614001.jpg" NDATA jpg>]>
<TEI.2 id="N2614001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="245">Newspaper Clipping, Harper's Weekly, [May 24, 1902]</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
<author>unknown</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management:</resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services<lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library<lb/>
University of Virginia Health System<lb/>
P.O. Box 800722<lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center<lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2614001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use. All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2003, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-05-24</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass><keywords><term></term></keywords></textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date></date>
<respStmt><resp></resp> <name></name></respStmt>
<item></item></change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper"></term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>
<name type="person">Baldwin, T.A.</name>
<name type="person">Lee, Fitzhugh</name>
<name type="place">Camp Columbia (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr></abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-05-24">May 24, 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2614001</idno>
<title>Newspaper Clipping, Harper's Weekly, [May 24, 1902]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Largest Military Post in the Island of Cuba</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="newspaper clipping" n="1902-05-24">
<head>Newspaper Clipping, Harper's Weekly, [May 24, 1902]</head>
<pb n="1" id="fn2614001"/>
<p>Photostat from<lb/>
Library of Congress</p>
<p>Vol 46 of 665<lb/>
May 24, 1902</p>
<p>HARPER'S WEEKLY<lb/>
665</p>
<p><figure entity="n2614001"></figure> A General View of Camp Columbia, Havana</p>
<p>The Largest Military Post in the Island of Cuba</p>
<p>ON May 20, 1902, when the United States<lb/>
left the island of Cuba, there was turned<lb/>
over to the Cuban government a military<lb/>
post that is larger than any in the Unit-<lb/>
ed States, and one that is so thoroughly<lb/>
and completely equipped that it stands<lb/>
pre-eminent as an example of the ability of the Amer-<lb/>
ican soldier to bring order out of chaos.</p>
<p>Many of the volunteers of 1898, who were in General<lb/>
Lee's corps, will remember the rough, desolate-look-<lb/>
ing camp of the Seventh Army Corps, near Quemados,<lb/>
Cuba. A few common wooden barracks were built in<lb/>
the early part of 1899 for the Eighth United States<lb/>
infantry, but it was not until July 27, 1899, when<lb/>
Colonel T. A. Baldwin, commanding the Seventh Unit-<lb/>
ed States Cavalry, and two squadrons of that regi-<lb/>
ment moved into Columbia Barracks, that the real<lb/>
work of building and beautifying the post began; and<lb/>
it is entirely due to the energy and ability of Colonel<lb/>
Baldwin that Columbia Barracks is to-day the beauti-<lb/>
ful post that it is. He had difficulties and obstacles<lb/>
to overcome that would have discouraged a less deter-<lb/>
mined man, but, in spite of all sorts of adverse con-<lb/>
ditions, he has raised a monument of beauty to his<lb/>
name.</p>
<p>The post is located on the hills about five miles<lb/>
from Havana, and, with the ocean on one side and the<lb/>
undulating country on the other three sides, it makes<lb/>
an ideal place for a post. The sea-breeze keeps the<lb/>
place cool, and not once during the past year has it<lb/>
been hot enough to be very uncomfortable.</p>
<p>There is a fine macadamized road from Havana to<lb/>
the post, and on entering the barracks by this road,<lb/>
one is impressed by the size and number of the build-<lb/>
ings. On the right, stretching in a long line, are the<lb/>
frame buildings, with red tile roofs, that form the<lb/>
officers' quarters for a regiment of infantry, a regi-<lb/>
ment of cavalry, and two batteries of light artillery.<lb/>
Each set of quarters is equipped with kitchens and<lb/>
bath-rooms, and connected with the main sewerage<lb/>
system that drains the entire post.</p>
<p>On the left, across the north parade-ground, are<lb/>
the general prisoners' guard-house and the quarters<lb/>
for the infantry. Next to the infantry barracks are the<lb/>
post non-commissioned staff quarters, the big dancing-<lb/>
pavilion, the adjutant's office, and the main guard-<lb/>
house and prison. In the rear of the dancing-pavilion<lb/>
are the Y. M. C. A. buildings, the bakery (which<lb/>
bakes bread for over two thousand men), the pack-<lb/>
train quarters and stables, the post barber shop, and<lb/>
the dentist's office.</p>
<p>Crossing a road that divides the post are the quar-<lb/>
ters which were used by the Seventh Cavalry, with the<lb/>
kitchens and stables, and adjoining these are the bar-<lb/>
racks of the batteries, with gun-sheds and stables in<lb/>
the rear.</p>
<p>Next comes the big south parade - ground, large</p>
<p><figure entity="n2614001"></figure> The Officers' Quarters</p>
<p>enough to drill an entire regiment of cavalry and two<lb/>
batteries of artillery on it at one time. Facing this<lb/>
are the quarters of the married non-commissioned offi-<lb/>
cers and the post laundry, where all the washing for<lb/>
both officers and men was done, in a far better manner<lb/>
than at most steam-laundries in the United States,<lb/>
and at a charge of $1 25 per month.</p>
<p>Beyond the laundry, on an isolated knoll, is the<lb/>
post hospital, which is equipped in the most thorough<lb/>
manner for isolating yellow - fever patients and for<lb/>
surgical operations. Fortunately, owing to the ex-<lb/>
cellent health of the men here, there were only a small<lb/>
number of patients and no yellow-fever cases.</p>
<p>Adjoining the hospital, on the line of the Marianao<lb/>
railroad, are the quartermaster's and commissary<lb/>
storehouses, and near them the huge quartermaster's<lb/>
corral.</p>
<p>The photographs give only a faint idea of the<lb/>
beauty of the post, but when one remembers that the<lb/>
grass is always green, the trees always in leaf, and<lb/>
the flowers always in blossom, one gets some concep-<lb/>
tion of the freshness and cleanliness of the post.</p>
<p>The barracks for the men are arranged with sides<lb/>
that swing open to give air, and are completely<lb/>
equipped with enough shower - baths to allow every<lb/>
man to bathe daily.</p>
<p>Each troop has its gymnasium equipment and troop<lb/>
library, which keep the men amused and occupied.<lb/>
There are two excellent baseball teams in the regi-<lb/>
ment, as well as a team in each troop and battery, and<lb/>
games are played three or four times a week.</p>
<p>On the north parade-ground are three band-stands,<lb/>
where the famous Seventh Cavalry Band have agree-<lb/>
ably entertained both men and visitors every Monday,<lb/>
Wednesday, and Friday night. Usually there was a<lb/>
&ldquo;hop&rdquo; on Saturday night, to which many officers and<lb/>
Cubans came from Havana.</p>
<p>The post is supplied with fine water from the Vento<lb/>
springs, where Havana gets her water-supply, and the<lb/>
sewerage system which drains the post runs to the<lb/>
ocean, three miles away.</p>
<p>At the Playa de Marianao there are excellent bath-<lb/>
ing, and bath-houses for both officers and men, with<lb/>
beach wagons making several trips daily.</p>
<p>Many people in the United States think that the<lb/>
American soldiers suffered great hardships in Cuba,<lb/>
but, while of course they all missed the American<lb/>
people and people who could speak English, still they<lb/>
were a remarkably contented and happy lot of men;<lb/>
and most of the officers and men knew and realized<lb/>
that when they left Cuba they left a post that is<lb/>
healthy, beautiful, and comfortable, and that their<lb/>
next post would have to be fine indeed to be able to<lb/>
make them as happy as they have been at Columbia<lb/>
Barracks.</p>
<p><figure entity="n2614001"></figure> Residence of the former Commanding Officer, Colonel Baldwin</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
