<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2653005">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, Md., December 23, 1902</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2653005</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1902-12-23</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation">YES</term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="person">Sternberg, George Miller</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Sanarelli, Giuseppe</name>
<name type="person">Agramonte, Aristides</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Central America</name>
<name type="place">South America</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1902-12-23">December 23, 1902</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2653005</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, Md., December 23, 1902</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>A World Benefactor</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1902-12-23">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Sun, Baltimore, Md., December 23, 1902</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2653005"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
<date value="1902-12-23">??? 23, 1902.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>A WORLD BENEFACTOR</p>
<p>-------------</p>
<p>Yet Major Reed Died Unre-<lb/>
warded By Government.</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>FOUND CAUSE OF A SCOURGE</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>It Was He Who Discovered That<lb/>
Yellow Fever Is Transmitted By<lb/>
Mosquitoes--Dr. Sternberg's Tests.</p>
<p>[Special Dispatch to the Baltimore Sun.]</p>
<p>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22. -- Dr. Charles M.<lb/>
Ellis, of Elkton, Md., in a very timely and<lb/>
appropriate communication to THE SUN re-<lb/>
cently called public attention to the serv-<lb/>
ices of Major Walter Reed, who died some<lb/>
weeks ago in Washington.</p>
<p>That favors and rewards do not always<lb/>
go to those most deserving, particularly in<lb/>
the military and naval branches of the<lb/>
Government, is conspicuously demonstrated<lb/>
in the case of the late Major Walter Reed,<lb/>
a distinguished surgeon of the army and a<lb/>
leading scientist of the day. For far less<lb/>
service to their country and humanity men<lb/>
were made major-generals and brigadiers<lb/>
during the Spanish War, and at its close,<lb/>
while Major Reed's work was unrecognized<lb/>
by the Government in any shape except in<lb/>
the perfunctory communications of con-<lb/>
gratulations which he may have received<lb/>
from his superior officers at the War De-<lb/>
partment. The fact that Major Reed proved<lb/>
through careful and painstaking investiga-<lb/>
tion yellow fever was communicated to<lb/>
persons through the bite of the mosquito<lb/>
is now generally accepted by the medical<lb/>
world, but his own Government has passed<lb/>
by his work and triumphant success with-<lb/>
out reward or public recognition. He was<lb/>
not advanced a single number, or even<lb/>
brevetted.</p>
<p>Reward On Field Of Battle.</p>
<p>An officer who rendered even some moder-<lb/>
ate service on the field of battle would un-<lb/>
questionably be rewarded in a general or-<lb/>
der published to his command, and perhaps<lb/>
later receive additional rank. While the<lb/>
medical men of the army gave valuable<lb/>
services, as a rule, during the Spanish War,<lb/>
recognition in the shape of higher rank and<lb/>
pay went to none except Leonard Wood,<lb/>
who jumped from an assistant surgeon and<lb/>
captain to the rank of major-general in less<lb/>
than two years, although at the time serv-<lb/>
ing as a volunteer of the line and not at-<lb/>
tached to the Medical Corps. Of Major<lb/>
Reed's work in the medical department<lb/>
and his scientific researches it is probable<lb/>
a complete history never can be obtained.<lb/>
His eminence as a bacteriologist and in<lb/>
practical hygiene as applied to military life<lb/>
led to his being intrusted with special in-<lb/>
vestigations, which were interrupted by<lb/>
his death and it is now believed will never<lb/>
be completed. He was regarded by his as-<lb/>
sociates as a man who combined and un-<lb/>
usual degree of scientific accuracy with<lb/>
calm judgment, which rendered him invalu-<lb/>
able in searching out the cause of epi-<lb/>
demic diseases and tracing their progress.</p>
<p>Begins Yellow-Fever Inquiry.</p>
<p>In 1900 he began the investigation of the<lb/>
cause of the prevalence of yellow fever,<lb/>
conducting the investigation at Quemados,<lb/>
near Havana, where he established head-<lb/>
quarters and was given every facility for<lb/>
carrying on his experiments. The condi-<lb/>
tions in Cuba were such as made the in-<lb/>
vestigations of Major Reed and his corps<lb/>
of assistants of special moment. An epi-<lb/>
demic of yellow fever existed despite the<lb/>
efforts of the sanitary experts. The houses<lb/>
of persons infected were subjected to rigid<lb/>
disinfection. Furniture was destroyed and<lb/>
every possible precaution was taken to<lb/>
prevent the spread of the disease under<lb/>
the old treatment. Major Reed became con-<lb/>
vinced that proper sanitation was not all<lb/>
that was needed. He believed that some<lb/>
agency other than accumulation of filth<lb/>
was responsible for the spread of the dis-<lb/>
ease and his attention was attracted to the<lb/>
fact that it took much longer for a house<lb/>
to become infected than the usual time of<lb/>
incubation. This suggested a biting insect<lb/>
as an intermediate host of the parasite,<lb/>
and he asked and promptly received from<lb/>
General Wood permission to make experi-<lb/>
ments with mosquitoes as the conveyers of<lb/>
yellow fever and a liberal supply of money<lb/>
for these experiments. By these experi-<lb/>
ments it was determined beyond question<lb/>
that through a certain species of mos-<lb/>
quito the yellow-fever germ was dissemi-<lb/>
nated.</p>
<p>Dr. Sternberg's Experiments.</p>
<p>For several years prior to the discovery<lb/>
that the mosquito conveyed the infection of<lb/>
yellow fever research and investigation had<lb/>
been made into the causes of the disease by<lb/>
Dr. George M. Sternberg, lately Surgeon-<lb/>
General of the army and a well-known<lb/>
scientist on this special branch of bac-<lb/>
teriology. General Sternberg's investiga-<lb/>
tions had been conducted for several years<lb/>
in Havana, Central and South America and<lb/>
later at the Johns Hopkins University, Bal-<lb/>
more, and in New York, and later, when he<lb/>
came to Washington, were continued by his<lb/>
chief assistant at a Brooklyn laboratory<lb/>
over which he presided. It was not until<lb/>
the summer of 1897, however, that the ques-<lb/>
tion received the consideration which final-<lb/>
ly culminated in the wonderful discoveries<lb/>
made by the board of which the late Major<lb/>
Reed was president. General Sternberg be-<lb/>
lieving the question deserving the utmost<lb/>
consideration, in view of its ravages yearly<lb/>
in tropical countries and the constant men-<lb/>
ace Cuba was to ports of the Southern<lb/>
States, designated a board of officers, con-<lb/>
sisting of Major Reed and Contract Sur-<lb/>
geon James Carroll, then stationed here at<lb/>
the Medical Museum, to begin the impor-<lb/>
tant work of investigating the germ ques-<lb/>
tion as relating to yellow fever.</p>
<p>Sanarelli's Bacillus.</p>
<p>About that time the famous Italian yel-<lb/>
low fever expert, Sanarelli, who had been<lb/>
conducting investigation in the yellow fever<lb/>
districts of South America, reported that<lb/>
he had discovered the bacillus which he<lb/>
believed was the cause of yellow fever and<lb/>
which he had named &ldquo;bacillus icteroides.&rdquo;<lb/>
Naturally so important an announcement<lb/>
to the medical world caused considerable<lb/>
interest and among some members of the<lb/>
medical profession it was believed the real<lb/>
cause of yellow fever had been definitely<lb/>
traced. General Sternberg, whose atten-<lb/>
tion was drawn to the statement, had cul-<lb/>
tures preserved of the only organism iso-<lb/>
lated by him to which any special signifi-<lb/>
cance might be attached. That year he was<lb/>
appointed a delegate to the meeting of medi-<lb/>
cal men held at St. Petersburg, where the<lb/>
subject of yellow fever received considera-<lb/>
tion among numerous others discussed. Re-<lb/>
turning by way of Paris, General Stern-<lb/>
berg secured a culture of Sanarelli's bacil-<lb/>
<unclear>lus</unclear> from Professor Roux, which he brought<lb/>
home and sent to the Army Medical Mu-<lb/>
seum for examination.</p>
<p>Major Reed and Dr. Carroll were desig-<lb/>
nated to study it in conjunction with a<lb/>
<unclear>bacillus</unclear> which General Sternberg had pre-<lb/>
viously had sent on from Brooklyn for<lb/>
study which he named bacillus &ldquo;X.&rdquo; Major<lb/>
Reed and Dr. Carroll were indefatigable in<lb/>
their examinations, but finally concluded<lb/>
after study of the organisms that each be-<lb/>
longed to a well-known group of bacteria--<lb/>
bacillus &ldquo;X&rdquo; to the Colon group and bacil-<lb/>
lus icteroides to the hog-cholera group.</p>
<p>Attention Given To Cuba.</p>
<p>This part of the work was not completed<lb/>
until the spring of 1900. That summer yel-<lb/>
low fever was as prevalent at Havana and<lb/>
other Cuban ports, where it made its ap-<lb/>
pearance with regularity every year. The<lb/>
disease was a subject of serious thought to<lb/>
the army medical men, because of the large<lb/>
number of troops then stationed in the is-<lb/>
land and the probability that they would<lb/>
be continued there for a number of years.<lb/>
In fact, yellow fever was then looked upon<lb/>
as one of the most serious problems with<lb/>
which the army had to deal, and it was<lb/>
therefore incumbent upon the Medical Corps<lb/>
to cope with it to the best of its ability. It<lb/>
had been a serious menace to the troops<lb/>
from the time they first set foot on Cuban<lb/>
soil, and unless it could be checked or<lb/>
stamped out entirely would always be a se-<lb/>
rious problem for the soldiers to face. Gen-<lb/>
eral Sternberg then decided upon the ap-<lb/>
pointment of a board for the study of yel-<lb/>
low fever and other tropical diseases <unclear>and</unclear><lb/>
selected for the president Major Reed,<lb/>
whose work in that field probably rendered<lb/>
him one of the best-qualified officers of the<lb/>
service to conduct the investigation.</p>
<p>Sanarelli's Bacillus Absent.</p>
<p>Major Reed had associated with him Con-<lb/>
tract Surgeons Carroll, Agramonte and La-<lb/>
zear, the latter, a Baltimorean, sacrificing<lb/>
his life in the interest of science. This<lb/>
board studied the question for several<lb/>
months and finally failed to find Sanarelli's<lb/>
bacillus in any of the cases studied and,<lb/>
abandoning that line of research, they took<lb/>
up the subject of the mode of conveyance<lb/>
of the disease. The prevailing idea had<lb/>
been for years that yellow fever was con-<lb/>
tagious and could be transmitted by con-<lb/>
tact with a patient or through causes other<lb/>
than inoculation. One of the first things de-<lb/>
termined upon by the board was to prove<lb/>
or disprove Sanarelli's claim for his bacil-<lb/>
lus, which had been supported by others.</p>
<p>Failing to find Sanarelli's germ in a sin-<lb/>
gle case, it became necessary to pursue<lb/>
some other line of investigation, and the<lb/>
mosquito theory advocated by Dr. Findlay<lb/>
was next taken up. This was a most diffi-<lb/>
cult matter, and it was not believed that<lb/>
there would be many persons volunteering<lb/>
to submit to this dangerous and perhaps<lb/>
fatal test in the interest of medical science.</p>
<p>Surgeons Volunteer.</p>
<p>Dr. Carroll and Dr. Lazear volunteer to<lb/>
submit themselves to the bite of a contam-<lb/>
inated mosquito, and one week after be-<lb/>
ing bitten Dr. Carroll was down with the<lb/>
disease in a most severe form, from which<lb/>
he recovered, however, early in September.<lb/>
Dr. Lazear was taken ill of the disease on<lb/>
September 18 of that year and died just<lb/>
one week later. Another individual bitten<lb/>
by the mosquito which had been applied<lb/>
to Dr. Carroll suffered from a mild attack<lb/>
of the disease and recovered. Major Reed<lb/>
was then satisfied that the board had made<lb/>
a most important discovery, and immedi-<lb/>
ately the War Department and the medical<lb/>
world were notified. Further experiments<lb/>
were made several months later, all of<lb/>
which went to prove the conclusions reached<lb/>
by Major Reed that yellow fever was com-<lb/>
municated by the mosquito bite and that<lb/>
contact by a well person with one suffering<lb/>
from the disease would not transmit the<lb/>
disease. As a result of the discoveries made<lb/>
by the Reed board it has been conclusively<lb/>
proved, and is so accepted by the medical<lb/>
men, that yellow fever is transmitted to<lb/>
non-immune individuals by the bite of the<lb/>
mosquito that has previously fed on the<lb/>
blood of those ill with the disease.</p>
<p>Period Of Contamination.</p>
<p>It was proved also that an interval of<lb/>
about 12 days or more after contamination<lb/>
appears to be necessary before the mos-<lb/>
quito is capable of conveying the infection,<lb/>
and that the bite at an earlier period did<lb/>
not appear to confer any immunity against<lb/>
a subsequent attack. The spread of yellow<lb/>
fever. It was concluded, can be most effect-<lb/>
ually controlled by measures directed to<lb/>
the destruction of mosquitoes and the pro-<lb/>
tection of the sick against the bites of these<lb/>
insects. While the mode of propagation of<lb/>
yellow fever was definitely determined by<lb/>
Major Reed the specific cause of the dis-<lb/>
ease remains yet to be discovered.</p>
<p>Appreciating fully the importance of the<lb/>
discovery<unclear>.</unclear> Major Reed decided in order to<lb/>
exclude all other possible sources of in-<lb/>
fection in future observations to establish<lb/>
a special experimental station, where fur-<lb/>
ther observation could be made of non-im-<lb/>
mune human beings, both as to the propa-<lb/>
gation of yellow fever by means of the bite<lb/>
of the insect and by exposure to the most<lb/>
intimate contact with infected clothing and<lb/>
bedding, and this under the strictest en-<lb/>
forcement of military quarantine.</p>
<p>Not Spread By Bed Clothing.</p>
<p>The station consisted of quite a large<lb/>
house. An acting assistant surgeon and two<lb/>
privates of the hospital corps entered the<lb/>
building and exposed themselves in every<lb/>
possible way to the contaminated linen and<lb/>
bed clothing. The sheets and pillow cases<lb/>
were used in preparing the beds in which<lb/>
members of the hospital corps slept; va-<lb/>
rious articles were hung around the room<lb/>
and placed about the bed occupied by the<lb/>
young surgeon. For 20 days this room was<lb/>
occupied by the non-immunes, and after<lb/>
being held in quarantine five days they<lb/>
were liberated in perfect health. They had<lb/>
in fact improved physically by their ex-<lb/>
perience. Such experiments were continued<lb/>
for several weeks, under direction of Major<lb/>
Reed, and when finally the board withdrew<lb/>
from the island the world knew positively<lb/>
that an important discovery had been made<lb/>
in medical science and that it was con-<lb/>
clusively proved that the mosquito con-<lb/>
veyed the yellow-fever germ.</p>
<p>Major Reed's Career.</p>
<p>This distinguished officer, Major Reed,<lb/>
was a Virginian, having been born, as stated<lb/>
in THE SUN at the time of his death, in<lb/>
Gloucester county, September 13, 1851, and<lb/>
graduated from the medical department of<lb/>
the University of Virginia in 1869, and<lb/>
Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New<lb/>
York city, in 1872. He was appointed an<lb/>
assistant surgeon June 26, 1875, and pro-<lb/>
moted through the various grades until he<lb/>
reached the rank of major, which he held<lb/>
at the time of his death. The honors con-<lb/>
ferred upon him by universities were many<lb/>
and included the degree of bachelor of arts<lb/>
by Harvard last June, at the time degrees<lb/>
were conferred upon President Roosevelt<lb/>
and Secretary Hay. About the same time<lb/>
the degree of master of arts was conferred<lb/>
upon Major Reed by the University of<lb/>
Michigan at Ann Arbor. During his army<lb/>
<unclear>career he</unclear> served at Willets Point, N. Y.:<lb/>
Harrisonburg, Va.: on general recruiting<lb/>
duty in the far West and at Fort McHenry,<lb/>
Md., during the year 1881.</p>
<p>--------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
