<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2709001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Richmond Times Dispatch, December 13, 1903</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2709001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1903-12-13</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Abbot, William R.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Carter, Henry Rose</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Gloucester (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1903-12-13">December 13, 1903</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2709001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Richmond Times Dispatch, December 13, 1903</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Tablet Unveiling</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1903-12-13">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Richmond Times Dispatch, December 13, 1903</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2709001"/>
<p>FROM DR. HOWARD A. KELLY</p>
<p>Please return to <unclear>Mr.</unclear><lb/>
E. <unclear>L. Reed.</unclear></p>
<p>THE TIMES-DISPATCH: RICHMOND, VA., <unclear>SUNDAY</unclear></p>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>TABLET<lb/>
UNVEILING</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>Memorials Erected in Gloucester<lb/>
Courthouse to Distinguished<lb/>
Sons of That County.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>WAS AN INSPIRING OCCASION</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>A Large Assembly Hear Inter-<lb/>
esting Addresses in Present-<lb/>
ing and Receiving Memorials.</p>
<p>----------</p>
<p>(Special to The Times-Dispatch.)</p>
<p>GLOUCESTER C. H., VA., Dec. 12.--<lb/>
The Gloucester Courthouse building was<lb/>
filled to repletion on Thursday by a rep-<lb/>
resentative audience, who assembled to<lb/>
do honor to the unveiling of tablets and<lb/>
portraits of distinguished Gloucester men.<lb/>
The walls of the old building are adorned<lb/>
with many such memorials, but none<lb/>
will be held with more reverence than<lb/>
those unveiled to-day.</p>
<p>Judge T. R. B. Wright, to whose genius<lb/>
the people of his circuit owe the thought<lb/>
of placing such memorials on their court-<lb/>
house walls, presided over the occasion<lb/>
with his usual genial charm of manner.<lb/>
In all there were about nineteen speak-<lb/>
ers, and though the ceremonies were<lb/>
continued without intermission from 11:30<lb/>
A. M. to 4:30 P. M., there was no sign of<lb/>
weariness in the audience; in fact, there<lb/>
was small cause for boredom, for each<lb/>
speech was a gem, some of purest ray,<lb/>
and brief and to the point.</p>
<p>OPENING EXERCISES.</p>
<p>The meeting opened with prayer by the<lb/>
&ldquo;Fighting Parson.&rdquo; honored of all men<lb/>
in Gloucester, the Rev. W. E. Royall,<lb/>
and the singing of &ldquo;America&rdquo; in fine<lb/>
style.</p>
<p>The first tablet to be unveiled was one<lb/>
in memory of Judge J. M. Gregory, judge<lb/>
of this circuit from 1860 to 1865. This<lb/>
tablet was erected by the court through<lb/>
the generosity of Mesdame and Mr.<lb/>
Gregory <unclear>Galbraith</unclear>, of <unclear>Spartanburg</unclear>, S. C.,<lb/>
the daughter and his grandson, Mes-<lb/>
dame A. Caskie Thomas, of New York,<lb/>
and was received by Hon. D. Gardiner<lb/>
Tyler in a speech replete with interesting<lb/>
matter. The Hon. John Lamb, of Rich-<lb/>
mond, received the same in a fine man-<lb/>
ner, which will insure him a welcome<lb/>
always as a speaker in Gloucester. Mas-<lb/>
ter John Gregory Warburton, of Wil-<lb/>
liamsburg, unveiled the tablet.</p>
<p>THE PAGE TABLET.</p>
<p>The second tablet was unveiled by Mas-<lb/>
ter Mann Page, of &ldquo;Shelly,&rdquo; and was<lb/>
the gift of Thomas Nelson Page, in mem-<lb/>
ory of the many distinguished men of his<lb/>
name who were born in Gloucester. This<lb/>
tablet was presented by Mr. Maryus<lb/>
Jones in his usual happy vein, and was<lb/>
received by Mr. Joseph Bryan, who, as<lb/>
be rose to speak, was met with an open-<lb/>
hearted welcome by the many friends<lb/>
of his youth, who are proud to claim him<lb/>
as a Gloucester man. Mr. Bryan's speech<lb/>
was one of the gems of the day.</p>
<p>MORDECAI COOK.</p>
<p>The third tablet was in memory of<lb/>
Mordecai Cook, of Murderers' Mount,<lb/>
Gloucester, and of other well known men<lb/>
of that name, and was the gift of Mr.<lb/>
Merritt Todd Cooke, of Norfolk, and<lb/>
was presented very gracefully by Colonel<lb/>
John <unclear>R.</unclear> Saunders and unveiled by Miss<lb/>
<unclear>Agnes Shackleford.</unclear></p>
<p>The next unveiling, Dr. Walter Reed.<lb/>
M. A., LL. D., major and surgeon in the<lb/>
army of the United States, who demon-<lb/>
strated in Cuba the transmission of yel-<lb/>
low fever by mosquitoes, was especially<lb/>
interesting. Mrs. Walter Reed, widow,<lb/>
and Mesdames Blincoe and Elam, sisters,<lb/>
and Rev. J. C. Reed, presiding elder of<lb/>
Lynchburg District, brother of Dr. Reed,<lb/>
were present. Major James Carroll, of<lb/>
the United States army, unveiled <unclear>the</unclear> tab<lb/>
let, which was erected by the <unclear>court</unclear> of<lb/>
Gloucester and a few friends. Major<lb/>
Jefferson Randolph Keen, of the <unclear>United</unclear><lb/>
States army, whose speech is given below<lb/>
in full, presented the tablet, which was<lb/>
received by Dr. W. B. Robinson, of Tap-<lb/>
pahannock, in a speech so chaste <unclear>and</unclear> so<lb/>
beautiful it remains in the memory <unclear>like</unclear><lb/>
music. An exceedingly <unclear>interestng</unclear><lb/>
feature of this occasion was <unclear>the</unclear><lb/>
presence of Major James Carroll, who<lb/>
was the first experimental case in the<lb/>
mosquito test, and a warm friend of<lb/>
Dr. Reed's. Dr. Reed was born in<lb/>
Gloucester in <unclear>1831</unclear>.</p>
<p>PORTRAIT UNVEILING.</p>
<p>The fine portrait to be unveiled was in<lb/>
memory of Catesby Jones, of the Confed-<lb/>
erate army, who was a type of all that<lb/>
is best of Southern chivalry, and whose<lb/>
short, brilliant life closed early in the<lb/>
war. The portrait was unveiled by Miss<lb/>
Maria Jones, and presented by Mr. Wal-<lb/>
lace Williams most appropriately.</p>
<p>Then was unveiled the portrait of one<lb/>
of Gloucester's truest and purest men,<lb/>
Mr. William Ash Jones, a lawyer of abil-<lb/>
ity. It was unveiled by his warm friend,<lb/>
Mr. T. G. Jones, of Middlesex, in a man-<lb/>
ner worthy of occasion and the man.</p>
<p>Judge J. L. Taliaferro, Commonwealth's<lb/>
attorney, received the whole collection<lb/>
in the name of the county in a very<lb/>
graceful speech, and was followed by Mr.<lb/>
Thomas Dowing, of Lancaster, who<lb/>
made an eloquent tribute in which he said<lb/>
the tablets which adorned the wall were<lb/>
but types of the sort of men Gloucester<lb/>
in part and Virginia in whole <unclear>had</unclear> and<lb/>
could produce. Major G. N. Stubbs, who<lb/>
also was appointed to receive the col-<lb/>
lection as a whole, now arose and gave<lb/>
the surprise of the day.</p>
<p>JUDGE WRIGHT'S PORTRAIT.</p>
<p>He asked Judge Wright to allow Rev.<lb/>
W. E. <unclear>Wiatt</unclear> to take the chair, and then<lb/>
presented to the crowd a most excellent<lb/>
portrait of his honor<unclear>,</unclear> Judge Wright. It<lb/>
was received with a very whoop of ap-<lb/>
plause, which testified to the love and ad-<lb/>
miration of the people of Gloucester to<lb/>
the retiring judge, who is now holding<lb/>
the last term of the Ninth Judicial Cir-<lb/>
cuit of Virginia. The portrait was un-<lb/>
veiled by the pretty little granddaughter<lb/>
of Mr. Stubbs. Surely the <unclear>burning words</unclear><lb/>
of Mr. Stubbs must have gratified the<lb/>
recipient of the compliment. Colonel J.<lb/>
R. Saunders, of Saluda, presented this<lb/>
portrait in a most delicate, touching<lb/>
manner, and in the same way it was<lb/>
received by Mr. Herbert Lewis, of West<lb/>
Point, who convulsed the audience by<lb/>
saying: &ldquo;If I had been born in Gloucester<lb/>
I would have been a great man.&rdquo; Pos-<lb/>
sibly he may yet attain. His speech cer-<lb/>
tainly gave such promise.</p>
<p>AN ABSENTEE.</p>
<p>A letter read by the judge from Thomas<lb/>
Nelson Page told of his profound regret<lb/>
at not being able to be present, an im-<lb/>
portant engagement at Yale alone pre-<lb/>
vented his appearing. Mrs. Galbraith<lb/>
received a telegram when she reached<lb/>
Baltimore, which recalled her to Spar-<lb/>
tanburg. Lines from Miss Molly Elliot<lb/>
Seawell, Mr. Cook, Major T. S. Talia-<lb/>
ferro, and Judge Wellford expressed re-<lb/>
gret at not being able to attend the ex-<lb/>
ercises. Among the visitors present from<lb/>
a distance were Mesdames Caskie Thom-<lb/>
as, of New oYrk; Walter Reed Blimroe,<lb/>
and Elam, Rev. J. C. Reed, the Messrs.<lb/>
Gardner Tyler, John Lamb, Maryus<lb/>
Jones, Joseph Bryan, Johnathan Bryan,<lb/>
John R. Saunders, Messrs. James Car-<lb/>
roll and J. R. Reed, of United States<lb/>
army; W. B. Robinson, T. G. Jones and<lb/>
John Waidurim, and three ladies and<lb/>
gentlemen were the guests at dinner of<lb/>
Mesdames Charles E. Gary and Mrs.<lb/>
W. E. Corr. The day was an inspiring<lb/>
one, and to Judge Wright, who all part<lb/>
with, with sincere sorrow. To his able<lb/>
assistant, Hon. J. N. Stone, is due the<lb/>
success of the occasion.</p>
<p>MAJOR KEAN'S ADDRESS.</p>
<p>One of the most interesting features of<lb/>
the day was the unveiling of the <unclear>tablet</unclear><lb/>
to Major Walter Reed surgeon United<lb/>
States army, by the County Court. The<lb/>
presentation speech, which was made by<lb/>
Major Jefferson Randolph Kean, was as<lb/>
follows:</p>
<p>"I am here by order of the Honorable<lb/>
Court of Gloucester--not to make a speech,<lb/>
for I am the only Virginian in the whole<lb/>
circle of my acquaintances who has not<lb/>
that accomplishment--but to lay my tri-<lb/>
bute of a laurel leaf on this memorial<lb/>
which you have <unclear>raised at this, his<lb/>
words</unclear> about the<lb/>
great and lovable qualities of Walter<lb/>
Reed and the magnitude of the work<lb/>
which he accomplished. In my story I<lb/>
hope you will pardon some personal allu-<lb/>
sions and reminiscences--for though I did<lb/>
not have the honor to be a member of the<lb/>
Yellow Fever Commission, I was its confi-<lb/>
dent and later its business manager and<lb/>
distributing agent. His parents were<lb/>
Lemuel Sutton Reed, who at the time of<lb/>
Walter's birth was the presiding elder of<lb/>
the Methodist Church of this circuit, and<lb/>
Pharaba White, his wife. Their home<lb/>
was at a little place, scarcely a village,<lb/>
called <unclear>Belle</unclear> Roy, about six miles from<lb/>
this courthouse, and there, Walter, the<lb/>
youngest of five children, saw the light<lb/>
on the 13th of September, 1851. I often<lb/>
wonder if Dr. William Waller, the good<lb/>
physician who presided on that momen-<lb/>
tous occasion, was blest with any pre-<lb/>
monition of the fact that the helpless<lb/>
babe which he held in his hands while it<lb/>
drew its first wailing breaths, was<lb/>
destined to solve that riddle of the<lb/>
Sphynx among diseases, and put an end<lb/>
to the tribute of human lives which for<lb/>
ages had been continually exacted for the<lb/>
failure to guess the secret</p>
<p>DR. REED'S CHILDHOOD.</p>
<p>The infancy and childhood of the little<lb/>
Walter passed without events worthy of<lb/>
note in other than a mother's chronicle<unclear>;</unclear><lb/>
unless it may interest a Gloucester au-<lb/>
dience to know that he early developed a<lb/>
taste for the good things for which the<lb/>
county is famous and attempted his first<lb/>
oyster at the age of one month. Fortu-<lb/>
nately, Dr. Waller was near at hand.<lb/>
His school of education was received at<lb/>
Charlottesville from Mr. William R. Ab-<lb/>
bot, who is still at the head of one of<lb/>
the best of our Virginia high schools, at<lb/>
whose feet I too sat in my youthful<lb/>
days<unclear>,</unclear> and to whose scholarly zeal and<lb/>
patience I am indebted for the small<lb/>
Latin and less Greek that still lingers in<lb/>
my memory along with many pleasant re-<lb/>
collections of boyish days.</p>
<p>It enables us to appreciate alike the re-<lb/>
markable preciousness of the youth and<lb/>
the limited field of medical knowledge<lb/>
thirty-five years ago as compared with<lb/>
our four and five years' course of to-<lb/>
day to learn that he graduated in medi-<lb/>
cine at the University of Virginia before<lb/>
the age of eighteen<unclear>,</unclear> and after one year's<lb/>
study. Fortunately so forced a curiculum<lb/>
was supplemented by several years' of<lb/>
careful study in the schools and hospitals<lb/>
of New York. In 1875 he entered the medi-<lb/>
cal corps of the army. He took this step,<lb/>
I suspect, not so much from a love of<lb/>
camps and adventures or a desire<unclear>.</unclear></p>
<p>To follow over sea and land.</p>
<p>Through cities and through solitudes.</p>
<p>The phantom with the beckoning hand<unclear>.</unclear></p>
<p>Which still allures and still eludes,<lb/>
as from a gentler and tenderer motive--<lb/>
the maiden passion for a maid. For this<lb/>
position gave him an assured income,<lb/>
and his marriage to the gentle lady who<lb/>
is here with us to-day soon followed.<lb/>
I have seen letters written by him at this<lb/>
period of his life, which strike a note<lb/>
unusual in a young man of twenty-four.<lb/>
There is nothing of the pleasant vanities<lb/>
and follies of lusty youth, or even of that<lb/>
last infirmity of noble minds, desire for<lb/>
fame, but only the scholar's love for his<lb/>
books and a great wish to benefit man-<lb/>
kind. This spirit of pure altruism greatly<lb/>
impressed me twenty-five years later on<lb/>
an occasion which I shall always remem-<lb/>
ber and shall mention further on.</p>
<p>The twenty-three years of his life as an<lb/>
army surgeon prior to the Spanish war<lb/>
contained the usual full measure of fron-<lb/>
tier service with its vicissitudes and jour-<lb/>
neys and varied trials and experiences<lb/>
which came to the lot of the army offi-<lb/>
cer of that time. I will only note the<lb/>
happy chance which in 1890 brought him<lb/>
for a year to Baltimore where he was<lb/>
enabled to study in the laboratory of the<lb/>
foremost pathologist in America, and not<lb/>
only to ground himself in the then rapid-<lb/>
ly developing science of bacteriology, but<lb/>
to win the esteem and affection of his<lb/>
praeceptor, the illustrous and genial Dr.<lb/>
Welch, of Johns Hopkins University. A<lb/>
year later he was ordered to Washington<lb/>
to establish the modest teaching labora-<lb/>
tory of the then recently established army<lb/>
medical school. His work in this labora-<lb/>
tory covered a wide field of research and<lb/>
was of much scientific value, but it can-<lb/>
not be touched on to-day except perhaps<lb/>
to mention the great and laborious in-<lb/>
vestigation of the camp epidemic of<lb/>
typhoid fever during the Spanish war by<lb/>
the board of which he was president.<lb/>
Congress last year appropriated $25,000 for<lb/>
the publication of the voluminous report<lb/>
of this board, a work upon which the<lb/>
only surviving member, Dr. Victor C.<lb/>
Vaughan, of Ann Harbor University, is<lb/>
now engaged.</p>
<p>DR. REED IN CUBA.</p>
<p>In June of 1900 Dr. Reed came to Cuba<lb/>
at the head of a commission for the<lb/>
study of yellow fever; to attack in its<lb/>
favorite stronghold that mysterious and<lb/>
deadly disease which, since the days of<lb/>
Columbus, had scourged the western<lb/>
shores of the Atlantic from Philadelphia<lb/>
to the Amazon. No one who has not read<lb/>
the long catalogue of its devastations<lb/>
spread through the 1,500 pages of La<lb/>
Roche's monumental work can appreciate<lb/>
how many thousand of lives, what oceans<lb/>
of tears, what millions of money this<lb/>
plague has cost humanity. It was at<lb/>
that time prevalent, as usual<unclear>,</unclear> in Havana<lb/>
and in the neighboring town of Quema-<lb/>
dos, where our <unclear>gallant</unclear> Virginia general,<lb/>
Fitzhugh Lee, had the headquarters of<lb/>
his military department<unclear>,</unclear> and I, who hap-<lb/>
pened to be chief surgeon on his staff,<lb/>
was lying sick of it. So I think that, in<lb/>
the visit which Reed promptly paid me,<lb/>
he saw his first case of the disease with<lb/>
which his fame will always be asso-<lb/>
ciated.</p>
<p>As he often remarked<unclear>,</unclear> the progress of<lb/>
modern medicine had stopped at this<lb/>
singular disease, and no single fact was<lb/>
known to us which was not to be found<lb/>
in the pages of La Roche fifty years ago.<lb/>
Of course, the theories of its causation<lb/>
and manner of spread were infinite in<lb/>
number, and more than one observer<lb/>
had claimed that the bite of the mosquito<lb/>
was instrumental in its propagation. Dr.<lb/>
Carlos Finlay, of Havana, the most<lb/>
prominent advocate of this theory, had<lb/>
even correctly fixed upon the special<lb/>
variety of mosquito. But scientific medi-<lb/>
cine takes no note of improved theories,<lb/>
and justly gives the palm of discovery<lb/>
to the demonstrator of scientific facts<lb/>
and not to the proclaimer of theories. I<lb/>
cannot go into the causes which led Dr.<lb/>
Reed's investigations into this path, ex-<lb/>
cept to say that Dr. Finlay's publications<lb/>
did not influence him, but more than any-<lb/>
thing else the observations of another<lb/>
Virginia doctor<unclear>,</unclear> Henry R. Carter, turned<lb/>
his mind in this direction. It was evi-<lb/>
dent that as man was the only creature<lb/>
known to be susceptible to yellow fever,<lb/>
experiments would have to be made on<lb/>
human beings, and the board determined<lb/>
to make the first trial on the persons of<lb/>
its own members.</p>
<p>SACRIFICE TO SCIENCE.</p>
<p>Dr. James Carroll, of the army, who<lb/>
is here to-day, was the first experimental<lb/>
case, and suffered a very severe attack,<lb/>
which carried him into the very shadow<lb/>
of the gates of death. I am glad to be<lb/>
able to bear witness to an act of self-<lb/>
devotion as gallant as the leading of a<lb/>
<unclear>forlorn</unclear> hope, and far more productive of<lb/>
good to others, I regret to add that it has<lb/>
not, however, been productive of any pro-<lb/>
motion or reward for him. The third Amer-<lb/>
ican member of the commission, the<lb/>
young and gifted Lazear, died, nobly<lb/>
sacrificing to this work a life full of<lb/>
promise of scientific achievement. The<lb/>
great secret was now discovered, but<lb/>
more experiments were necessary to clear<lb/>
up doubtful points, and accumulate a<lb/>
mass of evidence which would bring con-<lb/>
viction to every scientific mind. It was,<lb/>
therefore, necessary to seek the assis-<lb/>
tance of the military governor, whose<lb/>
word was law in Cuba, and without<lb/>
whose approval and financial assistance<lb/>
experimentation on the scale desired<lb/>
could not be conducted. Fortunately for<lb/>
Cuba and for science, that military gov-<lb/>
ernor was General Leonard Wood. It<lb/>
was my privilege to stand with these<lb/>
two in a window recess of the old palace<lb/>
in Havana, overlooking the Plaza del Ar-<lb/>
mas and the little chapel marking the<lb/>
spot where Columbus had landed, while<lb/>
Reed, with that lucidity and convincing<lb/>
eloquence which he had always at his<lb/>
command, told his story and made his<lb/>
request. &ldquo;You shall have ten thousand<lb/>
dollars, and more, if that is not enough,&rdquo;<lb/>
was General Wood's prompt reply. If<lb/>
all the accusations which jealousy and<lb/>
thwarted greed are now hurling at his<lb/>
back were as true as I know that they<lb/>
are false, that quick and intuitive recog-<lb/>
nition that this was no dreamer's tale,<lb/>
and his ready assistance to this great<lb/>
work would go far to balance the ac-<lb/>
count.</p>
<p>NOT OF SELF.</p>
<p>Half an hour later, when Reed and<lb/>
I sat at lunch in a quiet corner of the<lb/>
Cafe Paris and I drank his health in<lb/>
the red wine of old Spain and held forth<lb/>
on the grandeur of the achievement and<lb/>
the honor and fame that would be his,<lb/>
he turned to me with an air of sincerity<lb/>
and candor which forbade a suspicion of<lb/>
cant or affectation, and said: &ldquo;Keen, I<lb/>
swear to you that I do not give a rap for<lb/>
what this discovery will bring to me, but<lb/>
I am very thankful that it has been mine<lb/>
to confer so great a blessing on human-<lb/>
ity.&rdquo; The man spoke from his heart, and<lb/>
this lofty altruism was much a part of<lb/>
him, as was his fearlessness, his earn-<lb/>
estness, and the merry and playful hu-<lb/>
mor which bubbled through his daily con-<lb/>
versation.</p>
<p>Of the now famous experiments at<lb/>
Camp Lazear, which General Wood's<lb/>
help made possible; of how our brave<lb/>
hospital corps men volunteered to sleep<lb/>
for weeks in bedding in which the victims<lb/>
of yellow fever had died in order to prove<lb/>
that the infection is not carried by cloth-<lb/>
ing; of how they fearlessly bared their<lb/>
arms for the bite of the infected mosquito<lb/>
which alone could carry the infection--all<lb/>
this makes a thrilling story; but if you<lb/>
wish to hear it you must get it from Dr.<lb/>
Carroll.</p>
<p>Our visit to General Wood happened on<lb/>
the 12th of October, 1900, my note-book<lb/>
tells me. In a year from that time yel-<lb/>
low fever had been driven from Cuba,<lb/>
never again<unclear>,</unclear> we hope<unclear>,</unclear> to return. Two<lb/>
years later the Secretary of War was<lb/>
writing in his report to Congress with<lb/>
reference to Reed's work as follows:</p>
<p>&ldquo;The brilliant character of this scien-<lb/>
tific achievement, its inestimable value<lb/>
to mankind, the saving of thousands of<lb/>
lives<unclear>,</unclear> and the deliverance of the Atlantic<lb/>
seacoast from constant apprehension, de-<lb/>
mand special recognition from the gov-<lb/>
ernment of the United States. I ask<lb/>
that the President appoint him Assistant<lb/>
Surgeon-General, with the rank of col-<lb/>
onel.&rdquo; But before this report had left<lb/>
the hands of the printer or Walter Reed<lb/>
had seen these words, his eyes were<lb/>
closed in death, and that pure and lofty<lb/>
spirit had gone to receive a higher and<lb/>
more lasting reward.</p>
<p>------------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
