<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2735001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, September, 7, 1904</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2735001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1904-09-07</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Biography">YES</term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Osler, William</name>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="place">Towson (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">College of Physician and Surgeons, New York</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Maryland</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1904-09-07">September 7, 1904</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2735001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, September, 7, 1904</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Maryland in Medicine</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1904-09-07">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, September 7, 1904</head>
<pb n="1" id="N2735001"/>
<opener>
AC<lb/>
L<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1904-09-07">EMBER 7, 1904.</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>__________________________________________________</p>
<p>MARYLAND IN MEDICINE</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>Address Of Dr. V. M. Reichard At<lb/>
Blue Mountain House.</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>CUMBERLAND VALLEYDOCTORS</p>
<p>---------</p>
<p>They Meet And Have A Banquet--<lb/>
Dr. Reichard Tells Of Achieve-<lb/>
ments Of His Profession In State.</p>
<p>[Special Dispatch to the Baltimore Sun.]</p>
<p>Blue Mountain, Md., Sept. 6.--The sec-<lb/>
ond annual meeting of the Cumberland Val-<lb/>
ley Medical Association was held at the<lb/>
Blue Mountain House today. Many physi-<lb/>
cians from Maryland and Southern Pennsyl-<lb/>
vania were present. A business session pre-<lb/>
sided over by Dr. R. W. Ramsey, of Cham-<lb/>
bersburg, was held this morning.</p>
<p>The following officers were elected: Presi-<lb/>
dent, Dr. V. M. Reichard, Fairplay, Md.:<lb/>
vice-presidents<unclear>,</unclear> Dr. J. W. Humrichouse<unclear>,</unclear><lb/>
Hagerstown; Dr. T. H. Weagley, Marion,<lb/>
Pa.; Dr. A. R. Allen, Carlisle, Pa.; secre-<lb/>
tary, Dr. J. J. Kaufman, Scotland, Pa.; as-<lb/>
sistant secretaries, Dr. J. H. McCreary,<lb/>
Shippensburg, Pa.; Dr. D. B. Montgomery,<lb/>
Chambersburg, Pa.; Dr. D. C. R. Miller,<lb/>
State Line, Pa.; treasurer, Dr. J. J. Koser,<lb/>
Shippensburg, Pa.</p>
<p>Dr. D. C. R. Miller, State Line, read a<lb/>
paper on &ldquo;Pulmonary Hemorrhages.&rdquo; Dr.<lb/>
Guy <unclear>L.</unclear> Hunner, of Baltimore, a guest, read<lb/>
a paper on &ldquo;A Disease <unclear>Peculiar</unclear> to Women.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Dr. A. R. Allen, of Carlisle, read a paper<lb/>
on &ldquo;The Importance of Early Operation in<lb/>
Intestinal Obstructions.&rdquo;</p>
<p>A banquet was held tonight. Dr. James<lb/>
E. Pilcher, of Carlisle, was toastmaster.<lb/>
Dr. Thomas B. Johnson, of Frederick, was<lb/>
a guest. The society decided to meet next<lb/>
year in September at Mount Holly Springs,<lb/>
Cumberland county, Pa.</p>
<p>The principal address was made at the<lb/>
banquet by Dr. V. M. Reichard, of Fair-<lb/>
play, one of the leading physicians of Wash-<lb/>
ington county. Dr. Reichard said in part:</p>
<p>"Every citizen of Maryland has a just<lb/>
pride in her renown. To every department<lb/>
she has contributed her proportion of men<lb/>
and deeds, and in some she stands peerless.<lb/>
And when we turn to medicine we find her<lb/>
abreast with the very first and taking a<lb/>
position of enviable brilliancy. During the<lb/>
Colonial and Revolutionary periods her<lb/>
medical men stood for what was highest<lb/>
and best in their profession. Charles Fred-<lb/>
erick Wiesenthal, of Baltimore Town,<lb/>
though born in Prussia, entered with all<lb/>
the zeal of ardent patriotism into the de-<lb/>
fense of his adopted country. Surgeon to<lb/>
Smallwood's Marylanders, he became Sur-<lb/>
geon-General of the State and surgeon-in-<lb/>
charge of the military hospitals at Balti-<lb/>
more. In 1785 and 1786 he, assisted by Dr.<lb/>
<unclear>Ellsha</unclear> John Hall, of Frederick county, led<lb/>
a crusade to uplift the profession. They<lb/>
proposed a paid board of examiners. The<lb/>
first attempt to organize the State was<lb/>
made in December, 1788, when a meeting<lb/>
was held and Dr. Wiesenthal was elected<lb/>
president.</p>
<p>Medical And Chirurgical Society.</p>
<p>"The Medical Society was short lived and<lb/>
fell to pieces in 1790. But the work had<lb/>
begun, seed had been sown, and the leaven<lb/>
was at work. In due time the proper re-<lb/>
sult was manifest and in 1799 the State<lb/>
Medical Society was organized under the<lb/>
name of the Medical and Chirurgical Fac-<lb/>
ulty of Maryland, and it has continued<lb/>
ever since. Thus Maryland became the<lb/>
seventh in the Union to have a State so-<lb/>
ciety. The physicians of the State re-<lb/>
sponded to the call for a State meeting and<lb/>
the gathering was in every sense repre-<lb/>
sentative. Annapolis furnished the presi-<lb/>
dent, Upton Scott, a man of fine, not to<lb/>
say imposing, presence. The last survivor<lb/>
of that worthy company was Dr. Ashton<lb/>
Alexander, who died in Baltimore in <unclear>1855</unclear>.</p>
<p>"One of the striking features of the<lb/>
meeting was the prominence of the county<lb/>
men. These men had grown up learning<lb/>
from hard necessity to depend upon them-<lb/>
selves; and they were well able to take<lb/>
care of themselves. From my own county<lb/>
of Washington came five--Zachariah Clag-<lb/>
gett, of Pleasant Valley, the progenitor of<lb/>
a line of distinguished physicians: Richard<lb/>
Pindell, who was born in Hagerstown and<lb/>
served in the First Maryland Regiment un-<lb/>
der Col. Otho Holland Williams, and after-<lb/>
ward moved to Lexington, Ky., where he<lb/>
was the medical attendant of Henry Clay,<lb/>
his brother-in-law; the others were Jacob<lb/>
Schnively, Peter Waltz and Samuel Young.</p>
<p>Charles Alexander <unclear>Warfield</unclear>.</p>
<p>"Among this celebrated company at An-<lb/>
napolis there was one who was in the full<lb/>
<unclear>flood</unclear> of matured manhood, but whose<lb/>
utation which is practically the medical<lb/>
history of Maryland, so closely was he<lb/>
identified with all that was important in<lb/>
that history. The principles of surgery<lb/>
came to him as the result of his thorough<lb/>
knowledge of anatomy and his finely ma-<lb/>
tured and cultivated judgment, and it was<lb/>
no misnomer that the French surgeons<lb/>
should style him during a Continental trip<lb/>
which he made in 1867 &lsquo;the Nestor of sur-<lb/>
gery in America.&rsquo; And I sum up all that<lb/>
was great, all that was noble, all that was<lb/>
best in medicine in Maryland for half a<lb/>
century when I name that &lsquo;old emperor,&rsquo;<lb/>
Nathan Ryno Smith.</p>
<p>Jesse W. Lazear.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Nathan R. Smith had 11 years to live<lb/>
yet when in Towson, Md., Jesse W. Lazear<lb/>
was born. He was graduated from the aca-<lb/>
demic department of the Johns Hopkins<lb/>
University in <unclear>1880</unclear>. As the medical school<lb/>
was not yet open, he went to New York for<lb/>
his medical education, graduating from<lb/>
the College of Physicians and Surgeons in<lb/>
1893.<unclear>&rdquo;</unclear> He gave special attention later to<lb/>
bacteriology, studying abroad and at the<lb/>
Johns Hopkins and working in Professor<lb/>
Osler's clinic as his assistant. When the<lb/>
United States Government decided to send<lb/>
a commission to Cuba in 1900 under Dr.<lb/>
Walter Reed to study yellow fever Lazear<lb/>
enthusiastically joined the party and ren-<lb/>
dered most valuable service, studying the<lb/>
blood of many cases and helping materially<lb/>
to reach the conclusion which has led to<lb/>
the ridding of Havana of yellow fever and<lb/>
thereby protecting the United States. The<lb/>
commission had formulated, but not yet<lb/>
published, its hypothesis that the mosquito<lb/>
is an important factor in the causation of<lb/>
yellow fever and that by preventing the<lb/>
bite of the mosquito you prevent yellow fe-<lb/>
ver. Inoculation experiments had proved<lb/>
the truth of this hypothesis, and Lazear<lb/>
knew it.</p>
<p>&ldquo;While working in the yellow-fever hos-<lb/>
pital he noticed a mosquito alight on his<lb/>
hand and begin operations. Knowing that<lb/>
this in all probability meant yellow fever<lb/>
to him and great danger, he elected to prove<lb/>
the theory for all time and deliberately al-<lb/>
lowed the mosquito to fill itself. A brush<lb/>
with his hand, a breath, could at any time<lb/>
have chased the insect away. But this<lb/>
hero, as brave a man as ever led a forlorn<lb/>
hope, deliberately took his chances. In a<lb/>
few days he took ill, rapidly developed a<lb/>
very severe type of yellow fever and died,<lb/>
sealing with his life the truth of the theory<lb/>
he had helped to formulate. The anuals of<lb/>
medicine afford no nobler exhibiton of he-<lb/>
<unclear>roic</unclear> daring than this shown by Maryland's<lb/>
devoted son.&rdquo;</p>
<p>------------------------</p>
<pb n="2" id="N0273502"/>
<p>earlier career had been so brilliant as to<lb/>
demand mention. Charles Alexander War-<lb/>
field was the first in his State to propose<lb/>
separation from the mother country, and<lb/>
when the attempt was made to land tea<lb/>
at Annapolis from the Peggy Stewart it was<lb/>
this brilliant young leader of men who,<lb/>
backed up by his neighbors of Anne Arun-<lb/>
del, lined up before the house of the owner<lb/>
of the vessel and compelled him to accept<lb/>
one of two propositions--either to himself<lb/>
apply the torch to his own vessel or to<lb/>
hang before his own door. It did not take<lb/>
long to reach a decision.</p>
<p>The University Of Maryland.</p>
<p>"Such was the material of which the<lb/>
State society was composed. And, as one<lb/>
would expect, the association at once took<lb/>
high ground. Very early they arranged for<lb/>
an examining and licensing board and as-<lb/>
sumed control of the teaching of medicine<lb/>
in the State. Later on they actually or-<lb/>
ganized and put into operation a medical<lb/>
college, which in a few years became a<lb/>
university, and has since December 29,<lb/>
1812, been known as the University of<lb/>
Maryland.</p>
<p>"The latter part of the eighteenth cen-<lb/>
tury saw the country full of smallpox.<lb/>
Jenner had not yet-paved the way for pre-<lb/>
vention and all that could be hoped for<lb/>
was mitigation by inoculation. In this<lb/>
practice Maryland was well to the front.<lb/>
Adam Thompson introduced the so-called<lb/>
American method of inoculation, and wrote<lb/>
a tract on the subject which was printed<lb/>
by Franklin in <unclear>1730</unclear> and ran through sev-<lb/>
eral editions. In 1763 Henry Stevenson<lb/>
was styled &lsquo;the most successful inoculator<lb/>
in America.&rsquo;</p>
<p>Dr. John Crawford A Pioneer.</p>
<p>"While these men recognized the value<lb/>
of the method, they saw its weakness in<lb/>
that it always kept the disease alive. And<lb/>
when something better was offered they<lb/>
seized it with characteristic readiness. In<lb/>
1798 Jenner published his first paper on<lb/>
prevention of smallpox by vaccination,<lb/>
and in 1800 Dr. John Crawford, of Balti-<lb/>
more, made the first vaccination in Mary-<lb/>
land with virus he had received from Lon-<lb/>
don. The man who did most, however, to<lb/>
establish vaccination in Maryland was Dr.<lb/>
James Smith, who may properly be called<lb/>
&lsquo;the father of vaccination in Maryland.&rsquo;<lb/>
He used it in the almshouse and wherever<lb/>
it was possible to secure consent to its use.<lb/>
So advanced was the position of Mary-<lb/>
land in the matter of vaccination that she<lb/>
stands even with Massachusetts and sec-<lb/>
ond to none, being ahead of New York,<lb/>
Pennsylvania and Virginia. A vaccine in-<lb/>
stitute was founded in 1802, being the<lb/>
second in America.</p>
<p>"Time does not suffice to trace minutely<lb/>
the course and the events of medicine in<lb/>
Maryland during the following years. The<lb/>
University of Maryland has continued its<lb/>
sessions regularly ever since, and now num-<lb/>
bers over 5,000 alumni. Other schools have<lb/>
been founded and there are now six medi-<lb/>
cal schools in the State which have an<lb/>
aggregate of nearly 10,000 graduates.</p>
<p>"The latter 80s and early 90s marked a<lb/>
veritable renaissance in medicine. Johns<lb/>
Hopkins Hospital was opened in <unclear>1880</unclear> and<lb/>
the Medical School in 1893.</p>
<p>"As good work is being done by the<lb/>
Maryland schools as is done anywhere in<lb/>
America, and on some lines Maryland leads<lb/>
all the States of the Union. It is not well<lb/>
to estimate men before their work is done,<lb/>
but with Councilman in Boston, Flexner<lb/>
in New York and Barker in Chicago, Mary-<lb/>
land has no need to blush for the sons she<lb/>
has sent out from her border: and when<lb/>
Oxford wants a <unclear>Regius</unclear> professor of medi-<lb/>
cine and comes to Maryland to select him<lb/>
we feel that little is left that may shed<lb/>
honor on a profession already so highly<lb/>
honored.</p>
<p>"I dare not leave this period without<lb/>
emphasizing the part which the State<lb/>
Board of Medical Examiners has played in<lb/>
uplifting the profession. They have acted<lb/>
as the bulwark against which greed of gain<lb/>
and petty commercialism have beat in vain<lb/>
in trying to inundate the profession.</p>
<p>Nathan R. Smith.</p>
<p>"I cannot close without reference to two<lb/>
men who have shed such luster on medi-<lb/>
cine in Maryland as to compel mention.<lb/>
Two years before that meeting at Annapo-<lb/>
lis there was born in the town of Cornish,<lb/>
in Connecticut, a male child who was des-<lb/>
tined to pass through a long life and<lb/>
reach a <unclear>poistion</unclear> of high honor and prefer-<lb/>
ment in his profession. Educated in New<lb/>
England, a short stay in Virginia seemed<lb/>
to have inclined him to the South. When<lb/>
George <unclear>McClellan</unclear> founded the Jefferson<lb/>
Medical College he turned to this young<lb/>
man, then less than 30 years old, to take<lb/>
the chair of anatomy. For two years he<lb/>
continued in the place, but in 1827 he left<lb/>
for Baltimore. Here he built up that rep-</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
