<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2866008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, Springfield Republican, July 22, 1906</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2866008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1906-07-22</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Lawrence, Emilie</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (Md.)</name>
<name type="place">University of Virginia, Charlottesville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Bellevue Hospital, New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">Mexico</name>
<name type="place">Africa</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1906-07-22">July 22, 1906</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2866008</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, Springfield Republican, July 22, 1906</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Dr. Reed and Yellow Fever</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1906-07-22">
<head>Newspaper clipping, Springfield Republican, July 22, 1906</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2866008"/>
<opener>
Duplicate<lb/>
<dateline>
Springfield<lb/>
Republican<lb/>
<date value="1906-07-22">July 22, 1906</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>--------------------</p>
<p>DR REED AND YELLOW FEVER.</p>
<p>---------------</p>
<p>A deserved tribute to a brave and modest<lb/>
medical officer who was fortunate enough<lb/>
to play a foremost part in the discovery of<lb/>
the cause and mode of prevention of one<lb/>
of the most terrible of plagues, is given in<lb/>
the volume entitled &ldquo;Walter Reed and<lb/>
Yellow Fever&rdquo; by Howard A. Kelly,<lb/>
professor in Johns Hopkins university,<lb/>
which is published by McClure, Phillips &amp;<lb/>
Co. The author well says in his preface:<lb/>
&ldquo;The inspiration of Reed's life lies to me<lb/>
in the fact that, though a man of war, he<lb/>
ravaged no distant land, he destroyed no<lb/>
tens of thousands to make his reputation,<lb/>
but by quiet method, when there was no<lb/>
strife, he saved countless lives and swept<lb/>
away a hideous plague, which from time<lb/>
immemorial has periodically visited our<lb/>
shores.&rdquo; Very properly the basis of the<lb/>
book is scientific rather than personal,<lb/>
though the facts of Reed's fine career are<lb/>
briefly and simply stated. He was born<lb/>
in Gloucester county, Va., in 1851, of a<lb/>
family of English extraction. He was 10<lb/>
years old when the civil war began and<lb/>
had some slight glimpses of it as a non-<lb/>
combatant. His schooling was interrupted<lb/>
only one year, and he was able to enter the<lb/>
university of Virginia at 16, a special dis-<lb/>
pensation being required on account of<lb/>
his youth. He turned early to medicine,<lb/>
and realizing that his father's means did<lb/>
not permit of the whole university course,<lb/>
he took up medical studies as early as he<lb/>
could. The author says: &ldquo;This request was<lb/>
refused on the ground that he was under<lb/>
age. He then inquired whether he would<lb/>
be allowed to take the degree of doctor<lb/>
if he could pass the examination. To this<lb/>
this faculty silently assented, thinking that<lb/>
it was a safe promise, for the undertaking<lb/>
was an impossibility.&rdquo; He passed tri-<lb/>
umphantly. The incident shows the lad's<lb/>
strong bent toward science. He studied<lb/>
later at the Bellevue medical hospital in<lb/>
New York, where for the first time he saw<lb/>
a large city. As district physician in one<lb/>
of the poorest districts, he was for the<lb/>
first time brought into contact with the<lb/>
poverty and vice of the slums. He married<lb/>
Miss Emilie Lawrence of a North Carolina<lb/>
family that had come from Watertown and<lb/>
Salem, Mass. In 1874 he decided to give<lb/>
up general practice and entered the army<lb/>
as a surgeon, feeling that he lacked the<lb/>
closer connection needed for an early start<lb/>
in private practice. Several chapters are<lb/>
devoted to his frontier life, which was pic-<lb/>
turesque and interesting, but unimportant<lb/>
in comparison with his scientific work.</p>
<p>In 1889, Dr Reed began to feel the need<lb/>
for further study, and after some trouble<lb/>
secured an appointment as attending sur-<lb/>
geon and examiner of recruits in Baltimore,<lb/>
Md., with permission to study in the Johns<lb/>
Hopkins hospital. It is curious to read,<lb/>
however, that he was curtly and pointedly<lb/>
forbidden by the then surgeon-general to<lb/>
take courses in pathology and bacteriology.<lb/>
He was told that his business was to learn<lb/>
to take care of sick soldiers. Fortunately<lb/>
the new surgeon-general was more in sym-<lb/>
pathy with scientific pursuits, and Dr Reed<lb/>
was enabled to carry on study in pathology<lb/>
and bacteriology, without which splendid<lb/>
later results could not have been obtained.<lb/>
He took an early stand in favor of the use<lb/>
of the antitoxin serum, and throughout<lb/>
showed a disposition to test every new idea.<lb/>
He was very anxious when the Spanish<lb/>
war broke out in 1898 to hold some re-<lb/>
sponsible position in the care of sick sol-<lb/>
diers, but had the mortification of seeing<lb/>
untrained men with political influence pre-<lb/>
ferred. He himself said very frankly in<lb/>
private conversation, &ldquo;The army medical<lb/>
corps has received a black eye because of<lb/>
the neglect and incompetence of men who<lb/>
did not really belong to it.&rdquo; The lesson<lb/>
of the war as to the need of reorganization<lb/>
of the medical corps is forcibly pressed<lb/>
home by the author. Dr Reed's first sci-<lb/>
entific work during the war was in the<lb/>
investigation of the typhoid epidemic<lb/>
among the volunteers, to which he devoted<lb/>
more than a year as chairman of a com-<lb/>
mittee, whose report has but lately been<lb/>
issued by the government. While his part<lb/>
in this work is not separated from that of<lb/>
the other members of the committee, its<lb/>
importance justifies the space given to it<lb/>
by the author. The chief points in the<lb/>
report are that the infected water was not<lb/>
an important factor, that flies undoubtedly<lb/>
acted as carriers of the infection, and it<lb/>
is more than likely that men transported<lb/>
infected material on their persons.</p>
<p>The author takes up the subject of yellow<lb/>
fever with much thoroughness, devoting<lb/>
several chapters to the character and his-<lb/>
tory of the disease. He virtually contra-<lb/>
dicts the assertion made by several histo-<lb/>
rians that the fever was brought over from<lb/>
the west coast of Africa in slave ships, by<lb/>
saying: &ldquo;Some of the older writers claim<lb/>
that yellow fever was originally present in<lb/>
Africa, though Cortez found it in Mexico.<lb/>
It was certainly unknown in Europe until<lb/>
after the discovery of America.&rdquo; The<lb/>
history of opinion as to the cause of the<lb/>
disease and its mode of transmission is<lb/>
briefly but carefully traced. It is curious to<lb/>
note that one Prof P. Stille of Mobile, Ala.,<lb/>
advanced a theory which attributed the<lb/>
disease to the influence of the Gulf stream.<lb/>
Dr Labadie favored the &ldquo;explosive&rdquo; theory,<lb/>
that the disease was caused by "a peculiar<lb/>
subtle poison which exploded in the air<lb/>
like an inflammable substance, and that<lb/>
persons who inhaled it or swallowed it in<lb/>
greater or less quantity fell under its in-<lb/>
fluence after a certain time. In 1878 medi-<lb/>
cal experts appointed by Congress pre-<lb/>
sented a report which was nearer the truth<lb/>
than the doctrines which prevailed after<lb/>
that until the discovery of the part played<lb/>
by the mosquito. For it was about 1878<lb/>
that &ldquo;fomites,&rdquo; the term given to clothing<lb/>
and other articles which were supposed to<lb/>
transmit the infection, came into vogue.<lb/>
The theory on the subject was therefore<lb/>
turned in to a wrong channel which made<lb/>
discovery of the truth impossible. The last<lb/>
official statement under the old order, the<lb/>
last defense of the old fashioned theories<lb/>
of yellow fever, was in 1898, when the<lb/>
United States marine hospital service<lb/>
issued a report saying: &ldquo;While yellow fever<lb/>
is a communicable disease, it is not con-<lb/>
tagious in the ordinary acceptation of the<lb/>
term, but is spread by the infection of<lb/>
places and articles of bedding, clothing and<lb/>
furniture.&rdquo;</p>
<p>It was but a year or two before the truth<lb/>
was made known by the researches in<lb/>
which Dr Reed had the most important<lb/>
part and which are still too familiar in the<lb/>
general mind to require recapitulation, al-<lb/>
though Dr Kelly's is the first account of it<lb/>
from the biographical point of view. It<lb/>
would be hard to find finer examples of<lb/>
heroism than those offered by the volunteer<lb/>
soldiers who freely gave their services as<lb/>
subjects for experiment. One can under-<lb/>
stand the enthusiasm with which Dr Reed<lb/>
wrote to his wife: &ldquo;It is with a great deal<lb/>
of pleasure that I hasten to tell you that<lb/>
we have succeeded in producing a case of<lb/>
unmistakable yellow fever by the bite of a<lb/>
mosquito. . . . Rejoice with me.&rdquo; The<lb/>
patient could not be expected to share his<lb/>
enthusiasm, but it should be added that he<lb/>
made a good recovery. Dr Reed's own<lb/>
feeling is shown in the remark: &ldquo;Maj Kean<lb/>
says that the recovery is worth more than<lb/>
the cost of the Spanish war, including lives<lb/>
lost and money expended.&rdquo; This brilliant<lb/>
achievement was followed soon by his<lb/>
death, which occurred in 1902, as the result<lb/>
of an operation for appendicitis.</p>
<p>---------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
