<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'http://fedoraproxy.lib.virginia.edu/fedora/objects/xml:dtd/datastreams/teixlite.dtd/content' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2870001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Youth's Companion, January 10, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2870001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-01-10</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease">YES</term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History">YES</term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<name type="person">Reed, Walter</name>
<name type="person">Lazear, Jesse W.</name>
<name type="person">Carroll, James</name>
<name type="person">Kelly, Howard A.</name>
<name type="person">Finlay, Carlos J.</name>
<name type="person">Kissinger, John R.</name>
<name type="person">Moran, John J.</name>
<name type="person">Cooke, Robert Page</name>
<name type="person">Folk, Levi E.</name>
<name type="person">Jernegan, Warren G.</name>
<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="place">Eastern Europe</name>
<name type="place">Asia</name>
<name type="place">Southern United States</name>
<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">Farmville (Va.)</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
<name type="place">Camp Lazear (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-01-10">January 10, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2870001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Youth's Companion, January 10, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Lesson of Little Things: The Conquest of Yellow Fever</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-01-10">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Youth's Companion, January 10, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="N2870001"/>
<opener>
VOLUME 81. NO. 2.<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1907-01-10">JANUARY 10, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
THE YOUTH'S COMPANION<lb/>
$1.75 A YEAR.<lb/>
<unclear>6 CTS. A</unclear> COPY.<lb/>
<unclear>Copyright, 1907, by Perry Masun Company, Mass.</unclear><lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>JAN. 10, 1907</p>
<p>THE YOUTH'S COMPANION.</p>
<p>15</p>
<p>daylight turned out to be but a commonplace<lb/>
episode; and this, I may add, was our only<lb/>
adventure for the year. From our sixteen<lb/>
hundred eggs we raised nearly twelve hundred<lb/>
chickens, and-well, we are going on with our<lb/>
enterprise, in good hopes of success.</p>
<p>THE LESSON OF LITTLE THINGS:<lb/>
THE CONQUEST OF YELLOW FEVER<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">By Howard A. Kelly M. D.</hi></p>
<p>SO interesting are great<lb/>
events and great deeds<lb/>
that we are apt to de-<lb/>
spise the realm of little things.<lb/>
I strongly believe that the king-<lb/>
dom of Lilliput is more important<lb/>
than that of Brobdingnag, for<lb/>
attention to small duties is the only<lb/>
path to great achievement. To<lb/>
show how true this is, let me<lb/>
remind you that one of the great<lb/>
achievements of the last century,<lb/>
the control of the dreadful yellow<lb/>
fever, was accomplished by fixing<lb/>
the attention upon an object so<lb/>
insignificant that for centuries it<lb/>
had gone unheeded.</p>
<p>Yellow fever, like the plague, the<lb/>
cholera, and other kindred diseases, is found in<lb/>
suitable climates at all times; but at intervals it<lb/>
spreads from its center and becomes an epidemic.<lb/>
The plague and the cholera are now pretty much<lb/>
confined to eastern Europe and Asia; but yellow<lb/>
fever has existed for centuries in the southern<lb/>
United States, whence, from time to time, it<lb/>
has spread northward along the Atlantic sea-<lb/>
board as far as Philadelphia and New York,<lb/>
or even as Nantucket Island and Halifax. In a<lb/>
little over a century there have been three great<lb/>
epidemics of yellow fever in the United States:<lb/>
in 1793, in 1853, and in 1878.</p>
<p>The epidemic of 1793 was especially severe in<lb/>
Philadelphia, where it lasted from early August<lb/>
to late November. Another terrible visitation<lb/>
was in New Orleans in 1853, but the greatest was<lb/>
the epidemic in New Orleans and Memphis in<lb/>
1878. An excellent account of it has been left<lb/>
by Mr. J. M. Keating, a citizen of Memphis,<lb/>
who stayed in the city throughout the epidemic<lb/>
and gave what help he could to the unfortu-<lb/>
nates. The pestilence began in May, but not<lb/>
until August did it excite alarm. Then the city<lb/>
became panic-stricken.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Men, women and children,&rdquo; says Keating,<lb/>
&ldquo;poured out of the city by every possible con-<lb/>
veyance--by hacks, buggies, wagons, furniture-<lb/>
<unclear>vans</unclear> and <unclear>street-drays</unclear>; away by <unclear>bateater,</unclear> by<lb/>
boats, by anything that could float on the<lb/>
water; and by the railroads, the trains on which<lb/>
were so packed as to make every step of the<lb/>
way to St. Louis or Cincinnati a positive tor-<lb/>
ture. . . . The aisles of the cars were filled and<lb/>
the platforms crowded.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Those left in the city saw the usual scenes<lb/>
of cruelty, and also, it is good to remember,<lb/>
the usual instances of kindness. Much good<lb/>
was done by the Howard Association, named<lb/>
after the English philanthropist. Its members<lb/>
nursed the sick, relieved the destitute, and cared<lb/>
for the dead. Their work will always remain,<lb/>
as Keating says, &ldquo;a monument of human love.&rdquo;<lb/>
This epidemic was particularly wide-spread.<lb/>
It raged through nearly the whole South, and,<lb/>
like all others, lasted until the autumn brought<lb/>
frost and cool weather. But although people<lb/>
noticed this, no one thought of connecting it<lb/>
with the mosquito.</p>
<p>The loss by yellow fever is probably greater<lb/>
than by any disease except cholera and the<lb/>
plague. No treatment has ever been found of<lb/>
marked benefit. New Orleans has lost at differ-<lb/>
ent times forty-one thousand three hundred<lb/>
and forty-eight lives from it; Philadelphia,<lb/>
ten thousand one hundred and thirty-eight;<lb/>
Memphis,--in 1878 alone,--fifty-one hundred<lb/>
and fifty, and Norfolk, Virginia, in 1855, over<lb/>
two thousand. But these deaths, terrible as the<lb/>
number is, do not represent the whole loss.<lb/>
The pecuniary loss is great; directly, in sums<lb/>
spent to relieve the sufferers and to control the<lb/>
disease, and indirectly, through the injury to<lb/>
business. For example, the direct loss to the<lb/>
country in 1878, when the disease was wide-<lb/>
spread, was estimated as not less than one<lb/>
hundred millions of dollars.</p>
<p>The Theory of &ldquo;Fomites.&rdquo;</p>
<p>DURING the epidemic of 1793 the nature<lb/>
of yellow fever began really to be stud-<lb/>
ied, and then began the long debate<lb/>
between physicians as to the contagiousness of<lb/>
the disease. This was discussed for years, until,<lb/>
indeed, the rise of the theory of &ldquo;fomites.&rdquo;</p>
<p>According to this the disease was conveyed by<lb/>
invisible particles given off by the sick, and<lb/>
spread by their clothing and articles used by<lb/>
them. This idea was accepted, and an elaborate<lb/>
system of disinfection was introduced at all sea-<lb/>
ports to exclude the fomites. In New York, for<lb/>
instance, great screws were bored into bales of<lb/>
goods, and then steam was forced into the<lb/>
holes to kill the fomites. All such expensive<lb/>
precautions were mere waste of time and<lb/>
money; they did not touch the real cause of<lb/>
offense.</p>
<p>I have mentioned the horrors of yellow fever<lb/>
and dwelt upon the trouble and the expense<lb/>
of attempts to control it because I want you to<lb/>
appreciate our present blessing of immunity,<lb/>
and to realize the debt of grati-<lb/>
tude we owe to the men who<lb/>
gave it to us.</p>
<p>The time came at last when<lb/>
the problem of yellow fever was<lb/>
to be solved. Several times the<lb/>
secret had been nearly guessed.</p>
<p>In 1848 Dr. J. C. Nott of Mobile<lb/>
wrote a paper in which he insisted<lb/>
that yellow fever must be carried<lb/>
by some insect which kept close<lb/>
to the ground, and suggested the<lb/>
mosquito. In 1881 Dr. Carlos J.<lb/>
Finlay, still living in Havana,<lb/>
declared that if a yellow - fever<lb/>
patient were bitten by a mosquito<lb/>
of a particular species, which he<lb/>
named, and if the mosquito after-<lb/>
ward bit some one else, the second patient<lb/>
would have the disease.</p>
<p>After Doctor Finlay's suggestion, the mos-<lb/>
quito was not mentioned in connection with<lb/>
yellow fever for nearly twenty years. Scientific<lb/>
people were agreed that the only thing to do<lb/>
was to find its germ, as had already been done<lb/>
in the case of tuberculosis, of malaria and of<lb/>
typhoid fever. Several claimed to have discov-<lb/>
ered it, but careful investigation always showed<lb/>
that they were mistaken.</p>
<p>How the Right Man Came.</p>
<p>AT last, just at the close of the century,<lb/>
came the right man, and with him<lb/>
two associates, who again took up the<lb/>
problem and solved it by practical experiment.</p>
<p>Walter Reed was born at Farmville, Virginia,<lb/>
on September 13, 1851. He was educated at<lb/>
private schools and at the University of Virginia<lb/>
medical school. At twenty-four he became a<lb/>
surgeon in the United States army. When still<lb/>
very young, Doctor Reed made up his mind<lb/>
that what he wished most to accomplish was<lb/>
something which would relieve human suffer-<lb/>
ing. This desire never forsook him.</p>
<p>As an army surgeon he lived for eighteen<lb/>
years in remote places, most of the time on<lb/>
the Western frontier, where there were no facili-<lb/>
ties and no time for scientific work. But in<lb/>
1900, when Doctor Reed, then forty-nine years<lb/>
old, had for some years been stationed in<lb/>
Washington, where he was able to pursue scien-<lb/>
tific studies, an outbreak of yellow fever among<lb/>
the American soldiers at Havana gave him his<lb/>
opportunity. The United States government<lb/>
placed him at the head of a commission to<lb/>
investigate the disease. Dr. James Carroll of<lb/>
the army, Dr. Jesse W. Lazear of Johns Hop-<lb/>
kins University, and Dr. Aristides Agramonte,<lb/>
a Cuban gentleman, who, having had yellow<lb/>
fever, was considered &ldquo;immune,&rdquo; were the<lb/>
other members.</p>
<p>The first thing Doctor Reed did in Cuba was<lb/>
to study carefully the cases of yellow fever<lb/>
which he saw there. He soon concluded that<lb/>
there was no truth in the doctrine of fomites.<lb/>
He next decided that it was useless to spend time<lb/>
in looking for the germ of yellow<lb/>
fever, but that the thing to do was<lb/>
to find out how the disease spread.<lb/>
To this end, he concluded to test<lb/>
the suggestion made by Doctor Nott<lb/>
and Doctor Finlay, that the disease<lb/>
is carried by the mosquito.</p>
<p>Now there was one way only to<lb/>
prove such a theory, and that<lb/>
was by experiments upon human<lb/>
beings. If a mosquito which had<lb/>
bitten a yellow-fever patient were<lb/>
allowed to bite a well person, and<lb/>
the well person within a short<lb/>
time developed yellow fever, there would be<lb/>
every reason to accept the mosquito theory,<lb/>
although it would be necessary to repeat the<lb/>
experiment a number of times before the theory<lb/>
was established. Doctor Reed and his associates<lb/>
agreed that one of them ought to be the first<lb/>
subject. Doctor Carroll volunteered to risk his<lb/>
life for the purpose.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear applied a mosquito of the<lb/>
species suggested by Doctor Finlay to a patient<lb/>
in the yellow-fever hospital, and then, nearly<lb/>
two weeks afterward, to Doctor Carroll. Four<lb/>
days later Doctor Carroll fell ill of the disease,<lb/>
from which he barely escaped with his life.</p>
<p>Before Doctor Carroll had recovered Doctor<lb/>
Lazear contracted the disease also from a mos-<lb/>
quito bite received in the yellow-fever hospital.<lb/>
He was sitting with the yellow-fever patients<lb/>
when he noticed a mosquito on his hand. In-<lb/>
stead of brushing it off, he let it remain until<lb/>
it had bitten him severely. Five days later he<lb/>
was taken ill with the disease, and then, and<lb/>
not till then, did he tell the others what had<lb/>
happened. He was sure he had taken the<lb/>
disease from the mosquito.</p>
<p>For a while he did fairly well, but on the<lb/>
fourth day he became worse, and on the eighth<lb/>
day he died. He had given his life for the<lb/>
cause he served as truly as any soldier in battle.<lb/>
As his friend Doctor Carroll says, &ldquo;He died<lb/>
that his fellow men might live in comfort and<lb/>
happiness. It is no exaggeration to say that<lb/>
hundreds, nay, thousands, in the Southern<lb/>
States owe their lives, and certainly their pros-<lb/>
perity, to the work in which he was engaged,<lb/>
and for which he and his family have paid<lb/>
such a fearful penalty.&rdquo;</p>
<p>His death was a terrible loss to the commis-<lb/>
sion. His abilities were great, and his fine<lb/>
character and affectionate nature made him<lb/>
greatly beloved.</p>
<p>Doctor Reed and Doctor Carroll decided that<lb/>
there was now enough proof of the mosquito<lb/>
theory to justify further experiments on human<lb/>
beings, provided, of course, that these under-<lb/>
stood the risk fully, and gave their free consent.<lb/>
A station named Camp Lazear was built, and<lb/>
Congress appropriated money to reward volun-<lb/>
teers.</p>
<p>&ldquo;Gentlemen, I Salute You.&rdquo;</p>
<p>WHEN all was ready, Doctor Reed was<lb/>
told that two men wished to see him.<lb/>
These were two young privates from<lb/>
the regiment stationed at Havana. Both were<lb/>
from Ohio. Their names were John R. Kis-<lb/>
singer and John J. Moran.</p>
<p>They had heard of the intended experiments,<lb/>
and wished to offer themselves for the purpose.<lb/>
Doctor Reed explained fully the suffering and<lb/>
danger which they would have to endure, but<lb/>
they were not daunted. Then he spoke of the<lb/>
money reward, but both young men promptly<lb/>
declined it. They said that they had volun-<lb/>
teered for humanity's sake, and they made<lb/>
it a condition that they<lb/>
should not be paid.</p>
<p>Doctor Reed, greatly<lb/>
moved, touched his cap<lb/>
to them. &ldquo;Gentlemen,<lb/>
I salute you,&rdquo; he said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;In my opinion,&rdquo; he<lb/>
has said since, &ldquo;this<lb/>
exhibition of courage<lb/>
has never been sur-<lb/>
passed in the annals<lb/>
of the United States<lb/>
army.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Kissinger underwent<lb/>
the first experiment in Camp Lazear. On<lb/>
December 5, 1900, he was bitten by five infected<lb/>
mosquitoes, that is, mosquitoes which had bitten<lb/>
a yellow-fever patient, and on December 8th he<lb/>
was sharply attacked by the disease. For sev-<lb/>
eral days he was so seriously ill that Doctor<lb/>
Reed was most anxious, but finally he made a<lb/>
complete recovery.</p>
<p>Moran's turn came next, but he did not then<lb/>
take the disease. Later, however, in the course<lb/>
of another set of experiments, he was again<lb/>
inoculated, and had a well-marked attack which<lb/>
established the point then in question. Other<lb/>
experiments followed, and afforded abundant<lb/>
evidence that mosquitoes carry the disease.</p>
<p>But it was also necessary to show conclu-<lb/>
sively that yellow fever is not carried by means<lb/>
of fomites.</p>
<p>A tiny house was built. It had one room with<lb/>
two small windows and a door all on the same<lb/>
side, so that as there could be no draft through<lb/>
the room no germs could be blown away. The<lb/>
atmosphere was kept warm and moist. Three<lb/>
large boxes, containing sheets, pillow-slips,<lb/>
and so forth, used by the yellow-fever patients<lb/>
were brought from the hospital at Havana.</p>
<p>Three volunteers, Dr. R. P. Cooke,<lb/>
an army surgeon, and two privates,<lb/>
Folk and Jernigan, unpacked these<lb/>
unpleasant articles and made up<lb/>
the beds with them, hanging all<lb/>
not so used round the room. In<lb/>
these beds they slept for twenty<lb/>
nights, and at one time actually<lb/>
used the shirts which the yellow-<lb/>
fever patients had worn. Yet not<lb/>
one had yellow fever, and the com-<lb/>
mission felt it had proved that<lb/>
yellow fever is never due to fomites.</p>
<p>Other experiments cleared doubt-<lb/>
ful points connected with the mosquito theory.<lb/>
I wish I could describe these, but there is room<lb/>
only to state the conclusions drawn from them,<lb/>
as follows:</p>
<p>Only the female of the mosquito named<lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Stegomyia fasciata</hi> carries yellow fever.</p>
<p>The mosquito cannot infect any one until at<lb/>
least twelve days after biting a yellow-fever<lb/>
patient.</p>
<p>These experiments finished, Doctor Reed re-<lb/>
turned to the United States, and Doctor Carroll<lb/>
followed him soon afterward. The next summer,<lb/>
however, Doctor Carroll returned to Cuba to<lb/>
perform other experiments necessary to the<lb/>
perfection of the work.</p>
<p>What the Experiments Proved.</p>
<p>He proved that the mosquito can infect for<lb/>
at least fifty-seven days after biting the<lb/>
yellow-fever patient, and he also found<lb/>
that the specific germ of yellow fever, for which<lb/>
so many people had sought in vain, is almost<lb/>
certainly ultramicroscopic.</p>
<p>The only means of protecting cities and per-<lb/>
sons from yellow fever is the destruction of the<lb/>
mosquitoes and the larv&aelig;, or &ldquo;wrigglers.&rdquo;<lb/>
Fortunately, this is easy and cheap. It has<lb/>
been tried several times with entire success.<lb/>
At Havana in 1901 the disease was thus com-<lb/>
pletely and promptly stamped out. The same<lb/>
thing occurred in New Orleans in 1905, although<lb/>
as the theory was not fully accepted, success<lb/>
came more slowly.</p>
<p>The method of killing the mosquitoes is this:<lb/>
The city or town is divided into sections, and<lb/>
squadrons of workers under the control of a<lb/>
central office visit every house where a case of<lb/>
yellow fever is reported.</p>
<p>All the windows having been closed and the<lb/>
chimney stopped up, pots containing sulphur--<lb/>
or pyrethrum--are placed in the rooms, and a<lb/>
little alcohol is poured on each. The rooms<lb/>
are darkened except for one spot of bright light.<lb/>
Then the men, setting fire to the alcohol, go<lb/>
quickly out, shutting the door and carefully<lb/>
pasting paper over its cracks.</p>
<p>The mosquitoes, stupefied by the burning<lb/>
sulphur, crawl to the light, so that they are<lb/>
found collected there when the room is opened.<lb/>
At the end of about four hours the men return,<lb/>
sweep up all the mosquitoes, carry them away<lb/>
and burn them.</p>
<p>To destroy the mosquitoes, however, is not<lb/>
enough; their eggs and larv&aelig; must also be<lb/>
killed. The female mosquito deposits her eggs<lb/>
on stagnant water, where they float until<lb/>
hatched. The thing to do, therefore, is either<lb/>
to get rid of the water or else to prevent the<lb/>
eggs from hatching. To accomplish this, all<lb/>
streets are swept free of puddles. Pools of<lb/>
standing water, whenever possible, are filled<lb/>
up, and all cisterns, water-tanks and the like<lb/>
are covered by the working squadrons with<lb/>
kerosene oil. If this work is done as soon as<lb/>
a case of yellow fever is reported, there will<lb/>
never again be an epi-<lb/>
demic of the disease.<lb/>
And if mosquitoes are<lb/>
systematically de-<lb/>
stroyed wherever they<lb/>
exist, there will be no<lb/>
yellow fever at all, for<lb/>
a case of yellow fever<lb/>
without a mosquito is<lb/>
an impossibility.</p>
<p>At the close of his<lb/>
yellow-fever work in<lb/>
Cuba Doctor Reed<lb/>
taught for two years in<lb/>
Washington. It was a source of great happiness<lb/>
to him that his heart's desire had been granted,<lb/>
and he had been permitted to make a discov-<lb/>
ery which diminished suffering throughout the<lb/>
world. But he had worked so long and so hard<lb/>
in the service of his fellow men that his health<lb/>
began to fall. In November, 1902, he was<lb/>
attacked by appendicitis, and had to undergo<lb/>
an operation. Brave for himself, he was anx-<lb/>
ious about his wife and daughter.</p>
<p>The Close of a Noble Life.</p>
<p>JUST before the operation he said to<lb/>
Major Kean, an old friend, &ldquo;I am not<lb/>
afraid of the knife, but if anything<lb/>
happens to me I am leaving my wife and<lb/>
daughter so little!&rdquo; And as he became uncon-<lb/>
scious, he continued to murmur, &ldquo;So little, so<lb/>
little!&rdquo;</p>
<p>He did fairly well at first, but soon began to<lb/>
fail. He died November 22, 1902, at the age<lb/>
of fifty-one. He was buried at Arlington,<lb/>
where Mrs. Reed has erected a monument<lb/>
overlooking the city of Washington, with an<lb/>
inscription which closes with these words:<lb/>
&ldquo;He gave to man control over that dreadful<lb/>
scourge, yellow fever.&rdquo;</p>
<p>So ended a noble life. Its closing event was<lb/>
one of the greatest scientific discoveries of the<lb/>
century, and the deliverance of the world from<lb/>
a most terrible scourge.</p>
<p>Yet Doctor Reed's work has not received the<lb/>
gratitude it deserves at the hands of his country.<lb/>
The members of his own profession, it is true,<lb/>
have displayed a most hearty appreciation of<lb/>
the distinction conferred upon them all by<lb/>
Doctor Reed's achievements, and they, together<lb/>
with some outsiders, have contributed most<lb/>
generously to a fund for a memorial, which is<lb/>
now nearly completed, but this is entirely the<lb/>
work of individuals: the country has done<lb/>
nothing beyond granting Mrs. Reed a very<lb/>
modest pension.</p>
<p>Doctor Carroll's work was no less valuable<lb/>
than Doctor Reed's. He risked his life in the<lb/>
cause, a risk which circumstances did not call<lb/>
upon Doctor Reed to assume. Moreover, his<lb/>
attack of yellow fever has left him with a per-<lb/>
manent heart affection which hampers his<lb/>
activities. Yet the United States has made<lb/>
him no acknowledgment whatever.</p>
<p>Doctor Lazear laid down his life for his<lb/>
work, and his colleagues at the university have<lb/>
erected a tablet there to his memory, but the<lb/>
country has done nothing beyond granting his<lb/>
widow and her two little children a pension of<lb/>
a few dollars a month.</p>
<p>I take pains to tell all this, because some<lb/>
who read it may in the future become legislators<lb/>
and have it in their power to influence their<lb/>
country in other affairs of the same kind.<lb/>
Therefore I beg them to remember that the<lb/>
man who makes a scientific discovery which<lb/>
benefits his country and his fellow men is just<lb/>
as much entitled to the gratitude of that country<lb/>
as the man who wins a victory on the battle-<lb/>
field, or sets on foot a great commercial enter-<lb/>
prise; and it is the duty of those who administer</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
