<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2895008">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 21, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2895008</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-08-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces">YES</term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine">YES</term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health"></term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>

<name type="person">Kean, Jefferson Randolph</name>
<name type="person">Wood, Leonard</name>
<name type="place">Cuba</name>
<name type="place">Cienfuegos (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-08-21">August 21, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2895008</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 21, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>The Zeal and Efficiency Shown by Our Medical Officers</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-08-21">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 21, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2895008"/>
<opener>
PAGE TWO.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
THE HAVANA DAILY TELEGRAPH<lb/>
Published by The Daily Telegraph Company.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
PUBLISHED EVERY DAY IN THE YEAR.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Entered at the Havana, Cuba, postoffice as second class matter.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Circulation Rates. Prices in United States Currency.<lb/>
One Year, delivered by carrier or mail. .... .. .... <unclear>$5.00</unclear><lb/>
Six Months. delivered by carrier or mail.. .. .. .... 3.00<lb/>
Three Months. delivered by carrier or mail .... 1 75<lb/>
One Month, delivered by carrier or mail.. .... .... 75<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Telephone No. 3257.<lb/>
Cable, &ldquo;Telegraph.&rdquo;<lb/>
OFFICE NO. 7 O'REILLY STREET.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, Cuba, <date value="1907-08-21">August 21, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>THE ZEAL AND EFFICIENCY SHOWN<lb/>
BY OUR MEDICAL OFFICERS.</p>
<p>It is only too unlikely that persons<lb/>
living in the North and having no real<lb/>
knowledge of conditions in Cuba, may be led to suppose that because of the<lb/>
small outbreak of yellow fever among American soldiers at Cienfuegos, the offi-<lb/>
cers of our Medical Corps are to be looked upon as either incompetent or care-<lb/>
less. The truth is that yellow fever has probably never been entirely eradi-<lb/>
cated from the island, though kept well in check by a pursuance of the methods<lb/>
established by the former intervention. Mild cases of it among the natives<lb/>
have doubtless gone unrecognized, or have not been reported, but have served<lb/>
to keep alive potential infection. With the coming of non-immune American<lb/>
troops, the danger at once became vastly increased, for while here and there a<lb/>
Cuban of the interior highlands may be liable to the disease, there has not<lb/>
been but a very scant sprinkling of such in any locality, so that multiplica-<lb/>
tion of cases was nowhere likely to occur.</p>
<p>Had the Cuban government carried out the obligation entailed upon it by<lb/>
the Platt amendment and nationalized sanitation, the same methods that have<lb/>
kept Havana clean, or served always to prevent the spread of the disease from<lb/>
sporadic cases, would have placed the other cities of the island in a safe condi-<lb/>
tion. This obvious duty was not complied with, however, and the cities out-<lb/>
side the capital have been deft to their own devices, which have been those of<lb/>
indifference and dilatoriness. Cienfuegos is in a disreputably unhigienic condi-<lb/>
tion, and it is not at all surprising that a few American soldiers, peculiarly<lb/>
exposed because on duty in the vicinity of a hospital in charge of native doctors,<lb/>
who permitted some mild case of the disease to pass unreegnized or unreported,<lb/>
should have contracted the infection. So far from deducing from this that the<lb/>
American medical officers have been careless or incompetent, it should be in-<lb/>
ferred from the fact that with the infection on the island, na American sol-<lb/>
dier was attacked for nearly a year after the coming of the troops, that the med-<lb/>
ical officers have been wonderfully watchful and efficient. With detachments<lb/>
of non-immune soldiers scattered all over the island, and foci of yellow fever<lb/>
infection at several points, the officers must have exercised the greatest care<lb/>
and skill in selecting camps and quarters and keeping these and their occupants<lb/>
entirely free from infection, and it is safe to say that had there been a national<lb/>
sanitation law, so that the military supervisors of sanitation would have en-<lb/>
joyed a free hand in the cities of the island, the present small outbreak of the<lb/>
fever in Cienfuegos would have been avoided. But Major Kean and his able and<lb/>
zealous lieutenants have been hampered at every step by the indifference and the<lb/>
jealousy of the municipal doctors, who have resented their supervision and direc-<lb/>
tion, and who have been protected by political influence. It is notorious that<lb/>
many of these doctors owe their places, not to zeal or fitness, but to political<lb/>
influence, which in every sphere is the bane of the present intervention. Be-<lb/>
cause Secretary Taft, influenced by political exigencies at home, saw fit to treat<lb/>
with the revolutionists of last August and to make certain agreements with<lb/>
them, the present occupant of the executive palace is not free, as was General<lb/>
Wood, to do whatever there may be to do with an eye single to the island's<lb/>
welfare.</p>
<p>-----------------</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
