<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2895012">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 27, 1907</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2895012</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1907-08-27</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government">YES</term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito"></term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="person">Roosevelt, Teddy</name>
<name type="place">Havana (Cuba)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1907-08-27">August 27, 1907</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2895012</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 27, 1907</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>National Sanitation - Some Objections.</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1907-08-27">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Havana Daily Telegraph, August 27, 1907</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2895012"/>
<opener>
PAGE TWO.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
THE HAVANA DAILY TELEGRAPH.<lb/>
Published by The Daily Telegraph Company.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
PUBLISHED EVERY DAY IN THE YEAR.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Entered at the Havana, Cuba, postoffice as second class matter.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Circulation Rates. Prices in United States Currency.<lb/>
One Year, delivered by carrier or mail. .... .. .... $5.00<lb/>
Six Months. delivered by carrier or mail.. .. .. .... 3.00<lb/>
Three Months. delivered by carrier or mail .... 175<lb/>
One Month, delivered by carrier or mail.. .... .... 75<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
Telephone No. 3257.<lb/>
Cable, &ldquo;Telegraph.&rdquo;<lb/>
OFFICE NO. 7 O'REILLY STREET.<lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<dateline>
Havana, Cuba, <date value="1907-08-27">August 27, 1907.</date>
</dateline>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>NATIONAL SANITATION-SOME<lb/>
OBJECTIONS.</p>
<p>The Arabs say that one should not look a<lb/>
gift horse in the mouth, and Christians<lb/>
generally believed that blessings should be accepted in an humble and a grateful<lb/>
spirit, wherefore it may seem ungracious to find any fault with so indubitable<lb/>
a blessing as Governor Magoon's decree nationalizing the sanitation service of<lb/>
the island. Yet, while the measure in its entirety is so very good, we can<lb/>
not but question the wisdom (until we know why) of the clause providing that<lb/>
the chief of sanitation and the members of the board shall be appointed by the<lb/>
president for terms of four years.</p>
<p>This term of office coincides with the presidential incumbency, and therefore<lb/>
it seems that the sanitary department is to be political in character and its of-<lb/>
fices to be part of the political &ldquo;pap&rdquo; which a presidential candidate may hold<lb/>
out as a contingent fee to his supporters.</p>
<p>Now, it seems to us that the department of sanitation should be as far<lb/>
removed from politics as the judiciary, and after considerable pondering we find<lb/>
ourselves unable to divine any reason for changing its personnel every four<lb/>
years. Moreover, the decree expressly provides that the president may at any<lb/>
time remove the chief of sanitation or any member of the board &ldquo;for cause.&rdquo; This<lb/>
suggests that these officials should continue undisturbed in the discharge of<lb/>
their duties so long as they properly discharge them, and there can scarcely be<lb/>
any question but that one may grow old in the discharge of such duties, becom-<lb/>
ing by experience each year more valuable and efficient. To make continuance<lb/>
in such offices dependent upon the partisan possibilities occurring every four<lb/>
years is diametrically opposed to the whole theory and practice of the civil ser-<lb/>
vice system of which President Roosevelt, ever since he entered public life, has<lb/>
been so consistent a champion. We confess, somewhat regretfully, that we are<lb/>
not omniscient, and there may be some excellent reason for making tenure of<lb/>
sanitary office dependent upon political, or rather party, exigencies, but we can<lb/>
not find it, and would be grateful for enlightenment.</p>
<p>What seems to us another flaw in the decree is the perpetuation of the de-<lb/>
partment of &ldquo;Special Hygiene,&rdquo; by incorporating it in the National Board of<lb/>
Sanitation. Why not abolish it? The excuses for such legalizing of vice, on<lb/>
the score that the public health is thereby protected, while always lacking ethi-<lb/>
cally, have been proven by experience to be invalid, even from a hygienic stand-<lb/>
point. Eminent physicians in Havana declare that the protection thus afforded<lb/>
does not protect. If this be true, why longer disgrace the city by making it a<lb/>
procurer, deriving income from the vilest of traffics?--No, not the city now, but<lb/>
the Cuban republic, since sanitation has been made national. Surely, it is not<lb/>
fitting that any part of the president's salary should be paid by fallen women<lb/>
for the privilege of plying their trade.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
