<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2942001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, June 21, 1908</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2942001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1908-06-21</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians"></term>
<term type="Popular_Culture"></term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever"></term>

<name type="place">Baltimore (Md.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1908-06-21">June 21, 1908</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2942001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, June 21, 1908</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Mosquito Brigade Has Slain 234,678,548,876,234,789,432,623,734,816,212 of the Pesky Critters Wounded Number More Than 3,621,738,541,776,928,316,294,444,360,727,663,361,246,818</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1908-06-21">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Baltimore Sun, June 21, 1908</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2942001"/>
<opener>
<dateline>
THE SUN, BALTIMORE, SUNDAY MORNING. <date value="1908-06-21">JUNE 21, 1908.</date>
</dateline>
<unclear>15)</unclear><lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
</opener>
<p>Mosquito Brigade Has Slain 234,678,548,876,234,789,432,623,734,816,212 Of The Pesky Critters<lb/>
Wounded Number More Than 3,621,738,541,776,928,316,294,444,360,727,663,361,246,818</p>
<p>UP TO 12 o'clock last night<lb/>
the Mosquito Brigade of the<lb/>
Health Department had<lb/>
killed 234,678,548,876,234,789,-<lb/>
432,623 mosquitoes in and about<lb/>
Baltimore and had wounded,<lb/>
scared, tracked, trailed, mobbed,<lb/>
clubbed, crippled, walloped, basti-<lb/>
nadaed and chased away no fewer<lb/>
than 3,621,738,541,776,928,316,-<lb/>
294,444,360,727,663,361,246,818,-<lb/>
714,928,333,631,647,781,880,721,-<lb/>
620,228,913,627,366,063,837,145,-<lb/>
677,829,613,727,163,642,718,621,-<lb/>
814,364,821,936,821,999,642,721,-<lb/>
919,001,162,222,388,914,441,621,-<lb/>
864 more.</p>
<p>THESE figures, which are supplied by<lb/>
Dr. William N. Hill, commander-<lb/>
in-chief of the brigade, and certi-<lb/>
fied under the great seal of the Health<lb/>
Department by Prof. John William Mont-<lb/>
gomery Kiger, Auditor-General, may seem<lb/>
incredibly enormous, but all the same they<lb/>
are official and, in consequence, accurate.</p>
<p>Anyone who doubts them may verify<lb/>
them by visiting the battle fields whereon<lb/>
the brigade has won its most stupendous<lb/>
victories. Here the carcasses of dead mos-<lb/>
quitoes are piled mountain high. Near the<lb/>
3-cent bridge there is a stack as large as a<lb/>
brewery, and further eastward, along the<lb/>
romantic shores of Spring Gardens, are<lb/>
heaps which overshadow the gasworks.<lb/>
Dr. Hill himself has personally killed more<lb/>
than 364,721,864,211,731,848 mosquitoes.</p>
<p>NOT A SOLDIER KILLED.</p>
<p>During the numerous engagements and<lb/>
skirmishes between the skeeters and the<lb/>
brigade not a soldier has been seriously<lb/>
wounded. Several admit that they have<lb/>
been stung, but not one has been compelled<lb/>
to go to a hospital.</p>
<p>Doctor Hill (who is also a celebrated<lb/>
singletaxer and free-discussionist) has<lb/>
probably developed more new methods of<lb/>
exterminating a tribe of mosquitoes than<lb/>
any other mosquito warrior in this coun-<lb/>
try. He is ably surrounded by an army of<lb/>
roughriding, dashing, bold and gallant<lb/>
warriors, who know no fear and who fol-<lb/>
low their general on the battle field with-<lb/>
out the slightest hesitation.</p>
<p>With spades and picks and cans of kero-<lb/>
sene as their only weapons, the soldiers<lb/>
march into dismal swamps, charge with-<lb/>
out sounding the bugle and do their<lb/>
bloody work in a few minutes. The attacks<lb/>
are so well planned that never has one<lb/>
mosquito been known to escape without<lb/>
injury.</p>
<p>So expert are the warriors they do not<lb/>
need any chart or regular line of formation.<lb/>
They surround the swamp. Each man is<lb/>
given his instructions. The enemy is then<lb/>
routed and the battle is over.</p>
<p>Already the good work done by the bri-<lb/>
gade has been noticed in the suburbs, and<lb/>
Dr. Hill and his fighters are being highly<lb/>
commended. According to reports from the<lb/>
front the brigade has visited every section<lb/>
in the outlying district and its last report<lb/>
to Health Commissioner Bosley shows the<lb/>
above number of fatalities.</p>
<p>MORE MONEY IS NEEDED.</p>
<p>At present the force is not as large as<lb/>
Generalissimo Hill would like it to be. This<lb/>
is due entirely to the small appropriation<lb/>
which was made for it by the Board of Es-<lb/>
timates. The men in the army want their<lb/>
pay. If there was money in sight, says Dr.<lb/>
Hill, he would have no trouble in securing<lb/>
hundreds of volunteers, but they refuse to<lb/>
fight just for the glory that is in it.</p>
<p>When the work was begun last year Dr.<lb/>
Hill had an appropriation of $10,000. With<lb/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
of swamps and pools in the suburbs and<lb/>
made hundreds of drains to drain swamps<lb/>
which were not filled. It was during this<lb/>
period that mosquitoes were killed by the<lb/>
billions every day.</p>
<p>In compiling the ordinance of estimates<lb/>
for this year the board allowed only $5,000<lb/>
for the work. Undaunted by this only re-<lb/>
verse in his most successful fighting career,<lb/>
Dr. Hill resumed his command of the bri-<lb/>
gade this year as soon as the proclamation<lb/>
of war was issued by Dr. Bosley.</p>
<p>In a few days he had reorganized his<lb/>
brigade and was again on the job. Inci-<lb/>
dentally all the fighters, including the doc-<lb/>
tor, were put on the city's payroll.</p>
<p>But upon an investigation the General<lb/>
found that the little pests had been wiped<lb/>
off of the map in a number of localities.<lb/>
Most of the swamps which had been drained<lb/>
had become permanent dry spots and there-<lb/>
fore unfit for the abode and breeding places<lb/>
for mosquitoes, and likewise a majority of<lb/>
the fills were permanent.</p>
<p>Hundreds of the battles did not have to<lb/>
be fought over again. The first victories<lb/>
were decisive and, the news was hurriedly<lb/>
<unclear></unclear><lb/>
were then sent by wireless for the brigade<lb/>
to continue the work of filling and drain-<lb/>
ing swamps, and every day now Dr. Hill<lb/>
and his men can be seen sneaking through<lb/>
the alleys and roads of the suburbs look-<lb/>
ing for the breeding and hiding places of<lb/>
the enemy.</p>
<p>THE FIGHTING FORCE.</p>
<p>Those in the army this year are:<lb/>
<list type="simple">
<item>Col. Francis A. Lloyd, 805 West Frank-<lb/>
lin street, whose hearing is so good that<lb/>
he can hear the buzz of a mosquito three<lb/>
blocks away.</item>
<item>Major Thomas Freeze, 120 Dolphin street,<lb/>
who pours kerosene on the troubled waters<lb/>
and keeps account of the number killed.</item>
<item>Capt. Jacob List, of Forest Park, aid to<lb/>
the General.</item>
<item>Capt. Joseph E. Buxbaum, 927 West<lb/>
Lombard street, captain of the spade and<lb/>
pick muskeeters.</item>
<item>Lieut. John C. Lastner, 1723 North Reg-<lb/>
ester street, world's crack shot with a kero-<lb/>
sene repeating oil can.</item>
<item>Lieut. R. M. Betz, 417 North Washington<lb/>
street, official photographer, clerk to the<lb/>
brigade and general utility man.</item>
</list></p>
<p><unclear>pictures</unclear> have been taken of<lb/>
the battles by Mr. Betz, and within a few<lb/>
weeks the bloody scenes and massacres<lb/>
will be shown on moving-picture machines<lb/>
in the 5-cent amusement houses on East<lb/>
Baltimore street.</p>
<p>Although there is no record of a mos-<lb/>
quito escaping without injury, the mem-<lb/>
bers of the brigade admit that several<lb/>
large fellows, apparently heads of the<lb/>
tribe, have gotten through the lines and<lb/>
have only been killed after a strenuous<lb/>
chase. When a mosquito once gets away<lb/>
General Hill calls for volunteers. Several<lb/>
of them are usually found among the spec-<lb/>
tators standing on the banks of the swamp<lb/>
watching the battle. Of course, the oil can<lb/>
is not a valuable weapon in a chase, ex-<lb/>
cept to hurl at the fleeing mosquito.</p>
<p>As soon as the alarm of escape is sound-<lb/>
ed the entire army is commanded to cap-<lb/>
ture the fugitive dead or alive. With their<lb/>
picks and spades the soldiers fly over hills<lb/>
and through dales after the &ldquo;stinger.&rdquo;</p>
<p>CHASING THE SKEETER.</p>
<p>Standing near by at the time of the<lb/>
escape may be several persons who are<lb/>
resting after a round on the golf links.<lb/>
With their golf sticks they immediately<lb/>
join the pursuing force. On goes the<lb/>
chase. Persons playing tennis are passed,<lb/>
and when they learn of the escape they<lb/>
join in with their tennis racquets. A la-<lb/>
crosse game is next passed, and, of course,<lb/>
the players drop the ball and, with their<lb/>
lacrosse sticks, get into the run.</p>
<p>And so it goes. Like a fox, the mos-<lb/>
quito gains on his pursuers for the first<lb/>
few miles. But, encouraged by the thrill-<lb/>
ing commands of Dr. Hill, the army and<lb/>
the unpaid recruits keep on the chase.<lb/>
Realizing the damage that can be done to<lb/>
the community by the settlement of even<lb/>
one mosquito, everybody gladly aids in<lb/>
capturing the pest.</p>
<p>Boys with crab nets, washerwomen with<lb/>
washbaskets, county police on horseback<lb/>
and farmers with rakes and hoes join in.<lb/>
Sometimes they collide and roll down the<lb/>
hills. But &ldquo;Forward!&rdquo; is the command,<lb/>
and they keep going. Frequently they are<lb/>
compelled to wade and swim across peace-<lb/>
ful brooks. But this is all in the game.</p>
<p>Ah! the chase is nearly at an end. Col.<lb/>
Frank Lloyd, with his remarkable hear-<lb/>
ing, reports that the mosquito is gasping<lb/>
for breath, and that if he is not overtaken<lb/>
within the next mile he will fall exhaust-<lb/>
ed. The &ldquo;buzzer&rdquo; <unclear>is</unclear> seen to look back at<lb/>
his pursuers, and upon his face Dr. Hill<lb/>
sees the look of despair.</p>
<p>This makes the Doctor encourage his<lb/>
army on. It now consists of about 50 peo-<lb/>
ple, scattered for several squares back.<lb/>
The cops on horseback are near the head<lb/>
of the procession, for they know that if<lb/>
they capture the &ldquo;stinger&rdquo; they will be<lb/>
given medals of honor by the County Com-<lb/>
missioners. The boys with the crab nets<lb/>
get almost within reaching distance of<lb/>
the mosquito. They dive, but miss. La-<lb/>
crosse sticks and tennis racquets, oil cans<lb/>
picks, baskets, shovels, spades and rocks<lb/>
fly at its head.</p>
<p>Poor little fellow! Realizing that the<lb/>
end is near at hand and that if caught he<lb/>
will not be killed by a hard slap, but<lb/>
crushed under the foot of Dr. Hill, he<lb/>
spies a brick wall and then and there<lb/>
dashes out his brains. The pursuers reach<lb/>
him just as his lifeless body falls on the<lb/>
ground.</p>
<p>GOOD-BY THE SKEETER!</p>
<p>The remains are viewed by the army and<lb/>
the volunteers, all of whom are exhausted.<lb/>
Of course, they are sorry that they did not<lb/>
have the pleasure of beheading the pest<lb/>
or sticking his eye out with a pin, or pull-<lb/>
ing his stinger out. But the result is the<lb/>
same. It is dead!</p>
<p>Dr. Hill stands by the dead body, ex-<lb/>
tols his army and thanks the volunteers<lb/>
for their assistance. The volunteers re-<lb/>
turn to their respective duties and pleas-<lb/>
ures, while the army again continues on<lb/>
the job.</p>
<p>These exhilarating and dare-devil chases<lb/>
are never officially reported to Dr. Bosley,<lb/>
but he frequently hears rumors of them<lb/>
from those who have joined in the chase.<lb/>
At all times Dr. Hill refuses to be com-<lb/>
plimented for the good work that he and<lb/>
his army are doing, but he is a &ldquo;plugger&rdquo;<lb/>
and is always busy.</p>
<p>It may seem incredible to some people,<lb/>
but if the work is kept up it will be a<lb/>
matter of but a few years when mosqui-<lb/>
toes in and about Baltimore will be as<lb/>
scarce as hens' teeth. Of course, a stray<lb/>
one may be found here and there, but<lb/>
upon investigation, it is believed, it will<lb/>
be found that it got here on a train pass-<lb/>
ing through New Jersey or was blown in<lb/>
from Patapsco Neck by a high wind.</p>
<p>When that time comes the Doctor <unclear></unclear><lb/>
still be on the job, capturing <unclear>these</unclear><lb/>
pests.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
