<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="fever.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="N2969001">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
 
<title type="245">Newspaper clipping, The Boston Evening Transcript, February 26, 1910</title>
<title type="gmd">[electronic resource] </title>
 
<author></author>
 
<respStmt>
<resp>Transcriptions and TEI markup</resp>
<name>Innodata Inc</name>
<resp>Images, project design, and management: </resp>
<name>Historical Collections &amp; Services <lb/>
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library <lb/>
University of Virginia Health System <lb/>
P.O. Box 800722 <lb/>
Charlottesville, VA 22908-0722
</name>
<resp>TEI consultation:</resp>
<name>Electronic Text Center <lb/>
University of Virginia Library<lb/>
</name>
 
</respStmt>
 
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Claude Moore Health Sciences Library of the
University of Virginia Health System</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia 22908, USA</pubPlace>
<idno>N2969001</idno>
<availability>
<p>Publicly accessible for non-commercial use.  All rights reserved.</p>
<p n="public">URL: http://www.med.virginia.edu/hs-library/historical/</p>
<p>Copyright 2001, by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
</availability>
<date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl>
<idno type="callNo">The Philip S. Hench Walter Reed/Yellow Fever Collection
[manuscript] / [collected by] Philip S. Hench ; HEALTHSCI MS-1.</idno>
</bibl>
</sourceDesc>
 
</fileDesc>
 
<profileDesc>
<creation><date>1910-02-26</date></creation>
<langUsage><language id="eng">English</language></langUsage>
<textClass> <keywords> <term></term></keywords> </textClass>
 
</profileDesc>
 
<revisionDesc>
<change> <date></date>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name></name> </respStmt>
<item></item> </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
<front>
<div1 type="keywords">
<head>Keywords</head>
<p>
<term type="Armed_Forces"></term>
<term type="Artifact"></term>
<term type="Biography"></term>
<term type="Boards_of_Health"></term>
<term type="Courtship"></term>
<term type="Disease"></term>
<term type="Education"></term>
<term type="Ethics"></term>
<term type="French"></term>
<term type="German"></term>
<term type="Government"></term>
<term type="Human_Experimentation"></term>
<term type="Interpersonal_Relations"></term>
<term type="Military_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Mosquito">YES</term>
<term type="Newspaper">YES</term>
<term type="Philosophy"></term>
<term type="Photograph"></term>
<term type="Physicians">YES</term>
<term type="Popular_Culture">YES</term>
<term type="Portuguese"></term>
<term type="Public_Health">YES</term>
<term type="Religion"></term>
<term type="Social_History"></term>
<term type="Spanish"></term>
<term type="Tropical_Medicine"></term>
<term type="Yellow_Fever">YES</term>


<name type="place">Philadelphia (Pa.)</name>
<name type="place">New York (N.Y.)</name>
<name type="place">New London (Conn.)</name>
<name type="place">Memphis (Tenn.)</name>
<name type="place">New Orleans (La.)</name>
<name type="place">Charleston (S.C.)</name>
<name type="place">Mobile (Ala.)</name>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>Newspaper clipping</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1910-02-26">February 26, 1910</date>
<idno rend="suppress">N2969001</idno>
<title>Newspaper clipping, The Boston Evening Transcript, February 26, 1910</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Fiction and Yellow Fever. Charles Brockden Brown, the Father of Our Novelists, and His Lurid Stories</p>
</div1>
</front>
<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1910-02-26">
<head>Newspaper clipping, The Boston Evening Transcript, February 26, 1910</head>
<pb n="1" id="fN2969001"/>
<opener>
<unclear>BOSTON</unclear> EVENING TRANSCRIPT, <unclear>SATURDAY</unclear><lb/>
__________________________________________________<lb/>
<dateline>
<date value="1910-02-26">Feb. 26. 1910</date>
</dateline>
</opener>
<p>Fiction and<lb/>
Yellow Fever</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>Charles Brockden Brown, the Father of<lb/>
Our Novelists, and His Lurid Stories</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>BY WARREN <unclear>HARTON</unclear> BLAKE</p>
<p>---</p>
<p>CHARLES BROCKDEN BROWN<unclear>. the</unclear><lb/>
Philadelphia novelist who died just<lb/>
a hundred years since in the<lb/>
city of his birth, has often<lb/>
been called the &ldquo;Father of the American<lb/>
Novel&rdquo; by persons who have never read<lb/>
his tales. It is needless, at this late date,<lb/>
to characterize his novels. They were, to<lb/>
be sure, admired by readers both at home<lb/>
and in the old country, where Shelley and<lb/>
Mrs. Shelley both praised them with en-<lb/>
thusiasm<unclear>:</unclear> they may even be counted on to<lb/>
induce a pleasant shiver in the modern<lb/>
reader<unclear>. If</unclear> he be not oversophisticated.<lb/>
Their influence upon other story tellers, at<lb/>
home and abroad, has, indeed, never been<lb/>
very well worked out; though Richard<lb/>
Henry Stoddard has not hesitated to call<lb/>
Brown &ldquo;Poe's master in prose.&rdquo; If there<lb/>
were any present intention of writing an<lb/>
essay on Brockden Brown, it would be<lb/>
worth while, perhaps, to explain that he<lb/>
barked back, in a sense, to the &ldquo;terror<lb/>
school&rdquo; founded by Horace Walpole, and<lb/>
continued the work of that psychological<lb/>
&ldquo;shocker,&rdquo; William Godwin. But it is not,<lb/>
at present, a case of writing a literary<lb/>
paper on Charles Brockden Brown. Let us<lb/>
think of him as one who devoted himself,<lb/>
in his novel-writing, to a period become, to-<lb/>
day, very obscure. The interest of the<lb/>
historian in his work is keen enough; so,<lb/>
too, that of the amateur of American his-<lb/>
tory. For Brown saw the melodramatic<lb/>
advantages of that age when Young Amer-<lb/>
ica was still in the grip of the Yellow Jack.<lb/>
It was, in his hands, an age of many hor-<lb/>
rors.</p>
<p>In another story. &ldquo;Ormond.&rdquo; Brown told<lb/>
of Gotham's milder sufferings: in &ldquo;Arthur<lb/>
Mervyn&rdquo;--his least forgotten <unclear>fletion</unclear>--<unclear>be</unclear><lb/>
chose for his grewsome background plague-<lb/>
stricken Philadelphia. In those days it<lb/>
was neither typhoid nor trolley strikes for<lb/>
which the city was to be pitied<unclear>;</unclear> nor had<lb/>
it yet won a reputation as the worst gov-<lb/>
erened municipality. Yet &ldquo;plague-stricken&rdquo;<lb/>
is no figure of rhetoric when it comes to<lb/>
describing the Quaker City of <unclear>1793:</unclear> so that<lb/>
even thus early the prosperous and con-<lb/>
tented town deserved something of her<lb/>
neighbor's pity. The yellow fever epidemic<lb/>
that the Federal capital of those days<lb/>
passed through was far more terrible than<lb/>
that of <unclear>1862, or of 1797:</unclear> the attack was<lb/>
more general than those from which New<lb/>
York suffered in 1795 and <unclear>1798 and 1799,</unclear><lb/>
and infinitely worse than any of New Lon-<lb/>
don's; it was more terrifying, at least, and<lb/>
far less intelligently handled than those<lb/>
which threw into a frenzy the Southern<lb/>
towns of Charleston, Memphis and New<lb/>
Orleans, as late as the eighteen-fifties, and<lb/>
-in the case of Memphis-1878. Terrifying<lb/>
is indeed the word, however, for all these<lb/>
plagues. In 1819, for example, the popula-<lb/>
tion of Mobile fell, through deaths and<lb/>
<unclear>flight, from 1900 to 300</unclear>. In the last serious<lb/>
outbreak of the disease at that place, there<lb/>
were more than 17,000 cases, and over five<lb/>
thousand <unclear>fatalities.</unclear> This by way of pref-<lb/>
ace to the best known passage in any of all<lb/>
Brockden Brown's novels; a passage not,<lb/>
however, so well known that one need<lb/>
seriously apologize for reproducing it. It<lb/>
makes real to us even statistics, statistics<lb/>
make it even seem real. Here is the &ldquo;Ar-<lb/>
thur Mervyn&rdquo; description of a yellow<lb/>
fever hospital in Philadelphia-the de-<lb/>
scription that leads Professor Barrett<lb/>
Wendell to compare Brown with Defoe,<lb/>
imaginative historian of London's plague-<lb/>
year.</p>
<p>After a time I opened my eyes, and slow-<lb/>
ly gained some knowledge of my situation.<lb/>
I lay upon a mattress, whose condition<lb/>
proved that a half-decayed corpse had re-<lb/>
cently been dragged from it. The room was<lb/>
large, but it was covered with beds like<lb/>
my own. Between each, there was scarce-<lb/>
ly the interval of three feet. Each sus-<lb/>
tained a wretch, whose groans and distor-<lb/>
tions bespoke the desperateness of his con-<lb/>
dition.</p>
<p>You will scarcely believe that, in this<lb/>
scene of horrors, the sound of laughter<lb/>
should be overheard. While the upper<lb/>
rooms of this building are filled with the<lb/>
sick and the dying, the lower apartments<lb/>
are the scenes of carousals and mirth. The<lb/>
wretches who are hired, at enormous wages,<lb/>
to tend the sick and convey away the dead,<lb/>
neglect their duty and consume the cor-<lb/>
dials, which are provided for the patients,<lb/>
in debauchery and riot. A female visage,<lb/>
bloated with malignity and drunkenness.<lb/>
occasionally looked in. Dying eyes were<lb/>
cast upon her, invoking the <unclear>boon</unclear>. perhaps.<lb/>
of a drop of cold water, or her assistance<lb/>
to change a posture which compelled him<lb/>
to behold the ghastly writhings or dreadful<lb/>
<unclear>smile</unclear> of his neighbor.</p>
<p>The visitant had left the banquet for a<lb/>
moment, only to see who was dead. If she<lb/>
entered the room. blinking eyes and reel-<lb/>
<unclear>ing</unclear> steps showed her to be <unclear>totally</unclear> unquali-<lb/>
fied for ministering the aid that was needed.<lb/>
Presently she disappeared and others<lb/>
ascended the staircase, a coffin was de-<lb/>
posited at the door, the wretch, whose heart<lb/>
still quivered, was seized by rude <unclear>hands.</unclear><lb/>
and dragged along the floor into the pas-<lb/>
sage.</p>
<p>This piece of writing and others like it<lb/>
won for Brockden Brown comparison, not<lb/>
with Defoe alone, but also with Boccaccio.<lb/>
In reading some pages of &ldquo;Arthur Mer-<lb/>
vyn&rdquo; one is reminded, too, of the fact that<lb/>
after Brown came Poe, the author of &ldquo;The<lb/>
Red Death.&rdquo;</p>
<p>In recent years physicians have deter-<lb/>
mined the precise manner in which yellow<lb/>
fever is spread. Suspected long before, the<lb/>
criminal complicity of the mosquito as an<lb/>
agent of contagion was decisively demon-<lb/>
started only after the Spanish-American<lb/>
War. during the American occupation of<lb/>
Cuba. Now that we understand the case.<lb/>
the testimony of Latrobe's &ldquo;Journal,&rdquo; con-<lb/>
tributed shortly before the outbreak of our<lb/>
second war with Great Britain, has for us<lb/>
a freshened interest. Writing in New Or-<lb/>
leans, the architect and naturalist, whose<lb/>
memoranda are so impressive a document<lb/>
in Americans, notes that &ldquo;as soon as the<lb/>
sun sets the mosquitos appear in clouds,<lb/>
and fill every room in the house, as well as<lb/>
the open air. Their noise . . . fills the<lb/>
air, and there is a character of occasional<lb/>
depression and elevation in it, like that of a<lb/>
concert of frogs in a marah. . . . When<lb/>
(as was the case in Philadelphia) the city<lb/>
shall be supplied with water by pipes the<lb/>
evil may probably be considerably les-<lb/>
sened.&rdquo; The evil of mosquitos, that is; it<lb/>
never occurs to Latrobe to associate recur-<lb/>
rent epidemics of yellow fever with the<lb/>
bites of the insects that annoy him so<lb/>
And it is true that the disease was primari-<lb/>
ly propagated, not by the home-grown<lb/>
pests, but by those mosquitos imported on<lb/>
vessels from the south. Still there is a<lb/>
certain grim humor about Latrobe's writ-<lb/>
ing:</p>
<p>I say nothing of the yellow fever, because<lb/>
I believe this calamity may be moderated,<lb/>
if not entirely eradicated, by a good medi-<lb/>
cal police, and under a better understand-<lb/>
ing of its origin and treatment than now<lb/>
prevails at New Orleans.</p>
<p>How infinitely superior is the diarist's<lb/>
tone, as he writes of these ignorant Louisi-<lb/>
anians: Yet he himself was as much at sea<lb/>
in the matter as they were themselves.<lb/>
Referring to the yellow jack as an annual<lb/>
visitor at Philadelphia, he blames it upon<lb/>
the circumstance that clear water was to be<lb/>
found &ldquo;in every possible spot of ground.&rdquo;<lb/>
&ldquo;Every house,&rdquo; he ran on, &ldquo;has its privy<lb/>
and its drains, which . . . certainly con-<lb/>
taminate the water of every pump in the<lb/>
neighborhood.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Unsanitary to a degree as that arrange-<lb/>
ment was, we know, now, that it had little<lb/>
-even nothing-to do with the recurring<lb/>
plague. Quite as rational were the earlier<lb/>
explanations of the New York and Philadel-<lb/>
phia pestilences-explanations that blamed<lb/>
<unclear>it</unclear>all-somewhat variously-upon the<lb/>
&ldquo;spoiled coffee and fish&rdquo; dumped by a West<lb/>
<unclear>Indiaman</unclear>, and left to poison the air of the<lb/>
shipping quarter with its emanations (the<lb/>
supposition mentioned in the &ldquo;Journal of<lb/>
Elizabeth Drinker&rdquo;), the <unclear>'unfinished</unclear> situa-<lb/>
tion of the docks in Front <unclear>street"</unclear> (see<lb/>
James Hardie's &ldquo;Malignant Fever Lately<lb/>
Prevalent.&rdquo; etc.). and the heat of the sum-<lb/>
mers preceding the more severe outbreaks,<lb/>
followed by wet weather. The Philadelphia<lb/>
Academy of Medicine attributed one of the<lb/>
later outbreaks-that of 1798--to the exhal-<lb/>
ations of the alleys, gutters, docks and<lb/>
common sewers; to the foul air discharged<lb/>
with the ballast of the ship Deborah, from<lb/>
Hispaniola<unclear>.</unclear> etc. The origin of the disease<lb/>
<unclear>was</unclear> in fine, unknown. All men were sure<lb/>
of was its deadliness. The &ldquo;general extinc-<lb/>
tion of the disease by frost&rdquo; was widely<lb/>
recognized<unclear>:</unclear> what a pity that someone did<lb/>
not connect the coming of the frost and the<lb/>
killing off of the infected tropical mosqui-<lb/>
tos: Temperance was alleged to be a safe-<lb/>
guard against infection<unclear>:</unclear> so that the pesti-<lb/>
lence lacked not its sunny side. The greater<lb/>
cleanliness of European cities was cited as<lb/>
the explanation of their comparative immu-<lb/>
nity.</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that the ingenious La-<lb/>
trobe never coupled mosquito and disease<lb/>
in the relation of cause and effect-as he<lb/>
did couple them as twin pests of New Or-<lb/>
leans. But the insect was not as yet sus-<lb/>
pected. It was Brockden Brown's privilege<lb/>
to discover the literary possibilities of Phil-<lb/>
adelphia suffering from plague; it was our<lb/>
privilege-or that of our heroic army-sur-<lb/>
geons-to attack the evil scientifically.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
